<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4v06s</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">NX653.W47C36 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">West (U.S.)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">In art</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Place (Philosophy) in art</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Identity (Philosophical concept) in art</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Arts, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Rhizomatic West</book-title>
         <subtitle>Representing the American West in a Transnational, Global, Media Age</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Campbell</surname>
               <given-names>Neil</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">Series Editors</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Aranda</surname>
               <given-names>José</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Graulich</surname>
               <given-names>Melody</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>King</surname>
               <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib5">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lee</surname>
               <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib6">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lewis</surname>
               <given-names>Nathaniel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib7">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tatum</surname>
               <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803215399</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803217836</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803217838</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LINCOLN; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dgn4wh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Is the American West in Sergio Leone's "spaghetti westerns" the same American West we find in Douglas Coupland's<italic>Generation X</italic>? In Jim Jarmusch's movies? In Calexico's music? Or is the American West, as this book tells us, a constantly moving, mutating idea within a complex global culture? And what, precisely (or better yet, imprecisely) does it mean?</p>
         <p>Using Gilles Deleuze and Félix Guattari's concept of the rhizome, Neil Campbell shows how the West (or west-ness) continually breaks away from a mainstream notion of American "rootedness" and renews and transforms itself in various cultural forms. A region long traversed by various transient peoples (from tribes and conquerors to immigrants, traders, and trappers), the West reflects a mythic quest for settlement, permanence, and synthesis-even notions of a national or global identity-at odds with its rootless history, culture, and nature. Crossing the concept of "roots" with "routes," this book shows how notions of the West-in representations ranging from literature and film to photography, music, and architectural theory-give expression to ideas about identity, nationhood, and belonging in a world increasingly defined by movement across time and borders.<italic>The Rhizomatic West</italic>offers a new vision of the American West as a hybrid, performative space, a staging place for myriad intersecting and constantly changing identities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="392"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theorizing the Rhizomatic West</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Like people and schools of criticism, ideas and theories travel—from person to person, from situation to situation, from one period to another. Cultural and intellectual life are usually nourished and often sustained by this circulation of ideas, and whether it takes the form of acknowledged or unconscious influence, creative borrowing, or wholesale appropriation, the movement of ideas and theories from one place to another is both a fact of life and a usefully enabling condition of intellectual activity.” Edward Said’s words suggest how ideas and theories travel or are borrowed and used in different places for different purposes: “For</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>TOWARD AN EXPANDED CRITICAL REGIONALISM</title>
                     <subtitle>Contact and Interchange</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As discussed in the introduction, a central concern of this book is how to think differently about the American West, to decentralize and dislocate the ways it has so often been considered, even among so-called revisionist writers and scholars, so that we might see westness as part of a larger system of discourse, beyond the national imaginary, pointing in many directions at once. As I have written elsewhere, “The American West is more than geography, it is a complex, unstable signifier that has been given meaning by those who have lived within it, passed through it, conquered it, settled, farmed,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>FEASTS OF WIRE</title>
                     <subtitle>Rubén Martinez and the Transfrontera Contact Zone</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To examine one specific type of critical regionalism I wish to turn to José David Saldívar’s<italic>Border Matters: Remapping American Cultural Studies</italic>(1997), a work influenced by the theoretical syncretism of Stuart Hall’s and Paul Gilroy’s British cultural studies and seeking to present “the U.S.-Mexico border zone as a paradigm of crossings, intercultural exchanges, circulations, resistances, and negotiations as well as of militarised ‘low-intensity’ conflict.” Saldívar argues that the border represents “a model for a new kind of U.S. cultural studies … that challenges the homogeneity of U.S. nationalism and popular culture,” with the nation “re-imagined … as a site</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>WELCOME TO WESTWORLD</title>
                     <subtitle>Sergio Leone’s Once Upon a Time in the West</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An expanded critical regionalism like that explored in the previous chapters demonstrates that no region can be static or inward-looking, for it needs to recognize forces beyond the nation, considering how the regional travels and dialogues with other cultures, circulating as it is consumed and re-produced in other forms. As the West is performed and practiced outside its geographical and ideological boundaries (or grids), as in Khaled Hosseini’s Afghanistan-set novel<italic>The Kite Runner</italic>(quoted above), it undergoes changes akin to the “wandering lines” described by Michel De Certeau—“‘indirect’ or ‘errant’ trajectories obeying their own logic … [creating] unforeseeable sentences,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>“THE ‘WESTERN’ IN QUOTES”</title>
                     <subtitle>Generic Variations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I discussed in the previous chapter, Sergio Leone’s films were seen by some as the death knell of the Western and by others as its regenerative force, breathing new life into a tired, mythic formula and seeing the genre as the site for cultural critique and counterhegemonic practice. The established generic grid of the Western proved elastic and porous enough for new filmmakers looking to utilize its broad expectations and codes for different purposes, building on the promising works of directors such as Nicholas Ray, Sam Peckinpah, and Robert Altman. Often these innovations came from outside the Hollywood mainstream,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>DIALOGICAL LANDSCAPES</title>
                     <subtitle>“Outsider” Photography of the West</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joel Meyerowitz has written of how he believes photographs work: “You picture something in a frame and it’s got lots of accounting going on in it—stones and buildings and trees and air—but that’s not what fills up a frame. You fill up a frame with feelings, energy, discovery, and risk, and leave room enough for someone else to get in there. … A photo must have room in it for entrance by outsiders, so that the photographer himself or herself hasn’t built a structure that keeps you out, but instead has left some crack that allows you the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>STRATA AND ROUTES</title>
                     <subtitle>Living on Reservation X</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Writing this chapter from outside the United States and as a white critic has made me doubly conscious of my position in relation to the texts I am going to discuss, very much aware (again) of my “outsider” status. At the risk of making errors, of which I am sure there are many, I wanted to examine some notable critical positions and then to see how they related to the most accessible of texts, contemporary Indian film. Ironically, most of the books, films, and critical writings referred to in this chapter have never been readily available in the United Kingdom,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>POSTWESTERN GENERATIONS?</title>
                     <subtitle>Douglas Coupland’s “Plastic Radiant Way”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mike Davis writes of how the belief of Native American prophet Wovoka in the Ghost Dance as an apocalyptic reminder of the instability of a white West is still alive and evident as one surveys the “artificial world” of L.A.’s “neon landscapes”—“Turnerian history … stripped down to its ultimate paranoia,” he calls it. But as he reminds us, in the Ghost Dance tradition “this end point is also paradoxically the point of renewal and restoration.”¹ This association of apocalypse and renewal, of ending and beginning, has a curious resonance for this chapter as I continue my efforts to show</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>On “The Crystal Frontier”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean-François Lyotard’s postmodern experimental text<italic>Pacific Wall</italic>begins with a description of the University of California, San Diego library as a “transparent jewel” with its “walls of glass” pointing in all directions, both “internal” and “external,” radiating both total vision and knowledge “without problem or hindrance.” However, his narrator goes on to think more about this elaborate crystal grid as a “maze” or labyrinth whose refractions and angles draw the eye away from the books, “behind the western face,” from inside to outside and back again, until “it begins to jump from one to the other, and the suspicion arises</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dgn4wh.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>384</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
