<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR21.A85 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spenser, Edmund, 1552?–1599. Faerie queene</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chaucer, Geoffrey, d. 1400. Canterbury tales</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Shakespeare, William, 1564–1616. King Lear</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Milton, John, 1608–1674</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Intertextuality</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Symbolism in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Influence (Literary, artistic, etc.)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading the Allegorical Intertext: Chaucer, Spenser, Shakespeare, Milton</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Anderson</surname>
               <given-names>Judith H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823228478</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823246694</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13x0d91"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Judith H. Anderson conceives the intertext as a relation between or among texts that encompasses both Kristevan intertextuality and traditional relationships of influence, imitation, allusion, and citation. Like the Internet, the intertext is a state, or place, of potential expressed in ways ranging from deliberate emulation to linguistic free play. Relatedly, the intertext is also a convenient fiction that enables examination of individual agency and sociocultural determinism. Anderson's intertext is allegorical because Spenser's Faerie Queene is pivotal to her study and because allegory, understood as continued or moving metaphor, encapsulates, even as it magnifies, the process of signification. Her title signals the variousness of an intertext extending from Chaucer through Shakespeare to Milton and the breadth of allegory itself. Literary allegory, in Anderson's view, is at once a mimetic form and a psychic one-a process thinking that combines mind with matter, emblem with narrative, abstraction with history. Anderson's first section focuses on relations between Chaucer's Canterbury Tales and Spenser's The Faerie Queene, including the role of the narrator, the nature of the textual source, the dynamics of influence, and the bearing of allegorical narrative on lyric vision. The second centers on agency and cultural influence in a variety of Spenserian and medieval texts. Allegorical form, a recurrent concern throughout, becomes the pressing issue of section three. This section treats plays and poems of Shakespeare and Milton and includes two intertextually relevant essays on Spenser.How Paradise Lost or Shakespeare's plays participate in allegorical form is controversial. Spenser's experiments with allegory revise its form, and this intervention is largely what Shakespeare and Milton find in his poetry and develop. Anderson's book, the result of decades of teaching and writing about allegory, especially Spenserian allegory, will reorient thinking about fundamental critical issues and the landmark texts in which they play themselves out.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prior Publication</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading the Allegorical Intertext</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reading between and among texts is something I have been doing in articles, books, and classrooms over several decades. This kind of reading is a staple of the traditional, centuries-spanning literary survey course, as well as of literature courses more generally. It highlights specifically textual concerns with the generation of meaning. Such intertextual relations can be historicized in the survey of<italic>longue durée</italic>, either exemplarily or thematically, selectively, and therefore rather narrowly. With the latter options, the focus has tended to shift from linguistic text to thematized content and historical context, and from literary writing to other expressions of culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Chaucer’s and Spenser’s Reflexive Narrators</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reports of the “death of the author” in the closing decades of the twentieth century nowadays appear to have been greatly exaggerated. His (sometimes her) presumed demise, to be sure, was strategically useful, not merely in renewing the formalist critique of the intentional fallacy, but also in laying to rest the naive assumption of a unified, autonomous self essentially apart from history and in full control of the unconscious. Arguably, however, it was also misleading and even dangerous, since it tended to trivialize agency, accountability, and any responsibility to history that really matters. In its stead, I have preferred to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>What Comes After Chaucer’s But in The Faerie Queene</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The bearing of an article by Talbot Donaldson called “Adventures with the Adversative Conjunction in<italic>The General Prologue</italic>to<italic>The Canterbury Tales</italic>; or, What’s Before the<italic>But</italic>?” on the Proem to Book VI of<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>is unlikely, indirect, and illuminating. Donaldson’s article examines how the illogical use of<italic>but</italic>in Chaucer’s<italic>Prologue</italic>indicates the pressures of a mind “made nervous by the complexities of its own discourse, worried by subtle implications dimly perceived but not openly recognized, or harassed by emotional responses to the material it is trying to order.” Familiar examples of such subjective usage occur in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>“Pricking on the plaine”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Spenser’s Intertextual Beginnings and Endings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The opening line of the first canto of the first Book of<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>, “A Gentle Knight was pricking on the plaine,” introduces the Chaucerian intertext and does so problematically.¹ I doubt the Spenserian exists who has not heard some medievalist declare, “I could never get over, or never forgive Spenser, his opening line.” Yet for years Spenserians themselves, as if conspiring to accept the poet’s insensitivity to his own words, totally ignored the “hard begin” of Spenser’s best-known Book. By recalling Chaucer’s comic<italic>Tale of Sir Thopas</italic>, knight prickant, this remarkably bold and witty beginning serves notice of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Allegory, Irony, Despair:</title>
                     <subtitle>Chaucer’s Pardoner’s and Franklin’s Tales and Spenser’s Faerie Queene, Books I and III</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the following chapter about allegory, irony, and despair in<italic>The Pardoner’s Tale</italic>and Book I of<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>and in<italic>The Franklin’s Tale</italic>and Book III, I start with verbal echoes as a way of suggesting the plausibility of an interpretive context, but concentrate instead on intertextual relations between Chaucerian and Spenserian texts that are broader—more imaginative and conceptual—than local and explicitly verbal. Whether in art or life, readers and writers register, remember, and imitate much else in literary models besides the odd word or phrase, as I have noted in my introduction.¹ Both subtler and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Eumnestes’ “immortall scrine”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Spenser’s Archive</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like Chaucer, Spenser often finds or pretends to find in earlier books the enabling source of his own poetry, and for this reason, among others, he describes Chaucer’s writing as the wellhead of his own. A number of Spenser’s interpreters have sought the meaning of his deliberate reliance on a written tradition in pure textuality or in its effect on a community of readers.¹ While not rejecting their many valid perceptions, I want to suggest that this reliance also be referred to the claim the Spenserian poet made for it, particularly in<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>. In Spenser’s most massively allusive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Spenser’s Use of Chaucer’s Melibee:</title>
                     <subtitle>Allegory, Narrative, History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an important article on the relation of Spenser’s late lyrics to<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>, Paul Alpers is especially concerned to defend Spenser’s Melibee, the kindly old shepherd destroyed in the sixth book by marauding brigands, from other readers’ charges of laziness, carelessness, or blindness. In terms of traditional morality, Alpers seeks to defend Melibee from the charge of imprudence in the style of his life. To this end he asserts Melibee’s “parity” in Book VI with Colin Clout, Spenser’s own pastoral persona, who invokes the celebrated vision of the Muses on Mount Acidale.¹ By “parity,” Alpers means that both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Spenser’s Muiopotmos and Chaucer’s Nun’s Priest’s Tale</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most readers would probably agree with the editors of the Spenser<italic>Variorum</italic>that “in writing<italic>Muiopotmos</italic>[<italic>: or The Fate of the Butterflie</italic>] Spenser could hardly have been unconscious of Chaucer’s mock-heroic poems, but that he was not engaged in a studied imitation of them.”¹ As evidenced in<italic>Muiopotmos</italic>, Spenser’s specific interest in<italic>The Nun’s Priest’s Tale</italic>lies somewhere between sustained allusion and incidental reminiscence; it is persistent but elusive. The relationship between these poems includes but extends beyond general similarities of genre, theme, and plot and the odd detail, such as the name of Clarion, which is likely motivated by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Arthur and Argante:</title>
                     <subtitle>Parodying the Ideal Vision</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the more luridly colorful figures in<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>is Argante, the aggressively lustful giantess of Book III. She first appears bearing the Squire of Dames “athwart her horse,” bound fast “with cords of wire, / Whom she did meane to make the thrall of her desire.”¹ Within stanzas, she has discarded the Squire, replacing him with the mightier Sir Satyrane, whom she plucks by the collar right out of his saddle and evidently hopes to subject to her service, for “ouer all the countrey she did raunge, / To seeke young men, to quench her flaming thrust.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Chaucer’s Parliament of Fowls and Refractions of a Veiled Venus in The Faerie Queene</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The lack of weight most criticism has accorded the relationship between<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>and Chaucer’s<italic>Parliament of Fowls</italic>is surprising: for Spenser, Chaucer was a poet of love, an acknowledged poetic model who “well couth … wayle hys woes,” and the<italic>Parliament</italic>is Chaucer’s formative consideration of the various kinds of love.¹ Recurrently, from the initial canto of Book I through the Mutability Cantos,<italic>The Faerie Queene</italic>recalls Chaucer’s poem. The<italic>Parliament</italic>is a text that bears unmistakably, crucially, and complexly on the Spenserian conception of eros and on the broader question of the Renaissance poet’s use of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>The Antiquities of Fairyland and Ireland</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In our century the words<italic>antique</italic>and<italic>antiquity</italic>normally have a resonance different from what they had for late sixteenth-century readers of Spenser’s<italic>Faerie Queene</italic>. For us, these words suggest not only age but also antiquation. They signal both the distance of time and that of obsolescence: while something “antique” might be valuable or quaint or interesting, it is not essentially practical or even very useful. This sense of antiquation, which registers a lack of functional relevance, is not unknown to the late sixteenth century or to Spenser, but it is novel and rare rather than usual and standard. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Better a mischief than an inconvenience:</title>
                     <subtitle>“The saiyng self” in Spenser’s View of the Present State of Ireland</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The phrase “saiyng self” (<italic>sic</italic>) in my title comes from Nicholas Udall’s introduction to Erasmus’<italic>Apophthegmes</italic>and refers to the individual apophthegm, or, as we would say, to “the saying itself.”¹ To a modern ear, Udall’s phrasing also suggests both the self or subject who speaks an apophthegm and the one who is culturally spoken by it, thereby expressing its mixed, unstable ownership and agency. The particular “saiyng self” of Spenser that I intend, “Better a mischiefe then an Inconvenience,” occurs strikingly twice in the first half of<italic>A View of the Present State of Ireland</italic>.²</p>
                     <p>This saying, whose glossing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>The Conspiracy of Realism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Impasse and Vision in The Faerie Queene and Shakespeare’s King Lear</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite an established but controversial alignment of<italic>King Lear</italic>with Beckett’s absurdist dramas or, at the alternative extreme, with Dante’s<italic>Purgatorio</italic>, the relation of<italic>King Lear</italic>to allegory has remained an elusive topic. The interpretive extremes of this pendulum’s swing are thus conspicuous, but the nature of the pendulum itself seems under taboo. Those aligning a Dantesque or absurdist work with<italic>Lear</italic>have been interested in such analogous texts primarily as statements of meaning rather than as allegorical forms, that is, as content alone rather than as informed content or as the content of form. Even older critics like A.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>Venus and Adonis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Spenser, Shakespeare, and the Forms of Desire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Shakespeare’s<italic>Venus and Adonis</italic>, the switch from Venus as manhandler to Venus as the pathetic—some would say tragic—mourner over the body of dead Adonis has always been problematical. Although passion and grief are twinned conditions of want(ing), the shift in this poem from an aggressive, comic mode to a helpless, pathetic one proves larger than life and challenges credible mimesis and, otherwise put, human credibility. Or perhaps I should say balanced human credibility, since Venus’ behavior makes sense as an obsessive fixation transferred from hunger to loss. Yes, Venus is a goddess and a figure of myth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Flowers and Boars:</title>
                     <subtitle>Surmounting Sexual Binarism in Spenser’s Garden of Adonis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My story starts with two recent classroom experiences: the first concerns a class of Honors undergraduates whom I was trying to persuade to read and think more figuratively and mythically. After receiving a set of papers on sex and gender in Spenser’s third book, I took a leaf, as well as a tusk, from my own past and posed for discussion the difference between an analysis of Book III in terms of male and female attributes and in terms of the flower and the boar, two symbolic referents that variously weave through the fabric of this book.¹ The students were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Androcentrism and Acrasian Fantasies in the Bower of Bliss</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Harry Berger’s “Wring out the Old: Squeezing the Text, 1951–2001” will be a major critical statement on the Bower of Bliss for years to come, and serious work on the Bower needs to engage its generously annotated, tightly argued analysis of the structural discourse that constitutes this site.¹ In “Squeezing the Text” (is the trope laundry or lemon juice?), Berger exposes the workings of misogyny as a target, and emphatically not a given, of the Bower. He reads the Spenserian narrative as an instance of “<italic>specular tautology</italic>,” or self-reflection, which he also understands as an inversion of cause and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16.</label>
                     <title>Beyond Binarism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eros/Death and Venus/Mars in Antony and Cleopatra and The Faerie Queene</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shakespeare’s<italic>Antony and Cleopatra</italic>, like his earlier<italic>Venus and Adonis</italic>, is known to be generically mixed and even anomalous in the extent and degree to which it combines tragedy, comedy, and romance with lyric, allegory, myth, and history.¹ This is the first of several analogies I would draw between Shakespeare’s play and Spenser’s<italic>Faerie Queene</italic>, that hobgoblin’s garland of epic, romance, lyric, allegory, myth, history, and more. The breaking of formal conventions beyond their generic variousness also connects these works. In Ania Loomba’s view, for example, the nonteleological form of<italic>Antony and Cleopatra</italic>resists closure, and in Margot Heinemann’s, this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17.</label>
                     <title>Patience and Passion in Shakespeare and Milton</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>King Lear</italic>and<italic>Othello</italic>, when Shakespeare’s anguished protagonists memorably invoke patience, they do so with an unwitting irony that plays on the linguistic genealogy of this virtue, on its combination of passion and passivity. More than a half century later, Milton’s poetry recalls the centrality and complexity of Shakespeare’s engagement with patience but goes beyond it to render the traditional significance of this virtue dynamic and revisionary. In the unifying insight of the blind poet, patience becomes action, rather than simply giving way to action or being replaced by it. The traditional binarism of passive endurance and assertive action</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18.</label>
                     <title>“Real or Allegoric” in Herbert and Milton:</title>
                     <subtitle>Thinking through Difference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fourth Book of<italic>Paradise Regained</italic>, Satan tempts the Son with the intellectual splendors of ancient Greece, and these having been rejected, asks him in scornful frustration, “What dost thou in this World?”: what connects you to history and humanity? Satan adds that his reading of heaven portends a kingdom for the Son, “but what Kingdom, / Real or Allegoric I discern not.” With an irony approaching sarcasm, he goes on to say that he fails to see when the Son’s kingdom will ever be at hand, since it is “eternal sure, as without end, / Without beginning.”¹ By</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19.</label>
                     <title>Spenser and Milton:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Mind’s Allegorical Place</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of relatively recent studies of Milton’s poetics, Mindele Anne Treip’s<italic>Allegorical Poetics and the Epic: The Renaissance Tradition to “Paradise Lost”</italic>remains, for my purpose, the most historically significant.¹ In the Renaissance, Treip explains, Salutati’s theoretical discussions of poetry anticipate “a practical paradigm of epic allegory of the kind Tasso would evolve, suggesting how the poet may weave together the entire linguistic surface of a poem, along with its narrative substructure, so that ‘all’ in it (‘deeds’, ‘figures’, ‘things’) will hang together in one subtle system as forms of ‘translated’ discourse, together signalling the presence of an underlying Idea or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0d91.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
