<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PE1404.R494 1998</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English language</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Language and culture</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">English-speaking countries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English language</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Language and languages</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Knowledge, Theory of</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Rhetoric in an Antifoundational World</book-title>
         <subtitle>Language, Culture, and Pedagogy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bernard-Donals</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Glejzer</surname>
               <given-names>Richard R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>1998</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300070224</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0300070225</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300146578</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0300146574</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>new haven; london</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1998</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt32bdzr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this brilliant collection, literary scholars, philosophers, and teachers inquire into the connections between antifoundational philosophy and the rhetorical tradition. What happens to literary studies and theory when traditional philosophical foundations are disavowed? What happens to the study of teaching and writing when antifoundationalism is accepted? What strategies for human understanding are possible when the weaknesses of antifoundationalism are identified? This volume offers answers in classic essays by such thinkers as Richard Rorty, Terry Eagleton, and Stanley Fish, and in many new essays never published before.The contributors to this book explore the nexus of antifoundationalism and rhetoric, critique that nexus, and suggest a number of pedagogical and theoretical alternatives. The editors place these statements into a context that is both critical and evaluative, and they provide for voices that dissent from the antifoundational perspective and that connect specific, practical pedagogies to the broader philosophical statements. For those with an interest in rhetoric, philosophy, comparative literature, or the teaching of composition, this book sets forth a wealth of thought-provoking ideas.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="480"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bernard-Donals</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Glejzer</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an essay on antifoundationalism and the teaching of writing, Stanley Fish defined the term<italic>antifoundationalism</italic>as the assertion “that matters [of fact, truth, correctness, validity, and clarity] are intelligible and debatable only within the precincts of the contexts and situations or paradigms or communities that give them their local and changeable shape” (Fish 344). The foundations that had previously been assumed to be objective or neutral or value-free—for Fish, in this essay, the idea that language communicates real situations; for others, that we can have unmediated knowledge of historical events, or that we can move unproblematically between written</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fish</surname>
                           <given-names>Stanley</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Milton’s seventeenth-century readers this passage, introducing one of the more prominent of the fallen angels, would have been immediately recognizable as a brief but trenchant essay on the art and character of the rhetorician. Indeed in these few lines Milton has managed to gather and restate with great rhetorical force (a paradox of which more later) all of the traditional arguments against rhetoric. Even Belial’s gesture of rising is to the (negative) point: he catches the eye even before he begins to speak, just as Satan will in Book IX when he too raises himself and moves so that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Contingency of Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rorty</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>About two hundred years ago, the idea that truth was made rather than found began to take hold of the imagination of Europe. The French Revolution had shown that the whole vocabulary of social relations, and the whole spectrum of social institutions, could be replaced almost overnight. This precedent made Utopian politics the rule rather than the exception among intellectuals. Utopian politics sets aside questions about both the will of God and the nature of humanity and about dreams of creating a hitherto unknown form of society.</p>
                     <p>At about the same time, the Romantic poets were showing what happens when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A Short History of Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eagleton</surname>
                           <given-names>Terry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A political literary criticism is not the invention of marxists. On the contrary, it is one of the oldest, most venerable forms of literary criticism we know. The most widespread early criticism on historical record was not, in our sense, “aesthetic”: it was a mode of what we would now call “discourse theory,” devoted to analyzing the material effects of particular uses of language in particular social conjunctures. It was a highly elaborate theory of specific signifying practices—above all, of the discursive practices of the juridical, political, and religious apparatuses of the state. Its intention, quite consciously, was systematically</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Language Obscures Social Change</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eckford-Prossor</surname>
                           <given-names>Melanie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clifford</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Michel Foucault asserts the following, he presents us with a crucial problem:</p>
                     <p>Before the end of the eighteenth century, man did not exist—any more than the potency of life, the fecundity of labour or the historical density of language. He is a quite recent creature, which the demiurge of knowledge fabricated with its own hands less than two hundred years ago; but he has grown old so quickly that it has been only too easy to imagine that he had been waiting for thousands of years in the darkness for that moment of illumination in which he would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Toward a “Materialist” Rhetoric:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contingency, Constraint, and the Eighteenth-Century Crowd</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hill</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Walter Benjamin: or, Towards a Revolutionary Criticism</italic>, Terry Eagleton identifies two “epistemological options” which circumscribe the nettlesome encounter between antifoundationalist rhetoric and materialist critique. “Either the subject,” he writes, “is wholly on the ‘inside’ of its world of discourse, locked into its philosophico-grammatical forms, its very struggles to distantiate them ‘theoretically’ themselves the mere ruses of power and desire; or it can catapult itself free from this formation to a point of transcendental leverage from which it can discern absolute truth” (131). The terms<italic>transcendental, absolute</italic>, and<italic>free</italic>are, of course, meant as obvious caveats. Eagleton is trying here</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Decentered Subject of Feminism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Postfeminism and Thelma and Louise</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frost</surname>
                           <given-names>Linda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an end-of-the-year summary for 1991,<italic>U.S. News and World Report</italic>commented on the media debate surrounding that summer’s hit<italic>Thelma and Louise</italic>, noting that the film “may not have appealed to as many people as the producers hoped. In 1991, 36 percent of American women called themselves feminists, compared with 56 percent five years ago” (“Year” 100). Many film fans and commentators on popular culture, though, did not agree with this journalist’s description of the film as feminist. In fact, the polarized responses to the question, Is<italic>Thelma and Louise</italic>a feminist film? and the reports of those responses</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Habermas’s Rational-Critical Sphere and the Problem of Criteria</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roberts</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A recurrent issue in the study of public discourse is whether a public sphere might be so constituted as to be both free and liberatory: free in the sense that it would be perfectly inclusive; liberatory in that it would enable participants to identify and critique coercion in institutions. Jürgen Habermas’s lifelong project might best be understood as an attempt to define the characteristics of a sphere with both such qualities, as well as to argue the feasibility of attaining it. The recent translation of Habermas’s early book,<italic>The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere</italic>, is particularly important in this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Foundational Thuggery and a Rhetoric of Subsumption</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Farmer</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For some time now, Truth (with a capital<italic>T</italic>) has acquired a reputation as a fugitive of sorts, a runaway loose on the epistemological mean streets of the old neighborhood. According to a few who claim to have befriended Truth, what makes its capture so difficult is that Truth can assume any number of aliases and disguises, all of which provide it with an uncanny ability to elude those seeking its whereabouts. Occasionally, authorities report that the secret hiding places of Truth have, once and for all, been found out. But such reports, as everybody knows, are forever premature: Truth,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Hymes, Rorty, and the Social-Rhetorical Construction of Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert E.</given-names>
                           <suffix>III</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Today, yesterday, and tomorrow—it is 3:00 A.M. in the southern<italic>montana</italic>and lowlands of eastern Ecuador, in the tropical rain forests of the upper Amazon Basin. Inside a traditional Shuar house of palm and thatch, surrounded by the now-dark gardens of manioc and plantains and yams, set apart from any sort of village—living “concealed,” as the Indians sometimes call it—a Shuar father begins the day by instructing his children. This morning he is talking about “Takea and Hummingbird.”</p>
                     <p>“Of this Hummingbird long ago,” he tells his children,</p>
                     <p>who stole the fire from Takea</p>
                     <p>what was said of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>“Too Little Care”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Language, Politics, and Embodiment in the Life-World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spellmeyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Kurt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I think about the politics of speech and writing, I return again and again to the final scene in Akira Kurosawa’s movie<italic>Ran</italic>, or “chaos,” which contemplates, among many other things, the fragmentation of social life in postmodernity. Kurosawa shows us a man in the fading light, bent forward on his staff at the edge of an enormous cliff. This man, really a boy, cannot see that the sun is going down because he can no longer see anything, having lost his eyes in a dynastic struggle that left most of his family dead. Nor can he know that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>History and the Real</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shepherdson</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>292</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In spite of the difference between English and continental philosophy, there is a link between Michel Foucault and writers like Jonathan Swift, as there was between Nietzsche and Paul Rée: “The first impulse to publish something of my hypotheses concerning the<italic>origin</italic>of morality,” Nietzsche says, “was given to me by a clear, tidy, and shrewd—also precocious—little book in which I encountered for the first time an<italic>upside-down and perverse</italic>species of genealogical hypothesis, the genuinely English type …<italic>The Origin of the Moral Sensations</italic>; its author Dr. Paul Rée” (Nietzsche,<italic>Genealogy</italic>17–18, emphasis added). Taking this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>The Subject of Invention:</title>
                     <subtitle>Antifoundationalism and Medieval Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Glejzer</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>318</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past decade Medieval Studies has increasingly begun to question overtly the issues surrounding its object—the Middle Ages—in terms of methodology. The studies of Lee Patterson, Paul Zumthor, Norman Cantor, and others begin to consider the ways in which the Middle Ages are constructed as an a priori, where readings of medieval texts are grounded by particular<italic>inventions</italic>of the Middle Ages, to borrow Cantor’s title. Questions of medievalism have become central to the medievalist as a way to get outside particular methodological hermeticisms, outside contemporary foundations, whether they be New Critical (which is still very much</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Royal Road:</title>
                     <subtitle>Marxism and the Philosophy of Science</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sprinker</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is a consequent marxist view of the history and philosophy of science? Reference to Marx’s and Engels’s (or even Lenin’s) work will not yield a satisfactory answer, although certain signposts are evident. For example, there is the famous observation on method in the introduction to the<italic>Grundrisse</italic>, which argues that, contrary to the procedures adopted in classical economy, where the starting point for investigation is apparently concrete phenomena from which abstract theoretical descriptions are then derived, “the method of rising from the abstract to the concrete is the only way in which thought appropriates the concrete, reproduces it as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Beyond Antifoundationalism to Rhetorical Authority:</title>
                     <subtitle>Problems Defining “Cultural Literacy”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bizzell</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When students enter college, it soon becomes apparent that some of them are already comfortable with academic discourse, while other students seem quite unfamiliar with academic discourse and resistant to learning it. This state of affairs might not be considered a problem: the academy might simply expel those who do not share its discourse and welcome and reward those who do. Indeed, this is how the situation is handled in many schools today.</p>
                     <p>Many writing teachers, however, have not been satisfied with this response to the lack of a shared discourse. Many of us have felt that it is unfair,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Composition Studies and Cultural Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>Collapsing Boundaries</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Berlin</surname>
                           <given-names>James A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Calls for situating cultural studies, a radically different set of research and teaching practices, at the center of English studies have been frequent of late. These projects range from the liberal formulations of Jonathan Culler, Gerald Graff, and Robert Scholes to the frankly leftist proposals of Gayatri Spivak, Frank Lentricchia, Edward Said, and Fredric Jameson. Their common contention, admittedly within a dizzying range of differences, is that texts, both poetic and rhetorical, must be considered within the (variously defined) social context that produced them. Responses to texts, furthermore, must include the means for critiquing both text and context. For those</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>What We Need to Know about Writing and Reading, or Peter Elbow and Antifoundationalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gardiner</surname>
                           <given-names>Ellen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>411</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While the work of Peter Elbow has been a powerful force in composition studies, several composition theorists have been critical of the conservative political implications of Elbow’s pedagogy. James Berlin and Lester Faigley, for example, argue that Elbow’s theory “hides the social nature of language” (Faigley 531) and teaches students how to “to assert a private vision, a vision which, despite its uniqueness, finally represents humankind’s best nature” (Berlin 487). Theorists such as Patricia Bizzell have viewed Elbow as foundationalist because he believes, she argues, that students are capable of “learning to examine [their] beliefs in light of those advanced</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Teaching as a Test of Knowledge:</title>
                     <subtitle>Passion, Desire, and the Semblance of Truth in Teaching</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Metzger</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the end of the<italic>Protagoras</italic>, Socrates discovers that insofar as what we teach is knowledge we cannot teach it. The essential thrust of the<italic>Protagoras</italic>, as well as the<italic>Meno</italic>, is that if knowledge is particular, teaching cannot be and if teaching is particular, knowledge cannot be. In the<italic>Meno</italic>, Socrates asks what virtue is, and Meno insists on teaching him about virtue by examples. Socrates tells him that such teaching will not do; Socrates wishes to know what virtue is. Then Meno tells him how to be virtuous by acting virtuously. Socrates insists that Meno has not yet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Composition in an Antifoundational World:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Critique and a Proposal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bernard-Donals</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>436</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1982 Maxine Hairston wrote an essay that suggested the field of rhetoric and composition studies was undergoing a revolutionary change the likes of which Thomas Kuhn noticed occurring in the natural sciences (Hairston, “Winds of Change” 76–77). That essay is less notable for its assertion that composition studies was undergoing vast change than it is for its invocation of Kuhn. Three years earlier, Patricia Bizzell had written an article noting a similar shift in English studies, one closer to the spirit of Kuhnian paradigm shifts, suggesting that without foundations, students run the risk of thinking that all knowledge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32bdzr.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>457</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
