<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3537.T4753Z7682 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Stevens, Wallace, 1879–1955</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888–1965</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Humanism in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization, Western, in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Modern Dilemma</book-title>
         <subtitle>Wallace Stevens, T.S. Eliot, and Humanism</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SURETTE</surname>
               <given-names>LEON</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773533639</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773575059</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt809f7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Where Eliot's poetry is dominated by cultural, religious, and philosophical anxiety, Stevens' is bright, witty, and playful - and commonly dismissed as superficial. Surette demonstrates the seriousness of Stevens' life-long engagement with the modern dilemma of disbelief, showing that he, like Eliot, rejected the Humanist resolution. Surette proceeds by juxtaposing the two poets' responses in poetry and prose to the same texts and events: Marianne Moore's poetry, the Great War, Humanists and anti-Humanists, the Franco-Mexican Humanist Ramon Fernandez, Pure Poetry, and, finally, the gathering war clouds of the late 1930s.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="430"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Preface]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A comparative study of Wallace Stevens and T.S. Eliot might be seen as an unpromising enterprise since one of the most notable things about the relationship between them is that it was virtually non-existent. When William Van O’Connor claimed in<italic>The Shaping Spirit</italic>that Stevens knew Eliot “only slightly and principally through correspondence,” Stevens took the trouble to write to him: “As a matter of fact, I don’t know him at all and have had no correspondence whatever with him ... All I knew about him in the days of<italic>Others</italic>was the correspondence between him and the people who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A Modernist Poetic:</title>
                     <subtitle>Marianne Moore, Wallace Stevens, and T.S. Eliot</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Until postmodern revisionism altered our perception of modernist poetry, the consensus was that modernism represented an essentially stylistic revolution: an abandonment of the vague, suggestive, and mellifluous verse of the Aesthetes for a direct, ironic, and spare verse style. Eliot, of course, was seen to be the principal architect of this change, with some assistance from Pound and his Imagist movement. Stevens’ marginalization was in considerable part a consequence of his failure to participate in this stylistic shift, because of his persistence in a mode more compatible with the Aesthetes or the Symbolists, who preceded them. Marianne Moore is seldom</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Eliot and Humanism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Charles Maurras, J.M. Robertson, and Bertrand Russell</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eliot was such an indomitable warrior in the battles against Humanism conducted in the pages of the<italic>Criterion</italic>and Middleton Murry’s<italic>Athenaeum</italic>that his brief infatuation with that alternative to Christianity has been largely overlooked. Stevens, on the other hand, is widely assumed — and not without reason — to have adhered to Humanist ideas despite his statements to the contrary. It is certainly true that both poets lived and breathed in an intellectual climate in which Humanism was the most appealing option for those who had lost their religious faith but balked at the bleak prospect of social Darwinism or Socialism/</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Writing Poetry in a Time of War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the beginning of the previous chapter I postponed examination of Eliot’s and Stevens’ poetry of the First World War years until I had examined the evidence in Eliot’s prose and correspondence supporting my contention that in those years Eliot adopted – at least provisionally – a Humanist hostility toward religious belief. There was no necessity to demonstrate the same for Stevens, since it is widely assumed that his view of religion was essentially that of a Humanist – that religious beliefs are fantasies or fictions. In this chapter I examine the poems written and published by both poets before, during, and after</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Rethinking Western Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eliot regretted the failure of the belief that had permeated European and American culture, but he did not evidently share Stevens’ distaste for having “to think all these things over,” and persisted in a search for an unqualified belief. Like many converts, once baptized, Eliot led a much more pious and dutiful religious life than most of his fellow Anglicans. He apparently needed a degree of certainty that, as he told Montgomery Belgion,¹ his study of Bradley had not provided.</p>
                     <p>Early in 1940 Belgion sent Eliot an article on the philosophy of the Harvard philosopher Harold Joachim that prompted Eliot</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Eliot, Stevens, and “Pale Ramon” Fernandez</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like Eliot, Stevens flirted with Humanism as a response to the modern dilemma, and like him he found it wanting. As we have seen, poems like “Sunday Morning,” “Le Monocle de Mon Oncle,” and “The Comedian as the Letter C” express a disbelief characteristic of Humanism. The nearest thing to an admission that he was once attracted to Humanism is Stevens’ remark on his disaffection with Arnold in the letter of June 1953 to Barbara Church, cited above. Referring to Arnold’s Humanism, he remarked: “Anyhow, it may be that I don’t belong to that church anymore, or that I don’t</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Function of Poetry:</title>
                     <subtitle>The “Pure Poetry” Debate</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A middle position between orthodox religious belief and the secular Humanism that Russell preached can be found in the now largely forgotten “pure poetry” movement, which had its brief<italic>floruit</italic>at about the same time that Marianne Moore’s<italic>Selected Poems</italic>and Stevens’<italic>Ideas of Order</italic>were published. Because it has had little influence on the practice or the reception of poetry in English, it has not attracted much attention in English and American literary studies. Nonetheless, Stevens scholars have taken due notice of Stevens’ declaration on the dust jacket for the second edition of<italic>Ideas of Order</italic>(Knopf 1936) that it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Avoiding the Abyss:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ash-Wednesday and “The Man with the Blue Guitar”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is frustrating that Eliot nowhere gave any indication of why he had no interest in Stevens’ poetry. Since we have seen him admitting to taking pleasure in Valéry’s poetry despite disapproving its lack of content, and since he confessed in his contribution to the<italic>Trinity Review</italic>that he liked Stevens’ poetry “so much,” we can surmise that it was not Stevens’ manner or style that occasioned his lack of interest, but rather the substance or themes of his poetry. That circumstance did not prevent Eliot from commenting at considerable length on Valéry’s poetry, carefully articulating the ground for his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I was initially prompted to undertake this comparative study of Wallace Stevens and T.S. Eliot by the fact that two men of such similar background, and of comparable achievement in the field of letters, had avoided any sort of relationship, and even much comment on the work and accomplishments of one another. Given the considerable fame of both men, the avoidance had to be deliberate, and if deliberate, it must have had a discoverable motivation.</p>
                     <p>The motivation I found was their contrasting resolutions of the dilemma of the modern: how to write poetry after the “death of God.” As Stevens</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Consulted</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt809f7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
