<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Insights from Performance Criticism</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Perry</surname>
               <given-names>Peter S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>series editor</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>POWELL</surname>
               <given-names>MARK ALLAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506400167</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506400167</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506401126</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506401120</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c84g4c"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Peter S. Perry describes the rise of performance criticism and its application to biblical studies and theology. He discusses the new understanding of biblical texts, particularly Gospel writings, that performance criticism has proposed and presents challenges for the future of performance criticism and its role in biblical interpretation generally.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powell</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark Allan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“<italic>What does this mean</italic>?”</p>
                     <p>That is, perhaps, the most-asked question with regard to the Bible. What does this verse mean? What does this story mean? What does this psalm or letter or prophecy or promise or commandment mean?</p>
                     <p>The question can arise from a simple desire for information, or the concern may be one of context or relevance: What<italic>did</italic>this mean to its original audience? What<italic>does</italic>it mean for us today?</p>
                     <p>Someone has said that understanding the Bible is difficult not because meaning is hard to find but because it is so abundant. The problem for interpreters is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Performed Text</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Biblical Performance Criticism is a way of understanding the Bible. It is the result of many streams of thought meeting over the last century, including form criticism, oral-tradition studies, rhetorical criticism, narrative criticism, memory studies, media studies, and performance studies. In some way, each of these streams analyzes four elements: (1) someone speaking, (2) someone hearing, (3) a text, and (4) a social situation. Each has contributed to the understanding that the Bible should be read in terms of the interaction of those four elements rather than any one of them in isolation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Form criticism</italic>, developed at the end of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>What Is Biblical Performance Criticism?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To describe biblical performance criticism, I start by explaining how human beings communicate. Performance criticism analyzes and practices certain kinds of communication, specifically repeated behaviors for an audience. Inquiry, imagination, and intervention are three aspects of a performance and its analysis. Biblical performance criticism is the analysis and practice of performances of biblical traditions. The basic method of biblical performance criticism is to prepare, internalize, and perform a biblical text. Although it may make it sound like a step-by-step process, performance criticism is really more circular and interrelated, like nodes on a network that influence each other rather than a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Performing Habakkuk</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The basic method of performance criticism is<italic>prepare, internalize</italic>, and<italic>perform</italic>. These three steps roughly correlate to the three aspects of performance:<italic>inquiry, imagination</italic>, and<italic>intervention</italic>. As I demonstrate below, however, preparation requires not only inquiry but also imagination and intervention. Internalization is not only an act of imagination but also depends on inquiry and intervention. The performance itself integrates inquiry, imagination, and intervention into one experience for performer and audience.</p>
                     <p>I have chosen Habakkuk as the first example to illustrate the method and payoff of performance criticism. My translation and analysis is based on Jeanette Mathews’s book,<italic>Performing Habakkuk:</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Performing Revelation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The book of Revelation has long captivated the imagination with vivid images, colors, sounds, and drama.¹ It has moved artists to create paintings, music, and sculpture. People have used it to speculate on the timing of cosmic events and to identify enemies of God. For better and, sometimes, for worse, the book of Revelation has been performed for many audiences and has influenced<italic>culture, power relationships</italic>, and<italic>identity</italic>since its first performances in first-century Asia Minor, what we now call western Turkey.</p>
                     <p>The book of Revelation identifies itself as at least three things: a<italic>letter</italic>written by a Christian prophet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Ten Insights from Performance Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By preparing, internalizing, and performing texts, I have been given many insights into the texts themselves, the impact they have on audiences, and how biblical studies can change to better address how traditions were transmitted in ancient times and how they function in modern times. Of the many insights that could be chosen, here are my top ten.</p>
                     <p>While it is too strong to say that “the medium is the message,” the medium matters. Whether one is communicating face to face or via letter or inscription, the medium enables some possibilities while restricting others. A particular medium is enmeshed in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Conclusions, Challenges, and Considerations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>They are performers with texts and audiences in concrete situations. The father sits with his son practicing commandments. The reader opens the book and occasionally looks up at the group as she reads. The storyteller sits with others in a circle sharing a well-known tale. The leader reminds the group of their founder’s words and draws out new implications for their situation. The scribe explains what the law means for the people assembled. The song leader guides the rehearsal of a choir. The group follows the script of the annual gathering. A scholar reads her paper that analyzes the nuances</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix A:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Translation of Habakkuk for Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix B:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Translation of Revelation 17–19 for Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g4c.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
