<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Literary visions of multicultural Ireland</book-title>
         <subtitle>The immigrant in contemporary Irish literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Villar-Argáiz</surname>
               <given-names>Pilar</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781784992118</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1784992119</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Manchester University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1mf6zgx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first full-length monograph to address the impact that Celtic-Tiger immigration has exerted on the poetry, drama and fiction of contemporary Irish writersNow available in paperback, this pioneering collection of essays deals with the topic of how Irish literature responds to the presence of non-Irish immigrants in Celtic-Tiger and post-Celtic-Tiger Ireland. The book assembles an international group of 18 leading and prestigious academics in the field of Irish studies from both sides of the Atlantic, including Declan Kiberd, Anne Fogarty and Maureen T. Reddy, amongst others. Key areas of discussion are: what does it mean to be ‘multicultural’ and what are the implications of this condition for contemporary Irish writers? How has literature in Ireland responded to inward migration? Have Irish writers reflected in their work (either explicitly or implicitly) the existence of migrant communities in Ireland? If so, are elements of Irish traditional culture and community maintained or transformed? What is the social and political efficacy of these intercultural artistic visions?</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword:</title>
                     <subtitle>the worlding of Irish writing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kiberd</surname>
                           <given-names>Declan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There has been much talk in recent years of the worlding of Irish writing, in line with the proclamation of Ireland’s as one of the most globalised economies in Europe. But it’s not at all clear just how worlded Irish writing now is. Certainly, more writers are living abroad and writing about overseas life than were doing so in, say, 1990. The decade which followed that year was one in which Irishness became sexy, as people used Celtic pubs, the memoirs of Frank McCourt or the spectacle of Riverdance to connect with their inner Paddy.</p>
                     <p>That was, of course, a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Villar-Argáiz</surname>
                           <given-names>Pilar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xviii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>the immigrant in contemporary Irish literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Villar-Argáiz</surname>
                           <given-names>Pilar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Ireland became part of the European Union in 1973, the country entered a new phase of rapid social, political, and economic transformation. This radical change was perceived at all levels of Irish life. Ireland’s gradual transformation from a predominantly agricultural economy to a hi-tech multinational one was simultaneously accompanied by other influential events such as the rise and success of the women’s movement, the shrinking influence of the Catholic Church, and noteworthy political achievements in the North such as the 1998 Good Friday Agreement. New descriptions were needed for identifying this fresh and almost unrecognisable Ireland which was emerging.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>White Irish-born male playwrights and the immigrant experience onstage</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McIvor</surname>
                           <given-names>Charlotte</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Donal O’Kelly’s<italic>Asylum! Asylum!</italic>premiered in 1994 on the Abbey Theatre’s Peacock stage and was the first play by an Irish-born playwright to directly address the issue of racism and immigration in Celtic Tiger Ireland. O’Kelly represented the vanguard of a group of white Irish-born male playwrights including Charlie O’Neill, Declan Gorman, Dermot Bolger, Roddy Doyle, Jim O’Hanlon, Paul Meade, and Paul Kennedy who would deal with these issues head-on in their work throughout the 1990s and 2000s. In the context of an Irish theatre scene criticised by Jason King and George Seremba among others for being largely silent about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Strangers in a strange land?:</title>
                     <subtitle>the new Irish multicultural fiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tucker</surname>
                           <given-names>Amanda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his seminal essay ‘Imaginary Homelands’, Salman Rushdie describes how, at a conference on modern writing, novelists struggled to articulate the purpose of their artform. After these (unnamed) fiction writers outlined the need for ‘new ways of describing the world’, another participant suggested that this objective might be limited. Rushdie argues that description is in fact political and, moreover, that ‘redescribing the world is the necessary first step in changing it’ (Rushdie, 1991: 13). He is particularly interested in how fictional representations might lead to systemic change and sets creative perspectives against official, government-sanctioned points of view: ‘at times when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>‘A nation of Others’:</title>
                     <subtitle>the immigrant in contemporary Irish poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Villar-Argáiz</surname>
                           <given-names>Pilar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The changing face of Irish society and the new influx of immigration during the economic boom of the country have compelled Irish poets to rethink nationhood intersectionally, as modulated by race and ethnicity. Depictions of ethnic migrant communities in Ireland have appeared in the work of poets since the early 1990s. Eithne Strong, for instance, dealt with this topic in her poems ‘Let Live’, about the emotional impact the Indian community has on the native Irish population with its ‘oddness’ and ‘alternative culture’ (1993: 75–6), and ‘Woad and Olive’, which reflects on the difficulty of ‘harmonious coexistence’ among different</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Immigration in Celtic Tiger and post-Celtic Tiger novels</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Estévez-Saá</surname>
                           <given-names>Margarita</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of Ireland and of the Irish is full of stories of deprival, to the extent that they were, for a long time, divested of houses, estates, land, country, and nation, and forced to emigrate. Irish literature, inevitably, has bore witness to this history of deprivation recreating it once and again in an attempt to overcome that trauma, by means of the transformation, reorientation, or re-evaluation of the experience of loss (Balaev, 2008: 164). Recent examples by representative writers of the Irish literary scene are, among others, Joseph O’Connor (<italic>Redemption Falls</italic>, 2008), Colm Toíbín (<italic>Brooklyn</italic>, 2009), and Sebastian Barry</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>‘Who is Irish?’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Roddy Doyle’s hyphenated identities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>White</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva Roa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a result of its Celtic Tiger brief economic boom, Ireland has experienced a significant increase in inward migration. With the new influx of immigrants comes the necessity to pose the question ‘Who is Irish?’ In an effort to answer this question, Roddy Doyle, the only one of his siblings who did not emigrate, recounts the change in the traditional relationship Ireland has had with the experience of immigration, now that the tables are turned and Ireland is playing the role of host country on a larger scale than ever before. The wave of inward migration of the 1990s seems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>‘Our identity is our own instability’:</title>
                     <subtitle>intercultural exchanges and the redefinition of identity in Hugo Hamilton’s Disguise and Hand in the Fire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Llena</surname>
                           <given-names>Carmen Zamorano</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1995 the then President of Ireland Mary Robinson gave an address entitled ‘Cherishing the Irish diaspora’ to the Houses of the Oireachtas in order to commemorate the 150<sup>th</sup>anniversary of the beginning of the Great Irish Famine. This historical event, which has been reworked as one of the founding traumas of the Irish nation, also marked a dramatic increase in the Irish exodus that made Ireland the only country in Europe to experience a decline in population growth in the second half of the nineteenth century (Kuhling and Keohane, 2007: 53). Significantly, Mary Robinson’s speech did not delve into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>‘Many and terrible are the roads to home’:</title>
                     <subtitle>representations of the immigrant in the contemporary Irish short story</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fogarty</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Fox, Swallow, Scarecrow</italic>by Éilís Ní Dhuibhne (2007), Leo Kavanagh, the idealistic but struggling director of a small Irish-language press, muses about his most recent literary discovery. He dreams of the plaudits that await a volume of poems by Kambele Ngole, who is to the best of his knowledge the first black woman poet writing in Irish. The ethnic Otherness of this first-time author along with her gender, he conjectures, will be enticing selling points. Ní Dhuibhne’s novel, which deftly skewers literary culture in Ireland during the Celtic Tiger period, exposes this dream of literary success to be an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Writing the ‘new Irish’ into Ireland’s old narratives:</title>
                     <subtitle>the poetry of Sinéad Morrissey, Leontia Flynn, Mary O’Malley, and Michael Hayes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Poloczek</surname>
                           <given-names>Katarzyna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a relatively recent development that, as Tom Inglis notices, there have been more people arriving in Ireland than leaving the island, transforming the country into ‘a multi-racial, multi-ethnic, multi-religious culture’ (Inglis, 2008: 86). The progression of those changes has been so immense that even the Irish-born citizens returning to their country after years of living abroad look at the new Ireland with astonishment:</p>
                     <p>It’s a startling new Ireland, but why shouldn’t it be? I myself left the best part of twenty years ago and the finest thing about coming home is the rawness and the newness. I dislike</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>‘Marooned men in foreign cities’:</title>
                     <subtitle>encounters with the Other in Dermot Bolger’s The Ballymun Trilogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Murphy</surname>
                           <given-names>Paula</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Townlands of Brazil</italic>, the second play in Dermot Bolger’s<italic>The Ballymun Trilogy</italic>, multiculturalism in Ireland is explored by focusing on the small community of Ballymun, in Dublin city. The first act takes place in the 1960s and explores the fate of an unmarried pregnant woman, Eileen, who escapes having to give up her baby for adoption by fleeing to England. Her experience of being an emigrant in a foreign city echoes that of her baby’s father, Michael. Eileen and he met and conceived their child while he was at home in Ireland on holiday from his job in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>‘Like a foreigner / in my native land’:</title>
                     <subtitle>transculturality and Otherness in twenty-first-century Irish poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schrage-Früh</surname>
                           <given-names>Michaela</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ireland in the Celtic Tiger years saw an unprecedented influx of ethnically diverse migrants to a nation formerly perceived as comparatively monocultural. Sketching the two dominant representations of post-Celtic Tiger multiculturalism, Amanda Tucker notes that the first of these ‘emphasizes that fear and hostility continue to characterize Irish responses to inward migration since the Gaelic Catholic monolith remains’ at the heart of twenty-first-century Irish identity, thus reinforcing ‘the idea of Ireland as a monocultural rather than multicultural society’ (Tucker, 2010: 107).¹ The second type of response claims that, despite the legal situation of immigrants, Ireland is a country traditionally open</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Irish multicultural epiphanies:</title>
                     <subtitle>modernity and the recuperation of migrant memory in the writing of Hugo Hamilton</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>King</surname>
                           <given-names>Jason</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the height of the Irish economic boom on St. Patrick’s Day 2007, the<italic>Irish Times</italic>editorialised that ‘we are all the speckled people today. Confident, wealthy, forward-looking, internationalist, we can afford to define our identity in terms that celebrate our overlapping multiplicity of allegiances and diversity’ (Anon., 2007). In its allusion to Hugo Hamilton’s memoir<italic>The Speckled People</italic>(2003), the newspaper envisioned the author as the embodiment of a culturally diverse, inclusive, modern Irish nation. Its emphasis on the affordability of a more fluid and plural form of identity was obviously short-sighted in light of Ireland’s subsequent economic collapse,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Parts:</title>
                     <subtitle>whiskey, tea, and sympathy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Donnell</surname>
                           <given-names>Katherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a history of Irish empathy for black people. It can be argued that a key component in the construction of Irish political and cultural identity is the practice of emotion of ‘feeling with’ and standing in the same place with black Others. From the end of the eighteenth century we can see the articulation of Irish national identity being formulated (at least partially if not centrally) in terms of an ability to share in and hence represent the political and cultural sufferings and triumphs of the racialised Other. The location and ethnic identity of these Others fluctuates over</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Hospitality and hauteur:</title>
                     <subtitle>tourism, cross-cultural space, and ethics in Irish poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Armstrong</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles I.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tourism tends to be observed as an indispensable but regrettable epiphenomenon. For many states it provides a major source of income, facilitating commerce and jobs that make up an important part of the national economy. At the same time, there is a tendency to see tourism as involving a pernicious commodification of space, culture, and people’s lives in general. Common conceptions of tourism tend to circle around cliché and stereotype. In an increasingly globalised economy, tourism is seen as bringing with it particularly reductive and restrictive forms of interaction across national and cultural borders. Relatedly, it is interpreted as being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Towards a multiracial Ireland:</title>
                     <subtitle>Black Baby’s revision of Irish motherhood</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reddy</surname>
                           <given-names>Maureen T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the late 1980s, when Clare Boylan wrote<italic>Black Baby</italic>, few Irish thinkers were writing about race or about the role of race in Irishness and therefore in ideas of womanhood (and motherhood) in Ireland. Race remained transparent in prevailing definitions of Irishness until open expressions of racism pushed it into visibility in conjunction with the first wave of African immigration in the 1990s. Public debates on the 2004 Citizenship Referendum, disturbing as they often were, had the salubrious effect of making clear that one crucial task of Irish writers and cultural theorists in the twenty-first century is to rethink</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Beginning history again:</title>
                     <subtitle>gendering the foreigner in Emer Martin’s Baby Zero</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Balzano</surname>
                           <given-names>Wanda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Ireland, especially in the post-Celtic Tiger era, we are witnessing a radical move toward a new historicity and a new feminism. It is almost as if we were given the chance to record time on a new scale and thereby, still resisting patriarchal and capitalistic systems, begin history again, starting from zero. As Alice A. Jardine had anticipated over two decades ago in her ground-breaking critical study<italic>Gynesis: Configurations of Woman and Modernity</italic>, the master narratives of history, religion, and philosophy at the turn of the millennium have been placed under close scrutiny, while what was left out of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>‘Goodnight and joy be with you all’:</title>
                     <subtitle>tales of contemporary Dublin city life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Salis</surname>
                           <given-names>Loredana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tales of Dublin city life are a significant feature of Irish literature and drama. From Joyce’s<italic>Dubliners</italic>to plays by Seán O’Casey, Brendan Behan, Hugh Leonard, Bernard Farrell, and, more recently, Conor McPherson and Mark O’Rowe, Dublin and its people have definitely been the protagonists of many a story. In the 1990s, Ireland’s capital city became the epicentre of a large-scale transformation, which affected both its geographical and cultural landscapes, and which was inevitably reflected in theatre productions. ‘Dublin itself ’ – as Keating put it in the<italic>Irish Times</italic>– ‘became a stage again’ (2010: 5). This study focuses</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Mean streets, new lives:</title>
                     <subtitle>the representations of non-Irish immigrants in recent Irish crime fiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clark</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most interesting phenomena to appear in Irish literature since the late 1990s has been the rise of ‘homegrown’ crime fiction. Irish crime narrative has been strong, historically, as a sub-genre, but until the 1990s had largely been concerned with the representation of fictional crime in non-Irish settings, usually the US or the UK. Since the period immediately prior to the economic boom commonly known as the Celtic Tiger, however, a number of circumstances have given rise to a situation in which, for the first time, Irish readers are demanding novels and other narratives which portray Irish crime</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf6zgx.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
