<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442696907</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS8061.B43 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Experimental</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Avant-Garde Canadian Literature</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Early Manifestations</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BETTS</surname>
               <given-names>GREGORY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781442643772</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442696907</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442696907"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Avant-Garde Canadian Literature</italic>offers an entrance into the vocabulary of the ongoing and primarily international debate surrounding the idea of avant-gardism, providing readers with a functional vocabulary for discussing some of the most hermetic and yet energetic literature ever produced in this country.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="328"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1927, Europe and America’s avant-garde arrived in Toronto for a month-long exhibition of the strangest, most disturbing, most bizarre, and most exciting visual art being made anywhere in the Western world. The show included hundreds of works by 106 active, contemporary artists from twenty-three different countries, including work by cubists such as Pablo Picasso, Alexander Archipenko, Georges Braque, and Fernand Léger; Futurists like Wassily Kandinsky, Umberto Boccioni, and Joseph Stella; Dadaists like Marcel Duchamp, Kurt Schwitters, and Francis Picabia; Surrealists like Max Ernst, Hans Arp, and Joan Miró; and other avant-garde experimentalists like Joseph Albers, Paul Klee, and Piet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Theory of the Avant-Gardes in Canada</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of the term ‘avant-garde’ in Europe has been thoroughly documented by various continental scholars with no substantial disagreements about the early development and uses of the term.¹ The idea of an avant-garde was first coined in fifteenth-century France to describe the military unit at the fore of the army – the avant-garde was the group that defended the country and all it represented, and that, upon successful defence, pushed forth into new territory. The avant-garde used violence to protect and enlarge a nation’s territorial holdings. From this militaristic and nationalistic root, the term avant-garde transitioned from a literal implication</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>The Cosmic Canadians</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first node of Canadian aesthetic avant-garde activity began in smalltown Ontario at the turn of the century – in a period and geography that too many scholars hasten over, tripping to reach the urban promontory of modernism. Though there were substantial precursors to the moment, and certainly diverse coexistent influences, the landmark publication that begat the Cosmic Canadians was Dr Richard Maurice Bucke’s 1901 treatise<italic>Cosmic Consciousness: A Study in the Evolution of the Human Mind</italic>. In his book, Bucke – a distinguished psychologist (née alienist) in London, Ontario – unleashed a Futurist’s vision of human experience after a revolutionary transformation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Canadian Surrealism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Automatists</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Situated somewhere between the Cosmic Canadian pursuit of a postcolonial Canadian art through spiritualized abstraction and the<italic>TISH</italic>realization of a postcolonial Canadian geopoetics is another group of artists who worked with the explicit ambition of liberating art and, by doing so, revolutionizing their society. The Automatists of Montreal are the most celebrated and recognizable avant-garde movement in Canada’s history. All of the hallmarks of canonical avant-garde behaviour are present: they self-identified as a group, performed or exhibited as representatives of the group, wrote manifestos that sought to articulate the aesthetic ambitions of the collective, and produced work with radically</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Canadian Vorticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The final topic of this discourse concerns the smallest, least developed, yet conversely most internationally recognized collection of Canada’s early avant-gardists. There were only a handful of Canadian artists directly influenced by Vorticism, the English avant-garde movement, but three of the four that I will focus on here are among our most celebrated and distinguished writers: Marshall McLuhan, the internationally acclaimed theorist and media critic; Sheila Watson, the celebrated novelist and short-story writer; and Wilfred Watson, the award-winning poet and playwright. Vorticism is a notoriously difficult concept to pin down (William Wees quotes one of its participants Helen Saunders declaring</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>L’Envoi:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Future of the Avant</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The early avant-garde in Canada responded to the arrival of foreign cultural models at first by learning and imitating but eventually by translating cultural practices into the Canadian context. The Cosmic Canadians borrowed European models of idealism, occultism, and mysticism, as well as American models of transcendental idealism and poetic form, but developed these influences into a distinctly Canadian r/evolutionary node. The cultural products that emerged from this Anschauung remain marked by idealism, occultism, and mysticism, but became something else, something entirely new, as they colluded with the rising national spirit, the ideas of Richard Maurice Bucke, the general North</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442696907.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
