<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC261 M47W48 1988</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Merleau-Ponty, Maurice, 1908–1961</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Views on political science</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Merleau-Ponty and the Foundation of Existential Politics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Whiteside</surname>
               <given-names>Kerry H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400859733</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400859735</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1988</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7ztzb8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Drawing on previously unexplored sources, Kerry H. Whiteside presents the political theory of Maurice Merleau-Ponty (1908-1961), one of France's best-known twentieth-century philosophers. Whiteside argues that Merleau-Ponty's objective in his political writings was to make existentialism into the foundation for a philosophically consistent mode of political thinking. This study discusses the inadequacies Merleau-Ponty found in the traditional philosophies of empiricism and idealism, and then examines the subject-object dualism that he believed deprived previous forms of existentialism of political significance.</p>
         <p>Whiteside shows how Merleau-Ponty overcame these problems by grounding political reasoning in a theory of consciousness that emphasized both its individuality and its need for socially created meaning. After explaining Merleau-Ponty's modifications of the views of Sartre, Aron, and others, the book investigates how he applied his political theory in editorial exchanges with Communists and liberals. Throughout this study, Whiteside traces and criticizes the changes in the philosopher's concept of Marxism and points to his many ideas that bear on current controversies in political theory.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1988.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS AND SOURCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his first essay published after the liberation of France, Maurice Merleau-Ponty described with chagrin the facile reasoning with which he had once discounted political affairs. “Before the war,” he wrote, “politics seemed to us<italic>unthinkable</italic>because it is a statistical treatment of men, and it makes no sense, we thought, to treat these singular beings . . . as if they were a collection of substitutable objects” (SNS 255, tr. 145, emphasis added). Six years of destruction, foreign occupation, and resistance had shown how vital it was to overcome such naiveté. Making politics “thinkable” was the most urgent problem</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>FIRST ESSAYS:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE INTERSECTION OF PHILOSOPHY AND POLITICS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between 1925 and 1945 French philosophy underwent far-reaching changes in style, in the canon of authors it studied, in the subject matter it deemed worthy of attention. Merleau-Ponty’s primary thesis for his<italic>doctorat d’Etat</italic>included, for example, a chapter on “The Body as a Sexed Being.” His adviser, Émile Bréhier, a philosopher of apparently traditional sensibilities, was taken aback. Bréhier asked him if he could make this chapter a trifle more discreet; Merleau-Ponty promised that this suggestion would receive the thoughtful consideration it deserved. A week later he announced his decision: Alas, he could not change a single word.¹ Even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>PHENOMENOLOGY AS A PROLEGOMENON TO POLITICAL THEORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the mid-1930s the quality of results on the<italic>agrégation</italic>examination at the ENS had declined noticeably in relation to previous years. A meeting was called to discuss the problem, and Merleau-Ponty, then a tutor for candidates for the exam, gave an acute diagnosis. The variability in results was due, he maintained, to a shift in the focus and breadth of philosophical interests among the students. After explaining their almost unanimous rejection of empiricism, he described the direction of their research—in terms that applied equally well to his own. “Once the mind’s activity in constructing the sciences has been</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>COLLECTIVE MEANING:</title>
                     <subtitle>POLITICS AND VIOLENCE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Sartre first applied his existential ontology to political questions, the Marxist theorist Henri Lefebvre chided him for posing “the human problem” as “an individual question, abstract and theoretical.” This was in sorry contrast to Marxism, which sees man’s social condition as “a problem of action founded on objective knowledge.”¹ Merleau-Ponty, coming to Sartre’s defense, was suspicious of this Marxism that refused to “tarry over the task of describing being and of founding the existence of other people” (SNS 134, tr. 77). His use of “founding” suggests that political theory starts not by assuming that man’s nature is social, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>VALUES IN AN EXISTENTIAL PHILOSOPHY OF HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“We have learned history and we claim that we must not forget it” (SNS 265, tr. 150). This is the most profound lesson that war taught French philosophy. Its violence exposed the hidden dependency of every way of life—economic, religious, artistic, philosophical—on a political sphere whose practices and disorders accumulate meaning almost imperceptibly over generations. If violence is not to rule public life, each domain must become aware of this dependency and alter itself to accommodate “history.” Even philosophers must learn to<italic>think</italic>differently—to become sensitive to the historicity of ideas, to foresee impending changes in political</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>MARXISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE RADICAL HYPOTHESIS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his critique of Kantian-liberal politics Merleau-Ponty contends that there is a chronic divergence between the universal values that liberals preach and the self-interested values incarnated in the bourgeois way of life. Yet the precedence of lived values over verbal ones need not destroy all hopes for a more humanistic society. It is conceivable that a different class might exist whose incarnated values are not inherently self-serving. A class might exist that in its very existence stands a chance at actualizing the as yet only ideal claims of the liberal tradition. The symmetrical solution to the problem of a class</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>PRINCIPLES AND PREJUDICE IN LIBERALISM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In September 1944 Sartre and Merleau-Ponty brought together the editorial committee for a new journal.¹ Its title,<italic>Les Temps Modernes (Modern Times),</italic>was a sign that its journalism would be enmeshed in current affairs.² Merleau-Ponty stressed that a review “plays its role . . . by favoring a political awakening of consciousness.”³</p>
                     <p>Because of cold war tensions, this awakening required vigilance on two fronts.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Les Temps Modernes</italic>. . . battle[s] against the pathetic and prophetic spirit, every day more widespread, which requires blind choices and tortured commitments from our contemporaries. It is not true that the world is divided</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>THE COMMUNIST PROBLEM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marxism is not only a philosophy<italic>of</italic>history; it is a philosophy<italic>in</italic>history. Marx’s assertion of the unity of theory and praxis means that theoretical knowledge and practical change are inseparable. Understanding the workings of reality initiates a process that alters it, as when the proletariat’s “awakening of consciousness” changes it into a force for its own emancipation.¹</p>
                     <p>Theory inserts itself into this process of historical change through a pedagogical function: it brings its interpretation of reality to the working classes to catalyze those changes in outlook that will set in motion a revolutionary transformation of social structures. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>IN SEARCH OF MERLEAU-PONTY’S LATE POLITICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Adventures of the Dialectic,</italic>Merleau-Ponty explains how successive confrontations with the somber realities of the revolutionary experience finally forced him to call into question the guiding assumptions of his politics of the 1940s.</p>
                     <p>Could we continue to think, with all necessary reservations concerning the Soviet solutions, that the Marxist dialectic remained valid negatively and that history should be put into perspective, if not according to the proletariat’s power, at least according to its lack of it? We do not want to present as a syllogism what became clear to us gradually, in contact with events. But an event</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>POLITICS AND EXPRESSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The argument cannot be made that, having become liberal, Merleau-Ponty suddenly forgot what it meant to think politically. In<italic>The Adventures of the Dialectic</italic>he repeats once again the litany of requirements that he places on truly political thought: it begins with a probabilistic reading of events, it needs a philosophy of history, it treats people statistically, it aims at success (AD 239, 9, 226, 251, tr. 163, 3, 154, 172). Chastising Sartre for his notion of “pure action,” Merleau-Ponty reminds him that political actors cannot use the fact that history is “overflowing with meaning” to justify an arbitrary perspective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>THINKING POLITICS IN CONTEMPORARY THEORY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A convincing case for Merleau-Ponty’s importance to contemporary political theory could be made by documenting his direct impact on a variety of influential thinkers. Michel Foucault was his student at the Sorbonne and often used his teacher’s phenomenology as a foil in constructing his own archeology of the human sciences.¹ His inspiration is found in the social theories of Claude Lefort and Cornelius Castoriadis.² In the United States, a number of those interested in postbehavioral political inquiry gratefully acknowledge debts to Merleau-Ponty.³ And of course, Sartre’s understanding of history and class in the<italic>Critique of Dialectical Reason</italic>owes much to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzb8.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
