<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125wf1</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">cruz16400</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD181.7 .C77713 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political science</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>On the Difficulty of Living Together</book-title>
         <subtitle>Memory, Politics, and History</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cruz</surname>
               <given-names>Manuel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jacques</surname>
               <given-names>Richard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231541398</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231541392</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/cruz16400"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Manuel Cruz launches a nuanced study of memory and forgetting, defining their forms and uses, political meanings, and social and historical implications. Memory is not an intrinsically positive phenomenon, he argues, but an impressionable and malleable one, used to advance a variety of agendas. Cruz focuses on five memory models: that which is inherently valuable; that which legitimizes the present; that which supports retributive justice; that which is essential to mourning; and that which elicits renunciation or revelation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="176"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE TO THE ENGLISH EDITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Of Memory and Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the beginning was the body. At one end of the arc we find man as a species, at the other the<italic>self</italic>, the person, the social<italic>role</italic>, society now definitively stratified: the history of humanity is the history of that journey. In animal species the self only exists, at most, as sexual preening. What they have is a primitive sympathetic reaction, which sometimes occurs in man too, but only episodically. In animals, however, it is a way of being, a deep empathy through which an individual communicates with another member of his species, and maybe even with members of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Present Breathes Through History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The twentieth century tried to live bereft of the ideas that had accompanied humanity for a long time. God is dead, man is dead, matter has disappeared. It still seemed possible to continue to think. That roll call of absences was joined in the last years of the century by another, long known but silenced: history has ended. Perhaps now the question Ernest Renan posed in his<italic>Philosophical Dialogues and Fragments</italic>over a century ago has reached full meaning: “What will those who come after us live on?”</p>
                     <p>To more than one person that will sound like a terminal question</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>For an Urgent Typology of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The past has returned. And according to present indications, it looks as if it is back to stay. Following the postmodern apotheosis that criticized all of philosophy in its effort to turn any kind of history into pure metaphysical patter (that is, a sort of academic<italic>bullshit</italic>),¹ we seem to have arrived at a theoretical space of quite a different sort. Our present represents itself according to certain parameters that are undoubtedly quite different from those that exercised their hegemony just a few years ago.</p>
                     <p>Of all those parameters, one may deserve special attention in the present context thanks to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>We Need to Start Defending Ourselves from the Past</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More years ago than I care to think (time is always excessive for oneself), I ended a text with the kind of flat statement I was very attached to then: “To understand the present is to measure oneself against the past and to brave the future.”¹ Now I tend to think that they may have been fine words, but rather out of place. They may not have been a suitable way of concluding; they should rather have been a way of beginning to talk, of announcing a project, of starting to sketch out a task. Later, when I persevered with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>More About Traumas, Calamities, and Catastrophes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human action has always been a mystery, even for those who perform it. Beyond the obvious train of events, the monotonous and predictable taking of decisions (which is often no more than assuming one’s own destiny, what is given to us and what we can accommodate only with decorum),¹ on a very few exceptional occasions the dull cadence of action is interrupted and, with a flash of proof, with an almost luminous character of revelation, the agent is shown the emptiness of his existence, the irreparable hollowness of his existential becoming.</p>
                     <p>Such moments or occasions we could call<italic>experiences</italic>, meaning</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>By Way of an Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Future with Not Much Future (or About How the Perplexity of the Will Is Possible)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 2009 I embarked with enthusiasm on a reading of Ricardo Piglia’s novel<italic>Respiración artificial</italic>,¹ convinced that it was a debt I owed myself. I was sure that, after<italic>Plata quemada</italic>and<italic>Formas breves</italic>(the two last texts by the Argentine writer that had come into my hands), the moment had come to delve into what, for many people, is his best work. I did so, as I said at the beginning, fired with enthusiasm, not wishing to pay too much heed to certain small details that should at least have surprised (if not worried) me. And</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">cruz16400.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
