<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9dgg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HD7125.A775 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social security</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Government policy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Privatization</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social security individual investment accounts</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Invoking the Invisible Hand</book-title>
         <subtitle>Social Security and the Privatization Debates</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Asen</surname>
               <given-names>Robert</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>SERIES EDITOR</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Medhurst</surname>
               <given-names>Martin J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780870138430</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781609174996</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Michigan State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>East Lansing</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Robert Asen</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.14321/j.ctt16wd0hf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>In Invoking the Invisible</italic>Hand Robert Asen scrutinizes contemporary debates over proposals to privatize Social Security. Asen argues that a rights-based rhetoric employed by Social Security's original supporters enabled advocates of privatization to align their proposals with the widely held belief that Social Security functions simply as a return on a worker's contributions and that it is not, in fact, a social insurance program.By analyzing major debates over a preeminent American institution, Asen reveals the ways in which language is deployed to identify problems for public policy, craft policy solutions, and promote policies to the populace. He shows how debate participants seek to create favorable contexts for their preferred policies and how they connect these policies to idealized images of the nation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Market Reaches for Social Security</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this famous passage from<italic>The Wealth of Nations</italic>, Adam Smith employs a powerfully evocative metaphor that bursts through his prose to escape the confines of political economy and obtain the status of a common sense. Resonating across national contexts and historical eras, the metaphor of the “invisible hand” has spoken to many people as an intuitive description of how the world works and an unparalleled prescription for ethical individual action. The invisible hand artfully captures the spirit of a market ethics by insisting that in working for oneself, an individual works for the good of others. The invisible hand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Policy Polysemy and the 1935 Social Security Debates</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Americans know Social Security. They likely know it better than any other public policy. Whereas many policies appear distant from Americans’ everyday lives, seemingly addressed only to Washington insiders, Social Security touches ordinary citizens directly. For millions of Americans, Social Security has provided irreplaceable benefits to compensate for income lost through the tragic injury or death of a breadwinner. For millions more, Social Security has provided steady retirement benefits for oneself, a parent, or a grandparent, affirming, in the process, the honorific status of senior citizen. And virtually all Americans have experienced the rite of passage enacted by obtaining a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Competing Metaphors of Insurance and Investment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Privatization promised a policy revolution born in the legitimating discourses of Social Security. In this spirit, advocates of privatization, who made their case through multiple congressional hearings beginning in earnest in the mid-1990s, pressed the logic of the rights claims asserted by the original supporters of Social Security. They, too, saw Social Security benefits as a right secured by a worker’s contributions, but advocates rebuked government control of these contributions as usurping the title to an individual’s property. Since rights rested properly with their bearers, any break in this connection by another party without the full consent of the rights</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Representing Target Populations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Social policies ineluctably invoke target populations—people who, in the case of Social Security, would contribute to and benefit from an insurance or investment system. Whether supporting or opposing a policy proposal, debate participants address various qualities of a target population. Policymakers may assert that future retirees harbor hopes and dreams for their retirement, while retirees may expect policies to help them realize their visions. Beyond aspirations, potential beneficiaries may exhibit stated and unstated needs. Workers certainly do not plan to suffer a serious on-the-job injury or premature death, but they may need to protect their families against a tragic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Reconstructing a Time for Reform</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A new millennium brought a shift in the privatization debates. In the political realm, the year 2000 ended with great controversy as the winner of the November presidential election remained in doubt even after the polls had closed and the ballots had been counted. The nation focused its attention on the state of Florida, where reported problems with cast ballots placed in doubt the very outcome of the presidential election. Dramatic public statements and courtroom arguments by representatives of both campaigns ended only when the U.S. Supreme Court, in the case of<italic>Bush v. Gore</italic>, halted a partial recount of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Going Public with Privatization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a press conference two days after his election to a second term, President Bush assessed the import of his victory: “I earned capital in the campaign, political capital, and now I intend to spend it.” President Bush interpreted the election results as a clear expression of public opinion. Through their votes, citizens indicated their support for his policy agenda: “After hundreds of speeches and three debates and interviews and the whole process, where you keep basically saying the same thing over and over again, that—when you win, there is a feeling that the people have spoken and embraced</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Securing a Vibrant Democracy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FDR understood the dynamics of politics and public policy. Defending the dedicated financing of Social Security, he recounted that “we put those payroll contributions there so as to give the contributors a legal, moral, and political right to collect their pensions and their unemployment benefits. With those taxes in there, no damn politician can ever scrap my social security program.”¹ And he was right. Dedicated financing distinguished Old-Age Insurance from most other social policies and provided the program with a compelling basis for support. Old-Age Insurance ostensibly operated independently, and its conspicuous character enabled Americans to develop a proprietary view</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wd0hf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
