<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Creative Word</book-title>
         <subtitle>Canon as a Model for Biblical Education</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brueggemann</surname>
               <given-names>Walter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Revised and with a Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Erickson</surname>
               <given-names>Amy</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451499582</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451499582</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506400242</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506400248</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress Publishers</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>2</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13wwx1c"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Every faith community knows the challenges of inviting new members and the next generation into its shared life without falling into an arid traditionalism or a shallow relativism. Renowned scholar Walter Brueggemann finds a framework for education in the structure of the Hebrew Bible canon, with its assertion of center and limit (in the Torah), of challenge (in the Prophets), and of inquiry (in the Writings). Incorporating the best insights from his own career and from the fields of canonical criticism, Old Testament theology, and pedagogical theory, Brueggemann offers a vision of how the community can draw on the shape of Scripture to educate its members. First published in 1982, The Creative Word is now updated and introduced with a foreword by Amy Erickson of Iliff School of Theology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Erickson</surname>
                           <given-names>Amy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In August of 1997, I was actively second-guessing my decision to leave Vail, Colorado, to start the Master of Divinity program at Columbia Theological Seminary. My sister-in-law, Denise, a pastor in the Presbyterian Church (USA), trying to be encouraging, predicted that because I loved literature, I would surely love the Old Testament. Perhaps I was in a particularly skeptical mood, but her analogy struck me as untenable. It made as much sense as if she had said, “You love Colorado, and so surely you will love Georgia.” I couldn’t see the connection. I loved medieval tales of Arthur, Beowulf, eighteenth-century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Second Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brueggemann</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the 1982 edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Canon and the Educational Repertoire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every community that wants to last beyond a single generation must concern itself with education. Education has to do with the maintenance of a community through the generations. This maintenance must assure enough continuity of vision, value, and perception so that the community sustains its self-identity. At the same time, such maintenance must assure enough freedom and novelty so that the community can survive in and be pertinent to new circumstances.¹ Thus, education must attend to processes of both continuity and discontinuity in order to avoid fossilizing into irrelevance on the one hand, and relativizing into disappearance on the other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Disclosure of Binding</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our beginning must be with the Torah, where Israel always begins. Here I take the term to refer to the five books of Moses, though in other contexts, of course, the term Torah has other referents. Israel in all generations believes, with the enemies of Jeremiah (18:18), that the Torah of the priest will not perish. So we begin with the first division of Israel’s canon and with Israel’s most authoritative literature.</p>
                     <p>The five books of Moses as they now stand, however, were not given to us in their fixed form. While we may attend to the<italic>shape</italic>of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Disruption for Justice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A community that educates its members in the Torah will do them a great service. It will make available a center for life, a core of memory, a focus around which to organize all of experience. But if a community educates only in the Torah, it may also do a disservice to its members. It may nourish them to fixity, to stability that becomes rigidity, to a kind of certitude that believes all of the important questions are settled. The answers need only to be recited again and again.</p>
                     <p>That is why, alongside of the Torah, there is a second</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Discernment of Order</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The third division of the Old Testament canon, the Writings (<italic>kethubim</italic>), can hardly be spoken of as canon in the same sense as Torah and Prophets. That is true first because it is not a coherent body of literature as are the other two, but a miscellaneous collection. There is no agreement on the proper sequence of books, and the order varies from place to place. The second reason it is not properly a canon is that it does not seem to hold the same authority as the other parts of the canon.¹ In the first century ce, the Jewish</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Obedience as a Mode of Knowledge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have considered three elements of Israel’s scripture under the guidance of Jer. 18:18. We have suggested that in each of these elements there is to be found both a<italic>mode</italic>of knowledge and a<italic>substance</italic>that should concern us in our educational task:</p>
                     <p>1. The<italic>ethos</italic>of our community knows that the memory of the stones is given, settled, and can be trusted. We embrace the<italic>consensus of the Torah</italic>. We have a<italic>disclosure</italic>of God’s purpose for and way with his people. That disclosure is sure and undoubted among us.</p>
                     <p>2. The<italic>pathos</italic>of God leads to a giving of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Scripture References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wwx1c.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
