<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442695344</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B3051.Z7S64 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Herder, Johann Gottfried, 1744–1803</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Contributions in political science</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political science</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Herder's Political Thought</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Study on Language, Culture and Community</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SPENCER</surname>
               <given-names>VICKI A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781442643024</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442695344</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442695344"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Vicki A. Spencer reveals Herder as one of the first Western philosophers to grapple seriously with cultural diversity without abandoning a commitment to universal values and the first to make language and culture an issue of justice.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="368"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is a conversation between the thought of Johann Gottfried Herder (1744–1803) and recent Anglo-American political theory. Since John Rawls’s critique of utilitarianism and the enormous influence of his<italic>Theory of Justice</italic>(1971), liberal-communitarian critics have placed firmly on the agenda the notion that individual identity is partly constituted by the cultural community in which one is born and educated. Rawls subsequently came to contend that his once apparently universal principles are only applicable to modern, liberal-democratic states. Postmodernism, too, has had a significant impact with its critique of the one-sided universalism typically associated with ‘the Enlightenment,’ as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Origin of Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eighteenth-century philosophers were intensely interested in the question of language origination, for it raised a host of wider questions concerning the relationship between language and cognition, and the operations of the mind. Differences throughout Europe were equally evident in the disputes within the Berlin Academy. Heavily influenced by the French philosopher Étienne Bonnet de Condillac, the academy’s President Pierre Moreau de Maupertius delivered a lecture in 1756 that attempted to demonstrate how human beings naturally created and perfected language.¹ Johann Süßmilch, a skilled exponent of the Wolffian school of philosophy, responded in his<italic>Versuch eines Beweises, daß die erste Sprache</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Expressivism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Herder’s expressivist theory of language marks a distinctive break from the designative view of language held by both rationalists and empiricists in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. Put simply, according to the designative view, a word is a sign that ‘stands in for’ by serving as a substitute, or kind of proxy, for the object or idea it represents.¹ It is predicated on the long-held belief in the hierarchical dependence of language on the prior existence of thought, a position known in philosophy as ‘internalism.’ Herder rejects the very possibility of non-symbolic thought and instead develops a view of language</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Culture, Identity, and Community</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The abstract study of language in the previous chapter takes on a concrete basis through Herder’s study of specific cultural communities. Both are central to his ontological position – that is, to those factors he takes as meaningful in accounting for social life.¹ Herder is now commonly credited as one of the first thinkers in the Western tradition to celebrate cultural diversity. Yet the erroneous idea that he fails to grasp sufficiently the diversity that exists<italic>within</italic>cultures persists among some political theorists. The first section of this chapter begins the task of correcting this misperception by showing that Herder fully</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Pluralist Alternative</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Herder’s sustained attention to linguistic and cultural specificity means he rejects the rationalist and absolutist belief in a single and harmonious body of knowledge. Yet he never abandons many of the universal values associated with ‘the Enlightenment’ by adopting a relativist conception of ‘truth.’ Owing to the recent pluralist turn in Anglo-American political thought,¹ the dichotomy between relativism and absolutism that held such a dominant place in Western thought has undergone considerable re-evaluation. Richard Bernstein locates its intellectual force as having emerged from Descartes’s search for an absolute foundation, that is, some fixed point from which all metaphysical and epistemological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Nationalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Herder has long been seen as a central thinker in the development of a historical and cultural particularity that has fuelled nationalist claims for self-determination. Today his work still provides a powerful theoretical justification for oppressed communities to pursue their cultural and political autonomy. Linguistic and cultural domination of minority communities by the state is conceptualized in Herder’s theory as a fundamental issue of justice. Sovereigns have a duty to tolerate the cultural diversity within their states; indeed, they are obligated to honour that diversity.</p>
                     <p>This chapter demonstrates that this universal principle of respect for cultural diversity distinguishes Herder’s theory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Republicanism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is hardly surprising, given Herder’s views on the state, that he shows relatively little interest in government and administration. But the fact that Herder’s direct engagement with politics in this narrow sense forms only a small part of his extensive intellectual output has meant that it has often been thought that he ‘was not a political thinker in the true sense of the word.’¹ It should be clear that I reject the narrow conception of politics on which this assessment is based, but due to its pervasiveness and misleading nature it needs to be addressed directly.² Viroli in his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Multiculturalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the main tenets of Herder’s moral and political thought now outlined, this chapter applies the central principles of his ontology and his theories of language and culture to a number of issues that have arisen in contemporary political theory with respect to immigrant societies and long-standing communities. It is difficult to dispute that most states in the modern world are multi-cultural in a descriptive sense.¹ Despite the centralizing and homogenizing cultural policies of the modern ‘nation-state’ documented by scholars of nationalism like Gellner, many cultural minorities have been remarkably resilient. Typically states are as they were under the dynastic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Herder’s thought displays a richness and subtlety that with some notable exceptions has been inadequately appreciated in the Anglo-American tradition. There are now sufficient translations from which it is possible to obtain a far richer grasp of the complexity of his ideas, but there is still considerable work that needs to be done in this regard. This lack is itself indicative of the relatively scant scholarly attention paid in the English-speaking world to one of Germany’s most important thinkers of the eighteenth century. Despite the general acknowledgment of his profound influence on the development of a wide range of disciplines</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442695344.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
