<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ffjp1x</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD161.G57 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Knowledge, Theory of</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Liberation theology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Knowledge and Human Liberation</book-title>
         <subtitle>Towards Planetary Realizations</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Giri</surname>
               <given-names>Ananta Kumar</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780857284525</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780857289346</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Anthem Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LONDON; NEW YORK; DELHI</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Ananta Kumar Giri</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gxpb96"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Human liberation has become an epochal challenge in todays world, requiring not only emancipation from oppressive structures but also from the oppressive self. This book seeks to rethink knowledge vis-à-vis familiar themes such as human interest, critical theory and cosmopolitanism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="332"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Giri</surname>
                           <given-names>Ananta Kumar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clammer</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This valuable volume brings together in one place for the first time a number of essays by one of India’s (and indeed international sociology’s) most innovative thinkers, and one moreover who is committed to erasing the boundaries between social theory and practice. Essentially what is suggested in the following pages is an approach to social knowledge and to positive social transformation that transcends the normal boundaries that so commonly separate sociology from philosophy and both from religion and spirituality. To a great extent the social sciences have failed to deliver on their Enlightenment promises. Perhaps this was too much to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CALLING OF TRANSFORMATIVE KNOWLEDGE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Bible we read about a woman who is wailing in the streets and her name is Wisdom.¹ She is weeping because despite her knocking we are not opening our doors. But in the human journey as well as in our contemporary world it is not only wisdom which is weeping. Knowledge is also weeping, as it has become imprisoned within a variety of structures of domination, commodification, illusion and isolation. But to know is not only to know of but to know with – a practice of knowing with which involves both self-knowledge and knowledge of the world (see</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>KNOWLEDGE AND HUMAN LIBERATION:</title>
                     <subtitle>JÜRGEN HABERMAS, SRI AUROBINDO AND BEYOND</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human liberation has been a key concern with humanity from the dawn of history, and in the contemporary moment, it manifests before us as an epochal challenge, as the prevalent guarantors of liberation in modernity – liberalism and socialism – have left us alone in the street. The dead end at which our familiar projects of social emancipation and human freedom are at present urges us to rethink liberation as part of a new seeking, striving, and experimental subjectivity at the level of both self and society. Human liberation means liberation from the oppressive structures of society as well as from one’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>BEYOND WEST AND EAST:</title>
                     <subtitle>CO-EVOLUTION AND THE CALLING OF A NEW ENLIGHTENMENT AND NON-DUALITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evolution was once a dividing mark between the “developed us” and the “underdeveloped or primitive them,” but there have been certain foundational transformations in the theory and normative quest of evolution which challenge us to overcome both anthropocentrism and ethnocentrism. Developments in both the discourse and practice of socio-cultural evolution as well as biological and cosmic evolution point to the need for cultivating a new enlightenment and non-duality going beyond the dualism of environment and the organism, ontogenesis and socio-genesis and “us” and “them.” Evolutionary thinking as part of spencerian social darwinsim was used to rank societies in the scale</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>THE MODERN PRINCE AND THE MODERN SAGE:</title>
                     <subtitle>TRANSFORMING POWER AND FREEDOM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The prince has been the dominant archetypal model of being and becoming in modernity, and despite the supposed beheading of the kings in the modern world, as Machiavelli (1981) and antonio gramsci (1957), among many others, tell us it is the values of the prince, namely his will to power, that guide us in the modern world, rather than the values of an unconditional ethical obligation of the self to the other. Power, politics and empowerment have provided determinant frames of selfconstitution and social emancipation in the modern world, and they have provided the singular definition of freedom as well.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>KANT AND ANTHROPOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, we explore the challenge of rethinking modernist knowledge by looking at Kant’s conception of anthropology. Kant taught courses in both anthropology and physical geography, and his book<italic>Anthropology from a Pragmatic Point of View</italic>was published nearly thirty years after his initial engagement with anthropology. While his lectures embodied Kant’s crisis of identity as a professional philosopher, thus facilitating a border crossing between philosophy and anthropology,<italic>Anthropology from a Pragmatic Point of View</italic>was far short of his earlier critique of metaphysics and wanted anthropology to play by universal principles if not be totally subordinated to metaphysics.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>TOCQUEVILLE AS AN ETHNOGRAPHER OF AMERICAN PRISON SYSTEMS AND DEMOCRATIC PRACTICE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alexis de Tocqueville is one of the most influential interlocutors of modernity whose reflections on democracy continue to inspire, engage and haunt us as we are supposedly in an age of global democratization. Tocqueville’s work on democracy,<italic>Democracy in America</italic>, was published between 1835 and 1840. Around this period, european society was making a transition from an ancient regime to a form of social and political system whose full contours were yet to emerge. Not only the transition from feudalism to democracy but also other lines of transition, such as the transition from feudalism to the industrial and the capitalistic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>SOME RECENT RECONSIDERATIONS OF RATIONALITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of rationality has been subjected to numerous critiques in the history of modernity, and all these critiques have been helpful in opening rationality to crosscultural translations and examinations. Despite numerous anthropological critiques of a Eurocentric notion of rationality which looks at other people such as the tribal people having a primitive mind, a modernistic and West-centric view of rationality is still very much on the throne. This situation seems to be slightly altering in the realm of philosophical discourse with some recent foundational interrogations of rationality offered by thinkers such as alasdair macIntyre and Stephen Toulmin, who urge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>CONTEMPORARY CHALLENGES TO THE IDEA OF HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his inaugural address at the 61st session of the Indian history Congress at Calcutta, amartya Sen develops and defends a view of history as an enterprise of knowledge. Sen takes issue with postmodern critiques of knowledge in general and historical knowledge in particular, and argues that though all of us have our own perspectives and points of view, yet it does not preclude the possibility of arriving at “an integrated and coherent picture” (Sen 2001, 86). Sen goes on to argue: “… describing the past is like all other reflective judgments, which have to take note of demands of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>RULE OF LAW AND THE CALLING OF DHARMA:</title>
                     <subtitle>COLONIAL ENCOUNTERS, POST-COLONIAL EXPERIMENTS AND BEYOND</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The classical indian traditions had a different conception of both rule and law as compared to modern western traditions. While the constraining power of legality is central to modern western traditions, in India it is moral authority which is at the core of the rule of law (lingat 1973). The classical law of india is characterized not by positive law and legality but by moral authority and duty which is called<italic>dharma</italic>.<italic>Dharma</italic>refers to the totality of duties which are incumbent on individuals. It also signifies eternal rules which maintain the world. The rule of law entailed in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Nine</label>
                     <title>COMPASSION AND CONFRONTATION:</title>
                     <subtitle>DIALOGIC EXPERIMENTS WITH TRADITIONS AND PATHWAYS TO NEW FUTURES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Compassion is a key theme and foundation of life in paths of Buddha. it means to share in the suffering and joy of others. According to the Dalai Lama, this is the foundation of Buddhism, especially tibetan Buddhism. Compassion heals and makes new ways of human development and social transformations possible. But compassion needs to be accompanied by confrontation: the courage to confront those parts of self and society which do not help us to blossom and realize our potential. In my recent visit to China and tibet (July– August 2009) I saw images of Buddha as well as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Ten</label>
                     <title>RETHINKING PLURALISM AND RIGHTS:</title>
                     <subtitle>MEDITATIVE VERBS OF CO-REALIZATIONS AND THE CHALLENGES OF TRANSFORMATIONS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pluralism and human rights are epochal challenges now, and they challenge established modes of discourse and practice including our conceptions of the normative. both of these face challenges of multi-dimensional transformations in self and society. A key challenge here is to broaden our conceptions and realizations of law and rights. In his critical reflection on law and society in India, Andre Béteille writes, “individual rights do not have the same depth and firmness in india, the same anchorage in its social structure, than they do in the United States” (1997, 198). But this relativization of individual right in contemporary indian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eleven</label>
                     <title>THE CALLING OF A NEW CRITICAL THEORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>SELF-DEVELOPMENT, INCLUSION OF THE OTHER AND PLANETARY REALIZATIONS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Piet Strydom is a creative and critical seeker of our contemporary world who has asked many questions and has also created spaces of mutual learning and collective blossoming. Strydom originally comes from South Africa, and his critique of the thenprevailing apartheid regime made him homeless. He first came to England and then settled down in Ireland, where he has taught at the pre-eminent University College Cork for more than three decades. While teaching at Cork, he embodied a new mode of critique and creativity, which has presented his students and fellow learners a critical and creative way of blossoming beyond</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Twelve</label>
                     <title>RETHINKING THE POLITICS AND ETHICS OF CONSUMPTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>DIALOGUES WITH “SWADESHI” MOVEMENTS AND GANDHI</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consumption provides us with many important challenges now. The contemporary facts of consumption urge us to rethink the ethics and politics of it.² Concern with political consumerism tends to argue how appropriate consumption linked to life-style politics can have a politically significant critical function. But there are two related problems with such a contemporary approach to consumption. First, it is concerned with consumption without relating it to production, and second, the politics of consumption in the practice of political consumerism is not accompanied by a project of ethics. The present chapter seeks to rethink the politics and ethics of consumption</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Thirteen</label>
                     <title>SWARAJ AS BLOSSOMING:</title>
                     <subtitle>COMPASSION, CONFRONTATION AND A NEW ART OF INTEGRATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Hind Swaraj</italic>is an open dialogue in which not only the Reader and Editor¹ speak to each other with compassion but all of us, the whole humanity, are invited to join this journey of co-walking and the realization of fuller humanization and divinization (Gandhi 1938). It is an open text, a very different kind of manifesto. In the known and valorized manifestos of modernity we have a parade of assertions, but in<italic>Hind Swaraj</italic>there is no such one-sided assertion and preaching from a pulpit. This is a revolutionary departure from modernistic models of pedagogy, human emancipation and national liberation,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Fourteen</label>
                     <title>CIVIL SOCIETY AND THE CALLING OF SELF-DEVELOPMENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is Jürgen Habermas (1981) himself who quite some time ago had challenged us that now we need a new philosophy of science which is not scientistic. It is worth asking Habermas, and all of us sociologists for whom sociological engagement is nothing more than an elaboration of the agenda of modernity, whether we need an understanding of and relationship with modernity which is not modernistic. This inquiry is at the core of understanding paths of civil society and experiments with modernities, not only in India but also in Europe, East Asia, Africa, Latin America and around the world. Both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Fifteen</label>
                     <title>THE CALLING OF PRACTICAL SPIRITUALITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>TRANSFORMATIONS IN SCIENCE AND RELIGION AND NEW DIALOGUES ON SELF, TRANSCENDENCE AND SOCIETY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Daya Krishna and Ramachandra Gandhi were inspiring seekers in the gardens of transformational knowledge, and in this journey of knowledge and human liberation it is enriching to walk together with them. Let us begin this dialogue with the following lines of Daya Krishna: “The development of new<italic>purusarthas</italic>(ideals of human flourishing and excellence) in the history of a culture or civilization would perhaps be one of the more important ways of looking at man’s history as it will emphasize ways of making his life significant in the pursuit of new ends of a different kind… The emergence of any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Sixteen</label>
                     <title>SPIRITUAL CULTIVATION FOR A SECULAR SOCIETY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much water has flown down the Jordan, Jhelum, ganges, Cauvery, Mahanadi, thames, rhines and Mississippi rivers since the dawn of humanity and the independence of india, and in recent years much discussion has taken place over the nature of secularism in india, including its uses and abuses. Broadly speaking, we can classify the various contending positions on secularism in india into three approaches: a) those who defend the secular character of the Indian Republic as enshrined in the Constitution of India; b) those who oppose it on the grounds that the practice of Indian state-led secularism has been a pseudo-secularism;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seventeen</label>
                     <title>COSMOPOLITANISM AND BEYOND:</title>
                     <subtitle>TOWARDS PLANETARY REALIZATIONS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The vision that we are not just members of our tribes and nations but belong to the whole world – as the children of Mother Earth – has a long genealogy in many different cultures and traditions of the world; from the Stoic conception of human beings as citizens of the world in ancient Greece, to the Vedic vision of<italic>Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam</italic>(the<italic>Vasudha</italic>, meaningworld and Mother Earth), to the Buddha’s interrogation of such conceptions of cosmopolitanism by submitting the ideal of universal self-realization, which is not confined to the human realm and has challenged seeking human beings to realize the<italic>bodhisattva</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                     <subtitle>KNOWLEDGE AND PRAXIS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dallmayr</surname>
                           <given-names>Fred</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A transformative sociology? A transformative and transforming “knowledge” of social life? These phrases are signature notions of Ananta Kumar Giri. In a string of earlier publications, he has provided sketches adumbrating these notions. Now, in the present volume, he finally has enlisted all his rich intellectual resources in order to flesh out the meaning of an active kind of “knowledge” capable of promoting human “liberation” or emancipation. As one should note, liberation for Giri does not just denote deliverance from oppressive social and political structures, but also the overcoming of inner compulsions and addictions standing in the way of genuine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxpb96.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ADVANCE PRAISE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
