<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Facing the Fiend</book-title>
         <subtitle>Satan as a Literary Character</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Baillie</surname>
               <given-names>Eva Marta</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718893545</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718842666</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Eva Marta Baillie</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cg4ks4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>With the preponderance of visual imagery in our late modern period, why is it the literary Satan keeps emerging? And what can the literary figure of Satan contribute to the understanding of evil? Eva Marta Baillie argues that the literary is the only means by which Satan can survive, and that as a result of the changing literary (and cultural, philosophical, and theological) landscape and our changing perceptions of evil as we move into the twenty-first century, the satanic character must also change.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="218"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Setting the Stage The Birth of a Character</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The character of Satan is problematic; he is the “weak place of the popular religion, the vulnerable belly of the crocodile.”¹ Current popular culture makes Satan a subject of its attention. Films featuring the devil are successful blockbusters, books on the occult sell well, and Satan appears in various music genres, ranging from American folk to heavy metal. Outside popular culture, however, and in particular in the theological discourse, there is little “Sympathy for the Devil.”² The idea of Satan cannot be adequately expressed and discussed in terms of theology. The Christian system of monotheism does not allow a systematic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>one</label>
                     <title>Is Satan Evil?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Understanding Satan as a character requires the introduction of a<italic>context</italic>in which the character operates. Our search for Satan’s dwelling place takes us to different areas of definition and interpretation, but the most fundamental question at this point is the relationship between Satan and evil. The question of whether the character of Satan is evil or not cannot be answered readily, since the problem is twofold: like any character, Satan has many layers and describing him as evil is an over-simplification. At the same time, the abstract concept of evil depends on contextual circumstances. The best approach seems the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>two</label>
                     <title>Satan’s Biography:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Origins of the Satanic Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no one “biography” of Satan. There is no authoritative body of text we can refer to when we speak of Satan, rather Satan appears like a shape-shifter, and every story gives him another face and body, deploying the old stereotypes, but adding new elements at the same time, creating a curious mixture of familiarity and strangeness. The story that is retold here is the story of the Satan who grew out of various Jewish and Christian traditions, a Satan whose origins were inspired by the ancient near Eastern combat myths.¹ The most recent biography of Satan was published</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>three</label>
                     <title>Satan in Story and Myth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Satan is part of the myth of evil and if we assume that the story is one way to approach the reality of evil, we need to examine the myth in more detail. From a secular viewpoint, any metaphysical approach to the question of evil does not work. The responsibilities for all human actions lay, since Kant, in the agent’s will and accordingly, so does the decision to commit an evil deed. Nevertheless, despite all efforts to explain human behavior with psychology, sociology, biology, and psychoanalysis, there seems to be an explanatory gap when it comes to actions that hurt</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>four</label>
                     <title>Satan and the Written Word</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In many ways, Satan is closely tied to the written word. Visitors to the Wartburg in Eisenach can still see the stain that is allegedly the result of Martin Luther throwing an inkpot at Satan while he worked to translate the Bible. The invention of the movable printing press by Johannes Gutenberg in Mainz contributed to the massive increase of printed books in Europe, and together with the efforts of the Reformation and the Counter-Reformation to educate the people, it created a literate society. Early modernity can be seen as the époque of the written word and Satan quickly became</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part Two: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen in the discussion of his biography, Satan is a paradoxical figure, showing contradictory characteristics and constantly evading definition. In this section, I explore how different satanic characters in literature represent manifestations of evil, in conjunction with the theological concepts of theodicy and theological discussions of evil. I refer to it as a literary exploration of postmodern or contemporary thoughts on evil in philosophy and theology. We have seen now how Satan is a literary figure and finds his<italic>raison d’être</italic>through narrative. But what happens to Satan in late modern fiction? Is there room for talk</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>five</label>
                     <title>The Restless Wanderer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to his biography, Satan was cast out of heaven and fell into the abyss. At the same time, he has been described as roaming the earth. His state, however, is most certainly one of exile and homelessness, though freely chosen. The following takes a closer look at the notion of evil as alienation and elimination and explores the literary character of Satan as a wanderer between the worlds.</p>
                     <p>I start with a linguistic analysis of two terms that characterize a state of being—to dwell and to roam. Dwelling means to live and to reside, it expresses steadiness and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>six</label>
                     <title>The Tormented Shadow</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joseph Conrad’s character Kurtz is a restless wanderer,¹ dying in utter isolation and self-inflicted exile:</p>
                     <p>He cried in a whisper at some image, at some vision,—he cried out twice, a cry that was no more than a breath—“<italic>The horror! The horror!</italic>” I blew the candle out and left the cabin…. Suddenly the manager’s boy put his insolent black head in the doorway, and said in a tone of scathing contempt—“Mistha Kurtz—he dead.”²</p>
                     <p>Literary critics have offered different interpretations of Kurtz’s last words, but it is the ambivalence of them that make Joseph Conrad’s novel, published in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>seven</label>
                     <title>The Zeroing Zero</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Carl Gustav Jung was witness to another shadow that came over Europe during his lifetime: Adolf Hitler. In his essay<italic>Wotan</italic>(1936), Jung described Germany as “infected by one man who is obviously possessed” in addition to “rolling towards perdition.”² Jung’s analysis of Hitler, however, is just one of many attempts to understand the most notorious satanic figure of twentieth-century history. In his<italic>Anatomy of Human Destructiveness</italic>, philosopher and psychoanalysist Erich Fromm diagnosed Adolf Hitler as a clinical case of necrophilia.³ Fromm analyzes Hitler’s childhood, his main source being the biography by B. F. Smith (1967), to which author Norman</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>eight</label>
                     <title>The Creative Eliminator</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Blood Meridian or The Evening Redness in the West</italic>was published in 1985 and is today considered Cormac McCarthy’s masterpiece. After publication, the novel received only lukewarm critical reception, but is now generally regarded as part of the American canon of literature, and is compared to Hermann Melville’s great American myth<italic>Moby Dick</italic>. The narrative’s protagonist is a nameless youth, referred to as Kid, who leaves home at fourteen and joins a gang of scalp hunters under the leadership of Captain John Joel Glanton. The gang is paid by Mexican governors to kill Indians, in particular Comanche warriors who regularly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>nine</label>
                     <title>The Stumbling Block</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ruined churches of<italic>Blood Meridian</italic>are symbols for a world where institutionalized religion is in decline and the belief in metaphysical experiences is difficult to combine with the findings of empirical sciences. The death of personhood is closely connected to evil: wherever Being stops and Non-Being starts, there is space for negation and fear. The collapse of the house of religion in the West and the absence of a personal God contribute to a metaphysical void that is claimed by Satan who is the denier of any existence. The postmodern Satan appears without the attributes, both physical and behavioral</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ten</label>
                     <title>The Transgressor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It’s a legend; can a legend be true? Gideon Mack’s question sets the scene for our last account of the satanic presence in narrative. The encounter with Satan opened Gideon’s eyes to a metaphysical reality he had refused to believe in.¹ In a similar way, the encounter between the satanic figure of Woland and two Muscovites is described by him as the seventh proof of the existence of God: if you experience the reality of the devil, you will have to acknowledge the existence of God. The distinction between reality and imagination is one of the main themes of Bulgakov’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Satan’s Salvation or the Redemption Lies in the Text</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of the possessed from Gadara is popular in art and fiction, in particular the demon’s claim, “for we are many.”² It implies not only the possible diversity of the satanic character, but also the power that stands behind him. The different characters discussed in this work are only a very small aspect of the satanic figure, but they were chosen to highlight the ambiguity of Satan’s nature and to express the diversity of his appearance in the story. The origins of Satan lay, as we have seen, in his function as the stumbling block and the adversary, he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4ks4.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
