<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN98.D43G66 1991</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Deconstruction</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Skepticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Skeptic Disposition</book-title>
         <subtitle>Deconstruction, Ideology, and Other Matters</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Goodheart</surname>
               <given-names>Eugene</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400862238</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">140086223X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1984</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zv4x4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Eugene Goodheart examines the skeptic disposition that has informed advanced literary discourse over the past generation, arguing that the targets of deconstructive suspicion are fundamental humanistic values. "[This book] is a fair-minded, generous critique of the deconstructionist theories of Jacques Derrida, Paul de Man, and their followers. These writers have argued that language is so inherently slippery it can never express a speaker's intended meaning. The critic's role, in their view, is to explore the contradictions, subtexts, and metaphorical byways of works that may be most radically deceptive when they appear simple. Critics have castigated this language-centered skepticism as a form of nihilism geared to multiply numbingly similar readings of already familiar texts. Mr. Goodheart's objection is more subtle. He suggests that the philosophical orientation of deconstructive critics leads them to overemphasize the tricky propositional sense of words at the expense of the broader impact of literature--its power to wound, thrill, or transform us."--Morris Dickstein, The New York Times Book Review</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1991.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="220"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Until recently theory occupied an uncertain place in literary study. The New Criticism taught us how to read individual works of literature. Its theory consisted of heuristic concepts like paradox and ambiguity (concepts that told us what to look for). It cautioned against certain fallacies in reading, for example, the intentional fallacy, which mistakes the source of meaning in the author’s intentions or the affective fallacy, which confuses the reader’s private emotional associations with the feelings evoked by the work. To say this is to be unfair to the achievements of I. A. Richards and Kenneth Burke, but I am</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>CRITICISM AT THE PRESENT TIME</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a review of the Rockefeller Foundation report on<italic>The Humanities in American Life</italic>, Hilton Kramer remarks that “we are a long way here from Matthew Arnold’s notion of trying ‘to know the best that is known and thought in the world.’ ” And he ruefully observes that “Arnold’s name … is never mentioned in this report, which so systematically avoids any mention of our classic writers that one is left wondering what this committee has in mind when it speaks of the humanities.”¹ Once the inspiration of humanistic study in England and America, Arnold has now become something of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>THE TRANSCENDENTAL SITE:</title>
                     <subtitle>FROM HEAVEN TO EARTH</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is an unintended irony in Arnold’s view of romanticism as deficient in ideas. It was, after all, romanticism that made the greatest contribution to Arnold’s principal idea: the relocation of the transcendental site from heaven to earth. The idea is the legacy of both English and German romanticism, and studies of its literary consequences can be found in, among other works, Georg Lukács’s<italic>The Theory of the Novel</italic>(1920) and Meyer Abrams’s<italic>Natural Supernaturalism</italic>(1971), which provides an account of lyric poetry remarkably similar to Lukács’s account of the novel. In their most ambitious moods, the novel and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>ROLAND BARTHES AND THE MONSTER OF TOTALITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The work of Roland Barthes is pivotal in the history of post-structuralism, for it is marked by an incompletely resolved ambivalence toward “the monster of totality.” This ambivalence shows itself in his career as a demystifier.</p>
                     <p>In the preface to<italic>Mythologies</italic>(1957) Roland Barthes warns us that demystihcation is “a word which is beginning to show signs of wear.” We hardly need to be reminded that for Marx, as it had been for the thinkers of the Enlightenment, demystihcation was the very essence of criticism. All criticism, Marx had written in an early essay, was the criticism of religion: the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>READING WITH/OUT A TEXT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Roland Barthes, the pleasure of the text is in the making of one’s own text at the expense of the text of another. “Thus begins at the heart of the critical work, the dialogue of two histories and two subjectivities, the author’s and the critic’s. But this dialogue is egoistically shifted toward the present: criticism is not an homage to the truth of the past or to the truth of ‘others’—it is a construction of the intelligibility of our own time.”¹ In shamelessly confessing the egoism of the critical act, Barthes casts doubt upon the objective existence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>DISCOURSE WITHOUT FOUNDATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In its heroic beginnings, secularization was an attempt to rescue the substance of religious truth from a moribund dogmatism that literalized god terms. To conceive of God, virtue, salvation, blessedness as symbolic terms was not to diminish the reality of the religious quest but to heighten it. In<italic>Sartor Resartus</italic>, Carlyle understood the process of secularization (the word is not his) as a process of rescue: “For it is man’s nature to change his Dialect from century to century; he cannot help it though he would. The authentic<italic>Church-Catechism</italic>of our present century has not yet fallen into my hands:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>A QUESTION OF MEANING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The deconstructive view that language, because of its figural deviousness, never coincides with meaning is not unprecedented. The ambition of science to realize itself in the notations of mathematics reflects a suspicion of the treacherous ambiguities of language dating from the seventeenth century. Exponents of the power of poetry have always made a virtue of the equivocations of its language. Meaning is a portentous term against which the literary sensibility has always had a certain prejudice. It connotes gravity and immobility, conditions inimical to imaginative freedom. Meaning is the refuge of those incapable of following flights of imagination. In its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>LITERATURE AS PLAY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far we have addressed the cognitive rigor of deconstruction. What of its playfulness, which would seem to go counter to the ascetic direction of its rigor? The association of literature with play is hardly new. We need only invoke the self-delighting playfulness of Aristophanes and Shakespeare, among many others, to realize that the essence of comedy has always been play. Only a Puritan attitude within literature, which has affinities with a mistrust of literature itself, would want to banish self-delighting playfulness. The tradition of play in literature and in philosophical reflection about play has been strongly marked by theological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>DECONSTRUCTION AND SOCIAL CRITICISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The implications of deconstruction extend beyond texts. One potential casualty of deconstruction is social criticism. Deconstruction makes social criticism of whatever inspiration (literary, historical, philosophical) very difficult, if not impossible. The touchstone for a literary-inspired social criticism has been of course, Matthew Arnold. Arnold had an abundant capacity for doubt, but he assumed the presence and fullness of the cultural tradition. Disinterestedness, the free play of the mind upon our “stock habits of thought and feeling” never really extended to the touchstones that formed his convictions. Arnold’s particular touchstones are, of course, vulnerable to criticism. The Hebraistic or puritanical constraints</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Skeptic Disposition</italic>was written in the early eighties during the heyday of deconstruction and reader-centered criticism. The scene has changed, but the critical orientation represented by these “movements” has not disappeared. Rather it has been sublimated and to an extent transformed in the “ideology critique” that dominates literary studies at this moment. The most enduring effect of deconstruction has been the subversion of all universalist or foundationalist claims to truth. In the Marxist canon, ideology has as one of its principal meanings “false consciousness,” which is a kind of universalizing thought that conceals the particular, self-interested (class) motives that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv4x4.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
