<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442686199</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX891.L595 1988</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Theology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Early Works on Theological Method 1</book-title>
         <subtitle>Volume 22</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Doran</surname>
               <given-names>Robert M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Croken</surname>
               <given-names>Robert C.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781442610200</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442686199</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Bernard Lonergan Estate</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442686199"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>These lectures help to elucidate the development of Lonergan's ideas on such key notions as horizon, conversion, and meaning, as well as his evolving opinion on how best to divide theology into fields of specialization.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="688"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Editors’ Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DORAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-1</title>
                     <subtitle>Operations, the Subject, Objects, Method</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I wish to thank you all for coming. I shall try to do what I can with this subject, method in theology, which is not on the beaten track. There is no article in the<italic>Dictionnaire de théologie catholique</italic>that is expressly on the topic ‘method in theology,’ although Fr Congar’s article ‘Théologie’ has a section that does treat explicitly of method.²</p>
                     <p>Making a topic of method is, of course, first of all, not to try to provide a recipe on how to do theology, or to provide you with a cookbook. Again, it is not a question of an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-2</title>
                     <subtitle>The Human Good, Meaning, and Differentiations of Consciousness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What we had to say yesterday may be summed up under the five headings of object, operations, habits, subject, and the characteristic of the method as transcendental.</p>
                     <p>With regard to objects, we can distinguish between final objects (what you know) and terminal objects (the inner words by which it is known, the judgments).</p>
                     <p>The final object is being, which is the same as the good: everything about everything that is, insofar as it is. Consequently, it is completely universal and completely concrete at once. Again, since knowledge is of opposites, the final object is also all that is not, insofar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-3</title>
                     <subtitle>Integration of Worlds and Contemporary Theological Problems</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin by summarizing what we said yesterday. The first and fundamental point was that the analysis of human development in terms of spontaneous operations that become differentiated, combinations of differentiated operations, the grouping of combinations of differentiated operations, and finally the grouping of groups, runs into a limit. The dynamism of consciousness leads to a differentiation between operations that regard the ultimate – religious acts, the activities we perform when we say Mass, meditate, recite the breviary – and on the other hand the activities of studying and teaching, of eating and recreation. They tend to form – and the more they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-4</title>
                     <subtitle>Elements of Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We ended yesterday’s lecture by outlining certain fundamental problems that confront the contemporary theologian. Today we start trying to pick out elements that can be determined.</p>
                     <p>Our first question will be, Does theology contain a theoretic element? By that I mean, Is it, at least in part, within the world of theory in the strict sense of that term? Does it involve the psychological differences illustrated by the story about Thales and the milkmaid? Does it involve the concern for rigor that is illustrated by Plato’s early dialogues, in which Socrates shows the Athenians that they do not know what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-5</title>
                     <subtitle>Beyond Extrinsicism and Immanentism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Yesterday we reached the problem of certitude of judgment that is raised when one attempts to integrate the modern notion or fact of science with the ancient ideal. And we had something to say about the nature of the act of judgment, the nature of sufficient evidence, the objectifications of intellectual light, of the light of intelligence, in logic and method, and the remainder that never succeeds in being objectified. In other words, intelligence is something more than simply what can be objectified in logic or a method, no matter how elaborate. Not all problems are the same, and yet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-6</title>
                     <subtitle>Knowing, Believing, and Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin with a twofold point.² We can handle within the same science the necessary and the empirically intelligible, the universal and the imaginative scheme which approaches the singular, the changeable and the unchanging, the<italic>per se</italic>and the<italic>per accidens</italic>, insofar as we go behind the conceptual order. Within the conceptual order those terms are contradictory. But prior to conceiving, there is the act of understanding, and prior to the act of understanding, there is the state of mind that is expressed in the question. When it is expressed in the question, one has concepts. But the prior state of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-7</title>
                     <subtitle>Transitions and Thematizations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After distinguishing types and groups of operations under the names of common sense, natural science, philosophy, belief, divine faith, and theology, we want to examine more closely the transition, the movement, from faith to theology. It is the type of movement that occurs from the world of common sense, community, the visible universe, to the world of theory.</p>
                     <p>The<italic>terminus a quo</italic>and the<italic>terminus ad quem</italic>can be compared as the implicit and the explicit, the<italic>actus exercitus</italic>and the<italic>actus signatus</italic>, the<italic>vécu</italic>and the<italic>thématique, Verstehen</italic>and<italic>Erklären</italic>.<italic>Erklären</italic>means explaining, that is, giving a scientifically formulated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-8</title>
                     <subtitle>Positive and Systematic Theology, and Meaning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I shall this morning attempt something on positive and systematic theology, which will serve as a summary, and then go on to the topic of meaning and the different levels of meaning. Tomorrow I shall say something on hermeneutics, on interpretation, and on Friday something on history.</p>
                     <p>We began from theology as a dogmatic-theological context, where context is a remainder concept. It denotes the rest. In other words, when any theological or dogmatic statement is made, there is a somewhat indeterminate set of other statements that complement, qualify, explain, defend the statement that is made. No statement stands by itself</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-9</title>
                     <subtitle>Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hermeneutics and exegesis are concerned with the interpretation of the meaning of texts. A distinction is drawn between the two. Hermeneutics is concerned with general principles, and exegesis with their application to particular cases.</p>
                     <p>In general, exegesis is learned in practice, in a seminar. The four articles I wrote on<italic>gratia operans</italic>in<italic>Theological Studies</italic>in 1941–1942² represent the exegesis of an article in St Thomas,<italic>Summa theologiae</italic>, 1-2, q. 111, a. 2. What does this article mean? Well, you can easily write four articles and refer to all sorts of elements in St Thomas’s thought to set forth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962-10</title>
                     <subtitle>History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I endeavored yesterday to outline a few ideas that seem to me basic in the problems connected with interpretation. Today there is offered a similar sketch with regard to history in its various meanings. History sets a recurrent task for the theologian, and certain clarifications may be helpful.</p>
                     <p>A fundamental distinction is between the history that is written about and the history that is written. The Germans have a distinction or sometimes make a distinction – it isn’t anything rigid – between<italic>Geschichte</italic>, which means the history that is written about, the total course of human events, and, on the other hand,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 1</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>260</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: What is theological methodology? Is it merely a critique, or is it more than a critique?²</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: We spoke this morning about the world of common sense, the visible universe, the world of community that everyone knows all about. It sooner or later brings about, or leads to, or heads into what Georg Simmel in his<italic>Geschichtsphilosophie</italic>calls<italic>die Wendung zur Idee</italic>, the turn to the idea, the movement towards system, towards conceptualization.³ You not only have democracies but also people within democracies talking about what democracy is. This talk influences what in fact the democracy turns out to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 2</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: Can you contrast your usage of the term ‘method’ with the term as it is commonly used? For example, kerygmatic method, Medieval method, Thomistic method, etc.</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: It would be easier to effect the contrast if I was told what was meant by kerygmatic method, Medieval method, and Thomistic method.</p>
                     <p>Question: What about kerygmatic method?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: Kerygmatic theology, isn’t it? Kerygmatic theology is the effort to give the type of theology that people can preach. The students say, Why do you give us all this stuff? Why not give us scripture and the Fathers and something that we can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 3</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: What is the distinction between moral conversion and religious conversion?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: There needn’t always be a distinction, but there can be. If one ceased to be an Epicurean and became a Stoic, one would undergo a moral conversion. The Stoics had a very elevated morality in terms of the order of the universe. It was taken over by St Thomas and the Catholic tradition. Their moral doctrine was quite distinct from their philosophic doctrine, which was materialist. A religious conversion: it depends on what religion you’re talking about. If you’re talking about the Catholic religion, you’re moving from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 4</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>326</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: What is the relationship between freedom and the act of faith? Where does freedom come in the act of faith? Where do you place the freedom of the act of faith? Given the perception of the motives of credibility and credendity, how is it possible<italic>not</italic>to make the act of faith?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: With regard to the freedom of the act of faith, one can distinguish between a freedom<italic>in causa</italic>and an essential freedom. The freedom<italic>in causa</italic>: a man chooses to go to a Catholic university instead of to a secular university, or vice versa; and implicit</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 5</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: Not all thematization is dogmatic evolution, but all dogmatic evolution is thematization. What would you say to this proposition?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: Yes. In other words, there are all sorts of thematizations; every sermon is in fact a thematization of the gospel text that is preached on. It is only insofar as there are a whole series of thematizations involving similar topics that you start getting further questions: How do you reconcile this? The Middle Ages started off with a<italic>glossa</italic>of the scriptures and collections of passages from the Fathers; and when they started to compare them they didn’t seem</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 6</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: A question was asked about breaking theology up and having different professors teaching different divisions of each thesis in dogmatic theology, and another question had to do with the unity of everything that goes on in theology. Lonergan chose to begin by considering these questions together.</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: One can think of positive empirical science applied to the series of books in the Old Testament and to the series of authors in the New Testament, and to the Apostolic writers, the Apologists, the Greek Fathers, the Latin Fathers, the medieval theologians. This will suffice for our present question. Insofar as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1962</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 7</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>366</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: What is meant by horizon? Is horizon proper to the world of common sense, or more proper to it, or can it be found in all worlds?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: Horizon is the limit of the field of light or the limit of the penumbra beyond which there is just complete darkness – one can take it as either one. What lies within one’s horizon is what one can apprehend, choose, what one is willing to do, and what one has the necessary skills to do, whether it is in the world of common sense or the world of theory or the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1964-1</title>
                     <subtitle>The Contemporary Problem</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>377</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Medieval crisis led by appearance of Aristotle – led to 13th century.</p>
                     <p>Today: 1.Shift in ideal of science 2. Empirical human science – study of man as he concretely is in family, mores, education, economy, law, etc. Foundation of all such studies = enlargement of concept of meaning.</p>
                     <p>3. Historical consciousness</p>
                     <p>4. Emergence of philosophies that can handle preceding – that can deal with historical, etc.</p>
                     <p>In Middle Ages, theology as queen of sciences. But science taken in Aristotelian sense. Modern science has (a) enlarged field of science and (b) changed notion of science itself.</p>
                     <p>Theology is analogously a science – but analogous to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1964-2</title>
                     <subtitle>Reason Illumined by Faith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>388</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Vatican I: Two orders distinct both in principle and object</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Ratio fide illustrata</italic>is mating of the two. Today our concern is not with objects but with method – i.e., operations which theologian performs in dealing with object.</p>
                     <p>Operation: 2d act.</p>
                     <p>Dynamic structure: Cf.<italic>In Boethei de Trinitate</italic>, q.5 on abstraction. Thomas points out you can’t abstract foot from animal because its intelligibililty depends on its function – i.e., animal.</p>
                     <p>Structure: an element which with others forms an intelligible entity.</p>
                     <p>Form, matter,<italic>esse</italic>are not things but structural components.</p>
                     <p>So this morning we shall speak of human knowing. Knowledge, objectivity, consciousness.</p>
                     <p>‘Know’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1964-3</title>
                     <subtitle>Differentiation of Methods I</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Differentiation of methods</italic>is necessary because one cannot pursue different ends simultaneously. Different ends require different methods.</p>
                     <p>Reflection on whole process of experience, understanding, and judgment = foundations.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Foundations</italic>for theology is not fundamental theology in sense of foundation for reason.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Horizon</italic>: ‘Founding circle’ – limit of field of visibility. Husserl generalized this notion. We shall use as variation on Aristotelian-Thomist notion of<italic>formal object</italic>. Defined by correlatives of pole and field. Pole is subject, field is totality of objects. Potency is defined by its formal object. Scholastic concept concentrates on object and commonly conceives this abstractly:<italic>ratio sub qua objectum</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1964-4</title>
                     <subtitle>Differentiation of Methods II</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>406</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>(c)<italic>Understanding the author</italic>. To understand the words often requires one to understand the author. We can understand other people even when they think differently than we do. We say, ‘That’s just like you!’ Acquisition of the field – gradual accumulation of data with commonsense grasp of mentality of another way of life. Not a matter of defining terms, constructing hypotheses, etc.</p>
                     <p>Romantic hermeneutics speaks of<italic>Einfühlung</italic>. Herder, Winckelmann, Schleiermacher, Dilthey. Conceives the text as the<italic>Ausdruck</italic>of the writer. Feeling oneself into the writer’s soul. You become able to write and speak in same way. Romantic hermeneutics gets right down</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1964-5</title>
                     <subtitle>Special Questions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>415</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No one today disputes that it occurs. Not all dogmas evolve in just the same way. Some general features may, however, be singled out – Evolution of dogma may be conceived on analogy of universalization.</p>
                     <p>Universal:<italic>Unum multis commune</italic>{<italic>in re</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>{<italic>in mente</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>{<italic>reflexum</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>What was singular in mind of Christ became common by its diffusion to Apostles and to the believing Church. The process of teaching involves<italic>universale in mente</italic>. There are obvious differences between the way different minds assimilated. Each had his own<italic>modus recipientis</italic>which is brought to light by positive theology. Daniélou,<italic>Théologie du judéo-christianisme</italic>(Tournai-Paris, Desclée, 1958),³</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968-1</title>
                     <subtitle>Method</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I think I’d best begin by giving the chapter headings of the book I’m projecting. It will help you in the question periods to have some idea of the things that are better to leave until later and the things that can be handled right away in the question period each day. The first part of the book consists of six chapters, and the titles are, first, Method; second, Functional Specialties; third, Horizons and Categories; fourth, The Human Good, Values, Beliefs; fifth, Meaning; and sixth, Religion. It will mainly be with those six chapters that we will be concerned. Perhaps</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968-2</title>
                     <subtitle>Method (continued), Functional Specialties, and an Introduction to Horizons and Categories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The day before yesterday, I did most of the first chapter on method, and first of all I noted that there are three approaches to the notion of method: first, a purely empirical approach, where method is more an art than a science; secondly, a selective approach, where one picks the successful science and analyzes it and wishes all other sciences to be science insofar as they conform to it; that’s quite unsatisfactory for the less successful sciences that need more help really than anyone else; and consequently we were trying to work out a third approach through an analysis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968-3</title>
                     <subtitle>Horizons and Categories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>473</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We continue with ‘Horizons and Categories.’ Last time I spoke of the meaning of horizon, comparison of horizons, distinguishing them as complementary, genetic, and dialectical, and the differences of structure in horizons. I went on to method as horizon, and in particular to the difference between the traditional Aristotelian approach, however qualified, and the implications of horizon. Particularly the notion of necessity was fundamental in Aristotelian science, and it is marginal in modern science. We dealt with the many implications of that, especially with regard to the way the context of the statement of a truth is conceived, whether it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968-4</title>
                     <subtitle>The Human Good and Values</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>494</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of the chapter² is ‘The Human Good, Values, Beliefs.’ There are seven parts: first, the human good; second, development as operational; third, the development of feelings; fourth, progress and decline; fifth, the notion of value; sixth, judgments of value; and seventh, beliefs.³</p>
                     <p>The point to this is that we will wish to speak about the good of religion, religious values, religious beliefs; and one can do that only insofar as one has said something about each of these in more general terms. In other words, unless you want your theology to be locked away in an ivory tower,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968-5</title>
                     <subtitle>Beliefs and Carriers of Meaning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>513</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chapter 4 was on the human good, values, and beliefs, and we treated everything except beliefs. We are treating belief in general, not yet religious belief.</p>
                     <p>The appropriation of one’s social, cultural, religious heritage is largely a matter of belief. What we find out for ourselves is a very small fraction of what we know. We rely upon the experiences, the insights, the judgments of others; and this reliance is not merely on the experience, understanding, and judgment of our contemporaries, but also of our ancestors. The reason why man has progressed in the last 200,000 years (if that is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968-6</title>
                     <subtitle>Analysis of Meaning and Introduction to Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>534</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We spoke yesterday on the carriers of meaning, the ways in which meaning is embodied in intersubjective expression, in art, in symbols, and in language. Finally, we turn to the analysis of meaning, and first of all, to elements of meaning.</p>
                     <p>Distinguish sources, acts, and terms. Sources of meaning are all conscious acts and all intended contents, from the dream state right through the four levels of waking consciousness. The fundamental division is between transcendental and categorial meaning.</p>
                     <p>‘Categorial’ means the determinations reached through experiencing, through understanding and conceiving, through reflecting, weighing the evidence, judging, through deliberating, evaluating, deciding. One</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968-7</title>
                     <subtitle>Religious Expression, Faith, Conversion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>553</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sixth chapter, on religion, treats the question of God and religious values. We did that part yesterday. There remain three more sections: religious expression, faith, and conversions and breakdowns. First, then, religious expression.</p>
                     <p>Religious values may be briefly referred to as values connected with, arising from, ultimate concern. Our conception of religion in that section on values had to do primarily with religion conceived in its roots, as simply ultimate concern, as authentic human existence with regard to God and God’s world. The primary and ordinary manifestation or expression of ultimate concern is not any technically formulated question about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 1</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>569</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: Do you exclude the possibility of another animal developing that won’t work in this irrevisable structure?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: I don’t know anything about that. In other words, I’m going on ‘what do you mean by revision now?’ If we have some evidence for considering some other possibility, we will take that into account and proceed in accord with the evidence. I’m not given to speculation.</p>
                     <p>Question: How does memory fit into these operations or into this scheme that you have given us here?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: Well, enormously. In other words, I’ve been giving you a cross-section, but experience accumulates: you remember</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 2</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>580</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: I have a problem about the conversions and their meanings. How do I ever know that, when I accept something on the authority of God, this is an act of supernatural faith as distinct from a natural acceptance of something on the authority of God. If we’re going to reflect on our being Christian, how can I ever know that I’m authentically a Christian? I can accept the fact that I can be aware of my act of faith qua assent, but qua supernatural, qua activated by grace, how can I be sure? Can I experience an act of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 3</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>594</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: Were you dealing with ethics or metaethics?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: I was not dealing with any precise ethical question. You might call it general ethics or the elements that touch upon general ethics. What I was talking about was the human good. I wasn’t talking much about obligations. I was concerned to talk about various aspects of the human good: about human development, individual and social, about the notion of value and judgments of value, and about the complexity of the judgment of value: just what is the criterion in the judgment of value? What are the general criteria such as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 4</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>605</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: At the beginning of your talk this morning, you contrasted belief and knowledge,² but from reading<italic>Insight</italic>it seems better to say that one gets knowledge not only through firsthand experience but also through belief. And yet this is not the way you were talking this morning. You were simply contrasting sharply belief and knowledge.</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: The contrast is between belief and immanently generated knowledge, out of one’s experiencing, understanding, and judging.</p>
                     <p>Question: And so for all practical purposes the knowledge one gets from belief is just as good as what one has learned on one’s own.</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: Usually,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 5</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>617</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: Would you clarify the point that the terminating good is the universe?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: When we spoke of the good and values before, we spoke simply in terms of man’s being good, his self-transcending. We spoke of a cognitive self-transcendence in terms of knowledge, and a real self-transcendence in terms of benevolence and beneficence and love. We were setting up the human moral order, and we distinguished between originating value, namely, the existential subject that transcends himself, and the terminal value, i.e., the good that he does. When one goes on to the question of God and acknowledges God as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>1968</title>
                     <subtitle>Discussion 6</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>626</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Question: You say, ‘God loves.’ Is there any way that your transcendental method can arrive at the conclusion that God loves, or is it merely a conclusion of faith?</p>
                     <p>Lonergan: I believe that it is a conclusion that can be reached in the way it was reached in<italic>Insight</italic>. But that is not the further thing that comes with the gift of God’s grace. What I said about being in relation to God as subject, and speaking about God as the subject as object, which is a matter of religion, of faith, infused charity, and so on – the point I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>635</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lexicon of Latin and Greek Words and Phrases</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>655</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442686199.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>661</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
