<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD450 .B25613 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophical anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Subject (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Citizen Subject</book-title>
         <subtitle>Foundations for Philosophical Anthropology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Balibar</surname>
               <given-names>Étienne</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Miller</surname>
               <given-names>Steven</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823273607</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823273638</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1f89tnz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What can the universals of political philosophy offer to those who experience the living paradox of an inegalitarian construction of egalitarian citizenship? Citizen Subject is the summation of +ëtienne BalibarGÇÖs career-long project to think the necessary and necessarily antagonistic relation between the categories of citizen and subject. In this magnum opus, the question of modernity is framed anew with special attention to the self-enunciation of the subject (in Descartes, Locke, Rousseau, and Derrida), the constitution of the community as GÇ£weGÇ¥ (in Hegel, Marx, and Tolstoy), and the aporia of the judgment of self and others (in Foucualt, Freud, Kelsen, and Blanchot)._x000D_ After the GÇ£humanist controversyGÇ¥ that preoccupied twentieth-century philosophy, Citizen Subject proposes foundations for philosophical anthropology today, in terms of two contrary movements: the becoming-citizen of the subject and the becoming-subject of the citizen. The citizen-subject who is constituted in the claim to a GÇ£right to have rightsGÇ¥ (Arendt) cannot exist without an underside that contests and defies it. HeGÇöor she, because Balibar is concerned throughout this volume with questions of sexual differenceGÇöfigures not only the social relation but also the discontent or the uneasiness at the heart of this relation. The human can be instituted only if it betrays itself by upholding GÇ£anthropological differencesGÇ¥ that impose normality and identity as conditions of belonging to the community._x000D_ The violence of GÇ£civilGÇ¥ bourgeois universality, Balibar argues, is greater (and less legitimate, therefore less stable) than that of theological or cosmological universality. Right is thus founded on insubordination, and emancipation derives its force from otherness._x000D_ Ultimately, Citizen Subject offers a revolutionary rewriting of the dialectic of universality and differences in the bourgeois epoch, revealing in the relationship between the common and the universal a political gap at the heart of the universal itself.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="544"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Apter</surname>
                           <given-names>Emily</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is a citizen subject? A hyphenated subject, equal parts political citizen and subjected individual conscience? A freestanding agent capable of being federated with others? The ratifier of moral law, the self-punisher who dies by a thousand cuts at the hands of his or her own superego? The lead in a play about the psychic life of power in the era of weak states? The plebian legislator posed against the citizen king? A figure of possessive individualism reversed (which is to say, a self-dispossessed collectivist)? Or the<italic>Untertan</italic>, man of straw, anyone, “man without qualities,” figure of<italic>ressentiment</italic>, silently resisting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>After the Controversy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present work is finally appearing in print after having been announced as forthcoming on several occasions by the publisher who accepted it for publication nearly twenty years ago. Exasperated though he must have been by my broken promises, he did not show it; and he never gave up asking for the manuscript. I am profoundly grateful to him. Without such unflagging interest and friendship I might never have pursued my original intentions, in spite of the stimulus that I received along the way from various meetings and collaborations. No less grateful am I to Bruno Karsenti and Guillaume le</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Overture:</title>
                     <subtitle>Citizen Subject. Response to Jean-Luc Nancy’s Question “Who Comes After the Subject?”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Swenson</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Both following Hegel and opposed to him, Heidegger proposes Descartes as the moment when the “sovereignty of the subject” is established (in philosophy), inaugurating the discourse of modernity. This supposes that man, or rather the<italic>ego</italic>, is determined and conceived of as subject (<italic>subjectum</italic>).</p>
                     <p>Doubtless, from one text to another, and sometimes even within the same “text” (I am primarily referring here to the Nietz sche of 1939–46), Heidegger nuances his formulation. At one moment he positively affirms that, in Descartes’s<italic>Meditations</italic>(which he cites in Latin), the<italic>ego</italic>as consciousness (which he explicates as<italic>cogito me cogitare</italic>) is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Annex:</title>
                     <subtitle>Subjectus/Subjectum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Macey</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>“Ego sum, ego existo”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Descartes on the Verge of Heresy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mister President, you have imposed Draconian limits upon me. As a result, I must cut to the chase. The abstract that you might have received is not, as you no doubt grasp, a summary of my talk: not only because I hadn’t yet given my text a definitive form but also because what I have to say, since it remains highly open to discussion, is very difficult to summarize. Rather than drawing conclusions, my goal today is merely to arrive at questions; and I would consider myself a very happy man if, to some extent, you were to concur that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>“My Self,” “My Own”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Variations on Locke</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this lecture, I would like to tell a story about words. Or rather, two stories at once. The first is a public story, that of one moment within the great history of “personal” and “possessive” pronouns, which traverses the entire history of “Western culture,” thanks to what has been called its colingualism, and determines its understanding of subjectivity.¹ The second and much more modest story is a private one, although it owes every thing to public institutions of teaching and research: it concerns a stage in my own journey of initiation into the English language, from which, without indulging</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Aimances in Rousseau:</title>
                     <subtitle>Julie or The New Heloise as Treatise on the Passions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The chapter that Paul de Man devotes to<italic>Julie or the New Heloise</italic>in his<italic>Allegories of Reading</italic>does not only represent a central moment in the economy of the book, where the category that guides his readings (the “allegory” from the title) is explicated and justified; it is also a particularly illuminating discussion of a knot of questions regarding<italic>passion</italic>, which are generally considered to hold the philosophical key to the novel. In order to understand how writing and theory are superimposed in<italic>The New Heloise</italic>, I draw upon two of de Man’s assertions. The first says that “passion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>From Sense Certainty to the Law of Genre:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hegel, Benveniste, Derrida</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present discussion is not exclusively devoted to the thought and work of Jacques Derrida. It is rather an attempt to bring the reading and discussion of Derrida in relation with other texts, and other heritages, in order to illustrate how his manner of philosophizing has transformed our understanding of certain fundamental problems. I would argue that what distinguishes his specific practice of deconstruction is the way in which it displaces the classical question of the “paradoxes of the universal,” if only because it dismantles the metaphysical opposition between the universal and the particular, along with that of the absolute</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Ich, das Wir, und Wir, das Ich ist:</title>
                     <subtitle>Spirit’s Dictum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present talk—and I offer my thanks to Pierre Macherey for the invitation to speak to his working group, which afforded me an opportunity to write it—should fit, not too arbitrarily, I hope, into this year’s program devoted to exploring an discussing the category of “modernity.” That said, my intention is not to contribute directly to this discussion, even if the problems of philosophy and history that I elaborate are generally considered relevant to our prevailing ideas of a “modern moment” and our manner of situating ourselves in relation to it. About these ideas, I will restrict myself</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>The Messianic Moment in Marx</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the present essay, I would like to reexamine and, if possible, elucidate a question that often recurs in interpretations of Marx: What is the relationship between his concept of politics and religious (or theological) discourse? In view of the comparison that this issue of the<italic>Revue Germanique Internationale</italic>would like to draw, but also because of the strategic importance that, I believe, must be conferred upon this comparison, I will focus mainly upon a single text: the article, entitled “Zur Kritik der Hegelschen Rechtsphilosophie. Einleitung,” that Marx published in the<italic>Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher</italic>in March 1844. For the first aa</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Zur Sache Selbst:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Common and the Universal in Hegel’s Phenomenology of Spirit</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Certain great commentators on Hegel’s<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>(Kojève, Marcuse, Luk á cs), in part inspired by Marxism and Existentialism, built their interpretations around the statement that defines spiritual “substance” (<italic>Substanz</italic>) as a “work” (<italic>Werk</italic>) resulting from<italic>the activity of all and each (das Tun aller und jeder</italic>).¹ Sartre should also be included, since one section of the<italic>Critique of Dialectical Reason</italic>comprises an explicit allusion to the “animal regime of spirit” and could be read as a gigantic attempt, in permanent altercation with Hegel, to reformulate the dialectic of “action in common” as the collectivized (and thus aa a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Men, Armies, Peoples:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tolstoy and the Subject of War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter reprises several elements from a course taught at the University of California, Irvine, entitled “Politics as War, War as Politics” (January–March 2006). In this course, I opened to discussion the claim, frequent in contemporary discourse, that the “new wars,” which have broken out since the end of the Cold War and collapse of the world divided into “blocks” determined at the end of World War Two, would be essentially “non-Clausewitzian”—in that their protagonists are no longer solely territorial nation-states, operating by means of regular armies, or that they present an essential dissymmetry, or that they make</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>The Social Contract Among Commodities:</title>
                     <subtitle>Marx and the Subject of Exchange</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the first, Marx’s theory of commodity and money fetishism formed one of the most admired and contested aspects of his “critique” of political economy. In an astonishing fashion, it restores the correlation of sovereignty and subjection to the heart of the modern “social relation” that appears to herald the triumph of free individuality. To this end, it was necessary conceptually to reinscribe the classical schema of the “contract” into the representative and practical space of commodity exchange, whose immediacy he explodes by showing its latent metaphysics, which is also an anthropology and a politics. I will attempt in this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Judging Self and Others:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Political Theory of Reflexive Individualism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In French and several other languages, the notion of judgment designates both a “faculty” or “capacity” and an action that takes place within the sphere of public or private relations. It can have a general neutral signification (that of an evaluation about the adequacy of means to ends or to the quality of the ends themselves). But more often it designates, in dissymmetrical fashion, the determination of a deserved or undeserved sanction upon the action of a subject, especially when the action in question is a “crime” or a “delict.”</p>
                     <p>Judgment thus possesses both an anthropological side and an institutional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Private Crime, Public Madness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To clarify the questions raised today by the relations between madness and justice, with reference to the heritage of the French Revolution: such a project, if not confined to the stylistic exercises that typify certain commemorations, is paradoxical in several re spects. Indeed, what prompts current discussions on the function of the psychiatrist in the courtroom or on the role of judgments of civil capacity in the treatment of mental illness, is yet again the perspective offered by the reframing of the Penal Code (including the famous Article 64, which makes “insanity”—or, in the more recent version, “psychic or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>The Invention of the Superego:</title>
                     <subtitle>Freud and Kelsen, 1922</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the occasion of the 150th anniversary of the birth of Sigmund Freud, speaking in an amphitheater that bears the name of Jean-Martin Charcot, the theoretician of hysteria who was his teacher, I would like to present a synthesis—and thus inevitably a mere summary—of the initial results of the research that I have been conducting over the last several years, primarily within the framework of the seminars that Bertrand Ogilvie or ganized at the Université de Paris X–Nanterre. These seminars led me to reconsider what I believed I knew about the evolution of Freud’s thinking, in particular</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Blanchot’s Insubordination:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Writing of the Manifesto of the 121</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this chapter derives from a metonymical displacement. Blanchot himself never authorized any confusion between his role as a drafter of the<italic>Manifesto of the 121</italic>and that of the draft dodgers, deserters, and militants whom, along with his cosignatories, he intended to support and defend before the law. However, as we shall see, the word<italic>insubordination</italic>encompasses both a narrow and a broad sense; it connotes a community of action and feeling, evoked in what the<italic>Manifesto</italic>calls “the cause of all free men.” My point of departure is a footnote in Christophe Bident’s book<italic>Maurice Blanchot</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>Bourgeois Universality and Anthropological Differences</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this concluding chapter, I want to articulate the relationship between the political categories of modernity and the question to which its metaphysics always returns: that of subjectivity, endowed with consciousness—perhaps affected with unconsciousness—and with rights, duties, or individual and collective missions.³ Not only will I examine this relationship on the level of the history of ideas, morals, and social relations, but I will also articulate it as a<italic>conceptual</italic>unity that helps to clarify certain existential and institutional problems and, in so doing, ask whether they are still our problems (and why) or whether they are already</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f89tnz.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
