<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">AC85 .G37 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Muses on Their Lunch Hour</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Garber</surname>
               <given-names>Marjorie</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823273720</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823273751</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Marjorie Garber</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6bb4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>As a break from their ordained labors, what might the Muses today do on their lunch hour? This collection of witty, shrewd, and imaginative essays addresses interdisciplinary topics that range widely from Shakespeare, to psychoanalysis, to the practice of higher education today. With the ease born of deep knowledge, Marjorie Garber moves from comical journalistic quirks (GÇ£Fig LeavesGÇ¥) to the curious return of myth and ritual in the theories of evolutionary psychologists (GÇ£Ovid, Now and ThenGÇ¥)._x000D_ Two themes emerge consistently in GarberGÇÖs latest exploration of symptoms of culture. The first is that to predict the GÇ£next big thingGÇ¥ in literary studies we should look back at ideas and practices set aside by a previous generation of critics. In the past several decades we have seen the reemergence ofGÇöfor exampleGÇötextual editing, biography, character criticism, aesthetics, and philology as GÇ£hotGÇ¥ new areas for critical intervention. The second theme expands on this observation, making the case for GÇ£cultural forgettingGÇ¥ as the way the arts and humanities renew themselves, both within fields and across them. Although she is never represented in traditional paintings or poetry, a missing MuseGÇöwe can call her AmnesiaGÇöturns out to be a key figure for the creation of theory and criticism in the arts.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="216"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MUSES ON THEIR LUNCH HOUR</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Asking Literary Questions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fortunes of literary studies have gone up and down during the twentieth and twenty-first centuries with the same volatility as the stock market. And like the stock market, the market in literary studies can be charted with confidence only with the benefit of hindsight.</p>
                     <p>English studies held the comfortable middle-ground of the humanities in U. S. and Anglophile/Anglophone universities through the middle part of the twentieth century. The combined heritage of belletrism and the “little magazines” imparted a certain gloss of creativity and artiness to the practice of reading and writing about poems, novels, plays, and what was then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Ovid, Now and Then</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The consummate poet of bodily translation, Ovid has often been both a sign and an agent of shape-shifting in critical thought: metamorphic in himself and the cause of metamorphosis in others.</p>
                     <p>My object in what follows is not only to look at moments in which the stock of Ovid has risen or plummeted over the years, a question well addressed by several recent books and articles, but also to use this discussion as a way of predicting something about the future and interpreting something about the present in literary and critical studies. I am going to take the name of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Over the Influence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sometimes a term or phrase becomes so culturally powerful that it dislocates completely from its initial context. The various deformations of “deconstruction” are a case in point. Long after Jacques Derrida, headlines in the<italic>New York Times</italic>now routinely use—or misuse—the term: Recent examples include “Deconstructing a Demagogue” (on Newt Gingrich), “‘Diva’? Deconstructing Pop Images of Black Women” (a panel discussion at the Brooklyn Museum), and “Deconstructing the Perfect Burger” (use a cast-iron pan and an 80–20 ratio of fat to lean).¹ Harold Bloom’s phrase “the anxiety of influence” has enjoyed—or suffered—a similar fate. “Beware</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Fig Leaves</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where do dead metaphors go when they die? And why should we care? Consider the case of the fig leaf, a term that once, and not all that long ago, had a fairly secure referent, both in the Bible and in the history of art. But somewhere along the way the image—and the reference—parted company with the figure of speech. “Fig leaf ” today means something, for sure. Journalists use it all the time, and it is often to be found in newspaper headlines. But<italic>what</italic>it means is oddly distinct from<italic>how</italic>it means. Today’s fig leaves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Baggage Screening</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this increasingly visual moment, contemporary art often plays a dual role, as both “object” and critical interpretation. An exhibition at the Freud Museum effectively demonstrated why, and how, this double focus can illuminate both the present and the past.</p>
                     <p>By situating four of her digital media installations among the permanent artifacts of the Freud Museum, Renate Ferro ensures that her work interceded with, interrupted, and blended in with the collections and ephemera of the two Freuds: Sigmund and Anna. An installation in Anna Freud’s study on the second floor of the Hampstead house is called “This Suitcase Has No</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Identity Theft</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How might the teaching of psychoanalysis and, in particular, the teaching of psychoanalytic interpretations of Shakespeare be made more visible and effective in American colleges and universities? On this point it is tempting simply to paraphrase Lacan and say that there is no academic relation. A nominal adjective like “Freudian” can—and does—cover a multitude of (largely inaccurate) sins, but “Kleinian” and “Kohutian” are not part of the undergraduate vocabulary, nor, so far as I can tell, are names like Winnicott, Bion, Bowlby, or Kernberg.</p>
                     <p>Where, if at all, are the rudiments of psychoanalytic thinking taught today?</p>
                     <p>A keywords</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Czech Mates:</title>
                     <subtitle>When Shakespeare Met Kafka</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shakespeare and Kafka. At first glance it might seem as if no two writers could be less alike. One a playwright, an actor, an entrepreneur, a Christian; the other a novelist, a fabulist, an aphorist, a Jew. One supremely gifted in the creation of memorable dramatic characters, the other skilled in free indirect discourse, and in the first person narrative. One expansive, making the world a stage and the stage a world, the other a visionary claustrophobe, master of minimal spaces, the trial, the burrow, the animal-slave ship, the hunger artist’s cage. And yet they have been often, even insistently,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Occupy Shakespeare</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2011, the American Dialect Society voted to make “occupy” the 2011 Word of the Year, defeating contenders such as “tebowing,” “99%,” and the acronym FOMO, for “fear of missing out” (anxiety over being inundated by the information on social media). The chair of the Dialect Society’s New Words Committee was quick to acknowledge that “occupy” was, in fact, “a very old word,” but noted that “over the course of just a few months it took on another life and moved in new and unexpected directions.”³ When a column on this topic appeared in<italic>The Guardian</italic>, written by an after-dinner</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Shakespeare 451</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is the place of Shakespeare, and specifically the<italic>teaching</italic>of Shakespeare, in today’s changed—and still changing—academic world?</p>
                     <p>Despite the best efforts of humanities deans and English department chairs, and the resourceful invention by instructors of new courses designed to attract undergraduates to the humanities and the arts, today’s college students are more and more choosing the STEM fields (science, technology, engineering, and math) for reasons both practical and intellectual. English and history used to be among the largest undergraduate majors; now the preferred fields are often computer science, economics, and finance. It is not just that students</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6bb4.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
