<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">NX180.H57B59 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Arts and history</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Arts, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Themes, motives</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Arts, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Themes, motives</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Becoming Past</book-title>
         <subtitle>History in Contemporary Art</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Blocker</surname>
               <given-names>Jane</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780816696987</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781452944944</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1452944946</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Regents of the University of Minnesota</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt18s3115"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Is there such a thing as contemporary art history? The contemporary, after all-as much as we may want to consider it otherwise-is being made history as it happens. By what means do we examine this moving target? These questions lie at the center of Jane Blocker's<italic>Becoming Past</italic>. The important point is not whether there is-or should be-contemporary art history, Blocker argues, but how.</p>
         <p>Focusing on a significant aspect of current art practice?in which artists have engaged with historical subject matter, methods, and inquiry?Blocker asks how the creation of the artist implicates and interrogates that of the art historian. She moves from art history to theater, to performance, and to literature as she investigates a series of works, including performances by the collaborative group Goat Island, the film<italic>Deadpan</italic>by Steve McQueen, the philosophies of science fiction writer Samuel Delany and documentary filmmaker Ross McElwee, the film<italic>Amos Fortune Road</italic>by Matthew Buckingham, and sculptures by Dario Robleto.</p>
         <p>Many books have sought to understand the key directions of contemporary art. In contrast,<italic>Becoming Past</italic>is concerned with the application of art history in the pursuit of such trends. Setting the idea of temporality decisively in the realm of art, Blocker's work is crucial for artists, art historians, curators, critics, and scholars of performance and cultural studies interested in the role of history in the practice of art.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>HISTORY AS PROSTHESIS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To be a historian of contemporary art is to work in a rather challenging and uncomfortable profession. First, no one can really agree on what we’re talking about when we use the term<italic>contemporary</italic>, a word that develops etymologically from<italic>tempus</italic>and yet yields little understanding of time.<italic>Current, recent, new, up-to-date, modern, now, present, on the horizon—contemporary</italic>’s synonyms are as numerous as they are vague. Second, whatever the contemporary is, it’s clear there’s way too much of it. Terry Smith nicely explains the unique obstacles set in the way of the contemporary art historian when he writes: “Look</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>One</label>
                     <title>WOODEN LEGS:</title>
                     <subtitle>GOAT ISLANDʹS ACTS OF REPAIR</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter begins (despite Jacques Derrida’s suggestion that it be done otherwise) at a beginning. It is a borrowed beginning to be sure, but a beginning nonetheless. It is the story (a history, it seems important to emphasize, not of<italic>my</italic>making) of how the Chicago-based performance art group Goat Island began. Of this moment, Matthew Goulish (one of the group’s founding members) writes:</p>
                     <p>We began on Thanksgiving Day, 1986—Lin Hixson, the brothers Timothy McCain and Greg McCain, and I…. We agreed that we would share a kind of impossible problem from which we would generate material individually, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Two</label>
                     <title>HOUSES FALLING DOWN:</title>
                     <subtitle>ARCHIVAL VIOLENCE IN STEVE McQUEENʹS DEADPAN</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There’s a joke that goes like this: Pete and Repeat were sitting on a fence. Pete fell off so who was left? Repeat. Pete and Repeat were sitting on a fence. Pete fell off so who was left? Repeat.</p>
                     <p>Actor Walter Stevens tells this joke again and again, faster and faster, in Bruce Nauman’s 1987 video installation<italic>Clown Torture</italic>(Figure 12). Dressed in a garish clown costume, with ruffled cuffs and multicolored stripes, and made up in white greasepaint, a red nose, and exaggerated red lips, Stevens moves quickly from laughter to agitation and panic. He is trapped by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Three</label>
                     <title>INCORRECT AND INCOMPLETE:</title>
                     <subtitle>ROSS McELWEEʹS FICTIONS AND SAMUEL DELANYʹS LIES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Samuel Delany’s memoir begins with this laconic sentence: “My father had been sick almost a year.”¹ His journey of remembering sets out from and is oriented toward the emotional landmark of his father’s illness and death. That landmark, however, is no signpost, stone marker, or architectural structure heavily anchored to a place and drawn on a map. It is more like a scratch in a record that makes the needle stutter and skip. “For most of my life,” Delany recalls, “if it came up, I would tell you: ‘My father died of lung cancer in 1958 when I was seventeen.’”²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Four</label>
                     <title>THE EMPTY STAGE:</title>
                     <subtitle>A STORY ABOUT THE PAST BY MATTHEW BUCKINGHAM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I begin at the end. I begin in the melancholy and portentous mise-en-scène of the graveyard, the place where the dead lie among the living, where, as Joe Roach provocatively suggests, the tomb functions as a stage on which history is enacted. Roach, who argues that history is a theater of surrogates who stand in place of the dead, makes an intriguing comparison between the grave and performance. “A theatrical role,” he writes, “like a stone effigy on a tomb, has a certain longevity in time, but its special durability stems from the fact that it must be re-fleshed at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Five</label>
                     <title>STUPID BIRDS:</title>
                     <subtitle>TEMPORAL DISSIDENCE IN THE LASTMAKER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where you see an epigraph or a quotation, I am standing in the place of another, speaking in the voice of another, repeating the words of another. I am compressing and distorting time.</p>
                     <p>It starts with that stupid mechanical bird. In a scene near the beginning of Goat Island’s<italic>The Lastmaker</italic>, Matthew Goulish (one of the company’s performers, whom we met in chapter 1) positions a simple wooden chair on one side of an otherwise empty stage, pulls a small mechanical goldfinch from his pocket, starts it chirping by sliding a little switch on its feather-covered plastic belly, and sets</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Six</label>
                     <title>TRANSITIONAL OBJECTS:</title>
                     <subtitle>DARIO ROBLETOʹS SPOOLS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I begin with a game called “gone,” the rules of which Sigmund Freud describes in his famous account of his grandson Ernst’s peculiar behavior whenever his mother left him. “This good little boy,” Freud dotingly explains,</p>
                     <p>had an occasional disturbing habit of taking any small objects he could get a hold of and throwing them away from him into a corner, under the bed, and so on, so that hunting for his toys and picking them up was often quite a business…. I eventually realized that it was a game and that the only use he made of any of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                     <subtitle>WOODEN FEET: FRANCIS ALŸS AND SYNCOPATED TIME</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>About halfway into Goat Island’s final performance piece,<italic>The Lastmaker</italic>(2007–9), Karen Christopher is seated with erect posture on a simple wooden chair (Figure 49). With careful diction and precise enunciation, she gestures toward her shoe and instructs the audience: “The strip above the sole … that’s the welt. The frontal area that covers the instep … it’s called the vamp. The flap under the lace … the tongue. Laces, sole, heel. A front and a top. When I take my shoe to the shoemaker and he places it on a form to make repairs—a block shaped like</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18s3115.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
