<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h0b18</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">E99.M6R44 1995</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Micmac Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Maritime Provinces</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">18th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Micmac Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Maritime Provinces</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians of North America</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Government relations</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1830</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians of North America</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Government relations</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">1830-1860</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Micmac Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians of North America</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Maritime Provinces</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Acadia</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Myth, Symbol, and Colonial Encounter</book-title>
         <subtitle>British and Mi'kmaq in Acadia, 1700-1867</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>REID</surname>
               <given-names>JENNIFER</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776616599</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776616595</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cn6rz3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>From the time of the Treaty of Utrecht in 1713, people of British origin have shared the area of New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and Prince Edward Island, traditionally called Acadia, with Eastern Canada's Algonkian-speaking peoples, the Mi'kmaq. This historical analysis of colonial Acadia from the perspective of symbolic and mythic existence will be useful to those interested in Canadian history, native Canadian history, religion in Canada, and history of religion.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="133"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[ix]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is unabashedly concerned with the well-trod issue of native–white relations in Canada. I admit that the theme may be at best fashionable, at worst overworked; yet it remains that a great deal has yet to be said on the subject. My hope is that there might be some constructive value in approaching the issue from what will no doubt appear to be a less conventional perspective. The perspective I am suggesting is that of religion, and its value lies, I hope, in its potential for creatively confronting a problem of community that plagues Canadian society. I would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>RELIGION AND THE COLONIAL WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Oxford Dictionary</italic>defines the word<italic>stranger</italic>as a “foreigner, a person in a country or town or company that he does not belong to.” Rita Joe is Mi’kmaq, a poet born of a community of people who have lived in the region of Acadia² for at least five thousand years. She is also a stranger. She has experienced the ambiguity of the post-Columbian world, as one who knows her home has been re-created by a “company” of people to which she does not belong, a company that has taken precautions against her inclusion in a society constructed on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>LET NOT THY LEFT HAND KNOW WHAT THY RIGHT HAND DOETH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of thinking and living in the New World began, for the British in Acadia, with a problem of continuity of place. Fundamentally, theirs was the problem of imagining continuity where there was none. Complicating the issue, however, was the fact that a great many British settlers were possessed of a sense of identity that had been in some measure disfigured and that they were consequently trying to recover. In most cases, the identity that they sought to preserve was of British origin.</p>
                     <p>The two principal groups of immigrants who came to comprise the population base and colonial administrators</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>THE SHROUDING OF AMBIGUITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why is it that the British colonial language of inclusion (paternalistic and morally degrading though it was) was at such variance with colonial practice? The answer may lie in the British assertion of cultural purity that sought to create the colonial human being and Acadia itself, and that, paradoxically, constituted the foundation of calls for the civilization of aboriginal peoples. The claim to be firmly British was clearly problematic. These peoples’ European identity had been transformed in the process of becoming colonials. Western Europeans, for instance, were not scalpers; the British in eighteenth century Acadia were. After announcing in 1749</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>THE BOUNDARIES OF PURITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Colonial Acadia posed a different problematic for the Mi’kmaq. The influx of peoples of British ancestry that began around the turn of the eighteenth century threatened, first, the native community’s claim to be rightfully at home on the land desired by colonials and, subsequently, its liberty to exist at all in Acadia. For the Mi’kmaq, the problem was one of how to retain a sense of continuity of place and rootedness when these were placed in jeopardy by others’ denial of the fundamental human significance of aboriginal peoples.</p>
                     <p>Like their British contemporaries, the Mi’kmaq experienced eighteenth-century Acadia in terms of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>AT HOME IN COLONIAL ACADIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within both British and Mi’kmaq communities, the need for a sense of rootedness and continuity of place fuelled religious imaginations, giving rise to religious symbols that confronted the necessities of place while accounting for particular experiences. The lives that revolved around these were encrusted with myths that articulated specific instances of the unity provided by the symbols. In this sense, the religious imagination of all Acadia’s people struggled with the problem of identity and origins in a new world. Yet the problem was resolved in a critically divergent manner by each community so that, overwhelmingly, two distinct visions of human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>STILL STRANGERS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I began this inquiry by noting that one or another form of alienation appears to have been the experience of all Acadia’s peoples. The bulk of this work has concerned itself with a search for the historical roots of alienation, but it may not have constituted a historical analysis in any familiar sense of the term, since it has consciously focussed upon human religiosity as that which gives meaning to history. History, like religion, is very much a product of the scholar’s own historical context as well as of the scholar’s purpose for writing. In that sense, this historical work</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF NAMES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rz3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
