<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Imagining the popular in contemporary French culture</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HOLMES</surname>
               <given-names>DIANA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LOOSELEY</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781526130266</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1526130262</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Manchester University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1vwmf2w"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This groundbreaking book is about what ‘popular culture’ means in France, and how the term’s shifting meanings have been negotiated and contested. It represents the first theoretically informed study of the way that popular culture is lived, imagined, fought over and negotiated in modern and contemporary France. It covers a wide range of overarching concerns: the roles of state policy, the market, political ideologies, changing social contexts and new technologies in the construction of the popular. But it also provides a set of specific case studies showing how popular songs, stories, films, TV programmes and language styles have become indispensable elements of ‘culture’ in France. Deploying yet also rethinking a ‘Cultural Studies’ approach to the popular, the book therefore challenges dominant views of what French culture really means today.French Studies, Cultural Studies, Media Studies, Cultural Sociology, History/Cultural History. Specific chapters will be of relevance to: Cultural Policy, Popular Music Studies, Literary Studies, Film and TV Studies, Linguistics</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Figures and table</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction.</title>
                     <subtitle>Imagining the popular: lowbrow, highbrow, middlebrow</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holmes</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Looseley</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our aim in this book is to explore how the French in the twentieth and twenty-first centuries have come to imagine the popular in particular and distinctive ways: how popular-cultural texts or forms have, variously, been produced and received, theorised and judged. We are interested, then, in both discourse and practice in contemporary French popular culture.</p>
                     <p>This ambition is not quite as straightforward as it might seem. First, ‘discourse’ and ‘practice’ cannot always be neatly distinguished. Certainly, by discourse – or, more accurately, discourses – we partly mean what Morag Shiach (1989: 1) in her analysis of British popular-cultural discourse</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Politics and pleasure:</title>
                     <subtitle>inventing popular culture in contemporary France</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Looseley</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This first chapter focuses on political conceptualisations of popular culture in France, by which I mean conceptualisations developed by governments, parties, national institutions and the kind of public intellectuals who, as Ahearne (2010: 2) puts it, ‘have moved in and out of positions within public policy processes’. Other chapters in this volume will be concerned with popular-cultural artefacts themselves. My focus here is on how such artefacts have been institutionally represented over time. For if, as Kuisel claims, France itself is an invention, a conceptualisation, this is in part due to the way its popular culture has represented it and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Authenticity and appropriation:</title>
                     <subtitle>a discursive history of French popular music</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Looseley</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is about the meanings of popular music in France.¹ Music fans generally believe they know what they mean by ‘popular’ and ‘pop’; but not all of us can readily say what that is. Here, I shall use ‘popular’ to refer to what are, today, industrially produced forms of music directed at and appreciated by a very large, or ‘mass’, audience. Such forms do not usually require any conventional musical competence or erudition; and they are easily available on the market. I will take ‘pop (music)’ to mean something more specific, namely all forms of broadly speaking youth-oriented music</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The mimetic prejudice:</title>
                     <subtitle>the popular novel in France</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holmes</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As earlier chapters have pointed out, ‘popular’ is a capacious and slippery word. On the one hand, popular novels are simply the novels read and appreciated by a very large number of readers, as opposed to those that are canonised by critics and by literary histories but actually read by a relatively small élite. On the other hand, the ‘popular’ novel conjures up – if somewhat vaguely – a particular kind of fiction, raising the question of the aesthetic and philosophical specificity of the popular: do ‘popular’ novels conform to particular models of narrative? Do they deploy specifically ‘popular’ strategies?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Why popular films are popular:</title>
                     <subtitle>identification, imitation and critical mortification</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Platten</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To the intrepid film critic the term ‘popular French cinema’ might suggest an awkward taxonomy; in the bars and restaurants around town it would strike many as an oxymoron. Conventionally, France (and Paris especially) is seen as a hub of art-house cinema, a treasure trove of films of aesthetic and ethical superiority and a protected, national industry that epitomises the ‘European way’. The stereotype may obscure a diverse body of film, but outside the halls of the academy such diversities are rapidly homogenised; sophisticated cinema-goers mildly contemptuous of the feral free-marketeers of the American film industry happily juxtapose Eric Röhmer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>French television:</title>
                     <subtitle>negotiating the national popular</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mazdon</surname>
                           <given-names>Lucy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As has been argued in previous chapters, discourses relating to what constitutes popular culture in France have experienced a sweeping paradigm shift in the last fifty or so years. This has been witnessed across a range of cultural practices and philosophical and political debates. This period of change and negotiation coincides to a great extent with the development and gradual entrenchment of television in French cultural life, from its early days as a little-watched curiosity to its current incarnation as an ever-present and highly influential medium. To attempt to analyse the construction of the popular without addressing the role of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Social and linguistic change in French:</title>
                     <subtitle>does popular culture mean popular language?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Armstrong</surname>
                           <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The phenomenon of what might be called ‘social convergence’– the nexus of attitudes that in the last four decades or so has tended to erode hierarchical structures, emphasise the worth of the individual, promote the values of youth and working-class culture and accelerate the ‘decline of deference’– tends to be assumed as a given in the study of popular culture. Social convergence or levelling has had important effects on language in this period. In language, social convergence can be seen as standing in opposition to the ‘ideology of the standard’, a term in sociolinguistics used to refer to the attitude</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holmes</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Looseley</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ambition of this study has been to explore the diversity of ways in which the popular has been conceptualised and materialised in France. Whereas domestic and external accounts of French culture have spontaneously identified it with élite culture, we have argued that any rigorous analysis of it must integrate and engage with majority cultural practices. The relationship between state, national institutions and cultural production takes very particular forms in France, closely enmeshed as this relationship has been with a specific political history, and with the exceptionally strong presence of linguistic and literary tradition as a prized element of national</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vwmf2w.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
