<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Resounding Soul</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reflections on the Metaphysics and Vivacity of the Human Person</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lee</surname>
               <given-names>Eric Austin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kimbriel</surname>
               <given-names>Samuel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175989</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905562</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Wipf and Stock Publishers</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1hd17z7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>It is surely not coincidental that the term “soul" should mean not only the centre of a creature’s life and consciousness, but also a thing or action characterized by intense vivacity (“that bike’s got soul!"). It also seems far from coincidental that the same contemporary academic discussions that have largely cast aside the language of “soul" in their quest to define the character of human mental life should themselves be so – how to say it? – bloodless, so lacking in soul. This volume arises from the opposite premise, namely that the task of understanding human nature is bound up with and in important respects dependent upon the more critical task of learning to be fully human, of learning to have soul. The papers collected here are derived from a conference in Oxford sponsored by the Centre of Theology and Philosophy and together explore the often surprising landscape that emerges when human consciousness is approached from this angle. Drawing upon literary, philosophical, theological, historical, and musical modes of analysis, the essays of this volume vividly remind the reader of the power of the ancient language of soul over against contemporary impulses to reduce, fragment, and overly determine human selfhood.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="424"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kimbriel</surname>
                           <given-names>Samuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lee</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric Austin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is something curious about the frequency with which the term “soul” is now used in English in reference not to human beings but to inanimate objects. There is soul food and soulless fast food,² soul music and soulful music, and apparently, according to a friend, even my old Raleigh 3-speed bike has “got soul.”</p>
                     <p>Such language is one of many indications hidden within modern life that, whatever one may think in the clamorous halls of the academy<italic>about</italic>human nature, there are certain practices of humanity with which we are intertwined in daily existence. When faced with one another,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Experience of Death:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Immortality of the Soul and the Unity of the Person in Landsberg, Scheler, and Augustine</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Piazza</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most fecund themes of Paul Ludwig Landsberg’s anthropology, which stands out for a presentation of man’s potential “self-comprehension” on the basis of a lived “inner-experience,” is his reflection concerning death and the confrontation with the human conscience of death, which threatens the sense of life and the search for an overcoming of transitoriness. It was in<italic>Esprit</italic>where Landsberg published, in 1935, the two essays related to this topic,<italic>Die Erfahrung des Todes</italic>and<italic>Das moralische Problem des Selbstmorder</italic>. In particular, we would like to analyze the former, and compare it with the positions of two other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Bernard Stiegler’s Politics of the Soul and His New Otium of the People</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rossouw</surname>
                           <given-names>Johann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter will consider Bernard Stiegler’s political ideal, the new<italic>otium</italic>of the people, which, as will be shown, reveals his philosophical project ultimately to be not the consideration of “the pursuit of life through means other than life” (technics),³ but the pursuit of Christianity through means other than Christian. As will also be shown, of these means, art and the aesthetical are crucial for Stiegler, as is his “atheological” reading of Aristotle’s three levels of the soul.</p>
                     <p>For Stiegler, the central crisis of Western modernity is of a theological nature, namely, its loss of faith in its social order</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Eucharistic Anthropology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alexander Schmemann’s Conception of Beings in Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kaethler</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew T. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a broadcast to the Soviet Union, Alexander Schmemann boldly announced, “Christianity began with a new experience of time, in which time ceases to be bound-up with death. ‘O death, where is thy sting? O hell, where is thy victory?’ (1 Cor 15:55). This new experience is the very heart of Christianity and its fire ….”¹ Yet, throughout Schmemann’s extensive writing on time and the kingdom of God and his heavy emphasis on these themes, he does not explicitly, nor systematically lay out how this new experience of time shapes his theological anthropology. That is not to say that it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Psychology of Cosmopolitics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Milbank</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the contemporary world, defending the mind against reduction to the brain might seem task enough, without trying to defend that antique ghost, the soul. Theologians may presumptively seek to safeguard mind and the dignity of human status as a necessary first step, before mounting in some fashion an argument for the soul and its immortality.</p>
                     <p>But I would argue that this is a mistaken strategy. Outside a theological or a metaphysical purview, mind is actually indefensible and the human properly evaporates. Instead, the theologian needs to go for broke at the outset: soul is far more arguable than mind,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“Know Thyself”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Soul of Anatomical Dissection</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kornu</surname>
                           <given-names>Kimbell</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Sciences of the Soul</italic>, Fernando Vidal masterfully tells the story of the development of psychology as a discipline. He notes that the eighteenth century was the century of psychology, the empirical science that enables “knowing oneself.”¹ He argues that the “science of the soul” grows out of the Aristotelian-Galenic tradition of the Renaissance, evidenced by the introduction of the term<italic>psychologia</italic>by Protestant Scholastics in the later sixteenth century. On the one hand, the Aristotelian tradition maintains that body and soul are a unity, whereas the Galenic emphasizes the importance of anatomy for understanding physiology, on the other.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Persons and Narratives:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Physicalist Account of the Soul</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Forti</surname>
                           <given-names>K. Nicholas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the end, it did not take the promise of gaining the whole world to convince us to forfeit our souls; it just took a transformation of our minds by a reorientation of our hearts to a new story. Of course, some of the defenders and tellers of the new tale at times bemoan the vestiges of the old that still possess our language and thoughts, trapping the unenlightened in a demon-haunted world of make-believe. Among the concepts, tropes, phrases, and words that many of the heralds of the new age wish to sweep away like late day cobwebs obstinately</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Transcending the Body/Soul Distinction through the Perspective of Maximus the Confessor’s Anthropology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitralexis</surname>
                           <given-names>Sotiris</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does the question of the soul<italic>always</italic>and<italic>necessarily</italic>entail the dualistic dichotomy so characteristic of the body/soul discourse? And, if we do accept the existence of immortal souls and the prevalence of free will, how can these two coincide? How can the soul of a human person possessing a truly free will be<italic>compulsorily</italic>eternal? In this article I will address these two different but interconnected questions through examination of selected passages from Maximus the Confessor’s writings, in an attempt to trace possible answers.</p>
                     <p>A unique system of philosophical anthropology is to be discerned in St. Maximus the Confessor’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Nous (Energeia) and Kardia (Dynamis) in the Holistic Anthropology of St. Gregory Palamas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tănase</surname>
                           <given-names>Nichifor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Athonite spirituality of the fourteenth century is situated at the confluence of a theology of divine names already present in the Old Testament and of the ancient practice of monastic traditions, and is also illustrated by the writings of Evagrius and Ps.-Macarius. Hesychasm provides a deep, spiritual theological meaning by grafting the uncreated energies and a single word of prayer onto a theological conception of divine glory. Hesychastic spirituality is “able to assimilate and integrate creatively, as in the case of Evagrius, for whom the mystical tendencies are colored by Neoplatonism and Stoicism.”¹</p>
                     <p>The three stages of development of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Souls, Minds, Bodies, and Planets</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Midgley</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What does it mean to say that we have got a mind-body problem? Do we need to think of our inner and outer lives as two separate items between which business must somehow be transacted, rather than as aspects of a whole person?</p>
                     <p>Dualist talk assumes that we already have before us two separate things which we don’t see how to connect. This is a seventeenth-century way of seeing the problem. It is tied to views in physics and many other topics that we no longer hold.</p>
                     <p>“Mind” and “matter,” conceived as separate in this way, are extreme abstractions. These</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Soul in the Novel:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Daniel Defoe to David Foster Wallace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Waldstein</surname>
                           <given-names>Edmund</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The novel developed as a literary form particularly suited to a certain typically modern view of the division between soul and body—a view that makes a very sharp distinction between the inner, psychic reality and the outer corporeal reality; between the<italic>res cogitans</italic>and the<italic>res extensa</italic>; between interiority and exteriority; between the subject and the object; between the world of “the first-person” and that of the “third person.” The novel, I claim, was particularly suited to expressing the world as experienced through this dualism. I shall illustrate this by looking at Daniel Defoe’s<italic>Robinson Crusoe</italic>. I shall then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Difficult Conversion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Shakespeare and the Soul of Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baker</surname>
                           <given-names>Anthony D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the character Prologue comes to the stage in Ben Jonson’s<italic>Staple of News</italic>, he delivers an injunction at the bidding, he claims, of the playwright, that the audience mark “a difference ‘twixt Poetique elves, and Poets,” as something like the difference between imitators and the real thing:</p>
                     <p>All that dable in the inke,</p>
                     <p>And defile quills, are not those few, can think,</p>
                     <p>Conceive, expresse, and steere the soules of men,</p>
                     <p>As with a rudder, round thus, with their pen.¹</p>
                     <p>On one level, this is a simple brag that Jonson puts in the mouth of his narrator: I am a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Both, Between, and Beyond:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Third Term and the Relation Constituting Being</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilson</surname>
                           <given-names>L. C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Separated by centuries, but united by their faith, and a certain kind of idiosyncratic genius, both Evagrius of Pontus and Søren Kierkegaard developed the traditional concept of “the soul” within anthropologies grounded in their dynamic metaphysics. Each posited a tripartite composition of the human being, consisting of body, mind/soul, and soul/spirit. Despite the variable terminology used by the thinkers (and their translators), both employed a “third term” to designate the relation between the person’s corporeal and incorporeal aspects: a relation that is, itself, constitutive of the character of one’s being and a litmus test for one’s moral and spiritual health.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Strategies of the Gift:</title>
                     <subtitle>Body and Soul in John Paul II and Levinas</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zimmermann</surname>
                           <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of the body-soul relationship is treated by Emmanuel Levinas and St. John Paul II as one of describing the manifestation of the other person in terms of the gift. The soul, assuming such an objective reality exists, is taken to bear itself in the world only in so far as it is manifested in the body. However, in describing the significance of the body in Levinas and John Paul II, two differing trajectories of the gift emerge, which meet in convergence and departure. Both thinkers draw upon a phenomenologically informed set of intellectual commitments, and both incorporate language</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Redeeming Duality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anthropological Split-ness and Embodied Soteriology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eikelboom</surname>
                           <given-names>Lexi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There have been many recent theological attempts to argue for a more holistic anthropology than that which substance-dualism has traditionally provided.¹ The proponents of holistic anthropology have several motives—an increased recognition of the importance of the body,² a respect for scientific research that points towards physicalism,³ and a desire to reflect biblical anthropology,⁴ for example. However, the desire for a more holistic anthropology, whether of the materialist or non-reductive physicalist variety, is also motivated by a theological suspicion of split-ness itself. If Christians affirm the existence of the soul in some sense, they must also accept that the human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Music and Liminal Ethics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Facilitating a “Soulful Reality”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stone-Davis</surname>
                           <given-names>Ferdia J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This article takes as its starting-point the conception of the soul as “the medium in which we dwell as human beings.” It also acknowledges that this dwelling occurs relationally, since it is only in response to and in dialogue with an environment that a “soulful reality” can emerge. It is on this basis that a consideration of music is undertaken. Music operates by means of thresholds, encouraging a certain porosity that mediates notions of “inner” and “outer” in a unique way, and facilitating the development of the subject as both “interior” and “exterior,” both “active” and “passive,” as both “giver”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>The Soul and “All Things”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contribution to a Postmodern Account of the Soul</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hackett</surname>
                           <given-names>W. Chris</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The soul is a necessary concept for Christian theology, for an account of Christian religious experience and for the philosophy that cannot help finding itself thinking from within this domain—and perhaps, further, for any thinking that wants to do full justice to our human experience of ourselves and others as bearing permanent identities and inestimable value. This necessity is doubled when we recognize that the<italic>soul</italic>, like its perennial corollary concepts<italic>God</italic>and the<italic>world</italic>, is a concept that bears within itself a critique of the fundamental<italic>mythos</italic>of conceptual rationality: it asserts the primacy of personality and freedom</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>The Soul at Work:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Reading in Catholic Romanticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kotva</surname>
                           <given-names>Simone</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>330</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dresden, the winter of 1828–29. In the final months of a life not wanting in notoriety, Friedrich Schlegel (born 1772) delivers a set of curious lectures “concerning in particular the philosophy of language and words.”¹ They are the third part of a trilogy, collectively christened the Philosophy of Life<italic>(Philosophie des Lebens)</italic>,² which argues that the Divine telos of the soul, “the full and living centre of consciousness,”³ lies in the restoration of the imago Dei. Despite this stolid appeal to doctrine, Schlegel’s late<italic>Philosophy of Life</italic>has caused continual embarrassment for scholars of Romanticism, focusing the eye on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Soul Music and Soul-less Selving</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Desmond</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>352</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While there is such a thing as “soul music,” there is no such thing as “self music.” Why is this? What is the difference between the two? And is not the language of “self” all pervasive in our cultures, while the language of soul seems to have gone into eclipse, especially among the more modernly educated persons? Why is this? What might be at issue in the music of the soul in soul music, and the music-less self without soul. “Oh self, self, self. At every turn nothing but self”—so expostulates Charles Dickens’s Martin Chuzzlewit.¹ And yet for all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hd17z7.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>390</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
