<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Seamus Heaney</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Introduction</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Russell</surname>
               <given-names>Richard Rankin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474401654</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474401678</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Richard Rankin Russell</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g04zp7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This study will enable readers to gain clearer understanding of the life and major works of Seamus Heaney. It considers literary influences on Heaney, ranging from English poets such as Wordsworth, Hughes, and Auden to Irish poets such as Kavanagh and Yeats to world poets such as Virgil and Dante.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="312"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Legend</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Seamus Heaney’s 2013 poem, “On the Gift of a Fountain Pen,” provides an appropriate starting point for this critical introduction to his work since it encapsulates his central concern—the role of the writer. In pondering his vocation, Heaney has always worried about his obligation to others—not just readers, but also to the general public—and this poem vocalizes that worry ably. Moreover, he seems also to fear a drying-up of inspiration here. Drawing on John Keats’s “When I Have Fears that I May Cease to Be,” he opens by musing, “Now that your pen is in my hand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Life and Contexts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Seamus Heaney’s work vacillates restlessly between the demand for solitude by the artistic self and the lure of communal intimacy, a dialectic captured most memorably in his 1979 elegy “Casualty,” which begins by praising the solitude of a dead friend, an eel fisherman, moves to an appreciation of the Catholics murdered on Bloody Sunday, and then concludes in solitude again by recalling a fishing trip he took with the slain fisherman, Louis O’Neill. Somewhat surprisingly for one who “in the early 1970s … surely did identify with the Catholic minority,”¹ he rejects what he perceives as the “swaddling band” of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Burrowing and Bogs:</title>
                     <subtitle>Early Poems, Death of a Naturalist, Door into the Dark, Wintering Out, North</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter and the fifth one pay great attention to the volumes that bookend Heaney’s career—<italic>Death of a Naturalist</italic>and<italic>Human Chain</italic>—to show the arc of his poetic development, the way themes first adumbrated in the 1966 volume are carried through, re-explored, transformed, and sometimes dropped by the time of the 2010 volume. All the poetry chapters also spend more time on his best volumes—my top five, in chronological order, are<italic>North, Field Work, Station Island, Seeing Things,</italic>and<italic>Human Chain</italic>—than it does on the slighter ones, many of which nonetheless have poems I analyze that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Reading the Ground and the Sky:</title>
                     <subtitle>Field Work, Station Island, The Haw Lantern</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Heaney wrote that his four years living in Glanmore, County Wicklow, from 1972 to 1976 constituted “the first time in my adult life that I had lived continuously in the countryside, and the first time that I had lived anywhere as a full time writer, uncushioned by the routine—and salary—of a teaching position.”¹ That concentrated focus on his writing led him back to reflections about his poetic vocation:</p>
                     <p>Those four years were an important growth time when I was asking myself questions about the proper function of poets and poetry and learning a new commitment to the art.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Radiance:</title>
                     <subtitle>Seeing Things, The Spirit Level, Electric Light</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Heaney published his<italic>New Selected Poems 1966–1987</italic>in 1990 after turning fifty in 1989. The volume gathers his selections from his first seven volumes, but he also made sure to include seven prose poems from Stations and five sections from his translation,<italic>Sweeney Astray</italic>. Including those prose poems and translations suggests how he viewed that work in other genres as complementing his poetry from the same period. Moreover, the prose poems and the sections from<italic>Sweeney</italic>suggest a poet more formally adventuresome than admirers of Heaney the lyric poet may realize, maybe even than he presents: after all, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Return:</title>
                     <subtitle>District and Circle, Human Chain, and Late Uncollected Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Winner of the most prestigious prize for poetry in the United Kingdom, the T. S. Eliot Prize, along with the<italic>Irish Times</italic>“Poetry Now” Award,<italic>District and Circle</italic>both returns Heaney to his home district of Bellaghy in Northern Ireland and signifies his continued commitment to representing the suffering of others globally by incorporating the titles of two of London’s Underground lines in the wake of the bombings there in July, 2005. The title poem bespeaks his continuing interest in underground, subterranean spaces evinced from the beginning of his poetry by dwelling in the London Underground and interacting with actual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Prose, Drama, and Translations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First-time readers of Heaney may not be aware of his major achievement in other genres, which are so rich and deep that treating them in their entirety lies beyond the scope of this introductory study, focused as it is on his poetry. But those who teach Heaney’s work or who have followed his career know that he has become one of the foremost critics and translators of our time, as well as having written some fine “versions” of Greek drama, including<italic>The Cure at Troy</italic>, after Sophocles’<italic>Philoctetes</italic>, and<italic>The Burial at Thebes</italic>, after the same playwright’s<italic>Antigone</italic>. In what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Primary Works by Seamus Heaney</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>260</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Annotated Bibliography of Selected Critical Books, Book Chapters, Interviews, and Essay Collections</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g04zp7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
