<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX1795.N36 F54 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Grace (Theology)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Thomas, Aquinas, Saint, 1225?–1274</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Doctrines</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Analogies of Transcendence</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FIELDS</surname>
               <given-names>STEPHEN M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813228556</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813228563</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d8hbbv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The problem of nature and grace lies at the heart of Christian theology. No dimension of divine revelation can be addressed without implicitly drawing reference to this issue.Analogies of Transcendence focuses on the central role that the analogies of being and faith play in developing a solution to the problem. These link God, as self-manifesting transcendence, to the human person as both fallen and justified, and to the material cosmos. Although the proposed solution draws on the work of Maréchal, de Lubac, Balthasar, and Rahner, it criticizes their approach for its underdeveloped analogies that diminish nature in grace's engagement with it. In redressing this weakness, Fr. Fields adapts its solution to the intellectual struggle of our time. This volume examines the origins and structure of modernity, which, it asserts, has not been superseded and is therefore critical of'‘postmodernism,' as well as of some ambiguous legacies of Thomism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stephen Duffy observes that “no dimension of Christian life or thought can be addressed without” at least implicit recourse to the problem of nature and grace.¹ Precisely because of its fundamental importance, it embraces an exceedingly long and complex history. It has generated magisterial pronouncements, fulminated controversies that have fractured Christendom, and pitted religious orders against each other. Moreover, no commentator in whatever era can say anything meaningful about the subject without appealing to metaphysics, which finds little sympathy in today’s agnosticism about universal truth claims. The question thus arises: how is it currently possible for someone to address the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>MODERN ESTRANGEMENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contemporary philosopher of culture Louis Dupré argues that the passing of the Baroque lost for the West its last great harmony between nature and grace. The Baroque achieved this harmony through a dynamic understanding of the human person in its intrinsic relation to its transcendent source. In this understanding, human creativity is appreciated not only because it follows its own rules and standards but precisely because, in the complexity of these rules and standards, it symbolizes the divine.¹ Baroque culture is thus essentially representational.² In the plastic arts, for instance, Roman and Bavarian churches are filled with forms and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>ATTEMPTED REUNIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen that<italic>Dei Verbum</italic>expansively recapitulates medieval exegesis. Building on the letter as the intrinsic symbol of the spirit, it understands divine revelation as a system of continuous symbols that join together Christ, his words and works, the apostolic tradition of the church, and the written scriptures and their interpretation. Whenever a synthesis is grounded in symbolism, its aesthetic dimension cannot help but be invoked. Heidegger reminds us, for instance, that symbolism constitutes the essence of art.¹ In the creative fashioning of an artifact, truth itself is preserved as beauty. Accordingly, if the Son is the Father’s image,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>RECENT WEDDING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Influenced by recent efforts to reunite nature and grace, the thought of Popes John Paul II and Benedict XVI seizes on the harmonious interpenetration of both orders. Exploiting the creative tension between these orders, the pontiffs expound a paradox: nature realizes its own autonomy only when it mediates a higher synthesis. A theme thus uniting their work concerns nature as grace’s sacrament. In John Paul, this theme undergirds the reciprocity between faith and reason and guides his reflections on the eucharist. In Benedict, nature understood as grace’s sacrament structures the relation between justice and charity. In developing this relation, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>SACRAMENTAL CAUSALITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous three chapters have selectively probed into the last seven hundred years of nature and grace’s relation. Let us take stock of our findings. In the first place, we have seen what blind alleys to avoid. On the one hand, we have concluded that the theory of pure nature, at least as putatively grounded in Thomas, contains two equivocations of the concept of the good. These continue problematically to influence some modern theology, in addition to having contributed to the breakdown of the Baroque synthesis. Perhaps sensitive to this contribution, recent papal thought tends to signal a turn away</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>AESTHETICS, ANALOGY, AND GOD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have developed a sacramental model of nature’s relation to grace. As grace’s “own other,” nature incarnates grace in order for grace to realize its saving purpose. Because the redemption presupposes the created order for its own subsistence, nature cannot be conceived without its graced finalization. Grace, as we have seen, calls nature into being precisely so that grace can charge nature with its life. Drawing out the implications of this model, chapters 5 and 6 will now explore the following issue: if nature is never pure, but always obtains with grace as a unity-in-difference, then those data that belong</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>NOVELTY, ANALOGY, AND GOD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our argument thus far has relied on Dupré’s observation that the ontotheological synthesis of the West consists of three elements: the noetic subject as the interpreter of reality; the extra-subjective cosmos; and the transcendent source of both. Dupré affirms that modernity results from mind’s assertion of its creative prerogatives over against a more passive assimilation of the physical world on whose forms mind, in other respects, depends. In meeting the modern problem with a model of nature and grace, chapter 4 argued that Thomas’s instinct of faith, as retrieved by Seckler, accounts for the dynamic release of the human subject’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>RELIGIONS, ANALOGY, AND CHRISTIANITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among recent thinkers who affirm Christianity as absolute, discussion of its relation to other religions revolves—and often not too amicably—around the polarity between an “optimistic and broad” inclusivism and a “negative and strict” exclusivism.¹ These approaches are not altogether new. They retrieve and develop three models that have emerged in the tradition of Christian reflection. Inclusivism draws on two models. The first, notable in Thomas, sees non-Christian religions as useful preparations for the Gospel (<italic>praeparatio evangelii</italic>). Its scriptural roots lie in Romans 1: 18, where Paul defends knowledge of God and virtue from the natural law. The next</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If this modest work has achieved its purpose, it has indicated the need, within the human person’s single graced end, for a robust concept of nature. Although weakened, it can be rebuilt, we have argued, by developing a better understanding of the complex analogies that constitute its relation with its partner. We have also argued that the sacramental model constituted by these analogies can address modernity. Moreover, in the essay’s last part, we have shown how this model can deepen insights into several of Christianity’s perennial problems: the doctrine of God, God’s relation with the world, and the relation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix.</title>
                     <subtitle>The Realsymbol and Selected Modern Symbols</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hbbv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
