<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DG533.B867 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Renaissance</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Italy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Cultural fusion</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Italy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Italy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Court and courtiers</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Cities and towns</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Italy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Borderlands</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Italy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Italy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1268–1559</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Renaissance</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Cultural fusion</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Architecture and Architectural History</subject>
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Hybrid Renaissance</book-title>
         <subtitle>Culture, Language, Architecture</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Burke</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789633860878</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789633860885</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Budapest; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Peter Burke</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7829/j.ctt1d4txq4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Hybrid Renaissance presents the Renaissance in Italy, elsewhere in Europe and in the world beyond Europe as an example of cultural hybridization. It is impossible to give a clear definition of either of the two key concepts used in this book, “hybridization" and “Renaissance". Roughly speaking, hybridity refers to something new that emerges from the combination of diverse older elements. The term “hybridization" is preferable to “hybridity" because it refers to a process rather than to a state, and also because it encourages the writer and the readers alike to think in terms of more or less rather than of presence versus absence. The book begins with a discussion of the concept of cultural hybridity and a cluster of other concepts related to it. Then comes a geography of hybridity, focusing on three locales: courts, major cities (whether ports or capitals) and frontiers. There follow six chapters about the hybrid Renaissance in different fields: architecture, painting and sculpture, languages, literatures, music, philosophy and law and finally religion. The essay concludes with a brief account of attempts to resist hybridization or to purify cultures or domains from what was already hybridized</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="284"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Expanding Renaissance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is a revised and expanded version of the Natalie Davis lectures for 2013, delivered at the Central European University in Budapest. It presents the Renaissance in Italy, elsewhere in Europe and in the world beyond Europe as an example, or series of examples, of cultural hybridization. In this study, a wide range of the many products of the Renaissance will be examined as evidence of the processes of interaction from which they emerged.</p>
                     <p>Readers should be warned at the start that it is impossible to give a clear definition of either of the two key concepts used in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>The Idea of Cultural Hybridity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The central theme of these lectures was inspired, obviously enough, by current discussions of cultural hybridity, themselves a response to recent trends such as globalization, mass migration, and debates about multiculturalism. As the world changes, historians come to look at the past from different angles and to ask different questions about it from their predecessors. This point is as true of the Renaissance as it is of (say) the French Revolution. In the last generation, a number of studies of the Renaissance, and especially studies of the reception of the Renaissance, from Jan Białostocki to Thomas Kaufmann, from Fernando Marías</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>The Geography of Hybridity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Awareness of alternatives and particularly intensive hybridization could be found in three kinds of place in particular: in courts, which were often cosmopolitan; in multicultural cities; and on cultural frontiers.</p>
                     <p>Courts were magnets for talented people from a variety of countries. Italian humanist expatriates served as official historians to the rulers of Hungary, Spain, France, England and elsewhere. Some artists and musicians moved from court to court, like the lutenistcomposer Valentin Bakfark, who was active in his native Transylvania, Poland and Austria, or his English colleague John Dowland, who worked in Paris and Copenhagen as well as in London.</p>
                     <p>The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Translating Architecture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Walking round Paris in the 1980s, I was both surprised and impressed to discover the church of St Eustache, near Les Halles (fig.2). From a distance the church, begun in 1532, looks Gothic, but on a closer inspection many details, inside and out, are classical. How was such a mixture possible? At that point I was not aware of any discussion of the building, although in the nineteenth century, St Eustache had been condemned by the famous French architect Eugene Viollet-le-Duc as a “confused heap of debris borrowed from all over the place, lacking connections and lacking harmony”. Since Viollet’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Hybrid Arts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the introduction to this book remarked, the idea that some of the art of the Renaissance should be viewed as hybrid was put forward early in the twentieth century by some Central European art historians. This chapter will try to develop their ideas by discussing painting, sculpture and the decorative arts, first in Italy, then in the rest of Europe and finally in other parts of the world.</p>
                     <p>As we have seen, in the 1920s August Schmarsow and Frederick Antal were already discussing the survival of Gothic in Renaissance Italy. Antal presented a famous contrast between the classical Virgin</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Hybrid Languages</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An alternative title for this chapter might be “polyglossia”, a term that the Russian literary theorist Mikhail Bakhtin employed to describe the coexistence and consequent “dialogue” between different languages (his more famous term “heteroglossia” described the interaction of varieties of the same language).² The languages of Europe in the Renaissance were enriched by borrowing or appropriation on a massive scale. For example, the period 1530-1660 “presents the fastest word growth in the history of English in proportion to the vocabulary size of the time”.³ In the history of language, as in the history of visual culture, the movement we call</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Hybrid Literatures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is concerned with hybrid writing and especially those forms of writing now known as “literature” and formerly as<italic>belles-lettres</italic>, a term that is not easy to translate into English. It will include history alongside poetry, plays and the prose fiction we describe as “novels”, while contemporaries called them “romances”. In fact, writing was not the only medium in which these works circulated, since oral performances were commonplace. The circulation of texts in performance, manuscript and print suggests that we think in terms of hybrid media.</p>
                     <p>Different forms of script coexisted at this time. The movement to revive classical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Music, Law and Humanism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Music is often regarded today as the hybrid art<italic>par excellence</italic>. The twentieth century in particular offered a whole range of examples of new forms emerging from the encounter between European and African cultures, especially in the Americas, from New Orleans to Salvador or Havana. In the case of the Renaissance, on the other hand, musical hybridity is problematic. There are two problems in particular.</p>
                     <p>In the first place, the music of the period does not fit as well into the category of the Renaissance as other arts do.¹ The music of the ancient Greeks and Romans could not be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Hybrid Philosophies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of the compatibility or incompatibility of ancient Greek philosophy with Christianity, acute in the fourth century, resurfaced in the thirteenth, the time of the rediscovery of Aristotle in Western Europe. Thomas Aquinas might be said to have translated Christianity into the language of Aristotle in his famous<italic>Summae</italic>of philosophy and theology. Other medieval philosophers went even further than Aquinas in appropriating the ideas of Aristotle. They were described as “Averroists” (<italic>Averroistae</italic>) in other words followers of the twelfth-century Muslim polymath and commentator on Aristotle Ibn Rushd, known in the medieval West as Averroes. Aquinas criticized the Averroists</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Translating Gods</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the domain of religion, the evidence of interactions between different beliefs and practices in the long sixteenth century is inescapable. Whether or not these interactions are part of the Renaissance movement is a more difficult and controversial question. However, the revival of antiquity, especially the “patristic revival” (the renewed interest in Augustine, Jerome and other leading figures of the early Church), was important in the history of Christianity in this period. The writings of the Fathers, which exemplify the Hellenization of Christianity, were influential on Catholics and Protestants alike.</p>
                     <p>Like hybrid law, hybrid religion needs to be discussed at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda.</title>
                     <subtitle>Counter-Hybridization</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The processes which have been discussed in this book under the umbrella of the general term “hybridization” did not meet with everyone’s approval at the time, as the use of pejorative terms such as “mish-mash”, “hotchpotch” or “bastard” vividly suggest. In this brief coda, the attempt will be made to view them from a different perspective, not as solutions but as problems. The process of hybridization, it was suggested earlier, may be conscious or unconscious. On the other hand, opposition to the process is necessarily conscious, whether it takes the weaker form of resistance or the stronger form of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txq4.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
