<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ms2k</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PT8175.B545Z7 1994</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dinesen, Isak, 1885-1962</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminist literary criticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Isak Dinesen and Narrativity</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Woods</surname>
               <given-names>Gurli A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>1994</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780886292447</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773573949</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa, ON, Canada</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1994</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Individual Authors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zvc7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Responding to recent Dinesen scholarship and public exposure in such films as Out of Africa and</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="260"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rutland</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Woods</surname>
                           <given-names>Gurli A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much has happened in Dinesen criticism in North America since Robert Langbaum launched his ground breaking study<italic>The Gayety of Vision</italic>in 1964.This book opened up the academic world in North America to an interest in the fiction of Danish writer Karen Blixen whose chosen pen name for her English speaking readers was Isak Dinesen. It is beyond the scope of this brief introduction to list the considerable amount of criticism published since then, but for the purposes of situating the resent collection of Dinesen criticism in context, the following important factors should be mentioned.</p>
                     <p>Despite the fact that Dinesen herself insisted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Consuming Isak Dinesen</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aiken</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan Hardy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the wake of the Academy-Award winning films of<italic>Out of Africa</italic>and Babette's Feast, “Isak inesen” has once again become a pop icon, the subject of fascinated speculation, fashionable imitation, and culinary fabrication. In the United States alone stories about her have turned up everywhere from the sophisticated reviews of the<italic>New York Times</italic>to the cruder pages of<italic>People magazine</italic>;¹ her image inspired the so-called “Safari Look” and appeared on the cover of Banana Republic catalogues; and from coast to coast, those privileged few who possessed the purchase price have been able to regale themselves in posh restaurants on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Life as Fiction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narrative Appropriation in Isak Dinesen’s Out of Africa</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gunnars</surname>
                           <given-names>Kristjana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Out of Africa</italic>has been considered generically elusive. As Susan Hardy Aiken writes in her recent book<italic>Isak Dinesen and the Engendering of Narrative, Out of Africa is</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>[s]ituated between the discourses of history and myth, fact and fiction,prose and poetry; partaking generically of forms as diverse as pastoral elegy, classical tragedy, autobiography, memoir, and travel tale; compounded of narrative, philosophical speculation, aphorism, parabolic reflection and song. . . .¹</p>
                     <p>Rather than take the lack of generic distinctiveness as a weakness, Aiken celebrates the complexities of Dinesen's prose as an example of a woman's text. Rather than consider the author's</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sp(l)acing out of the (Sub)Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rewriting through Landscapes in Isak Dinesen’s Out of Africa</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Scott</surname>
                           <given-names>H. Jill</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sp(l)acing: For Derrida “spacing” is the becoming-absent, or the becoming-unconscious of the subject; it is the shifting of the metaphysical opposition of space/time off-centre, re-spacing, re-placing it. Writing is spacing, writing is woman, the inauthentic, the mime, at once present and absent, same and different (Jardine 184).</p>
                     <p>My bracketed (1) signifies the meeting point of “place” and “space” as presence, but mute and therefore absence, like its polysemic associations: “elle”/she; “ailes" the wings of her ex-positionality; capital “L” embodying the metaphysical dialectic of the angle, which must explode into the metaphors of woman;³ and lastly as the small (1), symbol</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lilith and Gender Equality in Isak Dinesen’s “The Supper at Elsinore” and “The Old Chevalier”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Woods</surname>
                           <given-names>Gurli A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Lilith figure is a very complex one that likely predates the Biblical Hebrews. Raphael Patai traces her “mythical biography” to the “Sumerianculture about the middle of the 3rd millennium B.C.”¹ He further states that</p>
                     <p>no she-demon has ever achieved as fantastic a career as Lilith who started out from the lowliest of origins, was a failure as Adam's intended wife,became the paramour of lascivious spirits, rose to be the bride of Samaelthe demon King, ruled as the Queen of Zemargad and Sheba, and finallyended up as the consort of God himself. . . . [B]y the Talmudic period (2nd</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tapping the Roots:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hidden Sources of Power in Isak Dinesen’s “The Dreamers”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barnwell</surname>
                           <given-names>Kathryn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The Dreamers” was probably the first story of Seven Gothic Tales tohave been written after Dinesen returned to Rungstedlund, having left her African life behind her. And since she did nothing to discourage a comparison between herself and Pellegrina Leoni, the story’s mysterious central figure, we might suppose that this particular tale had a special significance for its author. Like Pellegrina, Dinesen had suffered loss by fire, had attempted suicide¹ and was forced to leave behind a life which had seemed perfectly resonant of her deepest self. Also like her heroine,Dinesen ever after mistrusted investing herself fully in one persona.In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mallarméan Poetics and Isak Dinesen’s Politis in “The Blank Page”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gabriel</surname>
                           <given-names>Barbara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of Dinesen's haunting tale suggests the white-on-white of acanvas by Russian painter Kasimir Malevich, reversing the Derridean reading of Western thought to construct a metaphysics of<italic>absence</italic>. It is the same non-meaning at the centre of the still geometry of Mondrian and Rothko, echoing formally the vanishing point at the heart of the ancient Mandala paradigm. But although concepts of void, emptiness, and silenceare at the centre of a number of non-Western belief systems, they have been marginalized historically in the institutionalized teachings of the Judeo-Christian tradition, constituting a way of knowing for the most partsituated within hermetic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Poetics of the Story:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Symbolist Tendencies in Isak Dinesen’s Fiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JØrgensen</surname>
                           <given-names>Bo Hakon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Isak Dinesen’s youth coincided with the period of Symbolism in Denmark. She was fifteen years old in 1903, and nineteen when her favourite collection of poems<italic>Djævlerier</italic>[Devilries] (1904) was published,written by the Danish poet she appreciated most of all, Sophus Claussen. Later Dinesen made the statement to Aage Henriksen, one of the young men at Rungstedlund after the Second World War, that Sophus Claussen was theonly one, of all the Danish poets, who was “free.”</p>
                     <p>Unfortunately translations are unable to express the special mixture of humour and irony which characterizes Claussen's work. If this were not the case he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Isak Dinesen Among the Victorians:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Shared Symbolic Techniques</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stambaugh</surname>
                           <given-names>Sara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1985 I participated in the Karen Blixen/Isak Dinesen InternationalConference hosted by Poul Houe at the University of Minnesota. As I recall, of the opening speakers (not listed on the program), three, including Robert Langbaum, emphasized that reading Dinesen had shifted their perceptions and changed their way of reading. Like Malli in Dinesen's “Tempests,” I was struck, because Isak Dinesen had done the same thing tome. In this paper, therefore, I want to explain how Dinesen illustrates the reading of British Victorian literature and vice versa. In fact, my paper could perhaps be subtitled “An Apologia for a Victorian Scholar's</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Isak Dinesen Versus Postmodernism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Criticism of Modernity and the Problem of Non-simultaneousness in Relation to Isak Dinesen’s Works</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kyndrup</surname>
                           <given-names>Morten</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The very notion of a genuine postmodernist view of the world would certainly be a<italic>contradictio in adjecto</italic>. In this paper I shall discuss the criticism of Modernity and the problem of non-simultaneousness in relation to Dinesen's work, and this discussion will in turn be seen in relation to the ideas of postmodernism as a certain state of sign production and receptionon the borderlines, i.e., behind and consequently inside of what we call Modernity. As a start, I shall provide a rough outline of the kind of framework in which we talk about postmodernism. Secondly, I shall try to show</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Methods of Narratology and Rhetoric for Analyzing Isak Dinesen’s “The Blank Page”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Halsall</surname>
                           <given-names>Albert W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The principal problem posed by Dinesen's story, “The Blank Page” is one of<italic>ethos</italic>. Put very simply, and as Dinesen quite accurately foresaw, in my view, the story's credibility or plausibility is the problem most likely to trouble readers whose ideological presuppositions do not commit them to reading it as a tract, feminist or otherwise. To prove my thesis, I will have recourse to two critical methods which should, I hope, function as symbiotic agents of analysis. Formal narratology, of the sort developed by French Structuralists like Barthes, Genette and the<italic>École de Paris</italic>, enables one to describe the text's</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Silent Tale:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pragmatic Strategy in Isak Dinesen’s “The Blank Page”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kemp</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his analysis of a short narrative text which ends ambiguously,Umberto Eco concludes that the story being told is actually the story of the reader’s failure in reading the story.¹ This “naive” reader’s complacent acceptance of narrative conventions and ideological assumptions deliberately inscribed in the text leads to an impasse in interpretation. Instead of the expected denouement there is an impossible, or paradoxical, outcome. Only a critical reading, such as the one performed in “<italic>Lector in Fabula,</italic>” can overcome the frustrated conventional reading and detect the “pragmatic strategy” in the text. By self-critical I mean both the text's criticism of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Phenomenon of Intertextuality and the Role of Androgyny in Isak Dinesen’s “The Roads Round Pisa”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Black</surname>
                           <given-names>Casey Bjerregaard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Intertextuality can be construed in a narrow way as a synonym for the explicit or indirect references that go by the name of allusion. More broadly conceived, however, to speak of intertextuality is to recognize that allliterary texts are interlinked and that no single text is an island of meaningunto itself. As Jonathan Culler puts it in<italic>Structuralist Poetics</italic>:</p>
                     <p>A work can only be read in connection with or against other texts, which provide a grid through which it is read and structured by establishing expectations which enable one to pick out salient features and give them a structure.¹</p>
                     <p>Thus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Isak Dinesen’s “The Pearls:”</title>
                     <subtitle>Resentment and the Economy of Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Foshay</surname>
                           <given-names>Toby</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most writers on Isak Dinesen's fiction point to its narrative traditionalism. The precisely described historical settings, the distinct characters with their clearly determined social identities, and the classical third person omniscient narration employed by Dinesen in her tales are cited in evidence. But, as Robert Langbaum observes, this surface traditionalism is principally dedicated not to the unfolding of a conventional diachronic plot, but to the construction of a synchronic thematic structure. As he describes it:</p>
                     <p>The main question in an Isak Dinesen story is not what will happen next,but what is happening now or what is the meaning of what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Deconstructing the Fictional World of Isak Dinesen’s “The Monkey”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gheorghe</surname>
                           <given-names>Cristina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The paper explores the ironic narrative strategies used by Isak Dinesen to construct and deconstruct, authenticate and disauthenticate her fictional world, as illustrated by the short story “The Monkey.” In examining this short story and through reference to instances from other stories, I will point out Dinesen's disauthenticating technique in light of Derrida's philosophic strategy of deconstruction. My main concern here is, however, possibleworld semantics. The term deconstruction will be used as authorialde construction, applied by Dinesen in her specific narrative technique, and lectorial deconstruction—this reader's response to Dinesen's deconstructive technique which reveals in her literary discourse analogies to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited and Consulted</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvc7.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
