<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ3980.5.K36 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">African literature (French)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Women authors</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Caribbean literature (French)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Women authors</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Violence in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Violence in Francophone African and Caribbean Women's Literature</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KALISA</surname>
               <given-names>CHANTAL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803211025</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803226883</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803226888</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dfnvj2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>African and Caribbean peoples share a history dominated by the violent disruptions of slavery and colonialism. While much has been said about these "geographies of pain," violence in the private sphere, particularly gendered violence, receives little attention. This book fills that void. It is a critical addition to the study of African and Caribbean women's literatures at a time when women from these regions are actively engaged in articulating the ways in which colonial and postcolonial violence impact women.</p>
         <p>Chantal Kalisa examines the ways in which women writers lift taboos imposed on them by their society and culture and challenge readers with their unique perspectives on violence. Comparing women from different places and times, Kalisa treats types of violence such as colonial, familial, linguistic, and war-related, specifically linked to dictatorship and genocide. She examines Caribbean writers Michele Lacrosil, Simone Schwartz-Bart, Gisèle Pineau, and Edwidge Danticat, and Africans Ken Begul, Calixthe Beyala, Nadine Bar, and Monique Ilboudo. She also includes Sembène Ousmane and Frantz Fanon for their unique contributions to the questions of violence and gender. This study advances our understanding of the attempts of African and Caribbean women writers to resolve the tension between external forms of violence and internal forms resulting from skewed cultural, social, and political rules based on gender.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="236"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>Geographies of Pain</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By sharing a history dominated by the violent disruptions of slavery, colonialism, and latent neocolonialism, African and Caribbean peoples belong to what Francoise Lionnet calls “geographies of pain.”¹ Caribbeanist Jack Corzani identifies various forms of this historical violence. Physical violence manifests itself in the enslavement and killing of Africans and in the dispossession of their continent; in the fights between masters and slaves, between colonized and colonizers, and among colonizers themselves; in abolitionist struggles; and in several postcolonial revolutionary wars (Corzani 15). Figures such as the soldier or the policeman symbolize the violence used to maintain colonial regimes in Africa</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Exclusion as Violence</title>
                     <subtitle>Frantz Fanon, Black Women, and Colonial Violence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Critical studies of African and Caribbean women writing remain scarce.¹ The reasons for this absence are twofold. First, at the beginning of the formation of African literary studies in the mid-twentieth century, there were relatively few women writers in Africa and the Caribbean. This was mainly due to the external violence of colonialism, which privileged the schooling of the male. It was also attributable to internal violence originating from precolonial and postcolonial patriarchal conceptions that prevented women in traditional and contemporary societies from expressing themselves or acquiring the same educational level as men. Maryse Conde writes, for example, that “comme</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Representing Colonial Violence</title>
                     <subtitle>Michèle Lacrosil’s Cajou, Ken Bugul’s Le baobab fou, and Ousmane Sembène’s La noire de …</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I posit that the selected works by Michèle Lacrosil, Ken Bugul, and Ousmane Sembène complicate Fanon’s formula for colonial violence by offering a specifically female perspective on the experience and legacy of colonialism’s brutality. This chapter discusses these relationships in two different areas. First, I examine the process of epistemological violence — brainwashing through formal and informal education — as a legacy of colonialism. Second, I study the specificity of women’s experience within the colonial discourse. This involves a close analysis of Ken Bugul’s violent encounter with the West and Lacrosil’s depiction of a severe case of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Writing Familial Violence</title>
                     <subtitle>Storytelling and Intergenerational Violence in Simone Schwarz-Bart’s Pluie et vent sur Télumée Miracle and Calixthe Beyala’s Tu t’appelleras Tanga</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her article “Sheroes and Villains: Conceptualizing Colonial and Contemporary Violence against Women in Africa,” Amina Mama locates the source of contemporary African models of patriarchal violence in colonial states. These states not only used the famous colonial formula “Ayons les femmes et le reste suivra” [Let’s win over women and the men will follow] (“L’Algérie se dévoile” 18; “Algeria Unveiled” 37) but also adopted European concepts of womanhood such as repressive domestication. Patriarchal violence combines European models of violence against women with models of patriarchal oppression that existed both before and after colonialism. As Mama argues, colonialism “humiliated” African</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Sites of Violence</title>
                     <subtitle>Language, the Body, and Women’s Deterritorialization in Gisèle Pineau’s L’espérance-macadam and Calixthe Beyala’s C’est le soleil qui m’a brûlée</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Calixthe Beyala and Gisèle Pineau explore further the concept of “geographies of pain” by depicting intimate space, language, and the body as sites of pain, exile, and resistance to violence.¹ In the tradition of women’s literature, the two writers turn their attention to internal sources of violence and, through their characters, condemn those who still focus solely on the external factors of violence. They ask questions such as: How can women successfully re-territorialize their violated bodies within the intimate spaces from which they have been exiled? How can they overcome linguistic limitations in expressing pain? Beyala sees linguistic violence as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>War and Political Violence</title>
                     <subtitle>Nadine Bari’s, Edwidge Danticat’s, and Monique Ilboudo’s Literary Responses to Gender and Conflict</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I examine how women writers redefine war in their writing about political violence. The term<italic>war</italic>normally refers to a “hostile contention by means of armed forces, carried on between nations, states, or rulers, or between parties in the same nation or state; the employment of armed forces against a foreign power, or against an opposing party in the state” (<italic>Oxford English Dictionary Online</italic>). This definition needs to be expanded to include several consequences of war with a disproportionate impact upon women, such as sexual violence; the destruction of family and the loss of husbands, sons, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As African and Caribbean writings become ever more<italic>intimistes</italic>(intimist) — as authors present more intimate and deeply private topics — an examination of the subject of violence and particularly its gendered form in literature is crucial to the understanding of Francophone women writers. Reading violence in postcolonial women’s literatures entails understanding the tension between public and private violence that results in gendered violence. While it can be argued that gendered violence is a corollary to imperialism and colonialism, women writers show how their societies contribute to gendered violence.</p>
                     <p>In the present study, I have attempted to answer questions about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnvj2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
