<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8bdj</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">ML1156 .D38 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sonata</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chopin, Frédéric, 1810–1849</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Schumann, Robert, 1810–1856</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Brahms, Johannes, 1833–1897</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Sonata Fragments</book-title>
         <subtitle>Romantic Narratives in Chopin, Schumann, and Brahms</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Davis</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253025456</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253025451</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Andrew Davis</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxz0jw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In<italic>Sonata Fragments</italic>, Andrew Davis argues that the Romantic sonata is firmly rooted, both formally and expressively, in its Classical forebears, using Classical conventions in order to convey a broad constellation of Romantic aesthetic values. This claim runs contrary to conventional theories of the Romantic sonata that place this nineteenth-century musical form squarely outside inherited Classical sonata procedures. Building on Sonata Theory, Davis examines moments of fracture and fragmentation that disrupt the cohesive and linear temporality in piano sonatas by Chopin, Brahms, and Schumann. These disruptions in the sonata form are a narrative technique that signify temporal shifts during which we move from the outer action to the inner thoughts of a musical agent, or we move from the story as it unfolds to a flashback or flash-forward. Through an interpretation of Romantic sonatas as temporally multi-dimensional works in which portions of the music in any given piece can lie inside or outside of what Sonata Theory would define as the sonata-space proper, Davis reads into these ruptures a narrative of expressive features that mark these sonatas as uniquely Romantic.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Romantic Musical Discourse, or, a Rhetoric of Romantic Music</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a moment in the transition of the first movement of Chopin’s Piano Sonata in B minor, op. 58 that raises difficult questions. As shown in example 0.1, the movement opens with what seems to be a structurally unproblematic, if weighty, eight-bar primary theme (P) that ends by tonicizing its own dominant (F<sub>#</sub>minor) in m. 8. The transition (TR) then begins immediately (m. 9), opening with a restatement of the P idea on the subdominant E minor and continuing in a normative fashion. The rhetoric suggests tonal and motivic dissolution—as would be expected in a sonata transition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Fragmentation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aesthetics of Nineteenth-Century Romanticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Addressing questions such as those posed in the introduction requires considering the constellation of Romantic aesthetics and ideologies pervasive among European artists in the first half of the nineteenth century. These are normally understood as being marked by a skepticism toward older, Classical forms and procedures, the employment of which in music, literature, or other of the arts would have been viewed by the Romantics as something of an exercise in form—as the replication of older procedures for the sake of conformist repetition, as an endorsement of Enlightenment ideals that had long since become outdated. One of the clearest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Atemporality in Narrative and Music</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter sets out to construct a theory of structure and expressive meaning in the nineteenth-century Romantic sonata, within the view of Romanticism articulated in chapter 1.¹ The theory will focus particularly on the problematized moments of formal and expressive ambiguity characteristic of that genre. I first consider what we might mean by<italic>narrative</italic>or<italic>narrative forms</italic>in music, continue by examining issues related to time and temporality within those narrative forms, and finish by proposing ways that some of these (mainly literary) concepts might map onto music.</p>
                     <p>While the theory draws largely on structural narratology, I find that recent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Music with Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>Two Slow Movements by Brahms</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The slow movements of Brahms’s Piano Sonatas in C major, op. 1 and F<sub>#</sub>minor, op. 2 comprise text-based variations sets. In each, a poem motivates structure—stanzas of the poems correspond to variations in the music—and expression—each movement should be understood as Brahms’s own reading of the associated poem—in what amounts to a song without words. This feature proves helpful in interpreting certain of these movements’ structural and rhetorical devices, especially the most idiosyncratic among them: that is, the potential meanings of such features can be ascertained by considering their possible relationships to the underlying text. Such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Music without Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>Forms of Atemporality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rhetorical strategies in non-text-based Romantic music can be understood as analogous to the strategies that appear in the text-based slow movements by Brahms. Expressive meaning in such music may thus be interpreted in analogous ways. This chapter draws on the piano sonatas of Schumann, Brahms, and Chopin to examine situations that may be interpreted in terms of what I have defined as durational atemporality, ruptured atemporality, and conflations of these two atemporality types.</p>
                     <p>§1. Durational Atemporality: Schumann op. 11/i and Brahms op. 1/i</p>
                     <p>The first movement of Schumann’s Piano Sonata in F<sub>#</sub>minor, op. 1, like many Romantic-era sonatas (especially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Treatment of the Medial Caesura</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Romantic sonata—as in the Classical sonata—treatment of the medial caesura proves to be a critical expressive issue. The first movement of Brahms’s Piano Sonata in F<sub>#</sub>minor, op. 2 provides a representative example of how Romantic fragment aesthetics can inform the use of conventions surrounding this most critical of a sonata’s junctures. This movement specifically adopts a procedure that can be understood as a hallmark feature of Romantic sonatas in general: this is what I will call a<italic>post-MC interpolation</italic>, in which an MC normative in all apparent respects leads not to a normative S-theme but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Treatment of the S-Space</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Romantic sonata, the S-space is typically a central feature of the sonata’s dialogue with conventions of the pastoral narrative. Two specific issues are important in this regard: eighteenth-and nineteenth-century conventions surrounding the tonal and modal choices for S in minor-mode sonatas; and the pastoral as a narrative archetype for the Romantic sonata, and, in this context, the special significative potential carried therein by the S-theme.</p>
                     <p>First, on tonal and modal choices for S, the principal expressive concern is the Sonata Theory concept that minor-mode sonatas carry with them an extraexpressive “burden” that major-mode sonatas do not: minor-mode sonatas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Treatment of the Development and Recapitulation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Romantic development sections engage in their own characteristic ways with the aesthetics of fragmentation. Perhaps the most important among several common strategies is that in which the development is treated as a privileged, idealized space in which to explore, or propose new solutions to, structural and expressive problems facing the exposition.</p>
                     <p>The development section in Brahms’s op. 1 provides a good initial example. It contains two atemporal interpolations, as shown in figure 4.2. The first suggests a development section fragmented at its front end; the second splits open the center of the development to propose a new, idealized version of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Treatment of the Slow Introduction and Coda</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Slow introductions and codas, because they can be understood as outside the boundaries of the rotational sonata form proper, present obvious opportunities in which to disengage from first-narrative temporality and shift to the diegetic mode, within the context of a fragmented, Romantic sonata-aesthetic environment.¹ The finale of Brahms’s op. 2 provides a good initial example.</p>
                     <p>The movement’s first eight bars declare their status as outside the first-narrative stream almost immediately. They open in a rhetorically conspicuous, declamatory fashion, with a monophonic F<sub>#</sub>giving way immediately to an E: thus the movement opens on its tonic but then immediately falls away</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most important points in the foregoing analyses is that nineteenth century Romantic sonatas (and Romantic sonata forms more broadly) are governed in both structure and content by a central conflict—an essential expressive opposition that can be construed in a variety of ways: perfect versus imperfect, present versus nonpresent, real versus unreal, and so on. The conflict is best understood as stemming from the Romantic compulsion for creating, or re-creating, something better than what is currently available in one’s present situation—looking toward a better future, for example, or reminiscing on a better past. The most common</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0jw.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
