<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HE8689.9.C3C657 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Public broadcasting</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Translating</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Multilingual communication</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Constitutional amendments</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Press coverage</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canadian Broadcasting Corporation</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Everyone Says No</book-title>
         <subtitle>Public Service Broadcasting and the Failure of Translation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CONWAY</surname>
               <given-names>KYLE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773539334</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773587106</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.cttq93tk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Quebec has never signed on to Canada's constitution. After both major attempts to win Quebec's approval - the Meech Lake and Charlottetown Accords - failed, Quebec came within a fraction of a percentage point of voting for independence. Everyone Says No examines how the failure of these accords was depicted in French and English media and the ways in which journalists' reporting failed to translate the differences between Quebec and the rest of Canada. Focusing on the English- and French-language networks of the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, Kyle Conway draws on the CBC/Radio Canada rich print and video archive as well as journalists' accounts of their reporting to revisit the story of the accords and the furor they stirred in both French and English Canada. He shows that CBC/Radio Canada attempts to translate language and culture and encourage understanding among Canadians actually confirmed viewers' pre-existing assumptions rather than challenging them. The first book to examine translation in Canadian news, Everyone Says No also provides insight into Canada's constitutional history and the challenges faced by contemporary public service broadcasters in increasingly multilingual and multicultural communities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="232"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Public Service Broadcasting and Translation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is about translation and public service broadcasting, especially in Canada.</p>
                     <p>The institution of public service broadcasting is at a crossroads. Or, perhaps more accurately, institutions of public service broadcasting are at a crossroads. The audiences they serve are increasingly heterogeneous: in multicultural countries like Canada, the viewers that public broadcasters seek speak more languages and identify with a wider range of ethnic, cultural, and even national identities than they have at any time in the past. Public broadcasters face a considerable challenge in addressing this diversity. How do they reconcile their historical nation-building mandates with the new ways</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The News, the Nation, and the Stakes of Translation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Canada’s national television news anchors opened the programs of 27 October 1992 by taking stock of the dramatic and historic events of the day before. The country had just reached the end of a gruelling, month-long referendum campaign, and Canadians had just voted on the Charlottetown Accord, a sweeping agreement that held the potential to change the constitutionally defined relationships between the federal, provincial, and Aboriginal levels of government. The accord itself was a result of a yearlong consultation process during which representatives of federal and provincial commissions met with Canadians from across the country to find out their constitutional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Rise and Fall of Translated News on Newsworld and the Réseau de l’information</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the spring of 1990, Canada was at the beginning of what would prove to be a tumultuous decade during which the question of national unity would be constantly at the forefront of political debate. At the time, the concern was with the quickly unravelling Meech Lake Accord. Negotiated in 1987 in the hope of creating the political conditions necessary for Quebec to join the constitution, the agreement faced opposition in the legislatures of Manitoba and Newfoundland. Without ratification by all ten provincial legislatures, the accord would fail, and its failure would lead – or so feared many among the country’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Paradoxes of Translation in Television News</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Journalists covering the Meech Lake and Charlottetown accords for the CBC’s<italic>The National</italic>and Radio-Canada’s<italic>Le Téléjournal</italic>faced two important challenges when it came to explaining Canada’s linguistic and cultural groups to each other. The first arose from ongoing political debates about whether the national broadcaster should actively promote national unity. The second was that journalists had to translate between English and French so that their viewers could understand the many political actors involved, regardless of the language they spoke. The first challenge, however, complicated the second because the politics that shaped the debates about the proper role of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Quebec and the Historical Meaning of “Distinct Society”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The late 1980s was a heady time for Canadian constitutionalists. On 30 April 1987, five years after Quebec’s refusal to accept the patriation of the constitution from London,¹ Prime Minister Brian Mulroney and the premiers of all the provinces, Quebec included, met at Meech Lake outside of Ottawa. There they reached an accord in principle that would allow Quebec to rejoin the “Canadian constitutional fold,” as the<italic>Toronto Star</italic>put it, leading a proud Mulroney to declare, “what you have now is a whole country as opposed to part of a country” (Ruimy 1987, A1). The<italic>Constitution Amendment,</italic>1987, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“Distinct Society,” “Société distincte,” and the Meech Lake Accord</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Late on 9 June 1990, after a week of intense negotiations, Prime Minister Brian Mulroney and the provincial premiers emerged from a series of closed-door negotiations looking haggard but pleased. Only a month before, on 6 April, Newfoundland’s new premier, Clyde Wells, had rescinded the province’s approval of the Meech Lake Accord. Now, with only two weeks until the final deadline for approval of the accord, the first ministers had reached a compromise that appeared to be one that Newfoundland and the other hold-out provinces, Manitoba and New Brunswick, would be willing to ratify. The harmony among first ministers was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Charlottetown Accord and the Translation of Ambivalence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the failure of the Meech Lake Accord in 1990, Canadians and their leaders were tired, frustrated, and increasingly bitter. Nothing was settled, and in fact, constitutional matters were now even more complicated than before. English Canadians were exasperated by what they took to be Quebec’s unwillingness to compromise, while many in Quebec felt that the failure of Meech Lake represented a callous repudiation of the province’s concerns. In addition, the First Nations had now asserted themselves on the constitutional stage. With Meech Lake, they had succeeded in doing something that had long been in the making, channelling years of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Public Service Media and the Potential of Translation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nearly two decades after the defeat of the Charlottetown Accord, Canada’s public broadcaster faces a familiar set of challenges. The fragmentation characterizing the CBC/Radio-Canada’s audience has increased since 1992, and with it, so has a demand for the representation of different cultural groups. The desire for representation expressed by the country’s principal linguistic groups, by members of its different geographic regions, and by its Native peoples has been supplemented by a desire for representation expressed by members of Canada’s multicultural communities. At the same time, the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation has had to make do with progressively less funding – the cuts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX:</title>
                     <subtitle>Key Dates in Canadian Constitutional History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93tk.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
