<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN320.P73 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sahlins, Marshall, 1930–</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social change</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Practice of Anthropology</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Thought and Influence of Marshall Sahlins</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GOLUB</surname>
               <given-names>ALEX</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROSENBLATT</surname>
               <given-names>DANIEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KELLY</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773546882</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773598621</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773598626</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Chicago</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>20160501</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c99c4k"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Marshall Sahlins (b. 1930) is an American anthropologist who played a major role in the development of anthropological theory in the second half of the twentieth century. Over a sixty-year career, he and his colleagues synthesized trends in evolutionary, Marxist, and ecological anthropology, moving them into mainstream thought. Sahlins is considered a critic of reductive theories of human nature, an exponent of culture as a key concept in anthropology, and a politically engaged intellectual opposed to militarism and imperialism. This collection brings together some of the world’s most distinguished anthropologists to explore and advance Sahlins’s legacy. All of the essays are based on original research, most dealing with cultural change - a major theme of Sahlins’s research, especially in the contexts of Fijian and Hawaiian societies. Like Sahlins’s practice of anthropology, these essays display a rigorous, humanistic study of cultural forms, refusing to accept comfort over accuracy, not shirking from the moral implications of their analyses. Contributors include the late Greg Dening, one of the most eminent historians of the Pacific, Martha Kaplan, Patrick Kirch, Webb Keane, Jonathan Friedman, and Joel Robbins, with a preface by the late Claude Levi-Strauss. A unique volume that will complement the many books and articles by Sahlins himself, A Practice of Anthropology is an exciting new addition to the history of anthropological study.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table and Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LÉVI–STRAUSS</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAUDE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>TRANSLATED BY</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SALAUN</surname>
                           <given-names>MARRIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Practice of Anthropology – The Work of Marshall Sahlins, So Far</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOLUB</surname>
                           <given-names>ALEX</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSENBLATT</surname>
                           <given-names>DANIEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KELLY</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is time to add Marshall Sahlins to the short list of great anthropologists, time to celebrate his contributions to the discipline, and time to discuss the far–reaching impact of his works. Sahlins has proved a more difficult (and diffdent) subject for celebratory synthesis than many of his peers. The works of Eric Wolf (Abbink and Vermeulen 1992), Louis Dumont (Heesterman 1985), and others have received the attention they deserve, and the paeans for Clifford Geertz began even before his unfortunate passing in 2006 (Ortner 1999, Shweder and Good 2005). The most important anthropologist of the period afted the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>How Long Is a Longue Durée?</title>
                     <subtitle>Structure, Duration, and the Cultural Analysis of Cultural Change</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBBINS</surname>
                           <given-names>JOEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The drawing together of history and anthropology has been one of the major stories in the development of anthropological thought over the last forty years. It is a story in which Marshall Sahlins has played a central role, and the making of a marriage between these two disciplines has clearly been close to his heart: the words “history” or “historical” have appeared in the titles of five of his books since 1981. To the conjunction of history and anthropology he has done so much to effect, Sahlins has brought a robust notion of cultural structures, and he has shown how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Monarchical Visions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Constructions of “Kingship” in Colonial Samoa</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LINNEKIN</surname>
                           <given-names>JOCELYN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 18 August 1885 the Samoan high chief Malietoa Laupepa wrote a letter to Queen Victoria (Figure 2.1).¹ Addressing her as “Tupu Tamaitai,” the “Lady King” of Great Britain and Ireland, Laupepa endeavoured to clarify Samoan political custom for her. He would have her know that, according to the customary beliefs of Samoa from the earliest times,<italic>he</italic>– Malietoa Laupepa – was the “real King” (<italic>Tupu</italic>) of Samoa. Laupepa’s letter to Victoria was but one of many appeals by would-be Samoan kings to foreign powers and powerful resident foreigners. During the protracted “kingship dispute” of the late nineteenth century, Samoan chiefly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Slow Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Culture, Materiality and the Knowability of the Neolithic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KEANE</surname>
                           <given-names>WEBB</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In its origins, anthropology was a response not only to the colonial encounter with difference, but also to the discovery of deep time (Shryock and Smail 2011, Trautmann 1992). One of the most dangerous consequences of the convergence of global reach and deep time, of course, was to conflate the two, equating others with ancients. Disciplinary self-critique eventually made it obvious that such an equation was hopelessly naive if not outright vicious, or worse. In response, many cultural anthropologists came to confine their claims to the particularity of local knowledge (Geertz 1983). Others moved toward an increasingly narrow focus on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>From Jew to Roman:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mr Joske, Mr Brewster, The Hill Tribes of Fiji, and the Hill Tribes of Fiji</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAPLAN</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most scholars of Fiji are familiar with Adolph Brewster Joske, British colonial official, amateur anthropologist, and memoirist, through his books<italic>The Hill Tribes of Fiji</italic>and<italic>The King of the Cannibal Isles</italic>, books published in 1922 and 1937, respectively. By the time he published these works, he had retired to England (in 1910) and changed his name to A.B. Brewster. Some Fiji scholars have also read his copious administrative correspondence and reports, held at the Fiji National Archives and the Fiji Museum. For information on the cultural lives and political fortunes of the people of the highlands of Viti Levu,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Supplement to Marshall Sahlins’s Voyage Around the Islands of History (Tahiti 1768, Samoa 1787)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TCHERKÉZOFF</surname>
                           <given-names>SERGE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus of this contribution¹ is the apparent sexual offers that Polynesian women made to the first Europeans who arrived in Polynesia. If we go back to some journals written during the early voyages, which have still not been studied in as much detail as they deserve, we discover an unexpected aspect of these apparent sexual offers: the “girls’ very young” age and their “weeping.” This leads us toward a hypothesis.</p>
                     <p>Many Polynesian sources attest that young girls who entered into marriage with a high chief had to be virgins (or at least girls who had not given birth).² Other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Chassé–croisé:</title>
                     <subtitle>Or How Christianity Appropriated Indigenous Appropriation of Christianity on the Rio Negro</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CUNHA</surname>
                           <given-names>MANUELA CARNEIRO DA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The intellectual influence of Marshall Sahlins is pervasive in Brazilian anthropology. On a more personal level, since his groundbreaking essay “The Original Affluent Society” (in Sahlins 1972) I have counted myself as a devotee. This essay, however, is connected to Sahlins’s oeuvre in two more specific ways. I’ll spell out the first at once and will reserve the second for the end of this chapter.</p>
                     <p>Sahlins has repeatedly made the case for the indigenization of Western cosmologies and for the reconfiguration of Western happenings into Indigenous events. Around a single happening, different events take place for different people, simultaneous yet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Past Is Old, the Future Is Traditional:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ircenrraat, the DOT, and the Inventiveness of Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FIENUP-RIORDAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ANN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I never heard the word “culture” used in southwest Alaska thirty years ago – today it is on everyone’s lips. Conscious culture is the trademark of the new millennium in Alaska as elsewhere, requiring effort to preserve and reproduce past practices and defend them against assimilative pressures. In this struggle, as Marshall Sahlins (2000b: 196) says so well, “the continuity of indigenous cultures consists in the specific ways they change.”</p>
                     <p>This essay explores one such struggle – a debate over road-building – as an example of what Sahlins (2000b: 192) and others have called “culturalism,” that is, the self-conscious, deliberate use of identity,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Kafka Connection:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sturcture, Lifeworld, and the Cunning of History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRIEDMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JONATHAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marshall Sahlins has been one of the few anthropologists and certainly the most celebrated to have continued the tradition of argument and scientific reason that has been in large part abandoned in recent years by so many intellectuals. The tradition, if I may use such a dangerous term, consists in finding structure in reality. All structure is underlying insofar as it is not obvious “to the most casual observer.” It takes a great deal of work to arrive at structural understanding, and even then it is always in the form of hypothesis that is contestable. This is the burden of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Way–Finding:</title>
                     <subtitle>Respectfulness as a Performance Art</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DENING</surname>
                           <given-names>GREG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Way-finding” is the term that modern islanders use to describe their craft and the craft of their ancestors in piloting their voyaging canoes around the Great Ocean, the Pacific, and the Sea of Islands. They prefer to call themselves way-finders rather than navigators. Navigation is a more universal science of instruments and the application of systems of time and space as broad as the cosmos itself. Way-finding is a more interpretive craft closer to the signs the systems of the cosmos imprint on the environment. No navigators would distance themselves from the myriad of signs in sea and sky, wind</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99c4k.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
