<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Edinburgh Companion to the History of Democracy</book-title>
         <subtitle>From Pre-history to Future Possibilities</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Isakhan</surname>
               <given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Stockwell</surname>
               <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>23</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748640751</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748653669</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">074865366X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Benjamin Isakhan</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Stephen Stockwell</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0b6rb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Takes a fresh look at the history of democracy, broadening the traditional view with previously unexplored examples</p>
         <p>This substantial reference work critically re-examines the history of democracy, from ancient history to possible directions it may take in the future. 44 chapters explore the origins of democracy and explore new - and sometimes surprising - examples from around the world.</p>
         <p>Each of the 9 parts introduces the period, followed by 3 to 7 case studies.</p>
         <p>Key FeaturesThe first book to study lesser-known histories of democracy alongside familiar examplesIncludes historical accounts from leading scholars that document the development of democratic practices in their area or epoch of interestContributors include Jack Goody, John Keane, Larbi Sadiki, James Anderson, John Fisher and Seymour DrescherSplit into 9 partsPart I: Pre-Classical Democracy</p>
         <p>Pre-history o The Assyrians o Ancient India o Ancient China o Islam and Phoenicia</p>
         <p>Part II: Classical Democracy</p>
         <p>Early Greece and Sparta o Athens o Rome</p>
         <p>Part III: Medieval Democracy</p>
         <p>Islam o Venice o The Nordic Countries o Medieval Church</p>
         <p>Part IV: Early Modern Period</p>
         <p>English Parliament o Diggers and Levellers o Swiss Cantons o America o French Revolution</p>
         <p>Part V: Contacts and Colonialisms</p>
         <p>Africa o Native Americans o Australasia o Colonial Singapore</p>
         <p>Part VI: National Movements</p>
         <p>1808: South American Liberation o 1848: European Revolutions o 1919: After Versailles o 1945: Post WWII o 1989: Eastern Europe</p>
         <p>Part VII: Peoples' Movements</p>
         <p>Anti-Slavery o Women's Suffrage o Socialism, Communism, Anarchism o Civil Rights</p>
         <p>Part VIII: Democracy Today</p>
         <p>Anti-Apartheid in South Africa o 'Rose Revolution' in Georgia o Iraq o Bolivia o Burma o Chinese Local Democratisation o Islam since 9/11</p>
         <p>Part IX: Futures and Possibilities</p>
         <p>Transnational Democracy o Digital Democracy o Deliberative Democracy o Democracy Promotion o Radical Democracy o Democracy: New Thinking About an Old Ideal</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="384"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goody</surname>
                           <given-names>Jack</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Complex and Contested History of Democracy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Isakhan</surname>
                           <given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The twentieth century was a great success for democracy, but every victory was hard won. On the world stage, democracies had to fend off credible threats from various forms of fascism before 1945 and then communism until 1989. Inside each democracy, a myriad of civil society actors and peoples’ movements struggled for every gain of liberty, for every civil right and for an ever widening franchise. During the twentieth century, in countries all over the world, people took risks, pushed old laws and entrenched elites to their limits, and put their lives on the line in order to claim their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Prehistory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boehm</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Democracy is a political system that allows the will of the rank and file to be expressed in arriving at and executing policies that affect the group. A prerequisite for this sharing of power is a set of political institutions that prevent those in higher positions from increasing their power in ways that encroach on the autonomy of those below them; and while we think of these checks and balances mainly in the context of constitutional democracies, they were present less formally in egalitarian agricultural tribes (Fried 1967) and in egalitarian hunting bands (Glassman 1986). Because some obvious parallels were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>The Assyrians</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Isakhan</surname>
                           <given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fertile floodplains that stretch between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers, humankind settled to form perhaps the earliest organised and permanent settlements anywhere in the world. By around 3500 BCE, these relatively simple agricultural societies had evolved into city-states, the first of which was Uruk (modern Al-Warka, Iraq), centred around a temple complex and populated by traders, merchants, farmers and the temple bureaucracy. The need for a sophisticated accounting system led to the development of the world’s first written language, which itself evolved into a rich corpus of literary and bureaucratic texts. However, in order to compete for and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Ancient India</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Muhlberger</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the period before CE 400, ancient India was home to a variety of self-governing polities using quasi-democratic institutions comparable with those of the Greek city-states of the same era. Indeed, Greek and Roman historians, relying on the reports of Greek visitors, did not hesitate to say that the India they knew was largely democratic. But although the evidence has been carefully analysed and the existence of a multitude of republics has long been established, these republics and the political culture that they represent are little known to anyone but specialists. The purpose of this chapter is to set forth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Ancient China</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hui</surname>
                           <given-names>Victoria Tin-bor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Both Western and Chinese analysts often presume that democracy is unique to Western civilisation and alien to the Chinese. The roots of Western dynamism are, in turn, assumed to derive from the political complexity of Europe, whereas those of Chinese stagnation from political unity. However, as this chapter illustrates, China in fact experienced fluctuations between unification and division in history. Intense international competition in the classical era (770–221 BCE) gave rise to citizenship rights defined as state– society bargains over the means of war. Although the development of Chinese citizenship was aborted by Qin’s successful unification of the Warring</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Israel and Phoenicia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stockwell</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Greeks made major contributions to the development of democracy not only as an idea, but even more significantly as a set of practical laws and pragmatic institutions that evolved over centuries to translate the sovereignty of the people into a relatively stable and effective system of government. However, while the Greek invention of democracy is often treated as an indisputable truth, recent work suggests that democracy may have antecedents. Martin Bernal stirred a major controversy with his book,<italic>Black Athena</italic>, and its claims to establish the ‘Afro-Asiatic’ roots of classical Greek society (Bernal [1987] 1991). A later paper sought</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Early Greece</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Raaflaub</surname>
                           <given-names>Kurt A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Greek democracy emerged in either late sixth-or mid-fifth-century¹ Athens, with strong arguments supporting both dates (Raaflaub<italic>et al</italic>. 2007). However,<italic>demokratia</italic>, ‘rule by the people’, was the result of a long evolution that affected other communities as well (Robinson 1997). This chapter has two purposes. One is to trace the beginnings of this evolution from the earliest extant evidence on Greek communities, institutions and political reflection (in Homer’s epics and early laws) to the enactment of the first known<italic>polis</italic>constitution in Sparta and the breakthrough of political and constitutional thought in Solonian Athens. The other purpose is to explain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Athens</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Phillips</surname>
                           <given-names>David J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term<italic>dēmokratia</italic>most probably dates back to 508/7¹ (Ehrenberg 1950; Hansen 1986, 1991: 69–71; Sealey 1973). At that time in the Athenian<italic>polis</italic>(city-state), the aristocratic Kleisthenes ‘took the people (<italic>demos</italic>) into his faction’ (Aristotle [332 BCE] 1984: 20.1; Herodotus [430 bce ] 1972: 5.66.2). He did so in order to gain the upper hand in his struggle for political power with the aristocratic and Spartan-backed Isagoras who had been elected as the eponymous<italic>archon</italic>for 508/7. These two men contested power in the aftermath of the tyranny of the Peisistratids (545– 511/10), which had curbed the opportunities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Rome</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Matyszak</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although this chapter takes a broader view, democracy in Rome is generally considered in the context of the mid-to late Republic. The view that the oligarchy exercised<italic>de facto</italic>control of the voting process in this latter period has been challenged from the 1990s onward (Millar 2002). The ensuing debate has exposed extensive deficiencies in what is known about the democratic process in Rome (Sandberg 2001). Recently the focus has shifted to the role of the army, a focus which will be retained in this chapter (Southern 2007). It will also be stressed that throughout the history of Rome, voting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Islam</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sadiki</surname>
                           <given-names>Larbi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nothing is more perilous than trying to wed Islam and democracy, or engaging in endless discussions on Islam’s compatibility with democracy via a framework designed within the Western episteme. This episteme assumes that Islam and democracy are two distinct and autonomous systems and, in its worst iterations, it asserts that they are antithetical to one another. Since the European Enlightenment, the scholarly discussion of Islam and democracy has been one-sided. Western intellectuals condemn religion to the margins and Enlightenment’s singular practice of rationality denounces religious foundationalism. Fixity, singularity and determinacy have all been attributed to religion, especially Islam, and cited</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>Venice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stockwell</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A dense mythology surrounds the origins of Venice and its early development as a democratically inclined republic. This mythology was lovingly crafted by propagandists of the later regime, ably assisted by itinerant intellectuals, then and now, all keen to establish Venice as a republican exemplar for their own political purposes. Venice has a remarkable history. It is a rare example of an autonomous polity that survived for more than a millennium, from the barbarian invasions that presaged the fall of Rome at the start of the fifth century ce to the arrival of Napoleon in 1797, when the city surrendered</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>The Nordic Countries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hervik</surname>
                           <given-names>Frode</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Middle Ages should be studied and understood in its own terms and on its own premises, but a historian must also be able to explain progress, development and the great lineages of history. One of these great lineages is the history of democracy, in which the ‘Dark Ages’ are assumed to be a black hole. The experience of the Nordic countries during this period provides a worthy case study to test the accuracy of this assessment. The word ‘democracy’ directly translated from the Greek means a form of government where the people rule. In the city state (<italic>polis</italic>) of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>The Christian Church</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hittinger</surname>
                           <given-names>John P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the classic account of democracy, rule by the majority formally establishes a regime as democratic. Any such organisation is characterised as allowing the rise of those who are neither rich nor distinguished, but who utilise their equality to bring together a numerical majority of supporters (Aristotle [350 BCE] 1980: 3.11; Simon 1951: 76). Democracy emerges as a cluster of concepts and practices sustained by a set of ideas about human equality and popular sovereignty. Participation in actual self-rule is also an aspirational standard of democratic movements. It is commonly acknowledged that many aspects of modern democracy arise from beliefs,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 13</label>
                     <title>The English Parliament</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lyon</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The English Parliament is the subject of much mythology, both in its origins and in its development. It is often suggested that prior to the Norman Conquest, rather than having government imposed from above, the English governed themselves through local assemblies often referred to as folk moots (Oman 1919). The best evidence for pre-Conquest folk moots comes from place names such as Thingwall on the Wirral peninsula, Merseyside, and a lost<italic>Tingwala</italic>in the Yorkshire Domesday, cognate with modern Icelandic<italic>Thingvellir</italic>– meeting place of the<italic>thing</italic>or assembly (Mills 1998). The Icelandic Parliament, whose origins can be traced to 930,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 14</label>
                     <title>The Levellers and Diggers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bradstock</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It often takes a national crisis to prompt popular reflection on issues of fundamental social and political importance, and it is no coincidence that the most significant debate in England concerning the nature of democracy occurred in what was arguably its most turbulent decade, the 1640s. As the country endured three civil wars, which culminated in the execution of the king and the abolition of monarchy, and as other great institutions like the Established Church and House of Lords disappeared, so people of all classes began openly to debate the meaning of the crisis and the shape of the new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 15</label>
                     <title>The Swiss Cantons</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lau</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although sixteenth-century humanists regarded Switzerland as an old nation populated by the descendants of the ancient Helvetians, the country, while built on even earlier charters and treaties, emerged as a confederated alliance in a gradual process between 1350 and 1450 (Fossedal 2002: 11–42; Sablonier 2008). It consisted of rural communes in the central Alps and urban communes at Lake Constance, the Upper Rhine and the eastern part of Burgundy. The main reason these communes stayed together was their military success. The conquered territories they administered together could be protected only if the confederates found a way to solve their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 16</label>
                     <title>The American Revolution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shankman</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To consensus era historians of the 1950s, democracy in late colonial British North America scarcely needed to be explained. Colonists were middle class, jealous of their liberties and determined to assert their rights in powerful colonial legislatures (Brown 1955; Greene 1963). Since the 1970s this story has been dismantled; it is now clear that democracy was not inevitable in the region that became the United States. Between 1720 and 1760, from Massachusetts to Georgia, the colonies became more British in their political practices, social relations and cultural tastes. Each colony produced ruling elites who wielded economic power and monopolised political</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 17</label>
                     <title>The French Revolution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Markoff</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 17 June 1789, deputies elected to an old institution with an important but limited purpose announced that they were forming a new body with a much broader purpose. France’s Estates-General had been convened after a hiatus of 175 years as part of the royal attempt to manage a severe financial crisis. But many deputies hoped to make this crisis an occasion for significant reform, especially those who represented the Third Estate. After several weeks of fruitless dealing with the deputies of the first two estates – the nobility and the clergy – the Third Estate took a great leap into the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 18</label>
                     <title>Africa</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Owusu</surname>
                           <given-names>Maxwell</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Africa is the cradle of humankind and human culture. It is linguistically and culturally the most complex and diverse continent with hundreds of ethnic divisions, ranging from the Asante in the west to the Zulu in the south. In general, Africa lacked indigenous writing and therefore written records and literature with the exception of Amharic in Ethiopia. Although some examples are known of indigenous attempts, mostly after the mid-nineteenth century, to start elementary writing systems in West Africa, such as the Vai in Liberia, the Bamoun script in the Cameroons (the only one used in writing books) and a few</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 19</label>
                     <title>Native Americans</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Johansen</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Europe did not discover America, but America was quite a discovery for Europe. For roughly three centuries before the American Revolution, the ideas that made the American Revolution possible were being discovered, nurtured and embellished in the growing English and French colonies of North America. America provided a counterpoint for European convention and assumption. It became, for Europeans in America, at once a dream and a reality, a fact and a fantasy, the real and the ideal. To appreciate the way in which European eyes opened on the ‘new world’, we must take the phrase literally, with the excitement</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 20</label>
                     <title>Australasia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rowse</surname>
                           <given-names>Tim</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Australasia’ refers to Australia and New Zealand, two liberal-democratic nation-states arising from British colonisation – beginning in 1788 – of peoples that we now call Aborigines, Torres Strait Islanders and Maori. With Britain’s blessing, by the early twentieth century, the colonists of Australasia had replicated Westminster’s democratic model. However, the two dominions approached differently the enfranchising of Indigenous people. After the Second World War, the United Nations (UN) entrusted the Australasian democracies to establish democratic institutions in Pacific colonies.</p>
                     <p>‘Democracy’ was among their colonising projects.</p>
                     <p>The British began to create civil institutions in the penal colonies of eastern Australia in the 1820s.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 21</label>
                     <title>Singapore</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Doran</surname>
                           <given-names>Christine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Singapore the period from 1890 to 1914 was one of social transformation, demographic shifts, rapid economic development and intellectual ferment. This chapter explores the contributions to democratic thought made by two Chinese Singaporean intellectuals: Lim Boon Keng and Tan Teck Soon. Both were born in Singapore, of Chinese descent, and both became very influential in the dynamic intellectual scene that emerged at the turn of the twentieth century. Lim and Tan sought and found in Chinese religion, political philosophy and history a powerful democratic tradition. They believed that this could become the foundation upon which could be constructed a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 22</label>
                     <title>1808:</title>
                     <subtitle>South American Liberation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fisher</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although not used significantly in academic discourse until the early twentieth century, the term ‘Latin America’ – coined in Paris in the mid-nineteenth century to describe the Francophone Caribbean as well as Spanish and Portuguese America – now defines all the mainland American territories south of the border between the United States and Mexico (including Anglophone Belize and Guyana, as well as Dutch-speaking Suriname). It excludes, however, the former French and Spanish colonies acquired by the United States in the first half of the nineteenth century: Florida (purchased from Spain in 1819); Louisiana (purchased from France in 1803); Texas (declared independence from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 23</label>
                     <title>1848:</title>
                     <subtitle>European Revolutions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>Mike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between February and April 1848, the conservative order which had dominated Europe since the fall of Napoleon in 1815 was felled by the hammer-blows of revolution across the continent. The revolutions swept liberal governments to power, tasked with forging a new political order based on the principles of civil rights and parliamentary government. By the end of 1849, all the revolutions had collapsed and the short and violent European experiment in liberal (and, in some countries, democratic) politics was over. For the history of democracy, the fascination of 1848 lies in the variety of democratic forms that emerged in such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 24</label>
                     <title>1919:</title>
                     <subtitle>After Versailles</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fischer</surname>
                           <given-names>Conan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If a name can be attached to the Treaty of Versailles and the wider Paris Peace Settlement, it is that of the United States President, Woodrow Wilson. Of all the Allied leaders, it was Wilson who caught the international popular imagination, and it was Wilson who appeared to offer the defeated Germans and their allies the best prospects for a tolerable peace within a reformed global order. In December 1918, he arrived in France for the peace conference to a hero’s welcome and possessing an aura of moral authority to which many British and French delegates initially willingly deferred. Wilson</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 25</label>
                     <title>1945:</title>
                     <subtitle>Post-Second World War Japan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Inoguchi</surname>
                           <given-names>Takashi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>304</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines the undertaking of the United States to bring democracy to Japan between 1941 and 1952 during both the Pacific War and the American occupation of Japan. It explores the extent to which the United States was successful in its effort to democratise Japan. The United States was determined that the wartime government of Japan must be destroyed by repeated military campaigns. Step by step, the United States helped to craft a small, conservative, pro-American force in Japan into a majority political party, and, in doing so, successfully brought democracy to the island nation. Before discussing US democracy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 26</label>
                     <title>1989:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eastern Europe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Volten</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter M. E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The transitions to democracy in Eastern and Central Europe from 1989 onwards not only came as a big surprise both inside and outside the region, they were also characterised by incredible speed and by a radical challenge to the prevailing political cultures during the pressing phase of consolidation. The two companion concepts and processes – transition and consolidation of democratic transformation – are clearly culture-bound and dependent on the historical and present context of the country or region involved. This was particularly the case in Central Europe, where cultural and contextual confusion sometimes led to misunderstanding and friction. Westerners who showed their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 27</label>
                     <title>Anti-Slavery</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Drescher</surname>
                           <given-names>Seymour</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the last three centuries democratisation has occurred at three levels. For individuals, it was a process of extending access to equality of status and the security of liberty under law. Within civil societies, it was the process of extending access to the means of communication and association in economic, social and religious spheres of life. Within polities, it meant the formation of constitutional processes for law making, law enforcement and broadening the access to elections of legislators and executives at all levels of the state. In this perspective anti-slavery was a movement and an ideology primarily concerned with changing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 28</label>
                     <title>Women’s Suffrage</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Grimshaw</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sowerwine</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historians have often treated the introduction of women’s suffrage as a narrative of linear progress. In this view, women’s exclusion from the suffrage resulted from ageold prejudices, which, gradually and inevitably, gave way to modern egalitarian ideas. Recent scholarship, however, has complicated this story by emphasising the intractability of the issue. Enlightenment and republican discourse talked in universal terms, but constructed the citizen as public man in opposition to private woman, creating a feminine ‘other’ in order to create a ‘universal’, which was in fact gendered, masculine (Sowerwine 2010: 19). The idea of equal rights and the subordination</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 29</label>
                     <title>Socialism, Communism, Anarchism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hindess</surname>
                           <given-names>Barry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>348</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines important divisions in the history of socialism, focusing on the period before the schism between communists and others that followed the First World War and the subsequent revolutions in Russia (1917) and Germany (1918–1919). It considers divisions between anarchist and Marxist socialism (or, as the anarchist, Michael Bakunin framed it: between revolutionary socialism and communism (Bakunin 1950)); and, within European social democracy, the divisions over the projects of a peaceful, democratic road to socialism and the ‘dictatorship of the proletariat’.</p>
                     <p>Before the late eighteenth-century American and French revolutions, democracy was generally seen as government by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 30</label>
                     <title>Civil Rights</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ondaatje</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The civil rights movement is widely acknowledged as the greatest social movement in US history. Typically associated with the stirring oratory and leadership of Martin Luther King, its philosophies and legacies continue to reverberate throughout America and the world. Demanding freedom and democracy for all, record numbers of black people rose up to challenge the institutional foundations of US white supremacy. They stood nobly and non-violently in the face of police dogs, water cannons and violent mobs, adamant that only love and moral suasion could change America. In overturning segregation and securing black voting rights, the civil rights movement transformed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 31</label>
                     <title>South Africa</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Southall</surname>
                           <given-names>Roger</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The democratisation of South Africa has become widely celebrated. Apartheid, a legalised system of white domination over a majority black population imposed by post-1948 National Party (NP) governments, was peculiarly vilified in a post-Nazi, post-colonial world. By the 1980s, the polarisation between pro-democratic forces and the regime was threatening conflagration of the most advanced industrial economy in Africa. Yet in 1994 South Africa held a first democratic election following a four-year transition process whereby previously warring parties negotiated a highly praised constitution founded upon human equality, liberal democracy, a separation of powers, minority representation and socio-economic as well as individual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 32</label>
                     <title>Bolivia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arbona</surname>
                           <given-names>Juan Manuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Medeiros</surname>
                           <given-names>Carmen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>385</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On December 2005, Evo Morales won Bolivia’s presidential election by one of the widest margins in the country’s democratic history, while his party, Movement Towards Socialism (MAS), gained control of congress. The margin of victory (54 per cent of the votes and 25 percentage points ahead of his closest opponent) was, perhaps, overshadowed by Morales self-identification as an indigenous person and as a staunch critic of the neo-liberal project as neo-colonial and undemocratic. This victory raised many doubts from critics and opponents, who saw Morales as unprepared to assume the responsibilities of governing a country. However, under his leadership Bolivia</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 33</label>
                     <title>Georgia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                           <given-names>Lincoln A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ‘Rose Revolution’ in Georgia is a significant part of the narrative of democracy in the twenty-first century, despite not having played an important role in the expansion of democracy or contributed to new understandings of the concept. Instead, the Rose Revolution is important because it has become one of the most extreme cases of a nondemocratic country vesting much of its strategic and political capital in being perceived as democratic. The Rose Revolution, therefore, is less a critical moment in the evolution of democracy as a critical event in the evolution of geo-political spin. Nonetheless, the narrative of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 34</label>
                     <title>Iraq</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Isakhan</surname>
                           <given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In March 2003, the world’s last remaining superpower launched a pre-emptive strike on a sovereign nation without UN approval or popular domestic or global support. The justification given to the world for such an attack was twofold: Iraq was accused of harbouring weapons of mass destruction (WMD) and of having links to Al-Qaeda, both of which could not be permitted in a post-9/11 world. However, when evidence for either Iraq’s WMDs or links to terrorism failed to emerge in the wake of the war and the nine subsequent years of military occupation, the Bush Administration was forced to re-frame the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 35</label>
                     <title>Burma</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Seekins</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>418</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Burma is one of the poorest countries in southeast Asia and its people are among the least free. Since 1962, it has been ruled by a series of military regimes distinguished by their corruption, incompetence and authoritarianism: the 1962–88 Burma Socialist Programme Party (BSPP) regime of General Ne Win; the State Law and Order Restoration Council (SLORC), which staged a bloody seizure of power in September 1988 (its name was changed in 1997 to the softer-sounding State Peace and Development Council, or SPDC); and a new military-dominated regime with a constitutional fac ¸ ade, the Republic of the Union</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 36</label>
                     <title>China since Tiananmen Square</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>He</surname>
                           <given-names>Baogang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the wake of the 1989 Tiananmen Square event, the Chinese government has both tightened its authoritarian rule and introduced a wide variety of local mini-democratisation practices, including village elections, township elections, intra-party democracy, participatory and deliberative forums, and participatory budgeting. While these do not jeopardise the monopoly of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) on political decision making, they illustrate major trends and characteristics of Chinese democratisation and highlight the Chinese hybrid model of democratisation. This chapter focuses on official democratic mechanisms and institutions initiated at the local level, rather than on more general aspects of democratisation, such as rights</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 37</label>
                     <title>Islam since 9/11</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hashemi</surname>
                           <given-names>Nader</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In international affairs, 11 September 2001 was a watershed day. This day will forever be associated with the terrorist attacks in New York and Washington, DC that resulted in the deaths of 3,000 people. Over the course of the next decade more than 7,500 American, British and other allied troops would lose their lives in the wars and occupations of Afghanistan and Iraq. Civilians, too, have been killed and, while exact figures are unknown and often ignored, the widely accepted conservative estimate is that more than 130,000 Iraqi and Afghan citizens have lost their lives during this same time period</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 38</label>
                     <title>Democracy Promotion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hobson</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most notable features of the post-Cold War era has been the ideational dominance of liberal democracy. The majority of the twentieth century was shaped by a conflict between different ruling ideologies but, with the collapse of the Soviet empire, democracy outlasted its rivals. In this context, Amartya Sen proposed that: ‘democratic governance has now achieved the status of being taken to be generally right’, while one of the leading scholars of democratisation, Larry Diamond, has suggested that ‘democracy is really the only broadly legitimate form of government in the world’ (Diamond 2008: 13; Sen 1999: 5). Certainly,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 39</label>
                     <title>Transnational Democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>467</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Transnational democracy is an idea whose time has come, but it does not, as yet, have much substance. It is a thing of the future more than the present, but its future is far from assured. Such democracy as we presently enjoy it is mostly national, rather than transnational, and representative, rather than participatory. It is largely monopolised by elected ‘representatives’, rather than politically active citizens and almost entirely circumscribed by the territoriality of national state borders. The social communities, relations and processes beyond and across state borders that would constitute transnational democracy largely elude democracy’s remit. ‘Globalisation’ and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 40</label>
                     <title>Digital Democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Loader</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Political communication and the means of its production and diffusion have always been a significant factor shaping the nature of democratic politics. From the oral tradition of the<italic>Agora</italic>, through the pamphlets and newspapers of early modern Europe, to the prevalence of the mass broadcast media in the twentieth century, the communicative power of citizens has been influenced by their access to and use of the prevailing media technologies. It was no surprise, therefore, that the emergence of new information and communication technologies (ICTs), in the form of digital networks such as the Internet, once again raised the prospect of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 41</label>
                     <title>Radical Democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dahlberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Lincoln</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>491</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is radical democracy? Karl Marx’s definition of ‘radical’, from his 1844 ‘Introduction’ to<italic>A Contribution to the Critique of Hegel’s Philosophy of Right</italic>, states that to be radical is ‘to grasp the root of the matter’ (Marx [1844] 1970: 137). Thus, ‘radical democracy’ means to grasp or draw out the root meaning or conditions of democracy that have been obscured in its various historical appropriations. Radical democrats argue that there are two central, intertwined and historically constituted root meanings or conditions of democracy: first, the free and equal participation of ‘the people’ (the<italic>demos</italic>) in power (<italic>kratos</italic>); and,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 42</label>
                     <title>Deliberative Democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hansen</surname>
                           <given-names>Kasper M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rostbøll</surname>
                           <given-names>Christian F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>502</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the last twenty years deliberative democracy has become the most discussed theory of democracy. The term was coined by Joseph Bessette in 1980, but academic writing on deliberative democracy really picked up in the early 1990s (Bessette 1980; Hansen 2004). While the idea of giving deliberation a core role in democracy has roots throughout the history of democracy, the most important contemporary theoretical sources for deliberative democrats are the works of Jürgen Habermas and John Rawls (Habermas 1984, 1989, 1996; Rawls 1971, 1996). The theory of deliberative democracy is often directed at two related deficiencies of actual existing democracy,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 43</label>
                     <title>New Thinking</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keane</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>513</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1945, following several decades that saw most experiments in democratisation fail, there were only a dozen democracies left on the face of the earth. Since then, despite many ups and downs, democracy has bounced back from near oblivion to become a planetary phenomenon for the first time in its history (Diamond 2008; Dunn 2005; Keane 2009b). Fresh research perspectives are required because democracy has taken root in so many different geographic contexts that several fundamental presuppositions of democratic theory have been invalidated. This metamorphosis remains largely unregistered in the literature on democracy, which still has a distinctively Eurocentric bent,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Future History of Democracy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stockwell</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>525</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preceding chapters, the contributors have brought their expertise to bear on many democratic moments, both expected and unexpected, down through history. Together, these chapters tell quite a story of common people taking their chances to create ideas, opportunities and institutions of government where their collective voices have a role to play and often carry the day. But as more people identify themselves as democrats, as more countries embrace democracy, as there is more opportunity for participation at local, national and international levels, there is also evidence of a lapse of faith, a moment of uncertainty, a loss of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>543</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b6rb.51</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>547</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
