<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>From North to South</book-title>
         <subtitle>Southern Scholars Engage with Edward Schillebeeckx</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bergin</surname>
               <given-names>Helen F</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781922239204</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781922239211</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>ATF Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Hindmarsh, SA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>remains with the individual authors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt163t8h5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>From North to South brings together the interests in Edward Schillebeeckx of eight theologians from Australia, New Zealand and Malaysia. In each chapter, theologians dialogue from a southern context with one of Schillebeeckx’s themes or methods. Themes such as suffering and negative contrast experiences, political holiness, ecclesiology, God and the cross, resurrection and hope, and theology and culture are addressed. Attention to Schillebeeckx’s hermeneutics lies at the heart of several chapters but is generally woven throughout. Contributors bring their particular southern contexts into serious dialogue with Schillebeeckx’s northern thought. The book concludes with a response to the south from North American theologian, Kathleen McManus OP. In short, the book witnesses to the ongoing challenge and stimulation of Edward Schillebeeckx’s theology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="184"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Editor</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bergin</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This collection,<italic>From North to South: Southern Scholars engage with Edward Schillebeeckx,</italic>arose from an often articulated sense of gratitude inspired by the theology of Edward Schillebeeckx. For three members of the Catholic Institute of Theology in Aotearoa New Zealand, Neil Darragh, John Dunn and Helen Bergin, Schillebeeckx’s theology has over the years provided nourishment and challenge. Consequently, towards the end of 2009, we decided to invite scholars from the southern region of the world to consider participating in a project to highlight Schillebeeckx’s ongoing theological contribution—even to the ends of the earth! Little did we know that a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>St Mary MacKillop as a Fifth Gospel:</title>
                     <subtitle>Towards Understanding an Australian Saint Through the Lens of Edward Schillebeeckx</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rush</surname>
                           <given-names>Ormond</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 17th October 2010, Australia celebrated the canonisation of its first official saint, Saint Mary of the Cross MacKillop (1842—1909). In this chapter, I propose that Mary MacKillop’s life-story, example, and spirituality can be examined through categories of Edward Schillebeeckx’s theology, in ways that might aid Australian theologians in the contextualisation of this nineteenth century saint for twenty-first century Catholic Australians. Hopefully, this task will also be fruitful for others.</p>
                     <p>I will focus on two central categories of Edward Schillebeeckx’s theological project, namely ‘interpretative experience’ and ‘negative contrast experiences’, as being particularly relevant for this task.</p>
                     <p>Mary MacKillop embodied</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Thy Kingdom Come:</title>
                     <subtitle>Political Holiness for Papua New Guinea</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gibbs</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Edward Schillebeeckx makes no reference in his published works to Papua New Guinea—a nation of seven million people in Oceania. With the exception of those trained in Catholic seminaries, very few people in Papua New Guinea would have heard of the theologian, Schillebeeckx. Yet, his theology, particularly his efforts to find alternatives to dualistic thinking about Christian presence in the world, could contribute to developments in local theologies in a place such as Papua New Guinea. This chapter will focus on Schillebeeckx’s understanding of political holiness and will enter into dialogue with the Melanesian thinking of Bernard Narokobi—perhaps</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Church and its Ministries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Darragh</surname>
                           <given-names>Neil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Schillebeeckx was acutely aware in his later writings of the different circumstances that shape people’s faith and theology. He was aware too that this diversity of cultures and politics was particularly urgent for the world of his time. He uses the word ‘situation’ as a term that stands over against ‘tradition’. ‘Situation’ then refers to the cultural, social and existential context of the people to whom the gospel is proclaimed here and now, the concrete situation in which the tradition of faith is handed on by Christians to new generations.¹</p>
                     <p>In that light, contemporary readers of Schillebeeckx do well to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Was the Cross Necessary?</title>
                     <subtitle>Exploring Schillebeeckx’s View of God in Relation to the Death of Jesus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Edwards</surname>
                           <given-names>Denis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For many people in Australia and New Zealand, the death of Jesus on a Roman cross constitutes a problem of integrity in their life of faith. They ask: how could a loving God send the divine Son to be tortured to death? The theology of redemption they have imbibed involves God willing the death of Jesus on a cross as the means of our salvation. The biblical texts which say that Jesus ‘must’ suffer (Mk 8:31; Lk 24:26) are understood to mean that there was a divine requirement for the cruel death on the cross. This forms a pastoral problem</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Negative Contrast Experience and Edward Schillebeeckx:</title>
                     <subtitle>Critical Reflections</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dunn</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I wish to discuss one significant aspect of the thought of Edward Schillebeeckx: the role of negative contrast experiences in his theology. I will focus on his analysis of suffering, and its application to his Christology, in particular to the death of Christ. In a second part, I will then subject Schillebeeckx’s negative contrast experience to some critical analysis by engaging with a southern global experience still struggling with remnants of colonialism. Thirdly, I will bring the results of my investigation into dialogue with insights from indigenous New Zealand Maori theologian, Henare Tate, as he reflects upon</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Edward Schillebeeckx and Eschatology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Engaging with Hope</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bergin</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Late in November 2010 in Greymouth New Zealand, a coal mine explosion took the lives of twenty-nine men. Immediately after the explosion, the local West Coast community and most of New Zealand waited anxiously for the mine director to announce that rescuers would receive access to the mine and possibly emerge with survivors. However, high gas levels and the delay of receiving Australian robotic equipment led to a stalemate. The recent and safe release of trapped Chilean miners, along with messages of support, assurances of prayer, offers of assistance and compassionate leadership from those in charge—all kept hope alive.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Schillebeeckx’s Theological Method and Religious Pluralism in Asia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chia</surname>
                           <given-names>Edmund Kee-Fook</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My focus in this chapter will be on the theological method of Edward Schillebeeckx. I will examine Schillebeeckx’s method in order to discover how it may assist in appreciating Asian theologies of religious pluralism. I am exploring the latter on account of my Asian origins as well as my involvement in the ministry of interreligious dialogue. I state this at the outset not so much to establish my credentials but in order to take seriously Schillebeeckx’s assertion that theology needs to begin with experience. For him, theology must evolve from the concrete, personal and contemporary experience of the theologian. To</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Theology and Culture:</title>
                     <subtitle>Schillebeeckx’s Journey</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rochford</surname>
                           <given-names>Dennis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because of the wide range of themes and various methodological approaches present in the writings of Edward Schillebeeckx, it is difficult to find the core concern or unifying theological thread that characterises his life’s work. Does one identify particular texts as seminal to this task?¹ If so, what texts might one choose? What subjects stand out as commanding his attention?</p>
                     <p>In this chapter, I will argue that the one matter that concerned him, in one form or another, and which also claims the attention of theology today, can be dated to his very early writings in the Belgian journal,<italic>Kultuurleven</italic>.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A North American Response to From North to South:</title>
                     <subtitle>Southern Scholars Engage with Edward Schillebeeckx</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McManus</surname>
                           <given-names>Kathleen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This wonderful collection of essays explores key themes in the theology of Edward Schillebeeckx via concrete experiences and perspectives of ‘<italic>down under people</italic>’. As a North American theologian, my eyes have been opened to the great diversity of cultures that shape the contexts of Australia, New Zealand, and Papua New Guinea. The complex interweaving of these cultures and their relationships to the Gospel illuminate and enflesh what has been called Schillebeeckx’s pervasive<italic>culture theology.</italic>Many of the essays in this volume exemplify the ‘essayistic theology’ espoused by Erik Borgman, while others examine Schillebeeckx’s methodology from the perspective of contemporary questions.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Biographies of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of books by or about Edward Schillebeeckx</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t8h5.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Biblical References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
