<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">KU43.F73 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War crime trials</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Australia</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust, Jewish (1939–1945)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ukraine</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Daviborshch's Cart</book-title>
         <subtitle>Narrating the Holocaust in Australian War Crimes Trials</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FRASER</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803234123</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803234383</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803234384</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LINCOLN; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dfnskm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In the spring of 1942, Nazi forces occupying the Ukraine launched a wave of executions targeting the region's remaining Jewish communities. These mass shootings were open, public, and intimate. Although the victims themselves could never testify against their killers, many eyewitnesses could and did identify the perpetrators.</p>
         <p>Among these communities, three local men from the villages of Serniki, Israylovka, and Gnivan were intimately implicated in such killing operations: Ivan Polyukhovich, a forester in the German-controlled administration; Heinrich Wagner, a Volksdeutscher liaison officer; and Mikolay Berezowsky, a member of the local police force. More than fifty years later, these three men were arrested and brought to trial in Australia for their alleged war crimes.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Daviborshch's Cart</italic>is more than an account of Holocaust perpetrators who found a safe haven in postwar Australia. It is also the story of the Holocaust in the Ukraine, the War Crimes Act, Nazi policies, and the ways in which future generations translate history into law, archives into proof, and law into justice. Based on a review of previously unexamined historical and legal documents and transcripts,<italic>Daviborshch's Cart</italic>offers the first critical examination of Australian attempts to bring alleged Nazi criminals to justice.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="408"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Long and Winding Road from Ukraine to Australia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The lightning attack of Operation Barbarossa in late June and early July 1941 led to the rapid advance of German troops into Ukraine amid the retreat in disarray of the Red Army. Special extermination units of the ss, the Einsatzgruppen, accompanied the German advance, killing tens of thousands of Ukrainian Jews in the first wave of mass shootings.</p>
                     <p>One year after the arrival of German forces, as workers on the collective farms toiled in the fi elds throughout the region, the second wave of mass killings of Ukraine’s Jewish population began. The remaining Jews in the village of Israylovka, later</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>History, War Crimes, and Law in Ukraine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The odysseys that brought Ivan Polyukhovich, Heinrich Wagner, and Mikhail Berezowsky from the hinterlands of Europe, from war-torn Galicia and Volhynia, through a defeated and ruined Germany, to the peaceful suburbs of Adelaide are complex biographical episodes that are retold in the mass of court and investigative documents compiled during the efforts to prosecute them. In addition to these biographies of the three alleged war criminals, any complete accounting of the cases would have to include a detailed history of what would become present-day Ukraine. For it is in the intersections of the micro-histories of the three men and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>A Brief Political and Legal History of Australia and Nazi War Criminals</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first, legal part of the story of the war crimes trials program that unfolded in the three proceedings in Adelaide begins with Australia’s membership in the United Nations War Crimes Commission (UNWCC).¹ As a party to the UNWCC, Australia positioned itself at the level of diplomacy and international law as a country dedicated to the pursuit and punishment of Nazi war criminals. Yet as was the case with most other participants in the UNWCC, other priorities, both domestic and international, soon came to the fore. In 1947 Australia readily agreed that the UNWCC’s job was done. As Prime Minister</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Law and History in Australian War Crimes Trials:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ukrainian Foresters, the Shoah, and the Polyukhovich Case</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following the successful passage of the War Crimes Act amendments, which left little of the 1945 statute intact, the Special Investigations Unit (SIU) continued its inquiries. The files that were felt to contain the strongest evidence were sent to a leading Sydney criminal lawyer, Greg James QC, who reviewed the information and evidence and advised the Commonwealth’s director of public prosecutions (DPP) on those cases that in his opinion could be pursued through the courts. The practice that was adopted conformed with the underlying ethos of the prosecution scheme that had informed the Australian war crimes process from its beginnings.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Mikolay Berezowsky:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of “The Witness Who Knew Too Much”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mikolay Berezowsky of Royal Park, South Australia, was arrested by police attached to the Special Investigations Unit siu and charged under section 9 of the War Crimes Act. The case against him was in many ways reflective of the historical understanding of the practicalities of massacres in Ukraine. The indigenous police, the Schutzmannschaft, typically functioned in the preliminary stages of the<italic>Aktion</italic>by surrounding the village or ghetto and rounding up the local Jewish communities. The prosecution alleged that Berezowsky was a member of the Schutzmannschaft in the village of Gnivan in the Vinnitsa area and that he had participated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Story of Daviborshch’s Cart:</title>
                     <subtitle>Law, History, Truth, and the Holocaust in Ukraine</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Saul Friedlander has identified the anxieties that have come to characterize debates about the historical construction of events known as the Shoah, the killing of European Jews by the Nazis and their national collaborators in occupied Europe. He writes: “On the one hand, our traditional categories of conceptualization and representation may well be insufficient, our language itself problematic. On the other hand, in the face of these events we feel the need of some stable narration; a boundless field of possible discourse raises the issue of limits with particular stringency.”¹ These concerns about processes, rhetoric, and memory have an impact</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Translating Law, Translating History, in Australian War Crimes Trials</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eyewitnesses in the three Australian war crimes cases, both those who were Jewish survivors of the atrocities and non-Jewish Ukrainians, bystanders and perpetrators, had suffered psychologically from the trauma of the events. For some this means that their testimony might be considered to be more reliable than accounts in ordinary criminal cases because events would be fixed more firmly, more definitely, and, so the argument goes, more accurately, in their minds. On the other hand, trauma can adversely affect cognition. Memories can be fixed that do not necessarily coincide with physical reality. This does not mean that eyewitnesses are acting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Telling Stories about the Shoah:</title>
                     <subtitle>Perpetrators, Victims, and the Politics of Australian Identity in The Hand That Signed the Paper</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paul Ricoeur has identified the three principal genres that have been used in our collective search for a form of narrative truth about the Holocaust, or as Ricoeur puts it, a form of judgment about the Shoah.¹ The three forms of judgment are the judicial, the historical, and the literary. The focus here is primarily on the last two, the historical and the literary, although it will be clear throughout this discussion that the specter of the law haunts the readings that follow.</p>
                     <p>For Ricoeur each genre suffers from its own inherent limits when confronted with the enormity of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Law, Memory, and Justice:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Australian Experience</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The three trials of alleged Nazi criminals that took place under the Australian war crimes legislation are exemplary studies in the art of police investigation and the benefits that can be derived from international legal cooperation in the pursuit of those accused of the commission of atrocities and violations of international criminal law norms. Special Investigations Unit (SIU) investigators, historians, and lawyers tracked down witnesses to events in Ukraine during the Nazi occupation fifty years after the fact. These witnesses were identified through the combined expertise of historians and police officers. Their evidence was gathered by police and lawyers in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnskm.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
