<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PG2950.B48 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Russian literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mythology in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Superstition in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Superstitious Muse</book-title>
         <subtitle>Thinking Russian Literature Mythopoetically</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bethea</surname>
               <given-names>David M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781934843178</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781618116789</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Academic Studies Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Brighton, MA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Academic Studies Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxsj7q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>For several decades David Bethea has written authoritatively on the “mythopoetic thinking" that lies at the heart of classical Russian literature, especially Russian poetry. His theoretically informed essays and books have made a point of turning back to issues of intentionality and biography at a time when authorial agency seems under threat of “erasure" and the question of how writers, and poets in particular, live their lives through their art is increasingly moot. The lichnost’ (personhood, psychic totality) of the given writer is all-important, argues Bethea, as it is that which combines the specifically biographical and the capaciously mythical in verbal units that speak simultaneously to different planes of being. Pushkin’s Evgeny can be one incarnation of the poet himself and an Everyman rising up to challenge Peter’s new world order; Brodsky can be, all at once, Dante and Mandelstam and himself, the exile paying an Orphic visit to Florence (and, by ghostly association, Leningrad).This sort of metempsychosis, where the stories that constitute the Ur-texts of Russian literature are constantly reworked in the biographical myths shaping individual writers’ lives, is Bethea’s primary focus. This collection contains a liberal sampling of Bethea’s most memorable previously published essays along with new studies prepared for this occasion.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bethea</surname>
                           <given-names>David M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mythopoetics Meets the Living Person: How David Bethea Balances the Body and the Muse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Emerson</surname>
                           <given-names>Caryl</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The entries in this volume cover a huge amount of territory, but even so represent only a portion of David Bethea’s wide-ranging interests over the past three decades. One figure will serve as portal into these selected essays, arguably the fulcrum and inspirati on for Bethea’s mythopoetics: Alexander Pushkin. The shade of that great poet hovers over Bethea’s other perennial companions: Vladimir Nabokov, Vladislav Khodasevich, Joseph Brodsky, Gavrila Derzhavin. From this magical zone of Russian writers with Pushkin at its core, one question will be central. How, and through what charmed intermediaries, does a poet create and then continue to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>The Mythopoetic “Vectors” of Russian Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any national literature is to some significant extent a mirror held up to its people’s collective countenance: its myths, aspirations, national triumphs and traumas, current ideologies, historical understanding, linguistic traditions. But it is also more than that—more than a reflection in the glass of what has come before and what is now, even as one glances into it, passing from view. It is, in a real sense, generative of new meaning, and thus capable of shaping that countenance in the future. For the society that takes its literary products seriously, the text of a novel or poem can be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Mythopoesis Writ Large:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Apocalyptic Plot in Russian Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Humankind has always lived in time, but it has not always lived in history. Archaeologists and anthropologists provide countless examples of societies, “ancient” in time or “primitive” in development, where time was experi enced mythically rather than historically, where only those details of life that fit into and recapitulated the master plot of a sacred tale were worthy of remembrance.² The British social anthropologist Bronislaw Malinowski defined myth as</p>
                     <p>… not merely a story but a reality lived. It is not of the nature of fiction, such as we read today in a novel, but it is aliving reality; believed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Mythopoesis and Biography:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pushkin, Jakobson, and the Secret Life of Statues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Schools in the “human sciences” are bound virtually by their own phylogenetic principles to undermine and supersede their predecessors rather than disinterestedly, patiently, build on them. A prior school has to be razed and then a new one erected on the same spot, with the “school board” quickly forgetting the attractions and the still usable space of the now nonexistent building. Students get bussed to the new school without any knowledge (un less some teachers tell them so) that they are walking the halls of a place that once looked much different. The prior school is precisely not “refurbished” or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>The Evolution of Evolution:</title>
                     <subtitle>Genes, Memes, Intelligent Design, and Nabokov</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many of us know this famous passage from The Gift. Quite aside from its stylistic fireworks it has served as exhibit #1 in the ongoing debate about where Nabokov comes down on the issue of intelligent design (ID) and evolutionary theory. Depending on one’s epistemological point of departure, readers have tried now for some time to “get at” VN’s strategy for mixing and matching scientific and artistic observation. According to this strategy the artist must be able to observe and name the phenomenal world like the naturalist, the naturalist must be able to integrate different planes of reality like the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Relativity and Reality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dante, Florensky, Lotman, and Metaphorical Time-Travel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given his interest in complex semiotic structures and in a “semiosphere” whose ever ramifying interactions model the vast physical cosmos, it is not surprising that Yury Lotman paused in his writings to discuss the most elaborate of all texts, the worlds within worlds of Dante’s<italic>La Divina Commedia.</italic>Indeed, these two authors seem almost made for each other, for their passion for meaning (and meaning making) against a moving backdrop of epistemology and geo-and astrophysics are uncannily similar. In<italic>Universe of the Mind</italic>Lotman juxtaposes the vertical journey of Dante the pilgrim and the horizontal journey of the curious, courageous,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Whose Mind Is This Anyway?</title>
                     <subtitle>Influence, Intertextuality, and the Boundaries of Legitimate Scholarship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On a green island amid the dark-blue sea there appeared a man. Here he decided to erect a temple. He broke up and carted blocks of marble, hewed them, cut capitals and friezes, erected columns and walls. But before doing that he constructed a temple in his imagination, and all that he erected in stone was simply the recreation of his already created ideal. This ideal was not something dead and immobile: in the head of the builder there swarmed designs, with the variants pressing in on each other, and the view from a hill or the form of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Of Pushkin and Pushkinists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Introductions to books and collections about Alexander Pushkin tend to begin, especially when their origin is not Russian,<italic>with de rigueur</italic>nods to the poet’s massive presence in, and seminal influence on, the native culture. Such expository scaffolding falls under the category of preemptive advertising for a figure who, outside his context and more importantly outside his language, has difficulty translating. Thus, from the operas of Glinka, Tchaikovsky, Musorgsky and Rimsky-Korsakov to the stylish illustrations and set designs of Benois, Bilibin, and Dobuzhinsky; from endlessly anthologized paintings by Kiprensky and Repin to ghosts of allusion in better known works by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Pushkin’s Biography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>with</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Davydov</surname>
                           <given-names>Sergei</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As one considers any biographical treatment of Alexander Pushkin it is prudent to bear in mind the words of the eminent cultural historian, literary theorist, and biographer of the poet Yury Lotman. In his biography Lotman “wanted to show how, like the mythological King Midas who turned everything he touched to gold, Pushkin turned everything he touched into creativity, art. [But] Midas starved to death — his food became gold.”² This metaphor is strikingly apropos when it comes to the facts of Pushkin’s life. Let us take for an example the seemingly straightforward case of the poet’s hair color. In the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Pushkin’s Mythopoetic Consciousness:</title>
                     <subtitle>Apuleius, Psyche and Cupid, and the Theme of Metamorphosis in Eugene Onegin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pushkin was possessed of a richly mythopoetic consciousness. He was also, as numerous friends attest, intensely superstitious. Indeed, for a poet of Pushkin’s range and energy, it is not surprising that some of his finest works are motivated thematically on the dual and interpenetrating notions that myths can, literally, come to life and that forces beyond one’s control can prearrange one’s destiny. Yet Pushkin never made the connection between certain crucial myths (or beliefs, superstitions) and his own unfolding biography<italic>explicit.</italic>He was protected from this not only by his own<italic>amour propre</italic>but by the carapace of what Lydia</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>“A Higher Audacity”:</title>
                     <subtitle>How to Read Pushkin’s Dialogue with Shakespeare in The Stone Guest</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literary historian and poet Stepan Shevyryov was the first to iden tify what is doubtless a resonant intertextual echo of Shakespeare in Pushkin’s<italic>The Stone Guest</italic>. Writing in the<italic>Moskvitianin</italic>in 1841, Shevyryov stated:</p>
                     <p>The scenes with Don Guan and Dona Anna strongly recall the scene in<italic>Richard III</italic>with Gloucester (Richard III) and Lady Anne, the widow of Edward, Prince of Wales, right down to the detail of the dagger that Don Guan, like Gloucester, uses as a clever means for the coup de grace [<italic>dlia doversheniia pobedy</italic>]. The situation is precisely the same. I t is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>Stabat Pater:</title>
                     <subtitle>Revisiting the “Monu mental” in Peter, Petersburg, Pushkin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present study is about Pushkin’s Petersburg, what the city meant in the creative psychology of the poet. More specifically, it is about monuments — first, the famous equestrian monument to Peter I created by Etienne Falconet and unveiled on Senate Square by Catherine II in 1782 (the centennial of the great tsar’s ascension to the throne); second, the city itself, which became synonymous in people’s minds with the emperor’s project to reshape and westernize Russia; and third, the narrative poem/epos (poema) by Pushkin, which took the statue as its title and central plot device.² It will be my argument that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>Slavic Gift-Giving, The Poet in History, and Pushkin’s The Captain’s Daughter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like the bread and salt that are their folk embodiments, the values of generosity and hospitality are very old in the Russian mentality. And no writer is considered more “Russian” in this sense of spiritual generosity and inexhaustible “giftedness” than Alexander Pushkin. But what exactly does this mean, once one leaves the porous level of cultural myth? “There should not be any free gifts,” writes the social anthropologist Mary Douglas, since each gift and each personality donating and receiving each gift belongs to a larger system of ongoing and mutually implicating relations. “Gift cycles engage persons in permanent commitments that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 13</label>
                     <title>Pushkin’s The History of Pugachev:</title>
                     <subtitle>Where Fact Meets the Zero-Degree of Fiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The History of Pugachev</italic>is, conceptually speaking, one of the most fascinating works in Pushkin’s oeuvre. At the same time it is, belletristically if not historiographically, pretty much a flop, a point which has been made more than once over the past two centuries, most persuasively in recent decades by Marc Raeff.² Yet Pushkin was clearly up to something important here, in 1833–34, as he gained access to government archives and gathered materials, visited the sites of the 1773–74 rebellion in the Orenburg<italic>guberniya</italic>, took down eyewitness accounts, and drafted his history, a history which was intended to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 14</label>
                     <title>Sorrento Photographs:</title>
                     <subtitle>Khodasevich’s Memory Speaks</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Russian poet Vladislav Khodasevich (1886–1939), who spent the last seventeen years of his life in Western Europe, wrote a total of five books of verse: the first two, Youth (<italic>Molodost’</italic>, 1908) and The Happy Little House (<italic>Shchastlivyi domik,</italic>1914), are largely derivative and, by the poet’s own admis sion, immature;² the last three, Grain’s Way (<italic>Putem zerna,</italic>1920), The Heavy Lyre (<italic>Tiazhelaia lira,</italic>1922), and European Night (<italic>Evropeiskaia noch’</italic>, 1927), form the limited body of his mature work.³ It is on the basis of the last three collections that Khodasevich’s modest reputation has been established. It is ironic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 15</label>
                     <title>Nabokov’s Style</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a prodigiously gifted<italic>homo scribens</italic>such as Vladimir Nabokov, there is nothing more precious or distinctive about his constructed persona than his style. Indeed, the written trace is, to a degree potentially disturbing to some readers, that aspect of personhood Nabokov most valued. It was what<italic>remained behind,</italic>always under his control, to be wielded with consummate elegance and grace even as the enemy, time itself, took from him his homeland, his loved ones, and eventually his own life. “Summer<italic>soomerki</italic>—the lovely Russian word for dusk. Time: a dim point in the first decade of this unpopular century.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 16</label>
                     <title>Sologub, Nabokov, and the Limits of Decadent Aesthetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the more fascinating aspects of Nabokov’s artistic method is the way he “covers his tracks” when referring to potential intertextual sources or “ influences.” He prefers his readers to believe that each work has emerged fully formed from the broad forehead (as opposed to dark loins) of his Zeuslike consciousness. Or so the prefaces to his novels, with their disclaimers as to matters of genealogy and their repeated references to the “Viennese delegation,” would have us think. It is not that Nabokov hesitates to engage in intertextual punning or name-dropping, which practice clearly enriches the links within his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 17</label>
                     <title>Exile, Elegy, and Auden in Brodsky’s “Verses on the Death of T. S. Eliot”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Death,” writes Joseph Brodsky in his 1982 essay on Akhmatova, “is a good litmus test for a poet’s ethics. The ‘in memoriam’ genre is frequently used to exercise self-pity or for metaphysical trips that denote the subconscious superiority of survivor over victim, of majority (of the alive) over minority (of the dead). Akhmatova [in her poetic cycle<italic>Requiem</italic>] would have none of that.”² This statement, as self-regarding as it is self-effacing, is itself a kind of litmus test for the author’s own ethics and aesthetics. Versions of it reappear at strategic moments in Brodsky’s important essays on Tsvetaeva and on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 18</label>
                     <title>Joseph Brodsky and the American Seashore Poem:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lowell, Mandelstam and Cape Cod</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The two anglophone poets who exercised the greatest sway over the young exiled Russian poet Joseph Brodsky in the early 1970’s were W. H. Auden and Robert Lowell. In retrospect, this influence should not be puzzling, inasmuch as these two established older poets took the younger one under their wings after his forced expulsion from the Soviet Union in June 1972, extended him various kindnesses as he tried to adapt to a new linguistic environment, and then both died soon thereafter — Auden in 1973, Lowell in 1977 — leaving Brodsky, an obsessive elegist, to consider their passing in the light of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 19</label>
                     <title>Joseph Brodsky’s “To My Daughter” (A Reading)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joseph Brodsky is a bundle of contradictions. This statement might be problematic if he were a philosopher, but his consistent incon sistency makes perfect sense to those studying his primary sta tus — that of poet. Stoic toward the arbitrariness of the world order (or disorder), deeply melancholic (if not corrosively skepti cal) about “human nature,” yet passionately be lieving in language’s ontological priority as the only<italic>thing</italic>(note this word) in human existence approaching a genuine God-term, Brod sky could be maddening in the sheer outrageousness, the “demanding-the maximum-and-the-hell-with-the-rest” quality, of his metaphorical thinking. But that is what poets, especially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 20</label>
                     <title>Brodsky, Frost, and the Pygmalion Myth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Central to any understanding of Joseph Brodsky as poet and thinker is his myth of language, his belief in words, and not just any words but specifically poetic words, ability to restructure time and to outwit states, tyrants, history itself. “Prosody is simply a repository of time within language,”² writes Brodsky in a statement repeated many times over in different guises and contexts. Poetic words, by their very nature, got there, and are always still getting there, first. Indeed, what makes this idea a myth in the first place, that is, something larger than the life it explains, is these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsj7q.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
