<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Restless Secularism</book-title>
         <subtitle>Modernism and the Religious Inheritance</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mutter</surname>
               <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300221732</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300227963</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1q1xt6f"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A scholarly and deeply sensitive study that explores how religion and secularism are tightly interwoven in the major works of modernist literatureMatthew Mutter provides a broad survey of modernist literature, examining key works against a background of philosophy, theology, intellectual and social history, while tracing the relationship of modernism's secular imagination to the religious cultures that both preceded and shaped it. Mutter's provocative study demonstrates how, despite their explicit desire to purify secular life of its religious residues, Wallace Stevens, Virginia Woolf, and other literary modernists consistently found themselves entangled in the religious legacies they disavowed.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Modernist Secularism and Its Discontents</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a famous passage in Virginia Woolf’s<italic>To the Lighthouse</italic>where Mrs. Ramsay, knitting in solitude after her children have gone to bed, accesses a “self” beneath her social identity. She calls this self “a wedge-shaped core of darkness.”¹ Its fluidity and obscurity allow her to ignore the boundaries that establish discrete identities and separate things from one another. In this darkness there is no “personality” that confronts the world as a series of competing objects to be placated, mastered, or managed; rather, there is a “summoning together” of all things in a complete “rest” outside “the fret, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“The World Was Paradise Malformed”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Poetic Language, Anthropomorphism, and Secularism in Wallace Stevens</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scholars of Wallace Stevens have long recognized that his poetics is bound up with the loss of religious faith. The standard critical picture is that, like many Victorians before him, Stevens gave up certain consolatory beliefs in the “supernatural” and looked to poetry to fill the vacuum of “meaning.” Stevens himself wrote bluntly in a letter of mid-career: “[I]t is a habit of mind with me to be thinking of some substitute for religion” (L, 348 ). Critics have usually proceeded, however, as if the terms of Stevens’s secularism were self-evident and the transitional movement between religion and poetry—“substitution”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“Tangled in a Golden Mesh”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Virginia Woolf and the “Deceptiveness”of Beauty</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Wallace Stevens, the most dangerous residue of religion for aesthetics lay in the tendency of poetic language to generate religious metaphors and anthropomorphisms. The fiction of Virginia Woolf discloses another danger for aesthetics: the propensity of modern experiences of beauty and sublimity to engender religious modes of thought and desire that are no longer intelligible within a secular conception of the world. For Woolf’s characters, the beautiful (and its modern cousin, the sublime) is suspended in the uncertain space between religious and secular ontologies. The intensity of experiences of beauty<italic>among</italic>her characters is matched only by the suspicion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“Homer Is My Example”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Yeats, Paganism, and the Emotions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are a number of ways to figure the boundaries between religion and secularity in modernism. Stevens juxtaposes the theologically determined Christian with the unencumbered, self-legislating agent who is, in the language of “Sunday Morning,” “unsponsored, free” (<italic>CP, 56</italic>). One can also, like Stevens, pit the claims of “nature” against the “supernatural”: “the great poems of heaven and hell have been written and the great poem of the earth remains to be written” (730). Joyce’s<italic>Portrait</italic>juxtaposes the dogmatic, ecclesial priest with the “priest of the eternal imagination” who “transmut[es] the daily bread of experience into the radiant body of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>“The Power to Enchant That Comes from Disillusion”:</title>
                     <subtitle>W. H. Auden’s Anti-Magical Poetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Wallace Stevens makes an anonymous appearance in W. H. Auden’s “In Praise of Limestone” (1947). The limestone landscape, the speaker says, “calls into question”</p>
                     <p>All the Great Powers assume; it disturbs our rights. The poet, Admired for his earnest habit of calling The sun the sun, his mind Puzzle, is made uneasy By these marble statues which so obviously doubt His antimythological myth . . .¹</p>
                     <p>“The poet” is Stevens. The lines were recycled and modified from an unpublished comic lyric, “Miss God on Mr. Stevens,” originally scribbled in the margins of Auden’s copy of Stevens’s<italic>Transport to Summer</italic>.²</p>
                     <p>Auden’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Evil and the Adequacy of the Earth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Auden’s poetry shows that the religious and the secular do not have to be at loggerheads. Stevens wanted to write “the great poem of the earth” to rival “ the great poems of heaven and hell”<italic>(CP, 730</italic>); “religious” for him was synonymous with “otherworldly,” and he thought that a secular poetry could finally engage an earth no longer conceived as a spiritual way station. But the later Auden is unquestionably a poet of the earth. He did not, after converting to Christianity, turn to writing devotional or mystical poetry that strained toward transcendence. He became, rather, more thoroughly a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Credits</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q1xt6f.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
