<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Translator’s Doubts</book-title>
         <subtitle>Vladimir Nabokov and the Ambiguity of Translation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>TRUBIKHINA</surname>
               <given-names>JULIA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781618112606</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781618117038</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Academic Studies Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Brighton, MA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Academic Studies Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxsjwj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Using Vladimir Nabokov as its “case study," this volume approaches translation as a crucial avenue into literary history and theory, philosophy and interpretation. It attempts to bring together issues in translation and the shift in Nabokov studies from its earlier emphasis on the “metaliterary" to the more recent “metaphysical" approach. Addressing specific texts (both literary and cinematic), the book investigates Nabokov’s deeply ambivalent relationship to translation as a hermeneutic oscillation on his part between the relative stability of meaning, which expresses itself philosophically as a faith in the beyond, and deep metaphysical uncertainty. While Nabokov’s practice of translation changed profoundly over the course of his career, his adherence to the Romantic notion of a “true" but ultimately elusive metaphysical language remained paradoxically constant.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book singles out translation as a way of talking about literary history and theory, philosophy, and interpretation. Vladimir Nabokov is its case study. The advantage of making Nabokov a case study for an investigation of questions of translation is obvious. It is hard to separate Vladimir Nabokov from the act of translation, in all senses of the word—ranging from “moving across” geographical borders and cultural and linguistic boundaries to the transposing of the split between “here” and “there” and “then” and “now” (the essential elements of exile, components of every émigré experience) onto a metaphysical plane sometimes suggested</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Nabokov’s Beginnings:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Ania” in Wonderland or “Does Asparagus Grow in a Pile of Manure?”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1922, Gamaiun, a Russian publishing company in Berlin, commissioned the twenty-three-year-old Nabokov to translate<italic>Alice in Wonderland</italic>into Russian. As Nabokov’s biographer Brian Boyd aptly noted, Nabokov apparently “found the translation easy work after<italic>Colas Breugnon</italic>,” his first serious work of translation.¹ Though Nabokov later claimed he had translated Romain Rolland and Lewis Carroll simultaneously, Boyd, based on the evidence of Nabokov’s letters from Cambridge, dates the Carroll translation to the summer of 1922. The translation, with Sergei Zalshupin’s illustrations, was published in 1923 as<italic>Ania v strane chudes</italic>(“Ania in Wonderland”) under Nabokov’s pen name</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>The Novel on Translation and “Über-Translation”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nabokov’s Pale Fire and Eugene Onegin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his 1937 French essay for the<italic>Nouvelle Revue française</italic>, “Pouchkine, ou le vrai et le vraisemblable” (“Pushkin, or the Real and the Plausible”),³ Nabokov claimed that the truth of another’s life is inaccessible because thought inevitably distorts whatever it tries to encompass. However, the intuitions of a fictionalized biography motivated by love for its subject might convey a “plausible” life bearing a mysterious affinity for “the poet’s work, if not the poet himself.”⁴ This relatively early statement on this subject by Nabokov, made during centennial celebrations of Aleksandr Pushkin’s death, becomes poignant in light of Nabokov’s novel Pale Fire</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>“Cinemizing” as Translation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nabokov’s Screenplay of Lolita and Stanley Kubrick’s and Adrian Lyne’s Cinematic Versions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Alfred Appel effectively demonstrated in<italic>Nabokov’s Dark Cinema</italic>, cinematographic allusions and references are omnipresent in Nabokov’s fiction.²<italic>Lolita</italic>, however, is a special case not only because it employs multiple cinematic correlations and images, but also because of Nabokov’s involvement in 1959-1960 in the “cinemizing”—to use his own term—of his famous novel. The result of his well-known collaboration with Stanley Kubrick was the acclaimed motion picture Lolita (which left Nabokov with a “mixture of aggravation, regret, and reluctant pleasure” as well as the discovery that “Kubrick was a great director”)³ based on Nabokov’s original screenplay, of which very</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                     <subtitle>Vladimir Nabokov within the Russian and Western Traditions of Translation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this conclusion, I would like to provide an overview that situates Nabokov vis-à-vis the Russian and Western traditions of translation, and to bring together in this context the central issues of Nabokov’s ambivalent relationship to translation. These issues include his origin—his own “secret stem,” leading back to Russian Romanticism—as well as translation as a vehicle for expressing Nabokov’s own strongly held ideas about art. While Nabokov’s practice of translation undergoes significant changes in the course of his career, his adherence to the idea of some “true,” “metaphysical” language—ever elusive and ever present—remains surprisingly constant.</p>
                     <p>In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsjwj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
