<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Post-1990 Documentary: Reconfiguring Independence</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Deprez</surname>
               <given-names>Camille</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pernin</surname>
               <given-names>Judith</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>24</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748694136</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748694143</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Camille Deprez</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Judith Pernin</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt16r0hnq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This new book provides graduate students, scholars and professionals with critical and detailed insights into recent, yet significant, independent documentary makers and their varied works, practices and uses. Writing from a variety of areas and perspectives, the contributors to this book introduce innovative interpretations of under-studied contemporary subject matters and styles, as well as production, distribution and exhibition strategies, to the growing fields of documentary film and cross-media studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="280"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deprez</surname>
                           <given-names>Camille</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pernin</surname>
                           <given-names>Judith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The documentary field is arguably one of the most vibrant, challenging and creative areas in moving images today. In countries with well-established film and television industries, documentary production has been considerably revitalised since the late 1980s. From this period onwards, new distribution opportunities through specialised TV channels and circulation in both international film festivals and theatres have steadily ensured the vitality of both documentary TV programmes and feature-length documentaries. Simultaneously, the globalisation and popularisation of video and digital technologies around the world, and the concomitant development of video practices outside conventional cinema, have transformed the documentary form into a common</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Post-unification (East) German Documentary and the Contradictions of Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Byg</surname>
                           <given-names>Barton</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In assessing what post-German Democratic Republic (GDR) documentary brings to independent documentary film culture in Germany, one is struck in general by the relatively privileged status the ‘independent’ documentary has long had. Despite being ‘marginal’ to the major media industries based on entertainment, documentary films in Germany enjoy considerable status, exhibition outlets and funding, even where topics are politically controversial and methods are either avant-garde or critical of the mainstream. Prior to the fall of the Berlin Wall, the position of secure employment, steading funding and guaranteed screening outlets even made GDR documentary filmmakers the envy of their Western counterparts.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>No Going Back:</title>
                     <subtitle>Continuity and Change in Australian Documentary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Williams</surname>
                           <given-names>Deane</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hughes</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Documentary dealing with immigration and the migrant experience in Australia is a continuous thread running through Australian cinema, more recently eclipsed by works equally complex in their articulation of politics and culture, responding in different ways to Australia’s reaction to refugees and the troublesome obsession in Australian domestic political discourse with ‘border protection’. In what follows, we make reference to state-sponsored documentary of the early 1950s supporting immigration in post-war reconstruction, and to a number of recent documentary projects across a spectrum of contemporary forms, projects that respond to public debate around asylum seekers and refugees. Questions of editorial and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>A Space in Between:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Legacy of the Activist Documentary Film in India</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deprez</surname>
                           <given-names>Camille</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first international wave of activist documentary cinema began around the late 1960s and the early 1970s, including in India. This was a time when filmmakers leaned towards more personal arguments about political and social issues, when documentaries moved away from observation and favoured intervention in society and when a new documentary practice and style developed, determined by low budgets and striking content. Later, in the 1990s to 2000s, the digital revolution brought further developments to this mode of filmmaking worldwide. In India, along with the market-driven satellite TV boom and privatisation of the sector of the early 1990s, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Languages, Speech and Voice:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Heritage of Jean Rouch and Pier Paolo Pasolini in Convention: Black Wall / White Holes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Galmard</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2011, French filmmaker Joris Lachaise¹ directed the film<italic>Convention: Black Wall / White Holes</italic>. He used the fiftieth anniversary celebrations of Mali’s independence and his journey through the country as an opportunity to assess bodies and words, which – as the title suggests – constantly interrogate the conscious and unconscious relations with, and references to, the colonial heritage. Knowing that he is not on uncharted cinematic territory, the filmmaker explicitly refers in voice-over to Jean Rouch and Pier Paolo Pasolini, among other leading documentary makers (Chris Marker, Johan Van Der Keuken). He intends to ‘pay them a tribute’, but he also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Chris Marker:</title>
                     <subtitle>Interactive Screen and Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Feigelson</surname>
                           <given-names>Kristian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chris Marker (1921–2012), the creator of more than eighty films, has become a source of fascination for an entire generation of documentary filmmakers, as well as for the general public. In the 1950s, he succeeded in rejuvenating the documentary form and has since wielded considerable, though discreet, influence. The invention of mobile video cameras in the 1960s accorded greater liberty to documentary cinema. There was already talk of a New Wave in this field when Chris Marker reinvented the documentary essay, successively using various technologies from 16mm to Super 8, still photographs and digital images, while experimenting with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>The Survivor–Perpetrator Encounter and the Truth Archive in Rithy Panh’s Documentaries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morag</surname>
                           <given-names>Raya</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I propose an analysis of Rithy Panh’s documentaries,<italic>S21: The Khmer Rouge Death Machine</italic>(2003),<italic>Duch, Master of the Forges of Hell</italic>(2012) and, to a lesser degree,<italic>The Missing Picture</italic>(2013), as what I term ‘perpetrator documentaries’ – that is, documentaries that focus on the figure of the perpetrator, while unravelling the long-time enigma of the ‘ordinary man turned perpetrator’ (Browning [1992] 1998: 159–89). I suggest that the survivor– perpetrator encounter staged at the heart of<italic>S21</italic>and<italic>Duch</italic>is a major characteristic of Panh’s perpetrator documentary cinema, aiming at undermining the perpetrator’s ideology of extermination</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Contesting Consensual Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Work of Remembering in Chilean Autobiographical Documentaries</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goursat</surname>
                           <given-names>Juliette</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The plebiscite of 5 October 1988, in which 55.99 per cent of Chileans said ‘no’ to Pinochet, marked the end of military dictatorship, but did not restore a proper democracy. It opened a new period that political analysts named the ‘transition’, to designate an alliance between politics (re-democratisation) and economics (neoliberalism). During those years, the post-dictatorship presidents – until 2010, all from the Concertación de Partidos por la Democracia¹ – were determined to reconcile Chileans, whom the dictatorship seemed to have irreparably divided. As Peter Winn writes: ‘in the face of the left’s demand for “truth and justice” and the right’s reluctant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>‘We All Invented Our Own Algeria’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Habiba Djahnine’s Letter to My Sister as Memory-Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Petty</surname>
                           <given-names>Sheila</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Filmmaking in the Maghreb is often considered to be a relatively recent phenomenon, having been virtually born alongside Maghrebi nations’ independence from France (Tunisia and Morocco in 1957; Algeria in 1962). And while each country’s film industry has a distinct history, there are some similarities, one of which is an auteur-style production context, where filmmakers are generally responsible for all aspects of production, including financing and creation (Armes 2009: 5). The predominant film style in the 1960s and 1970s following independence veered toward realism and didacticism alongside a total commitment to the liberation struggle in ‘<italic>cinema moudjahid</italic>or “freedom-fighter cinema”’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>From the Ashes:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fall of Apartheid and the Rise of the Lone Documentary Filmmaker in South Africa</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maasdorp</surname>
                           <given-names>Liani</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>South African documentary filmmaking has changed substantially since 1990. Repressive state control of the media under the apartheid regime from 1948 to 1990 led to filmmaking that either overtly eschewed the political or made a strong statement on political and social issues. In both cases, personal stories and artistic expression were neglected. Thanks to the official transition to democracy that started in South Africa around 1990, space has been created for a new era in fiction and non-fiction filmmaking.</p>
                     <p>Since its launch in 1976, the South African Broadcasting Corporation (SABC) has been the predominant funder of non-fiction productions in South</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>A Personal Vision of the Hong Kong Cityscape in Anson Mak’s Essayistic Documentary Films One Way Street on a Turntable and On the Edge of a Floating City, We Sing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ingham</surname>
                           <given-names>Mike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Standing in sharp contrast to the predominantly journalistic, expository or vérité documentaries which Hong Kong is recognised for producing, is one of its rare experimental, essayistic documentaries. Anson Hoi Shan Mak’s highly idiosyncratic filmic record of a quasi-Bloomian pilgrimage through traditional districts of Hong Kong, entitled<italic>One Way Street on a Turntable</italic>(2007), premiered at the Hong Kong International Film Festival in 2007 to mixed critical reviews.¹</p>
                     <p>As Timothy Corrigan has implicitly acknowledged in his recent book on essay films, it is an important contribution to recent documentary critical discourse. By privileging Mak’s work and placing it in the company</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Documentary Filmmakers on the Circuit:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Festival Career from Czech Dream to Czech Peace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vallejo</surname>
                           <given-names>Aida</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the 1990s onwards, festivals specialising in documentary film have spread across the globe, and their new features have changed the roles these events previously played in film culture and business. Where festivals once served primarily as exhibition sites, the recent incorporation of industry sections to their programmes has resulted in these events having a profound influence not only on film criticism, but also on production and distribution. In this context, independent filmmakers have found a professional space to develop their projects at different stages, from searching for pre-production funding to finding distributors for theatrical release or television broadcasts. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Material Traces of Lebanon:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Documentary Aesthetics of Feeling in the Art Gallery</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Takahashi</surname>
                           <given-names>Tess</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the mid-1990s, artists have explored the status of documentary reference and the material trace in the gallery with increasing frequency. In part, this line of investigation stems from a situation in which the power of documentary images has been met with a widespread cultural uncertainty about their trustworthiness. As Hito Steyerl and Maria Lind write: ‘The double bind is strong: on the one hand documentary images are more powerful than ever. On the other hand, we have less and less trust in documentary representations’ (2008: 1). In response to this uncertainty, artists and filmmakers alike have turned increasingly to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 13</label>
                     <title>Autonomous Navigation?</title>
                     <subtitle>Multiplicity and Self-reflexive Aesthetics in Sergio Basso’s Documentary Film Giallo a Milano and Web Documentary Made in Chinatown</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chung</surname>
                           <given-names>Hilary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Luciano</surname>
                           <given-names>Bernadette</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent decades, many Italian filmmakers have been turning to the documentary medium in response to the lack of commitment by public and private broadcasters to the production of programmes of cultural significance (Bertozzi 2008: 305). Unfortunately, the contestable funding available for their production (mostly local, regional or special interest) is limited, as is documentary distribution beyond the festival circuit. The emergence and evolution of the web documentary has provided an opportunity for new channels of distribution and increasingly foregrounds the role of the user/viewer in their engagement, interaction and negotiation with the reality documented. The key distinction between linear</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 14</label>
                     <title>Fukushima and the Shifting Conventions of Documentary:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Broadcast to Social Media Netizenship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Broderick</surname>
                           <given-names>Mick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jacobs</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Documenting the effects of nuclear energy on the screen is itself as old as the discovery of radiation and the invention of the motion picture (Broderick 1995b). Following academic Eric Barnouw’s lead with<italic>Hiroshima-Nagasaki</italic>– August, 1945 (1970), filmmakers in the 1970s began to access and distribute previously classified nuclear footage, including suppressed images of the human effects of the atomic bombs dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki (Hirano 1996; Nornes 1996). During that decade, documentarians produced a ‘surge of investigative filmmaking’, where both military and civilian nuclear energy ‘came under sharp scrutiny’ (Barnouw 1993: 308–9.) These whistle-blowing films, aired on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 15</label>
                     <title>Independent Documentaries and Online Uses in China:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Cinephilia to Activism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pernin</surname>
                           <given-names>Judith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the late 1980s, radical transformations of the Chinese film industry and art circles have led to the emergence of a significant body of independent documentary films produced and circulated without the backing of state institutions. This was definitely a breakthrough, since state documentary studios and television stations were the sole producers and broadcasters of non-fiction films in China for more than thirty years. Reforms that gradually adjusted the film and television industries to a market economy in the 1980s and 1990s generated, as a side effect, a grey area in which individual projects could be produced without prior submission</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deprez</surname>
                           <given-names>Camille</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pernin</surname>
                           <given-names>Judith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The variety of case studies included here should not give the impression that this volume was conceived as a comprehensive overview of the issue of independent documentary in contemporary times. Rather, it aimed at prompting new interest for, and innovative academic perspectives on, the manifold significations of independent documentary production today.¹ Besides demonstrating the complexity, variability, pragmatism and paradoxes that this notion of ‘independent’ documentary entails, this collection of case studies also endeavoured to reveal important similarities among different practitioners in the field. In fact, the book chapters may be reshuffled to highlight other significant connections between them.</p>
                     <p>As Kristian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hnq.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
