<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Happy Endings in Hollywood Cinema</book-title>
         <subtitle>Cliche, Convention and the Final Couple</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MacDowell</surname>
               <given-names>James</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748680177</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0748680179</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748680184</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748680187</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>James MacDowell</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt5hh2m4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Hollywood ‘happy ending’ has long been considered among the most famous and standardised features in the whole of narrative filmmaking. Yet, while ceaselessly invoked, this notorious device has received barely any detailed attention from the field of film studies. This book is thus the first in-depth examination of one of the most overused and under-analysed concepts in discussions of popular cinema. What exactly is the 'happy ending'? Is it simply a cliché, as commonly supposed? Why has it earned such an unenviable reputation? What does it, or can it, mean? Concentrating especially on conclusions featuring an ultimate romantic union – the final couple – this wide-ranging investigation probes traditional associations between the 'happy ending' and homogeneity, closure, ‘unrealism’, and ideological conservatism, testing widespread assumptions against the evidence offered by a range of classical and contemporary films. Key Features: Defines key features of the Hollywood ‘happy ending’ through detailed textual analysis and theoretical debate. Traces the historical development of the scholarly approaches taken towards the cinematic ‘happy ending’ Reassesses the concept of cinematic closure and its relationship to genre, ideology and ‘unrealism’</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The ‘happy ending’: the making of a reputation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Hollywood ‘happy ending’ is among the most over-utilised and under-analysed concepts in discussions of popular cinema.¹ Though it has seldom been addressed in any detail, the term is nonetheless ceaselessly employed by audiences, filmmakers, critics and scholars, and is one that evokes a whole host of assumptions about mainstream American filmmaking.² This book is the first to interrogate some of the most significant and tenacious of those assumptions, and it does so by delving more deeply than is usual into one especially famous feature associated with the ‘happy ending’: concluding a film with the union of a romantic couple.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>The ‘happy ending’ and homogeneity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an ideal world the central argument advanced by this chapter would not require making. Yet, such is the weight of reputation that it seems the necessary place to begin. This chapter is, first and foremost, concerned to question the existence of<italic>the</italic>‘happy ending’, that is: a homogeneous, clichéd ending, which recurs consistently across the majority of Hollywood movies. This is a separate issue from the existence of ‘happy endings’ – a broad category of conclusions that (according to criteria yet to be defined) ‘could be said to end happily’ (Bordwell 1986: 159) rather than ‘unhappily’. Thus, while this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Happy endings and closure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Happy endings are commonly treated as synonymous with closure, and final couples are commonly regarded as synonymous with happy endings. The logical extension of these assumptions also holds, meaning we often come across claims to the effect that Hollywood films tend to be ‘closed by the […] heterosexual couple’ (Russell 1995: 6); likewise, Strinati speaks of closure entailing ‘the coming together of the male and female leads in a romantic happy ending. This is a ‘closed’ narrative’ (Strinati 2000: 217); Hayward, meanwhile, offers the simple dictum that, in Hollywood cinema, ‘closure means a resolution of the heterosexual courtship’ (2006: 83).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Happy endings and unrealism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the term ‘happy ending’ is spoken in Hollywood movies, it is usually being debunked for promulgating idealism in the face of life’s true hardships. One of the most bitterly ironic uses of the phrase, for instance, comes in the WWII romance<italic>Waterloo Bridge</italic>(1940) when Roy (Robert Taylor), unaware that his fiancée has been forced into prostitution via a combination of economic circumstance and erroneous news of his death, tells her upon his reappearance, ‘Darling, don’t cry – it’s a happy ending …’; almost fifty years later, at the somber and amoral conclusion of<italic>Crimes and Misdemeanours</italic>(1989), Judah</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Happy endings and ideology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Girls are taught a lot of stuff growing up,’ says Gigi, the narrator of<italic>He’s Just Not That Into You</italic>: ‘If a guy punches you he likes you. Never trim your own bangs. And some day you will meet a wonderful guy and get your very own happy ending’. A seven-year-old Mary (Cortney Shounia) in<italic>The Wedding Planner</italic>tells her Barbie doll ‘You’ll live happily ever after,’ as she marries her off to a Ken. In<italic>French Kiss</italic>Kate (Meg Ryan) tearfully says of her ex-fiancé: ‘I’m going to get him<italic>back</italic>, and make him<italic>love</italic>me, and we are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                     <subtitle>Provisions for the future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How does one conclude a book about the complexities of endings? Given my recurring interest in how happy endings tend to contain promises of continuation, it seems inescapable that I should end by hinting at what future scholarly work on this convention might look like. First, though, a few words about what we have learned.</p>
                     <p>Clearly, the ‘happy ending’ is not as simple as is commonly assumed. This is unsurprising, however, since most assumptions about how simple the convention is have themselves been notable precisely for their tendency to oversimplify. Indeed, if being uncharitable we could say that the true</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2m4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
