<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccm4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS2705.52.P46 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. Philippians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philippi (Extinct city)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Church history</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philippi (Extinct city)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The People beside Paul</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Philippian Assembly and History from Below</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Marchal</surname>
               <given-names>Joseph A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781628370980</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781628370973</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt189tt2d"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Who are the people beside Paul, and what can we know about them?</p>
         <p>This volume brings together an international and interdisciplinary group of scholars with a broad range of expertise and a common interest: Philippi in antiquity. Each essay engages one set of contextual particularities for Paul and the ordinary people of the Philippian assembly, while simultaneously placing them in wider settings. This 'people's history' uses both traditional and more cutting-edge methods to reconsider archaeology and architecture, economy and ethnicity, prisons and priestesses, slavery, syncretism, stereotypes of Jews, the colony of Philippi, and a range of communities. The contributors are Valerie Abrahamsen, Richard S. Ascough, Robert L. Brawley, Noelle Damico, Richard A. Horsley, Joseph A. Marchal, Mark D. Nanos, Peter Oakes, Gerardo Reyes Chavez, Angela Standhartinger, Eduard Verhoef, and Antoinette Clark Wire.</p>
         <p>Features</p>
         <p>An examination of the social forms and forces that shaped and affected the Philippian churchEssays offer insight into standard questions about the letter s hymn and audience, Paul's 'opponents,' and the sites of the community and of Paul's imprisonmentA focused exploration of more marginalized topics and groups, including women, slaves, Jews, and members of localized cults</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="354"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Philippian (Pre)Occupations and Peopling Possibilities:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marchal</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume addresses several questions. How can we begin to imagine what ancient assembly communities were like “on the ground” or “from the bottom up”? In what ways can scholars conceptualize and describe the everyday Philippians or, more simply, people other than Paul? Are there any ancient or even more recent resources for helping us focus upon different people or even some of the usual suspects differently? Indeed, recent events have an odd way of making these questions urgent in new and more specific ways.</p>
                     <p>The working group that produced this collection of essays had been meeting and working together</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Priestesses and Other Female Cult Leaders at Philippi in the Early Christian Era</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Abrahamsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Valerie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A people’s history of Philippi must, of necessity, include an examination of women. Recent work on Philippi, the region of Macedonia, sociological contexts, and related topics has greatly expanded our knowledge of women in antiquity, their status in the culture, their independence (or lack thereof), their family connections, their contributions, and their limitations. Examination of women at Philippi in the first centuries of the Roman Empire can expand our knowledge of the “people beside Paul.”</p>
                     <p>In the patriarchal and imperial Greco-Roman culture of Philippi, women at all levels of society—slave, free, and freed—suffered certain degrees of oppression and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Economic Situation of the Philippian Christians</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Oakes</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Texts give us access not only to their author’s message but also, with varying degrees of clarity, to historical evidence on a wide range of subjects: evidence of linguistic usage at the time of the text; evidence of cultural reference points and their significance; evidence of social structures, practices, and norms; and evidence of events and people. In the case of Philippians, we learn some significant points about the community of people to whom Paul is writing. Understanding these people is important in itself, as the present volume argues. It also helps our understanding of what the letter means. Seriously</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Collaboration of “Samothrakiasts” and Christians in Philippi</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Verhoef</surname>
                           <given-names>Eduard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the frame of the overarching theme of this study, I will try to describe the position of the young church among the other religions or cults in Philippi and especially its relation to the cult of Euephenes in the fourth and fifth century CE. I will argue that this relation is based on earlier good contacts.¹</p>
                     <p>There were many religions and cults in the Roman Empire at the beginning of the Common Era (see the description of several cults in this volume in the chapter by Valerie Abrahamsen). Christians lived next to adherents of Diana, worshipers of the Egyptian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response:</title>
                     <subtitle>Broadening the Socioeconomic and Religious Context at Philippi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ascough</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The foregoing essays by Valerie Abrahamsen, Peter Oakes, and Eduard Verhoef raise important issues for a project that takes seriously a history from below that does not privilege elite writings and considers carefully the cultural situation at Philippi. All three of the essays focus to some degree on the socioeconomic and religious context of the early Christadherents. Although a full excavation of the site of ancient Philippi is far from complete, the authors use the extant material remains at the site and, by analogy, from elsewhere to construct the social situation of the Philippian Christ-adherents in the first few centuries.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Letter from Prison as Hidden Transcript:</title>
                     <subtitle>What It Tells Us about the People at Philippi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Standhartinger</surname>
                           <given-names>Angela</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, reconstructions of the Christ-community in Philippi have been much improved by research focusing on the letter’s local and sociohistorical context.¹ With the help of archaeological, numismatic, and epigraphic data and studies on the political, cultural, and social impact of Roman imperialism to the provinces of Roman east, we have learned a lot about the local environments of the<italic>Colonia Iulia Augusta Philippensis</italic>. But not at least because archaeological and historical data remain ambiguous and open to different interpretations, it still remains difficult to identify those everyday Philippians to whom Paul wrote and their specific socialcultural contexts in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Slaves as Wo/men and Unmen:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflecting upon Euodia, Syntyche, and Epaphroditus in Philippi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marchal</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paul names several people beside himself in his letter to the Philippians. These include Timothy (Phil 1:1; 2:19–24), Epaphroditus (Phil 2:25–30; 4:10–20), Euodia, Syntyche, and Clement (Phil 4:2–3). Who are these people? They certainly could be some of those “people beside Paul” on which this collection seeks to reflect. But three of these seem especially important rhetorically in the letter. The exhortation to Euodia and Syntyche displays a major concern and even the climax of the letter,¹ as it turns more explicitly to address them to “think the same thing” as Paul.² These verses are a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wire</surname>
                           <given-names>Antoinette Clark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Angela Standhartinger’s and Joseph A. Marchal’s essays can be seen as parallel studies in that they focus on a particular, radically disadvantaged group in the society of the time and place of Paul’s Philippian letter, Standhartinger on the imprisoned and Marchal on the enslaved (although Marchal sets out to consider women as well as slaves, it is the enslaved or freed of both genders that get his attention). The parallel between the two chapters extends to the fact that each group is a victim of social structures and practices. They are<italic>im</italic>prisoned,<italic>en</italic>slaved, and should be described that way. What</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Out-Howling the Cynics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reconceptualizing the Concerns of Paul’s Audience from His Polemics in Philippians 3</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nanos</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Recent efforts to revisit the interpretation of Philippians, including those from a people’s history approach, retain the consensus interpretation for identifying the targets of Paul’s oppositional polemic in these verses.¹ Even those that focus on the political (i.e., Roman imperial) as well as Greco-Roman polytheistic pagan² social context of the letter overall do not question the traditional view that Paul negatively values the continuation of Jewish identity and Judaism (or Christian Judaism) in his communities as well as in his own life. They suppose that the concern of the audience addressed in Philippi is<italic>Judaism</italic>, as if it is an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>An Alternative Community and an Oral Encomium:</title>
                     <subtitle>Traces of the People in Philippi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brawley</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unmistakably the recipients of Philippians told their own stories and took initiatives to make major shifts in identity and behavior related to their narratives. Joining a new group with a foreign orientation was the product of a narrative that began with deficiencies, closely related to their social and economic situation, and belonging to the assembly played a major role in surmounting them. But their initiatives are hidden under the initiatives of another—Paul. They are subjects of his discourse rather than spokespersons of their own. Is it possible for them to speak for themselves?</p>
                     <p>Because the perspectives in Philippians are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Determining What is Best:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Campaign for Fair Food and the Nascent Assembly in Philippi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Damico</surname>
                           <given-names>Noelle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chavez</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerardo Reyes</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paul was a pivotal, but not the only, leader building an expansive social movement of poor, subjugated peoples in the cities of Greece and Asia Minor.¹ This-first century movement confronted the Roman imperial order with the very different power of God in Christ Jesus. What might considerations and challenges around the beginning and growing of such a movement suggest about how the assembly at Philippi was organized and the way leadership was developed and exercised? To explore these questions, we will reflect on our experiences within a twenty-first-century social movement, the Coalition of Immokalee Workers’s Campaign for Fair Food. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Component Community of an Alternative Society</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Horsley</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A decade ago some historians of Christianity persuaded a few of us in New Testament studies to explore a “people’s history” approach to the early Jesus movements and Christ loyalists. We recognized right away that those who formed the earliest communities and movements (that later developed into what came to be known as Christianity) were subordinated and largely impoverished people. Our exploration of “history from below” entailed a departure from standard procedure in New Testament studies as well as in the related fields of classics and ancient history. In such fields, research has usually been conducted by the modern cultural</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189tt2d.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
