<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Speak Thus</book-title>
         <subtitle>Christian Language in Church and World</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hovey</surname>
               <given-names>Craig R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227172711</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903483</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Craig R. Hovey</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16wdm5z"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In its various forms, speech is absolutely integral to the Christian mission. The gospel is a message, news that must be passed on if it is to be known by others. Nevertheless, the reality of God cannot be exhausted by Christian knowledge and Christian knowledge cannot be exhausted by our words. All the while, the philosophy of modernity has left Christianity an impoverished inheritance within which to think these things. In Speak Thus, Craig Hovey explores the possibilities and limits of Christian speaking. At times ethical, epistemological, and metaphysical, these essays go to the heart of what it means to be the church today. In practice, the Christian life often has a linguistic shape that surprisingly implicates and reveals the commitments of people like those who care for the sick or those who respond as peacemakers in the face of violence. Because learning to speak one way as opposed to another is a skill that must be learned, Christian speakers are also guides who bear witness to the importance of churches for passing on a felicity with Christian ways of speaking. Through constructive engagements with interlocutors like Ludwig Wittgenstein, George Lindbeck, Jeffrey Stout, Stanley Hauerwas, John Howard Yoder, Thomas Aquinas, and the theology of Radical Orthodoxy, Hovey offers a challenging vision of the church'able to speak with a confidence that only comes from a deep attentiveness to its own limitations while able to speak prophetically in a world weary of words.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="172"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theme that unites these essays is speech. It is a theme that is woven in different ways (and in admittedly more and less obvious ways) throughout what follows. I have brought together these writings hoping that they will prove useful for students and practitioners of theology and ethics who are looking for a display of the difference Christian ways of speaking make to the ongoing life of the church in our time.</p>
                     <p>Christian speech is more normatively prayer, liturgy, and hymnody than it is theology. It is also more straightforwardly witness. When Christian communities speak the gospel, they are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Narrative Proclamation and Gospel Truthfulness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us begin with an observation that is at home within Radical Orthodoxy: Written texts can be misleading insofar as what they report can be imagined as free-floating facts, events, or ideas; that is, unbounded by the realities of cultural existence, of conditions surrounding both the production and reading of texts. This observation makes plain the ways we may be tempted to draw a straight line from the meaning of a text to the truth of that meaning, assuming that both can be exhaustively captured and assessed on the basis of the written word alone.</p>
                     <p>Radical Orthodoxy pursues these kinds</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>On Hauerwas and Yoder</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stanley Hauerwas has claimed that “Everything John Howard Yoder believes, I think is true.”¹ Indeed, this is also a common assumption regarding the two theologians since Hauerwas is better known and also makes plain his indebtedness to Yoder in nearly every essay and book. However, Craig Carter recently wrote that “The biggest problem in Yoder interpretation arises with regard to Stanley Hauerwas.”² This is because many readers come to Yoder by way of Hauerwas and, as a consequence, impose an interpretive grid whereby the differences between the two are overlooked.</p>
                     <p>Some have tried to address this concern by pointing out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Democracy Beyond Democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A number of contemporary ethical debates appear to have foreclosed on some crucial questions: Is there any possibility for moral discourse, given pluralism? Are the available modes of discourse—such as democracy—true vehicles for conversation or just disguised ways of conceding to one or more groups? Princeton University professor of religion Jeffrey Stout, in refusing to accept the finality of the answers given to these and related questions, has produced a book important by any reckoning.<italic>Democracy and Tradition</italic>will significantly advance the discussion about liberalism and democracy, particularly among those who are weary of these notions. At its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Metaphors We Die By</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Caring for the ill is a great moral task that brings into sharp relief our convictions about life and death. Not only does such care place the caregiver in unavoidable proximity to profound questions, but also the acts of care themselves reveal the nature of deeply held assumptions. Even the language that forms our descriptions of illness indicates some level of how we conceive of illness; our descriptions of illness also indicate how we understand the significance of life when it is in good health. In short, the words used for illness carry strong interpretive and evaluative power.</p>
                     <p>Perhaps no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Story and Eucharist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The thought and practice of sixteenth-century Anabaptism seem peculiar to many moderns precisely because modernity has no conceptual framework capable of correctly understanding the movement. Recent philosophical trends within postmodernity, however, provide fresh models for reassessing Anabaptism in terms more attuned to Anabaptism’s unique character. Some working within the Anglo-American strains of postmodernity have addressed and advanced post-Enlightenment thought in a remarkably successful manner, especially in regard to theology.¹ In this idiom, George Lindbeck is prominent among recent scholars using postmodern philosophy to help us imagine new ways of thinking about theology, particularly regarding the nature of religion, doctrine, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Forester, Bricoleur, and Country Bumpkin</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The introduction of Aristotle into the Christian world posed serious critical challenges, especially at the University of Paris in the 1260s and 1270s, and much of what resulted from this introduction received formal condemnation by Stephen Tempier, the bishop of Paris, in 1277. Many thought that Aquinas had not sufficiently distanced himself from the heterodox interpreters of Aristotle in his appropriation of the philosopher for Christian doctrine. Today Aquinas’s work is again at the center of a crisis, but in many ways an opposite one. Since Pope Leo XIII, in the 1879 encyclical<italic>Aeterni Patris</italic>, rekindled interest in Aquinas as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>This Is My Brother’s World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am aware that my reading of Aquinas in the previous chapter makes him an ally of Karl Barth. If nature’s participation in God bears on our natural moral knowledge, then nature’s participation in God surely also applies to what we more straightforwardly think of as “natural,” namely, the natural world, which is the focus of this chapter. However, in what follows, it will become evident that I am not attempting to draw careful distinctions between concepts like “earth” and “world.” If by “world” we are led to think about the realm of unbelief, of that part of creation—exclusively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>How Free Are We?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How free are we?</p>
                     <p>Of course a lot depends on who is asking the question. A philosopher who asks it may be wondering if anything we do is really free, or if it is all just determined. A politician who asks it may want us to consider who we are as a nation and what it means to be free from oppression.</p>
                     <p>In modern times, there is almost nothing better we can think of than being free. Just think about the freedom of choice. What could be better than the ability to choose freely? Nothing. In fact, choice has become</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Basking and Speaking in Ordinary Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some people never can escape from the academic calendar. For them, it is fall rather than spring that is full of new beginnings. Spring is the time to finish things up. And for them, summer is not just a time of activity in the sun, but also a time of waiting. The academic calendar has a great pause for a few months in the summer, and for those who live by it, it can even come to feel like a bore after a while.</p>
                     <p>Now, for those who pay attention to such things, the Christian calendar actually seems to allow</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16wdm5z.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
