<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f89g3</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Cosmopolitanism and Place</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wahman</surname>
               <given-names>Jessica</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Medina</surname>
               <given-names>José M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Stuhr</surname>
               <given-names>John J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253029393</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253030337</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253030331</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005th6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Addressing perspectives about who "we" are, the importance of place and home, and the many differences that still separate individuals, this volume reimagines cosmopolitanism in light of our differences, including the different places we all inhabit and the many places where we do not feel at home. Beginning with the two-part recognition that the world is a smaller place and that it is indeed many worlds, Cosmopolitanism and Place critically explores what it means to assert that all people are citizens of the world, everywhere in the world, as well as persons bounded by a universal and shared morality.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="384"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We live in an increasingly interconnected world. it is a world of global manufacturing and trade, international travel and almost instant communication, shared climate change and epidemics, and far-flung wars and campaigns of terror. and it is a world of different languages, different narratives, different standards of living. nations and their borders and boundaries mark us differently as citizens or tourists or immigrants or refugees or homeless.</p>
                     <p>What is the place of a cosmopolitan morality or politics or culture in this world? What is required of us, and what is possible for us, if we adopt a cosmopolitan worldview that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wahman</surname>
                           <given-names>Jessica</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The chapters in this first part confront key topics to be addressed by a contemporary cosmopolitanism. All suggest that cosmopolitanism is an orientation worth considering, and some argue explicitly in favor of the position. Many of the authors draw our attention to an increasingly globalized world and suggest this is a prominent reason for taking cosmopolitanism seriously. Our growing access to and consistent impact on one another, they argue, increase our awareness of human connectedness, rendering the possibility of entirely localized commitments both rationally untenable and ethically irresponsible. At the same time, each author claims that a feasible cosmopolitanism, despite</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Déjà Vu All Over Again?:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Challenge of Cosmopolitanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lysaker</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At one time, let’s say 1990, it seemed as if relational ontologies marked a significant advance for those trying to think past the limits of liberal political theory and the more general posture of the modern subject. Appreciating the interconnectedness of all things, and thus the dependency of any given thing, was taken to have more or less clear ethical-political implications, the kind that should lead to a less violent, even a more cooperative, world. The thought was that reified ideologies lead liberal automata to operate in ahistorical silos, producing power and accumulating capital without a feel for the karmic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Home, Hospitality, and the Cosmopolitan Address</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McAfee</surname>
                           <given-names>Noëlle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marshall mcluhan began his curious little book of 1967,<italic>The Medium Is the Massage</italic>, with an epigraph by Alfred North Whitehead: “The major advances in civilization are processes that all but wreck the societies in which they occur.”¹ For McLuhan’s purposes, the meaning is clear. The old world became undone by the literacy that the printing press created. Literate readers of the Bible no longer needed to defer to priests for the word of God, which led to the Protestant Reformation and shortly thereafter to new ideas about government legitimacy, heralding the English, American, and French revolutions. Invented during the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Cultural Heritages and Universal Principles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Failache</surname>
                           <given-names>Juan Carlos Pereda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Socialization processes normally imply that we stimulate and praise—or discourage and scorn—some of our desires. And something comparable happens to our beliefs, emotions, interests, and, of course, to our actions. A tradition or cultural heritage is not just something out there; it entails a complex, and usually implicit, social normativity. However, communities also make explicit, in a fragmentary way, that normativity by means of codes, regulations, exhortations, suggestions, prohibitions, historical narratives, monuments, songs—all in a more or less vague and inconsistent manner. Is this how a public normativity becomes rooted in every person’s life?</p>
                     <p>What Matters and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Not Black or White but Chocolate Brown:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reframing Issues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kegley</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacquelyn Ann K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In concert with the classic American philosophical tradition, I argue that philosophical inquiry is best advanced when one avoids black-white thinking and the trap of false alternatives. Much of the contemporary, as well as historical, discussion of cosmopolitanism has framed the debate in terms of a dichotomy between cosmopolitanism and nationalism. But both concepts are complex and thus clarity is demanded in delineating what notions are being opposed as opposites or in dichotomy. Further, both concepts are often oversimplified. Thus, cosmopolitanism is generally seen as promoting moral obligations to all human beings as contrasted to obligations to one’s groups or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Pragmatism and the Challenge of a Cosmopolitan Aesthetics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Framing the Issues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Innis</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his<italic>Art Without Borders: A Philosophical Exploration of Art and Humanity</italic>, Ben-Ami Scharfstein, writing against the background of his deeply pragmatic<italic>The Dilemma of Context</italic>, contends, “Art is not a single problem, nor does it have a single solution, rational or mystical.”¹ Art’s multiple contexts, and types of contexts, are, he argues, the sources of this radical plurality, which characterizes thought itself. In this, art mirrors life itself. Nevertheless, in spite of the admitted plurality, he issues a call for an “open aesthetics” and an “aesthetic pluralism” and asks, “Is there really an aesthetics that cuts across all human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Medina</surname>
                           <given-names>José</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The chapters in this part of the book cover various themes concerning making and unmaking places, being placed and displaced, orienting and disorienting yourself and/or others, remembering and forgetting places, connecting and disconnecting places, finding a home and being homeless, and so on. In different ways, all the chapters on place in this part of the book stage an original and provocative philosophical dialogue on the notion of place between classic American philosophers such as Emerson, Peirce, James, Addams, and Dewey, and a wide range of contemporary theorists: cultural critics and phenomenologists (Colapietro and Craig), global ethicists and critical theorists</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Toward a Politics of Cohabitation:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Dwelling” in the Manner of Wayfarers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Colapietro</surname>
                           <given-names>Vincent</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is first and foremost a reflection on place, precisely as a verb—that is, not as an antecedently fixed container or enclosure, but as a historically evolved and evolving set of processes and practices. While unavoidably abstract in some respects, it is pointedly political and, to a less extent, polemical. For I am taking this occasion to urge a shift from a politics of occupation (including dwelling) to one of cohabitation, based on a reconstructed self-understanding of ourselves as<italic>wayfarers</italic>in a sense to be defined later. I am also urging a shift in focus from the cosmos</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Cosmopolitan Ignorance and “Not Knowing Your Place”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Medina</surname>
                           <given-names>José</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Vincent Colapietro urges us to do,<italic>place</italic>should be thought of a verb, as referring to activities, and more specifically shared activities or social practices. As Colapietro puts it: “Whatever else places are, they are sites of activity, loci for dramas, above all, those improvised scenes in which the unintended consequences of our most careful deliberations quickly acquire (no matter how slow our acknowledgement) their fateful significance” (Chapter 6, pages 88–89). Whereas in traditional<italic>views place</italic>was conceived as “a fixed container or enclosure,” Colapietro proposes a pragmatic reconceptualization of place as “a historically evolved and evolving set</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>America and Cosmopolitan Responsibility:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Thoughts on an Itinerant Duty</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Edmonds</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the nature of cosmopolitanism and its relationship to place is not just a question of how these logical categories might be properly determined and defined. While it would be perhaps convenient for philosophers to share a definition of cosmopolitanism and come to agreement on its limits and possibilities, philosophical convenience or agreement is hardly the reason the question of cosmopolitanism is worth talking about.</p>
                     <p>The conversations on cosmopolitanism rise out of the practical problems of a world that is increasingly mobile, changing, and intimate. Cosmopolitanism is a lived condition—the name of a problem that perhaps cannot</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Loss of Place</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Craig</surname>
                           <given-names>Megan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Each of us has a place we presently occupy, a place from whence we came, and an ambiguous place toward which we are heading. Even if the present place is makeshift or temporary, if one is a refugee or homeless, being in the world entails occupying, however minimally, some shred of ground. Heidegger underscored this fact of existence by the term<italic>Dasein</italic>: “being-there.” One is always emplaced one way or another in the wider world. Levinas responded to Heidegger by noting that wherever one finds oneself, the “there” of “being-there” entails the usurpation of someone else’s place.¹ Quoting Pascal at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Loss of Confidence in the World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corbí</surname>
                           <given-names>Josep E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I focus on the experience of torture and, more specifically, on Jean Améry’s account of it in his book<italic>At the Mind’s Limits</italic>.¹ There he claims that<italic>the loss of confidence in the world</italic>is the most devastating effect he experienced as a victim of torture. I thus explore what cosmopolitan aspiration may be revealed by this loss and also discuss whether it is to be discredited as an irrational reaction on the victim’s side or instead as proportional to the facts and, consequently, as relevant to the conditions under which a certain cosmopolitan aspiration could be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Climate Change and Place:</title>
                     <subtitle>Delimiting Cosmopolitanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tuana</surname>
                           <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few would contest the claim that climate change raises complex and profound ethical issues including questions of responsibility for climate change related damages, how to act in the face of the deep uncertainties (how much and how fast) regarding the future impacts of climate change, what current generations owe future generations, or how to balance the costs of climate change related mitigation and adaptation with other global problems like poverty and healthcare.</p>
                     <p>The most significant human impact on the climate results from fossil-fuel burning, which increases the atmospheric concentrations of greenhouse gases. This leads to a warming of the lower</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stuhr</surname>
                           <given-names>John J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To consider seriously cosmopolitan ideals (in Part I of this volume) is to engage universalism of one or more sorts—moral, political, economic, religious, and cultural. It is to take up notions of universal and equal intrinsic worth, the dignity of all persons, and border-blind, history-blind, color-blind, money-blind, gender-blind (and so on) rights and responsibilities. And it is to entertain worldviews in which tribal, local, regional, national, and other differences are mere artifacts of time, inessential contingencies, instances of good luck or bad fortune, and facts that cannot serve as bases for reason-based values and actions.</p>
                     <p>On the other hand,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Citizen or Guest?:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmopolitanism as Homelessness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wahman</surname>
                           <given-names>Jessica</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term<italic>cosmopolitan</italic>typically connotes a “citizen of the world.” Such citizenship suggests a kind of belonging to or being at home in the entire world and, furthermore, enjoying all the rights and privileges while accepting the responsibilities that citizenship implies. Furthermore, to many it suggests participation in a universal common ground of humanity transcending all particularities and differences. (It is, perhaps, this purported unifying ground that anchors us “at home” in any part of the world.) I am going to argue, however, that cosmopolitanism requires a different sort of relationship to one’s sociocultural environment. A cosmopolitan should be thought</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Cosmopolitan Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hansen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Presumably, there are many cosmopolitans: the well-traveled, sophisticated, polyglot; the stoic serenely navigating heterogeneous (and fractious) cultural spaces; the migrant following new capital flows; the hospitable host; the religious seeker; or, the peace builder appealing to our shared earth. Cosmopolitans—whatever motive—are mapmakers redrawing the boundaries of the familiar in order to seek what is better.¹ And, it is this broadly shared goal—seeking what is better—that occupies me here because it is often motivated by hope. To seek what is better might be a way to describe what Gabriel Marcel calls “the fundamental situation to which it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Hospitality or Generosity?:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmopolitan Transactions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gayman</surname>
                           <given-names>Cynthia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While “there are many cosmopolitanisms,” as Jennifer Hansen notes in Chapter 13, “Cosmopolitan Hope,” a feature linking them in their various contemporary instantiations is a certain requisite generosity of perception, an openness to the unfamiliar, foreign, or strange.¹ Perceptual generosity puts no additional demand on the function of eyesight, although it is a refusal of blindness; what is required is a capacious moral purview. This is a shift in relational comportment, something like what Noëlle McAfee in Chapter 2, “Home, Hospitality, and the Cosmopolitan Address,” terms “cosmopolitan imaginary,” by which we think about “how and where we and others are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>On Cosmopolitan Publics and Online Communities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tarver</surname>
                           <given-names>Erin C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is no secret that life in the twenty-first century happens, for many of us, in a “place” that defies traditional conceptions of place, community, and communication—namely, in the nebulous and Heraclitean world of the internet. Not only information but socialization and political life exist online; for many people, in fact, those relationships and conversations accessed via electronic mediums constitute the majority of all such interactions. And despite the hand-wringing that this fact might inspire in those nostalgic for pre-internet days, these interactions are<italic>real</italic>: they are lived by flesh-and-blood people who not only inhabit traditionally physical communities but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>A New “International of Decent Feelings”?:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmopolitanism and the Erasure of Class</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lewis</surname>
                           <given-names>William S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fifteen years before he renewed philosophical Marxism with his re-readings of Marx and Lenin, Louis Althusser authored a polemic titled “The International of Decent Feelings.” The student philosopher who wrote this piece had yet to renounce his Christianity and was heavily influenced by Catholic theology as well as by Hegelian interpretations of Marx. Though these interests do not distinguish him from many of his philosophical peers who were also looking to Hegel to make Marxism more philosophically sophisticated or were trying to reconcile Marxism with progressive theology, the scope of his critique of postwar Internationalism is startlingly original.</p>
                     <p>In “The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Somewhere, Dreaming of Cosmopolitanism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stuhr</surname>
                           <given-names>John J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of cosmopolitanism and provincialism is the longstanding philosophical problem of the one and the many in that problem’s only real—that is, political—form. In its traditional meanings and forms, provincialism is no solution to this problem. Just as Winston Churchill once observed that the best argument against democracy is a brief conversation with the average voter, so the best argument against tribalism, parochialism, provincialism, partisanship, patriotism, protectionism, nationalism, jingoism, and all forms of self-congratulatory exceptionalism is a brief account of the record of their accompanying narrowness, ignorance, failures of imagination, fear, smugness, opportunity costs, and their sad</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005th6.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
