<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4v0cc</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN3352.P7A87 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Appreciation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Evolution in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Useful Fictions</book-title>
         <subtitle>Evolution, Anxiety, and the Origins of Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>AUSTIN</surname>
               <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803230262</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803232976</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803232977</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dfnsfj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"We tell ourselves stories in order to live," Joan Didion observed in<italic>The White Album</italic>. Why is this? Michael Austin asks, in<italic>Useful Fictions</italic>. Why, in particular, are human beings, whose very survival depends on obtaining true information, so drawn to fictional narratives? After all, virtually every human culture reveres some form of storytelling. Might there be an evolutionary reason behind our species' need for stories?</p>
         <p>Drawing on evolutionary biology, anthropology, narrative theory, cognitive psychology, game theory, and evolutionary aesthetics, Austin develops the concept of a "useful fiction," a simple narrative that serves an adaptive function unrelated to its factual one. In his work we see how these useful fictions play a key role in neutralizing the overwhelming anxiety that humans can experience as their minds gather and process information. Rudimentary narratives constructed for this purpose, Austin suggests, provided a cognitive scaffold that might have become the basis for our well-documented love of fictional stories. Written in clear, jargon-free prose and employing abundant literary examples-from the Bible to<italic>One Thousand and One Arabian Nights</italic>and<italic>Don Quixote</italic>to<italic>No Exit</italic>-Austin's work offers a new way of understanding the relationship between fiction and evolutionary processes-and, perhaps, the very origins of literature.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Big Question</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Here are some of the questions that this book will try to answer: Why do stories with sad endings make us cry? Why do we like scary movies but not scary situations in real life? How is it that we can think of a fictional character as a “friend” whose triumphs thrill us and whose misfortunes cause us pain? Why will we continue to watch a movie or television show that we don’t really like just to see how it turns out? Why can a single summer blockbuster movie earn more than a billion dollars in worldwide box-office receipts and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Scheherazade’s Stories and Pangloss’s Nose</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin this study—as so many previous studies of storytelling have begun—with perhaps the most impressive collection of stories in human history:<italic>The Book of One Thousand and One Nights</italic>, often called, simply,<italic>The Arabian Nights</italic>. Though this collection contains hundreds of individual stories, all of the stories are placed within the context of a single frame tale: the story of Scheherazade and Shahryar. This famous tale begins three years after the great Sultan Shahryar vowed to avenge his wife’s infidelity by marrying a new woman each night and executing her the following morning. Determined to put a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Stories for Thinking</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Book of Matthew, nine of the seventeen parables told by Jesus begin with the words: “the kingdom of heaven is like. . . .” As it turns out, the kingdom of heaven is like a number of very different things, including people (a sower, a king, a merchant, and two different householders), food (a mustard seed and leaven), and several inanimate objects (a fishing net and a buried treasure). None of these comparisons gives a clear picture of the kingdom of heaven, but how on earth could they? For those of us stuck on earth, heaven is an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Influence of Anxiety</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the twenty-fifth of Sigmund Freud’s<italic>Introductory Lectures on Psychoanalysis</italic>, first delivered in 1917, Freud acknowledges that anxiety is “a riddle.” Though he offers no real definition of the term anxiety, he does flatly reject the value of examining it physiologically. “I know of nothing less important for the psychological comprehension of anxiety,” he writes, “than a knowledge of the nerve paths by which the excitations travel.”¹ In Freud’s updated “New Introductory Lectures on Psychoanalysis,” he still rejects the value of biochemical inquiry, but feels that he is in a much better position to explain the origins of anxiety—at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Information Anxiety</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The turning point of<italic>Robinson Crusoe</italic>occurs precisely halfway into the narrative when Crusoe, after fifteen years of presuming himself the only inhabitant of his island, discovers a single footprint on a sandy beach.¹ Before this incident,<italic>Robinson Crusoe</italic>tells the story of a solitary individual and his relationship with nature, God, and himself. Afterward, it becomes a political novel full of battles, colonial aspirations, social contracts, and an expanding cast of characters—including cannibals, excannibals, mutineers, Spaniards, and English sailors. For the two years after Crusoe discovers the footprint—an interval of time that requires a mere ten pages</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Problem of Other People</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The human brain is adapted—of that much we can be sure. However, nobody is quite sure what it is adapted to. The usual evolutionary explanation—that the brain adapted to the natural environment in which humans developed—doesn’t account for all of the facts that need to be explained. For one thing, humans and other hominids have developed and flourished in nearly every habitable environment on the earth. Even more perplexing, however, is the fact that human cognition seems to be so much more complex than it needs to be. There can be no question that some advanced cognitive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Sex, Lies, and Phenotypes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though lying is not the same as storytelling, the two are not entirely unrelated. Both involve the construction and communication of counterfactual propositions and narratives. The difference between the two is in both the intent of the speaker and the understanding of the audience. Liars know the truth and attempt to conceal it, usually to advantage themselves at the expense of their auditors. On the other hand, both storytellers and story hearers (or story readers) usually understand that a fictional story is something other than literal truth—rather than working against each other, they collaborate in a mutually beneficial form</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Deceiving Ourselves and Others</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first chapter of this study began with literature’s greatest storyteller; the final chapter begins with its greatest madman. The two occupations are not all that different. All that separates Don Quixote and Scheherazade is a thin layer of self-consciousness about the fictional nature of their shared enterprise; Scheherazade understands that the truths she tells her husband are embedded in fictions, while Quixote believes that the fictions he tells himself are derived from the truth. Quixote deceives himself, but this does not mean that his fictions are not useful. In many cases his fantastic stories are more valuable to him</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>WHY “JUST THE FACTS, MA’AM” DOESN’T WORK</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human beings are not fact machines—beings who scan the environment for information and then process it in their extremely large brains to produce pasteurized lumps of truth. Thomas Gradgrind’s vision in Charles Dickens’s<italic>Hard Times</italic>—a board of fact, composed of commissioners of fact, who will force the people to be a people of fact—has never been realized.¹ Through the course of the novel, Gradgrind comes to understand that human beings are not governed by facts and that they cannot be forced into a world of fact without a substantial amount of violence against their very natures. There</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnsfj.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
