<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6t9j1g</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN849.C3M865 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Caribbean literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Performance in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Self-perception in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Caribbean Area</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Performance and Personhood in Caribbean Literature</book-title>
         <subtitle>From Alexis to the Digital Age</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Murray-Román</surname>
               <given-names>Jeannine</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813938493</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">081393849X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Charlottesville; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19jchc5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Focusing on the literary representation of performance practices in anglophone, francophone, and hispanophone Caribbean literature, Jeannine Murray-Román shows how a shared regional aesthetic emerges from the descriptions of music, dance, and oral storytelling events. Because the historical circumstances that led to the development of performance traditions supersede the geopolitical and linguistic divisions of colonialism, the literary uses of these traditions resonate across the linguistic boundaries of the region. The author thus identifies the aesthetic that emerges from the act of writing about live arts and moving bodies as a practice that is grounded in the historically, geographically, and culturally specific features of the Caribbean itself.</p>
         <p>Working with twentieth- and twenty-first-century sources ranging from theatrical works and novels to blogs, Murray-Román examines the ways in which writers such as Jacques Stephen Alexis, Zoé Valdés, Rosario Ferré, Patrick Chamoiseau, and Marlon James experiment with textually compensating for the loss of the corporeality of live relationship in performance traditions. Through their exploration of the interaction of literature and performance, she argues, Caribbean writers themselves offer a mode of bridging the disjunction between cultural and philosophical approaches within Caribbean studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A starting point for engaging the intersection of the performing arts and literature in the Caribbean region is the famous exchange between the storyteller and the writer-figure in Patrick Chamoiseau’s<italic>Solibo Magnifique</italic>: “To write is to take the<italic>lambi</italic>out of the sea to shout: here’s the conch! The word replies: where’s the sea? But that’s not the most important thing, I’m going and you’re staying. I spoke to you, you’re writing, announcing that you come from the word. You give your hand over the distance. It’s all very nice, but you just touch the distance” (28; see French in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Performance and the Expansion of Personhood in Marissa Chibas’s Daughter of a Cuban Revolutionary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The task of this book is to think through how Caribbean textual representations of performance broaden understandings of personhood. To explore how the genre of performance specifically can intercede in definitions of personhood, this chapter offers a performance analysis of Marissa Chibas’s 2007 one-woman play<italic>Daughter of a Cuban Revolutionary</italic>. Throughout the play, Chibas performs much of the “backstage” work—such as establishing the scene’s time and place, or getting in and out of character—and exposes otherwise unseen labor. In so doing,<italic>Daughter</italic>demonstrates how the means of creating theater give us a point of entry into redefining personhood.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Creole’s Thinking Body:</title>
                     <subtitle>Patrick Chamoiseau and Marlon James</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all the performance forms, the oral performance of storytelling is the most deceptively difficult to write: in musical or dance performance events, instruments and bodies must be accounted for, but for storytelling, the temptation is to focus solely on the storyteller’s rhetorical style. What is lost in this strategy of transcription is the circle that sustains the storyteller’s performance. In a footnote to a discussion of writing history in<italic>Le Discours antillais</italic>, Glissant meditates on the role of the writer and speech in the Caribbean context, namely if the writer can open a conversation akin to that which organizes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>From Spectator to Participant:</title>
                     <subtitle>Audience Formation in Guillermo Cabrera Infante’s Tres tristes tigres, Oonya Kempadoo’s Tide Running, and Ernest Pépin’s L’Envers du décor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen in Chamoiseau’s and James’s novels, observing how witnesses of a performance event are impacted by it is an important tool for writers to describe the significance of performance. Two reasons this strategy works particularly well for Caribbean representations of social performance are that first, audience members form the circle with their bodies, presence, and attention; and second, any audience member is a potential participant, to return to Marlene NourbeSe Philip’s encapsulation, “you crossing from looking to dancing and back again to looking” (152). This chapter focuses on the role of audience members in creating the dance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Staceyann Chin and Zoé Valdés:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sexilic Politics in the Blogosphere</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Can a dance circle exist without the copresence of persons to form it? Just as the dark and densely textured spaces examined in chapter 3 stretch the concept of the dance circle to include spaces where performer and audience are not configured in a literal circle, this chapter looks to social media interactions for examples of the circle’s permissive protection. Here, the dance circle stretches to sites where moving bodies are separated by time and space but are connected by digital networks. I analyze the online presence and interactive literary engagements of two Caribbean writers, Zoé Valdés and Staceyann Chin,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“Dansez et Revivez!”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reviving Personhood in Rosario Ferré’s “Maquinolandera” and Jacques Stephen Alexis’s Les Arbres musiciens</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Jacques Stephen Alexis’s<italic>Les Arbres musiciens</italic>(1957), the patriarch of a Haitian peasant community, Papa Bois-d’Orme, voices a question that continues to plague Caribbean nations at the outset of the twenty-first century: “Pourquoi alors nos ancêtres ont-ils combattu? Pourquoi Dessalines a-t-il existé, si les Blancs devaient venir reprendre les terres?” (Alexis 351; So why did our ancestors fight? Why did Dessalines exist, if the whites were going to take back the land?” [my translation]). While Bois-d’Orme mournfully takes as a given the twentieth-century collusions between the nation’s leaders and multinational corporations that seek a pliable work force, Alexis uses</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Performance and Personhood in Caribbean Literature</italic>is about Fanon’s<italic>damnés</italic>and how social performance can function as a site for rehearsing self-possession. The texts examined here underscore the socioeconomic conditions and philosophical grounds that have led to their protagonists’ exclusion from the body politic. They also highlight the interruptions to those conditions in the moments to which I have turned our attention, the ekphrastic descriptions of performance events that break from the plots of the texts in order to inform them. In the breaks, they depict the spaces where the distended time of performance both ruptures and extends the present</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19jchc5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
