<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3q3963</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">F213 .S96 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Southern States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1775–1865</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hospitality</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Southern States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hospitality</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Southern States</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Southern States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral conditions</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Racism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Southern States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Southern States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Public opinion</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Regionalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Public opinion</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Southern Hospitality Myth</book-title>
         <subtitle>Ethics, Politics, Race, and American Memory</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Szczesiul</surname>
               <given-names>Anthony</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">SERIES EDITORS</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Smith</surname>
               <given-names>Jon</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Richardson</surname>
               <given-names>Riché</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780820350738</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0820350737</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Georgia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>ATHENS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Georgia Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1g2km4s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Hospitality as a cultural trait has been associated with the South for well over two centuries, but the origins of this association and the reasons for its perseverance of­ten seem unclear. Anthony Szczesiul looks at how and why we have taken something so particular as the social habit of hospitality-which is exercised among diverse individuals and is widely varied in its particular practices-and so generalized it as to make it a cultural trait of an entire region of the country.</p>
         <p>Historians have offered a variety of explanations of the origins and cultural practices of hospitality in the antebellum South. Economic historians have at times portrayed southern hospitality as evidence of conspicuous consumption and competition among wealthy planters, while cultural historians have treated it peripherally as a symptomatic expression of the southern code of honor. Although historians have offered different theories, they generally agree that the mythic dimensions of southern hospitality eventually outstripped its actual practices. Szczesiul examines why we have chosen to remember and valorize this particular aspect of the South, and he raises fundamental ethical questions that underlie both the concept of hospitality and the cultural work of American memory, particularly in light of the region's historical legacy of slavery and segregation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>What Can One Mean by Southern Hospitality?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How important is “southern hospitality” to “your definition of today’s South?” So asked question 82 of the spring 1995 edition of the Southern Focus Poll conducted by John Shelton Reed and the Howard W. Odum Institute for Research in Social Science at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill. Reed and the Odum Institute ran the Southern Focus Poll from 1992 to 2001, interviewing by phone thousands of southerners and nonsoutherners, seeking their responses on a wide range of political, economic, social, and cultural issues, as well as their sense of regional identity and cultural characteristics. Question 82 was one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>A Virginian Praises “Yankee Hospitality”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rethinking the Historicity of Antebellum Southern Hospitality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early years of the sectional crisis between the northern and southern states, a southerner could still praise the hospitality of northerners and even suggest that “Yankee hospitality,” though admittedly diff erent, was possibly more sincere and meaningful than the hospitality of the South. Lucian Minor’s “Letters from New England” were published in the first volume of the<italic>Southern Literary Messenger</italic>, appearing in five installments between November 1834 and April 1835. His second letter opens with the following extended comparison between “Yankee hospitality” and “good old Virginia hospitality”:</p>
                     <p>Of<italic>Yankee hospitality</italic>(curl not your lip sardonically—you, or any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Amphytrion and St. Paul; the Planter and the Reformer:</title>
                     <subtitle>Discourses of Hospitality in Antebellum America</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While the Virginian Lucian Minor could praise “Yankee hospitality” during the early years of the sectional crisis in the 1830s, by the 1850s sectional tensions had caused regional prejudices, stereotypes, and suspicions to harden to such an extent that such praise would have seemed impossible. The language of “southern hospitality” emerged in the 1830s amid the growing sectional crisis that began to consume American culture, and it would only proliferate as the crisis intensified in the decades leading up to the Civil War. As Americans became preoccupied by the political and moral questions of slavery, they also defined, discussed, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Making Hospitality a Crime:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fugitive Slave Law of 1850</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early 1850s, Americans North and South entered into a bitter, protracted debate over the relationship between hospitality and slavery. This debate—carried out in the halls of Congress, in newspapers and magazines, in sermons and denominational papers, in poems and novels, and in the domestic space of American households—was sparked by the passage of the Fugitive Slave Law of 1850, the most controversial provision of the set of legislative acts known collectively as the Compromise of 1850. The compromise, ushered through Congress largely through the efforts of Senators Henry Clay of Kentucky, Stephen Douglass of Illinois, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Southern Hospitality in a Transnational Context:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Geopolitical Logic of the South’s Sovereign Hospitality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Writing against the backdrop of the civil rights movement in the 1960s, the historian and activist Howard Zinn offered the following assessment of what he described as the South’s pervasive xenophobia, linking it to southern hospitality: “It is one of the curious paradoxes of Southern life that suspicion of strangers, of outsiders, goes along with what is called ‘Southern hospitality.’ The answer to the paradox is that there is a line of demarcation which separates the accepted person from the unaccepted. Within that line, the warmth is almost overwhelming. But outside it, the coolness can become hostility to the point</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Reconstructing Southern Hospitality in the Postbellum World:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reconciliation, Commemoration, and Commodification</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a sermon delivered at St. Mary’s Church of Keyport, New Jersey, on January 27, 1867, the Reverend Telfair Hodgson, a Confederate veteran, made an emotional appeal to the northern congregation about charitable aid for his fellow southerners. Hodgson’s “A Sermon in Behalf of Southern Sufferers” paints a dire picture of the South in the two years since the war had ended, with floods, droughts, and impending famines adding to the grim reality of an already devastated economy and a defunct social system. With this picture in mind, Hodgson reminds his audience of the Christian imperative of hospitality by citing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>The Modern Proliferation of the Southern Hospitality Myth:</title>
                     <subtitle>Repetition, Revision, and Reappropriation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unfortunately for his tourist guests from the North, when Mayor Earl Buckman promises them the best of southern hospitality, what he actually has in mind includes torture, mutilation, dismemberment, burning, cannibalism, and ritualistic mob violence. The shock film<italic>Two Thousand Maniacs!</italic>was screened in drive-in theaters around the country, North and South, in the summer of 1964, and it was ardently promoted and particularly popular in southern markets. I begin this concluding chapter with<italic>Two Thousand Maniacs!</italic>for a number of reasons. First, like perhaps no other text, the film shows the incredible, even absurd, ranginess of the myth of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE:</title>
                     <subtitle>New Strangers of the Contemporary South</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Today, the discourse of southern hospitality is so burdened with a long history of jaded, empty, and meaningless repetitions that it perhaps seems impossible to reconstruct it as a meaningful regional ideal. Take, for example, the “Southern Hospitality Experience” program developed in 2006 by<italic>Southern Hospitality</italic>magazine, a Florida-based trade magazine for hoteliers and restaurateurs in the southeastern United States. Here we see the crass commercialization of southern hospitality at perhaps its worst. The Fall 2006 issue of the magazine announced this “certification program” as “an unparalleled opportunity to brand your property as a provider of the authentic Southern Hospitality</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2km4s.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
