<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt45kbrb</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Performing Arts</subject>
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Film Museum Practice and Film Historiography</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Case of the Nederlands Filmmuseum (1946-2000)</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LAMERIS</surname>
               <given-names>BREGT</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789089648266</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789048526741</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Amsterdam University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>B.G. Lameris</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Amsterdam University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1v2xssp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Rich in detail, this is a study of the interrelationships between film historical discourse and archival practices. Exploring the history of several important collections from the EYE Film Museum in Amsterdam, Bregt Lameris shows how archival films and collections always carry the historical traces of selection policies, restoration philosophies, and exhibition strategies. The result is a compelling argument that film archives can never be viewed simply as innocent or neutral sources of film history.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the archive of the Nederlands Filmmuseum there is a photograph that shows a number of people gathered together on a podium: the wall behind them is dominated by a large film screen, and a woman with long curly hair is speaking into a microphone (Image 3, page 60). All those present look slightly overwhelmed, shy but proud – perhaps of the speaker, perhaps of themselves. It was taken in 1991, at the Teatro Verdi in Pordenone, during Le Giornate del Cinema Muto (Days of Silent Cinema), and the people on stage were employees of the Nederlands Filmmuseum (now EYE Filmmuseum).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paul Ricoeur explains in<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>that the interpretation of history does not begin with the historian but with the archivist. The decisions made by archivists on what should and should not be included in a collection are the first step in the process of interpreting historical facts; all the succeeding choices the historian makes depend on the composition and structure of the archive. As a consequence, the archive is not only the ‘starting point’ of historical research, it is also part of the historiographical discourse.¹ Furthermore, the act of collecting documents and objects always implies a change in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Private Collectors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The acquisition of silent films has been beset by a particular problem: by the time the first film archives were established in the 1930s, a large part of the entire corpus of silent films had already perished or been destroyed (Meyer and Read, 2000: 2). This was also the period when the ‘talkies’ replaced silent cinema, which meant it was no longer possible to acquire silent films from distributors after they were withdrawn from circulation. As a consequence, the NHFA – as EYE was called at the time – was dependent on the resources of private individuals who had built up collections</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Blind Choices:</title>
                     <subtitle>Parameters and Repetitions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As with private collectors, film museums and institutes held specific views on which film material they preferred to collect. These preferences had the following three broad parameters: first, film museums showed a preference for the well-known canonical titles from the silent period (Bordwell, 1997: 24); second, they tended to favour films that were old or rare, even if they were less well-known – although when it comes to the collection of unidentified film material, this begs the question as to why film institutes were interested in these unknown titles if they could not screen them in their theatres; third, all the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Eyes Wide Open:</title>
                     <subtitle>Duplicates</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The change in archival priorities more or less paralleled developments in film historiography, causing film museums to re-evaluate what they considered to be, in Bourdieu’s words, re-evaluating their ‘specific capital’. This consisted of old film titles that were at risk of perishing or already listed as ‘lost films’. The focus on endangered and lost films was clearly in tune with the new ideas that had started to dominate film historiography: the aim appeared to be to acquire as many unknown films as possible and rehabilitate them by including them in the museums’ programming and in the new film historiography. These</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Museums and archives share an inherent objective: to keep memories alive for the future by preserving objects from the past (Pearce, 1995: 249). To realise this goal, they endeavour to prevent the decay – or further decay – of their artefacts by, first, treating these objects with extreme caution and trying, as much as possible, to limit the destructive impact of environmental factors (Pomian, 1988: 14); and, second, cleaning and restoring them, repairing the damage that inevitably accrues over time. Both of these activities can be categorised as part of the ‘preservation process’.</p>
                     <p>Film museums handle the films in their collections with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Passive Preservation:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Historical Overview</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three different views on nitrate material are apparent during the period under investigation: the nitrate copy was seen as a functional item, as a perishable, fragile object, or as a unique print. These varying attitudes not only directly determined how film museums and institutions coped with the active and passive preservation of the nitrate films in their archives, but were also closely related to the positions film historians adopted towards this material and the value they attached to ‘original prints’. Hence, the most interesting question is how ideas about the value of this material as a historical source were synchronised</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Impressions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Restoration of the Film Image</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1995, during the Filmmuseum workshop, ‘Disorderly Order’, mentioned above, Meyer (cited in Hertogs and Klerk de, 1996: 18) asked the participating film historians the following question: ‘[S]hould we preserve these films just as we find them, or should we try to get as close to the original as possible?’ Film museums and restorers are confronted with this choice with each restoration: either to restore the imaginary ‘original version’ of the film or to make the best possible duplicate based on what the starting material looks like at the time of restoration. What is fascinating is the way these two</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Reconstructions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘ The current discourse of film restorers is a model for history making because it makes transparent the ways that a history is spliced together’ (Jones, 2012: 138). This comment clearly summarises the focus of this chapter: the reconstruction of films and the consolidation of a film museum editing structure, literally ‘ splicing’ the fragments of film history together. As with the activities of acquisition and collection, reconstruction is a matter of selection: the curator chooses which film clips will end up in the final restoration print. As a result, the reconstruction is generally aimed at ‘ completing’ a film,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A film is not just a physical object, an amalgam of celluloid and chemicals, it also consists of fleeting images projected onto a screen. Hence, it is both a fragile material object and an elusive, temporary, performative one. This means that all the elements related to its display, such as its projection and the interior design of the screening room, form a crucial part of the film’s presentation. The screening situation fundamentally affects the meaning an audience creates out of the images that appear before it. As Paolo Cherchi Usai says: The nature of the light source, the apparatus, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Film Museum Exhibition Spaces</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As with film theatres and cinemas, film museums are ‘other spaces’, with very different rules, customs and time dimensions to those we are accustomed to in daily life (Foucault, 1984: 48). These other spaces, which Foucault also calls ‘heterotopias’, are separated from the world we normally live in and can only be entered after performing a number of rituals. To step over the threshold of one of these institutions is literally to make the transition from our everyday world into that other space (Poppe, 1989: 21). From the moment that the visitors enter a theatre, for example, their expectations are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Framing Programmes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Programming allows works to contaminate one another’ 34 – this quotation by Dominique Paini (1992: 25), former director of the Cinémathèque française, sums up the following chapter in a nutshell: namely, the way films ‘contaminate’ one another when shown together in the same programme. A similar phenomenon occurs in museum displays and exhibitions. In the field of museology, Barbara Kirshenblatt-Gimblett (1998) has coined the phrase ‘incontext presentation’ to describe how contagion works in these settings. An in-context presentation is created by means of a number of different strategies. The first entails positioning objects adjacent to one another, connecting them spatially; this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Performances</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Each film museum is embedded in a history of performances. Sometimes they attempt to deny this history, showing their films in screening rooms stripped of any historical reference. In other cases, however, they choose to show films in a ‘historically accurate’ way, which often results in hybrid forms of display, a mixture of historical reconstruction and modern experimentation. What seems central to the choice of display at the Filmmuseum is the way it defined its films – as individual works of art, to be displayed and viewed in isolation, or as examples of the way films were presented in the past</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda:</title>
                     <subtitle>Past Futures, Future Pasts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The 2012 celebration of Unesco’s annual World Day for Audiovisual Heritage, held by EYE Filmmuseum in its newly opened venue on the banks of the IJ in Amsterdam, was a remarkable event. The celebration consisted of a programme of newly restored films, dating from exactly 100 years earlier. Before the screening started, however, a dazzling display of pink, green, and blue light was projected onto the walls of the institute, suffusing them with colour. Then, a strange pattern began to appear, which slowly resolved itself into a full-colour projection of an art-deco interior, complete with lacquered wood panelling. This was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xssp.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
