<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442661486</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1851.R43 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Drama</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Drama</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Performing Arts</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading Modern Drama</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ackerman</surname>
               <given-names>Alan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781442612815</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442661486</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442661486"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Taken together, these essays enter into an ongoing, fruitful debate about the terms 'modern' and 'drama' and build a much-needed bridge between literary studies and performance studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ACKERMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ALAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why publish a collection of essays entitled<italic>Reading Modern Drama</italic>? Individually, each of these words is apt to raise eyebrows. Yet “reading,” “modern,” and “drama” continue to play vital roles in organizing university curricula and defining activities of the broader culture. In the following pages, each of these words elicits new questions and definitions. This volume, moreover, is assembled from articles published in one journal,<italic>Modern Drama</italic>, and the title is also meant to suggest the value of reading this particular journal cohesively, in addition to the benefits of dipping into individual articles online (for pragmatic reasons, the articles were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Gossip Girls:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lady Teazle, Nora Helmer, and Invisible-Hand Drama</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROACH</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSEPH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gossip is to modern drama what myth was to ancient tragedy. Gossip, like myth, offers playwrights a selection of favourite story types, well stocked with embarrassing details. Gossip, like myth, brings secrets into the public light, charming audiences with the socially cohesive pleasures of other people’s pain. Gossip, like myth, unites communities against deviance in the cause of normality or, with equal efficiency, against normality on behalf of popular subversion. Ancient myth, however, handing down the world-historical heritage of atrocious deeds, concerned itself primarily with relations of kinship; modern gossip, by contrast, retailing damaging new information pertaining to just about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“Vinløv i håret”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Relationship between Women, Language, and Power in Ibsen’s Hedda Gabler</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THRESHER</surname>
                           <given-names>TANYA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The difficulty Ibsen’s women experience accessing the dominant male discourse finds its most acute example in<italic>Hedda Gabler</italic>(1890), the play in which Ibsen’s dramatic dialogue is at its most condensed and circumlocution is the dominant narrative technique.¹ The paucity of Hedda’s words has been a matter of critical concern since the very inception of the play. In an 1891 review of<italic>Hedda Gabler</italic>, Edmund Gosse stated that</p>
                     <p>I will dare to say that I think in this instance Ibsen has gone perilously far in his desire for rapid and concise expression. The<italic>stichomythia</italic>of the Greek and French tragedians</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“¡Silencio, he dicho!” Space, Language, and Characterization as Agents of Social Protest in Lorca’s Rural Tragedies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BLUM</surname>
                           <given-names>BILHA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The art of our time,” said Susan Sontag, “is noisy with appeals for silence” (12). Although originally meant as an assessment of the cultural function of modern art, Sontag’s juxtaposition of such antithetical terms as “noise” and “silence” places the work of art at a stylistic and thematic crossroads where the explicit and the implicit, the visible and the invisible, text and subtext or, indeed, what is said, shown, or done (and therefore “noisy”) and what is not, can meet and interact. Each one of these levels constitutes an integral part of the work of art and, as such, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Money Shot:</title>
                     <subtitle>Economies of Sex, Guns, and Language in Topdog/Underdog</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TUCKER-ABRAMSON</surname>
                           <given-names>MYKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In “An Equation for Black People Onstage,” playwright Suzan-Lori Parks lays out the difficulty of writing plays about black people without falling into an essentializing “Black Aesthetic.” Theatre, she argues, is useful for black people because it “can ‘tell it like it is’; ‘tell it as it was’; ‘tell it as it could be’” (21); and, indeed, Parks’s plays are continually exploring the limits and intersections of all three. “[T]he writing is rich,” she continues, “because we are not an impoverished people, but a wealthy people fallen on hard times” (21). When we consider this metaphor in light of Parks’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Space Stage and the Circus:</title>
                     <subtitle>E.E. Cummings’s Him and Frederick Kiesler’s Raumbühne</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CARRUTH</surname>
                           <given-names>ALLISON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1926, two experimental theatre companies in Greenwich Village sponsored an international exposition to showcase avant-garde work in dramaturgy, stagecraft, and acting. In the exposition’s keynote address, Bauhaus-trained architect Frederick Kiesler, whose circus-inspired “space stage” had debuted two years previously in Vienna, called on New York theatre practitioners to develop an “agitator’s theatre” that would be radical in form and ideology and that would be rooted not in the conventions of the proscenium-arch stage but in the practices of popular subcultures. This essay argues that Kiesler’s polemic profoundly influenced modernist poet E.E. Cummings,³ who attended the exposition as a theatre</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>How to Do Nothing with Words, or Waiting for Godot as Performativity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BEGAM</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past generation, performance studies has largely transformed how we think about the contemporary stage, expanding our idea of serious theatre to include such “lowbrow” forms as mixed media, vaudeville, and monologue.¹ The “happenings” of the 1960s and 1970s serve as the immediate precursor to much contemporary art, as more distantly do the Dadaist and surrealist exhibitions of the 1910s and 1920s. These avant-garde beginnings are notable because, like the performance artists of today, the Dadaists and surrealists challenged the idea that life and art are distinct and autonomous spheres, unambiguously separated by a stage proscenium.² Yet, as we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Reinventing Beckett</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GONTARSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>S.E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Samuel Beckett’s creative life (and personal life, for that matter) was marked by a series of transformations and reinventions. In the process of remaking himself, over and again, from donnish academic to avant-garde poet, from Joycean acolyte to post-Joycean minimalist, from humanist to post-humanist, perhaps, most certainly from poet to novelist to playwright to theatre director, Beckett was simultaneously reinventing every literary genre he turned his attention to. In the midst of remaking narrative in the wake of World War II, for example, he began simultaneously the reinvention of theatre, writing the ground-breaking (but still unproduced)<italic>Eleutheria</italic>between<italic>Molloy</italic>and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Uncloseting Drama:</title>
                     <subtitle>Gertrude Stein and the Wooster Group</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SALVATO</surname>
                           <given-names>NICK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the late winter and early spring of 2005, the New York theatre troupe the Wooster Group staged, both in Brooklyn and Manhattan, a limited return engagement of their 1999 piece<italic>House/Lights</italic>, an “adaptation” of Gertrude Stein’s 1938 play<italic>Doctor Faustus Lights the Lights</italic>. The word “adaptation” belongs firmly in scare quotes, not only because it is a methodological description that the members of the Wooster Group would themselves resist, but also because it simultaneously over- and underrepresents the terms of the group’s engagement with Stein’s text. If an adaptation is a modified version of a work that nevertheless retains</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Synge’s Playboy and the Eugenics of Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CRAWFORD</surname>
                           <given-names>NICHOLAS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Playboy of the Western World</italic>(1907)¹ has received much critical attention for its unlikely blending of genres, its ethnographic elements, and its striking language. The play’s dramatic mode is a puzzling hybrid, drawing as it does upon traditions of tragedy, comedy, and romance. Although the plot is marginally predicated on an anecdote familiar to Synge about “a man from Connaught who killed his father with the blow of a spade” and then sought refuge on the Western islands (<italic>Aran, Collected</italic>2: 95), the drama’s development distinguishes itself more by its departures from this local account than by its faithfulness</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Pillowman and the Ethics of Allegory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WORTHEN</surname>
                           <given-names>HANA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WORTHEN</surname>
                           <given-names>W.B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Martin McDonagh’s 2003 play<italic>The Pillowman</italic>allegorizes a key question about the meaning and purpose of art: what are its consequences in the world beyond the stage? Set in an interrogation room in an unnamed, apparently eastern-European totalitarian state, the play centres on the writer Katurian Katurian, whose violent short stories seem to have inspired a local wave of copy-cat crimes. As children, Katurian and his brother Michal had been the subject of a bizarre educational/artistic experiment. Their parents systematically tortured Michal to inspire their younger son’s storytelling skills. Katurian has become a writer and discovers that Michal has committed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Cognitive Catharsis in The Caucasian Chalk Circle</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOBERT</surname>
                           <given-names>R. DARREN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Bertolt Brecht’s 1930<italic>Lehrstück</italic>[learning play]<italic>The Measures Taken</italic>, the Four Agitators relate to the Control Chorus (and their offstage audience) the events leading up to their killing of the Young Comrade, whose violation of the teachings of Communism has endangered their cause and justified his sacrifice. During their propaganda efforts, they explain,</p>
                     <p>[W]e went down into the lower section of the city. Coolies were dragging a barge with a rope. But the ground on the bank was slippery. So when one of them slipped, and the overseer hit him, we said to the Young Comrade: “Go after them,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Jane Harrison and the Savage Dionysus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Archaeological Voyages, Ritual Origins, Anthropology, and the Modern Theatre</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PETERS</surname>
                           <given-names>JULIE STONE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In March of 1888, Jane Ellen Harrison and a large party headed toward the Greek islands and the coast of Turkey, chartering a black ship to “see all the places Pausanias pretended he had visited” (qtd. in Stewart 11). The trip’s official purpose was research for<italic>Mythology and Monuments of Ancient Athens</italic>, the edition of Pausanias-turned-travel-guide that (dubbed the “Blue Jane”) was to become the intelligentsia’s<italic>Blue Guide</italic>to Athens.² But Harrison was also drawn by what she later described as “the irresistible tide of adventure” (<italic>Reminiscences</italic>83), which began to bring her regularly to Italy, Greece, and Turkey in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442661486.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
