<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BL241.R35 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion and science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Religion and Science Debate</book-title>
         <subtitle>Why Does It Continue?</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Attridge</surname>
               <given-names>Harold W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>With an Introduction by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Thomson</surname>
               <given-names>Keith</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="other">Essays by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Numbers</surname>
               <given-names>Ronald L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Miller</surname>
               <given-names>Kenneth R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib5">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Plantinga</surname>
               <given-names>Alvin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib6">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Krauss</surname>
               <given-names>Lawrence M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib7">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wuthnow</surname>
               <given-names>Robert</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300152982</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0300152981</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300165005</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0300165005</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vm5wc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Eighty-one years after America witnessed the Scopes trial over the teaching of evolution in public schools, the debate between science and religion continues. In this book scholars from a variety of disciplines-sociology, history, science, and theology-provide new insights into the contemporary dialogue as well as some perspective suggestions for delineating the responsibilities of both the scientific and religious spheres.</p>
         <p>Why does the tension between science and religion continue? How have those tensions changed during the past one hundred years? How have those tensions impacted the public debate about so-called "intelligent design" as a scientific alternative to evolution? With wit and wisdom the authors address the conflict from its philosophical roots to its manifestations within American culture. In doing so, they take an important step toward creating a society that reconciles scientific inquiry with the human spirit. This book, which marks the one hundredth anniversary of The Terry Lecture Series, offers a unique perspective for anyone interested in the debate between science and religion in America.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ATTRIDGE</surname>
                           <given-names>HAROLD W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction.</title>
                     <subtitle>The Religion and Science Debate: Why Does It Continue?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THOMSON</surname>
                           <given-names>KEITH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Science and religion, science versus religion: the subject was argued by the ancient Greeks and scholars of the Middle Ages and the Enlightenment. In choosing this subject for its centennial occasion, the Committee for the Terry Lectures has highlighted an issue that is both ancient and modern, exquisitely complex and painfully simple. The one certainty that we share with our intellectual forebears in this matter is the need for well-considered dialogue. For both Cicero and David Hume (<italic>Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion</italic>) a dialogue was not just a literary device but the best way to discuss “any question of philosophy …</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aggressors, Victims, and Peacemakers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Historical Actors in the Drama of Science and Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NUMBERS</surname>
                           <given-names>RONALD L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Talk of the relations between “science” and “religion” first became audible in the early 1800s, about the time that students of nature began referring to their work as science rather than natural philosophy (or natural history). Because natural philosophy allowed its practitioners, in the words of Isaac Newton, to discourse about God “from the appearances of things,” one searches almost in vain for references to “natural philosophy and religion.” Some writers expressed concern about tension between faith and reason, but they never pitted religion against science.¹</p>
                     <p>The nineteenth century had barely begun, however, when the American Samuel Miller offered one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Darwin, God, and Dover:</title>
                     <subtitle>What the Collapse of “Intelligent Design” Means for Science and Faith in America</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MILLER</surname>
                           <given-names>KENNETH R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To many within academia, the notion of a “religion and science debate” seems to be the stuff of history.¹ It conjures up visions of papal courts and forbidden books, of nineteenth-century confrontations between reason and superstition in the halls of royal societies, of a world in which the value of science had yet to prove itself, even in the minds of the most learned members of society. It comes as somewhat of a shock, therefore, to realize that this debate is as contemporary as the last election, as far-reaching as the global village itself, and as important to the future</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Science and Religion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Why Does the Debate Continue?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PLANTINGA</surname>
                           <given-names>ALVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First,<italic>is</italic>there a debate? Well yes, I suppose there is. Many Christians have the vague impression that science is somehow unfriendly to religious belief; for other Christians it is less a vague impression than a settled conviction. Similarly, many scientists and science enthusiasts argue that there is opposition between serious religious belief and science; indeed, some claim that religious belief constitutes a clear and present danger to science.¹ Still others see religious belief as steadily dwindling in the face of scientific advance. Our question is: Why does this debate continue?</p>
                     <p>I shall try to answer that question; more modestly,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religion vs. Science?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KRAUSS</surname>
                           <given-names>LAWRENCE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the 100th anniversary of the inception of the Terry Lectures in mind, I would like to focus on the long-standing tension between science and religion, epitomized in different contexts by the quotations above from two distinguished physicists, the agnostic Albert Einstein and the atheist Steven Weinberg, and on how this tension currently manifests itself in the public debate regarding so-called intelligent design as a scientific alternative to evolution.</p>
                     <p>Religion and science are in collision today, as they have been many times throughout human history, or at least as long as science has been pursued separately from religion. Two recent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>No Contradictions Here:</title>
                     <subtitle>Science, Religion, and the Culture of All Reasonable Possibilities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WUTHNOW</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In seeking perspective on recent controversies about religion and science, one can hardly do better than the wisdom provided by that bible of guidance and revelation for academics, the<italic>New York Times</italic>. In its coverage of litigation about the teaching of intelligent design, of school board decisions about evolution, and of policy debates about stem cell research and genetic engineering, the nation’s favorite arbiter of elite opinion has documented beyond doubt that questions about the respective roles of science and religion remain of great public interest. It is this public interest—or, more precisely, the cultural role—of these controversies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vm5wc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
