<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8wwmwx</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Psychology</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Grand Hotel Abyss</book-title>
         <subtitle>Desire, Recognition and the Restoration of the Subject</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Safatle</surname>
               <given-names>Vladimir</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789462700628</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789461661937</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Leuven University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Leuven (Belgium)</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Leuven University Press / Universitaire Pers Leuven / Presses Universitaires de Louvain</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1b9x1k5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Long-expected translation of the Portuguese academic bestseller Grande Hotel Abismo. In the last two decades recognition - arguably one of the most central notions of the dialectical tradition since Hegel - has once again become a crucial philosophical theme. Nevertheless, the new theories of recognition fail to provide room for reflection on transformation processes in politics and morality. This book aims to recover the disruptive nature of the dialectical tradition by means of a severe critique of the dominance of an anthropology of the individual identity in contemporary theories of recognition. This critique implies a thorough rethinking of basic concepts such as desire, negativity, will and drive, with Hegel, Lacan and Adorno being our main guides. The Marxist philosopher György Lukács said that the Frankfurt School (Horkheimer, Adorno, etc.) left us with nothing but negativity towards the state of the world. Their work failed to open up a concrete possibility of practical engagement in this world. All too eager to describe the impasses of reason, the Frankfurt philosphers remained trapped in a metaphorical Grand Hotel Abyss (Grand Hotel Abgrund). It was as living and being guardian of lettered civilization in a beautiful and melancholy grand hotel, of which the balconies face a gaping abyss. But perhaps in this way Lukács gave – and no doubt without realizing it himself – a perfect definition of contemporary philosophy, namely to confront chaos, to peer into what appears to a certain rationality as an abyss and to feel good about it. Touching Hegelian dialectics, critical theory and psychoanalysis, Grand Hotel Abyss gives a new meaning to the notion of negativity as the first essential step for rethinking political and moral engagement.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="322"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction.</title>
                     <subtitle>An indistinct picture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a certain sense, it is the intention of the present book to provide a long-form answer to the above questions, posed by Wittgenstein, by showing how, when it comes to human beings, an openly indistinct image is preferable to a falsely sharp one. Accurately recognizing the moments where indistinct pictures become necessary, however, might be the greatest challenge yet posed for philosophical reflection. For indistinct pictures are elusive: in them, the contours of a familiar image may be discerned, yet must not be completely determined. Such an image is pervaded by something that incessantly corrodes it from within, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter I</label>
                     <title>Love is colder than death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These remarks – taken from Hegel’s<italic>Phenomenology of Spirit</italic>– stand as an adequate synthesis of all that has been imputed to the German philosopher by multiple hegemonic strands in twentieth-century philosophical thought: the philosopher of Absolute Knowledge in its totality, who is nevertheless unable to account for the irreducibility of difference, or of individual aspirations for recognition, through his strategies of conceptual synthesis. In him one finds the most highly refined expression of the philosophical belief that thinking is not possible save through the articulation of strongly hierarchical systems, as well as a subsequent disregard for the ontological dignity of contingency</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter II</label>
                     <title>On how law becomes freedom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If we take seriously the definition of desire outlined in the previous chapter, important questions remain concerning its ultimate social application. Still, it is a useful starting point for unpacking the concepts of individuality and intersubjectivity underlying the reflection on the modern subject conducted by one of its most definitive theoreticians – namely, Hegel; Hegel’s efforts in this direction turn on a critique, buttressed by the concept of negativity, of that which some have termed the “analytics of finitude.” In this sense, a return to Hegel allows us to ask what was truly at stake in his complex, polyphonic movement towards</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter III</label>
                     <title>Not all things are destined for transience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us dwell for a moment on the suggestive closing lines of the preceding chapter: the transformation of individualities into political subjects implies their having the ability to convert subjective gestures into manifestations of a trans-individual multiplicity of desires. Were that to be the case, political subjects could conceivable attain a historical density of such great proportions within social struggles that they would in effect become modes for the actualization of a past never entirely gone, and, subsequently, points of contact for experiences scattered throughout time. This is unequivocally grasped by Walter Benjamin, as evidenced in the following statement: History</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter IV</label>
                     <title>The coupling of sex and death is not exclusive to decadent romantics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After our initial look at how certain aspects of Hegel’s account of desire might transform the concept of individuality, we turned to possible repercussions for his theories of juridical ordering and the state. Then, a third textual movement attempted an articulation of subjectivity, history and infinity, the foremost aim of which was to show that the Hegelian subject exceeds all egological reductions, analytics of finitude or anthropological limitations. That is to say, Hegel leaves us with a subject sufficiently inclusive to allow for both reflections on models of institutional association, as well as modes of determination or the process of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter V</label>
                     <title>An impulse toward lawlessness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus far, our main concern has been to adequately develop notions of subject and of individuality on the basis of articulations between psychoanalysis and Hegelian philosophy. These articulations have been silently guided by a strategy which consisted in adopting as our own critical perspectives aimed at the work of both authors; this procedure in turn allowed us to ultimately conclude that the commentators in question, while to some extent right, had been right for the wrong reasons.</p>
                     <p>We know, for instance, how Hegelian thought would be seen by many as deeply reliant on the conceptual framework of a philosophy of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter VI</label>
                     <title>Below zero:</title>
                     <subtitle>the “negativity deficit” in Axel Honneth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last two chapters, we saw how a reflection on the Freudian theory of drives led authors such as Lacan and Adorno to rebuild the concept of subjectivity, thus starting a movement that had major consequences for any theory of recognition that does not want to depend on the reiteration of a certain type of non-problematized normative anthropology. In my view, this perspective can serve as basis for criticizing one of the most successful attempts to recover Hegel’s concept of recognition in the philosophical debate of the past twenty-five years, which was carried out by Axel Honneth. This chapter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter VII</label>
                     <title>Our time unlocks a multiplicity in each desire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While the foregoing discussion of psychoanalytic drive theory has brought us to a renewed understanding of the problem of negativity, and allowed us to conceive of an individuality no longer subjugated to what we have termed the egological reduction of the subject, we have yet to examine how the restructuring of psychic activity is to be conducted; in particular, how psychic syntheses – understood here as being no longer exclusively dependent on egoderived modes of synthesis – operate.</p>
                     <p>In Chapter III, we have seen how a proper conception of negativity demanded that any syntheses conducted within time be conceived in terms of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter VIII</label>
                     <title>On the political power of the inhuman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If we accept: (a) the general consequences that follow from the mode of reflection on the nature of the subject presented in the first two parts of this book; as well as (b) the demands that recognition theory must consequently be able to meet, how are we to conceive of the practical dimension of rationality? Or, more specifically: once the rational normativity dependent on transcendental determinations of free will is removed as a reference point, for instance, what grounds remain for reflections on the morality of an action? Once we accept the proposed articulation between modes of psychic synthesis and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter IX</label>
                     <title>Towards an anti-predicative concept of recognition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As has been suggested above, the concept of<italic>recognition</italic>has attained almost hegemonic status within the philosophical and social debates of the past two decades, as the central operator through which the rationality of political demands is understood. First recovered in the 1930s, the political dimension of the concept would not be systematically explored until the early 1990s, with the publication of third-generation Frankfurt School theorist Axel Honneth’s<italic>The Struggle for Recognition: The Moral Grammar of Social Conflicts</italic>(1992), and of Hegel-influenced philosopher Charles Taylor’s<italic>Multiculturalism: Examining the Politics of Recognition</italic>(1992). Hence, if we are to adequately reflect on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Such were the questions that confronted us at the beginning of this book. Through the constitution of a system of conceptual interpenetrations derived from a dialectical tradition which has Hegel, Lacan and Adorno as its central figures – a system designed to privilege questions set in motion by the notions of desire, drive, fantasy and action – the aim of the ensuing pages has chiefly been to demonstrate how, remarkably often, an indistinct picture is indeed the one we need. After all, the adoption of a sharp image in place of an indistinct one frequently leads to the loss of precisely the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Name index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b9x1k5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
