<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1998.3.G63M58 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Godard, Jean-Luc, 1930</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Motion pictures</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Late Godard and the Possibilities of Cinema</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Morgan</surname>
               <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>23</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780520273313</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780520953963</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Berkeley; Los Angeles; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Regents of the University of California</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1ppvj2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>With<italic>Late Godard and the Possibilities of Cinema</italic>, Daniel Morgan makes a significant contribution to scholarship on Jean-Luc Godard, especially his films and videos since the late 1980s, some of the most notoriously difficult works in contemporary cinema. Through detailed analyses of extended sequences, technical innovations, and formal experiments, Morgan provides an original interpretation of a series of several internally related films-<italic>Soigne ta droite</italic>(Keep Your Right Up, 1987),<italic>Nouvelle vague</italic>(New Wave, 1990), and<italic>Allemagne 90 neuf zéro</italic>(Germany 90 Nine Zero, 1991)-and the monumental late video work,<italic>Histoire(s) du cinéma</italic>(1988-1998). Taking up a range of topics, including the role of nature and natural beauty, the relation between history and cinema, and the interactions between film and video, the book provides a distinctive account of the cinematic and intellectual ambitions of Godard's late work. At the same time,<italic>Late Godard and the Possibilities of Cinema</italic>provides a new direction for the fields of film and philosophy by drawing on the idealist and romantic tradition of philosophical aesthetics, which rarely finds an articulation within film studies. In using the tradition of aesthetics to illuminate Godard's late films and videos, Morgan shows that these works transform the basic terms and categories of aesthetics in and for the cinema.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="326"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a book about Jean-Luc Godard’s late work, in particular the films and videos he has made since the late 1980s. It is also a book about the place of aesthetics in cinema, and about the persistence of modernism, political radicalism, and late nineteenth-century artistic and philosophical concerns into the end of the twentieth century. Last, it is a book about how all these things go together, about the way Godard’s films and videos make use of this inheritance and in so doing transform it in and for the cinema.</p>
                     <p>As any viewer of Godard’s work over the past</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Work of Aesthetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If my argument is for the importance of aesthetics within Godard’s films and videos since the late 1980s, two kinds of questions quickly arise. First, if I am taking a tradition of philosophical aesthetics to be not only an interpretive framework but also explicitly present within these works, what evidence is there in the films and videos? Where does this concern manifest itself? Second, if aesthetics is as prominent as I am claiming, why have critics by and large failed to bring it up, much less discuss it as a central orientation?</p>
                     <p>Though the primary purpose of this chapter is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Nature and Its Discontents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Godard’s reputation in the 1960s was built in part on the claim of being one of the great filmmakers of urban locales, especially Paris. The genre-infused films in the early part of the decade—from<italic>À bout de souffle</italic>and<italic>Bande à part to Made in U.S.A.</italic>(1966), even<italic>Une femme est une femme</italic>—are all oriented around and have their narratives defined by, the contours of the city in which they take place.<italic>Deux ou trois choses que je sais d’elle</italic>goes a step further by placing the city explicitly within the film’s title:<italic>elle</italic>refers not just to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Politics by Other Means</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, I argued that<italic>Soigne ta droite</italic>and<italic>Nouvelle vague</italic>explicitly move away from the treatment of nature in Godard’s films of the early 1980s. Against an aesthetic based on the sublime, Godard gives a normative argument in<italic>Soigne ta droite</italic>for a move to the register of the beautiful, the mundane, and the ordinary. With<italic>Nouvelle vague</italic>, Godard uses the trope of the garden to show the natural world as inextricably caught up in the human and the historical; at the same time, he situates the category of the miraculous within the natural world as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Cinema without Photography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the very beginning of the book, I described a scene from<italic>Allemagne 90 neuf zéro</italic>that takes place in the Alte Nationalgalerie in Berlin. It starts with a shot of a woman in the act of taking a photograph; a 180-degree cut over her shoulder shows that she is photographing Gustave Courbet’s painting<italic>The Wave</italic>(see figure 1). As she presses the shutter, Lemmy Caution says in voice-over, “Bonjour, Monsieur Courbet,” and Godard cuts to a black-and-white film clip of a large wave rising up from the bottom of the frame and tossing a small ship. When I discussed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>What Projection Does</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Spurred by the 1995 centennial of cinema’s invention, an occasion to evaluate the medium’s past, present, and future, the rhetoric of a “death of cinema” became prominent at the close of the twentieth century. The discourse ranged from the popular to the scholarly: Susan Sontag’s “The Decay of Cinema,” Paolo Cherchi Usai’s<italic>The Death of Cinema</italic>, Laura Mulvey’s<italic>Death 24x a Second</italic>.¹ The reasons given for cinema’s death were varied: shifts in viewing habits, economic and industrial transformations, and, most frequently, the slow eclipse of celluloid in favor of new digital technologies. Godard was by no means immune. Indeed, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Cinema after the End of Cinema (Again)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The closing moments of<italic>Histoire(s) du cinéma</italic>have the feel of an elegy, of being at the end of something: the single rose, the solitary figure of Bacon’s<italic>Study for a Portrait of Van Gogh</italic>, and the past tense of the final words (“I was that man”). In case we weren’t sure to whom the sequence was referring, Godard includes a black-and-white photograph of his own face, weaving it in and out of the other images before slowly resolving on it. This final sequence suggests an end both to cinema itself and to Godard’s career—and, more than anything else,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ppvj2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
