<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">maju15694</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR9080.5.M35 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Commonwealth fiction (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Banality (Philosophy) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Place (Philosophy) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Narration (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Commonwealth countries</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Prose of the World</book-title>
         <subtitle>Modernism and the Banality of Empire</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Majumdar</surname>
               <given-names>Saikat</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231527675</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231527675</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/maju15694"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Everyday life in the far outposts of empire can be static, empty of the excitement of progress. A pervading sense of banality and boredom are, therefore, common elements of the daily experience for people living on the colonial periphery. Saikat Majumdar suggests that this impoverished affective experience of colonial modernity significantly shapes the innovative aesthetics of modernist fiction.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Prose of the World</italic>explores the global life of this narrative aesthetic, from late-colonial modernism to the present day, focusing on a writer each from Ireland, New Zealand, South Africa, and India. Ranging from James Joyce's deflated epiphanies to Amit Chaudhuri's disavowal of the grand spectacle of postcolonial national allegories, Majumdar foregrounds the banal as a key instinct of modern and contemporary fiction -- one that nevertheless remains submerged because of its antithetical relation to literature's intuitive function to engage or excite.</p>
         <p>Majumdar asks us to rethink the assumption that banality merely indicates an aesthetic failure. If narrative is traditionally enabled by the tremor, velocity, and excitement of the event, the historical and affective lack implied by the banal produces a narrative force that is radically new precisely because it suspends the conventional impulses of narration.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[ix]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Poetics of the Prosaic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Just about two years before the December made famous by Virginia Woolf as the time of momentous change for “human character,”¹ her fellow Bloomsbury writer, Katherine Mansfield, wrote the following in her diary on December 21, 1908:</p>
                     <p>I should like to write a life much in the style of Walter Pater’s ‘Child in the House’. About a girl in Wellington; the singular charm and barrenness of that place, with climatic effects—wind, rain, spring, night, the sea, the cloud pageantry. And then to leave the place and go to Europe, to live there a dual existence—to go back and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>James Joyce and the Banality of Refusal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>If the radical aesthetic of the banal thrives at the urgent confluence of modernist innovation and colonial anxiety, it has no greater exponent than James Joyce, who transforms the banality of provincial life into an unprecedented narrative force. If the successful artist, in Joyce’s fiction, charts a troubled arc of migration from the provincial margin to the metropolitan center, his path is littered with bodies that fail to do so. Bodies of Dubliners, almost always male, whose desire for the energetic aesthetic culture of the metropolis is stifled by the paralysis that pervades the colonial periphery like dreary smog. Such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Katherine Mansfield and the Fragility of Pākehā Boredom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In Katherine Mansfield’s best-known story, “Prelude,” Stanley Burnell, who has just moved to a new house, is delighted by his new life in the wide-open space of New Zealand countryside: “Ah, it was splendid to live in the country—to get right out of that hole of a town once the office was closed; and this drive in the fresh warm air, knowing all the while that his own house was at the other end, with its garden and paddocks, its three tip-top cows and enough fowls and ducks to keep them in poultry, was splendid too.”¹ It is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Dailiness of Trauma and Liberation in Zoë Wicomb</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Published in 1988, James Clifford’s <italic>The Predicament of Culture</italic> is an insightful exploration of metropolitan modernist aesthetics against the backdrop of a troubled global modernity in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. It is, moreover, representative of a critical momentum in the developing relationship between literary and anthropological discourse in the late twentieth century. The book has been considered a critical work in the so-called literary turn in anthropology, which was already exemplified by the influential collection co-edited by Clifford, <italic>Writing Culture</italic>, published in 1986.¹ In his introduction to the collection, Clifford points to the rising popularity of literary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Amit Chaudhuri and the Materiality of the Mundane</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>More than a quarter-century after its initial publication, Fredric Jameson’s controversial essay “Third World Literature in the Era of Multinational Capitalism” retains something of an unfortunate relevance to Anglophone fiction from India. The central claim in that essay—that all Third World cultures are characterized by a fusion of private and public lives and that this fusion ensures that all narratives (especially the novel) from such cultures are structured on the paradigm of the national allegory—still continues to resonate with an overarching trend of Indian English fiction. Ever since the publication of Salman Rushdie’s <italic>Midnight’s Children</italic>, the novel many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Uneventful</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>At the heart of the genre of prose fiction exists a set of fundamental questions about time and narrative. If narrative is inextricably bound up with the category of time, what is—and what should be—the relative importance of the ordinary everyday and that of the major event? Is narrative essentially event bound? Is it embedded in what Franco Moretti calls a Hegelian “teleological rhetoric,” wherein “the meaning of events lies in their finality” and where “events acquire meaning when they lead to <italic>one</italic> ending, and one only”?¹ Does the crux of narratives, as Moretti puts the question, rest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">maju15694.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
