<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Indebted</book-title>
         <subtitle>Capitalism and Religion in the Writings of S. Y. Agnon</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sagiv</surname>
               <given-names>Yonatan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780822944577</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780822981503</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Pittsburgh Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Pittsburgh, PA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Hebrew Union College Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1g2kmnj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This is the first book to examine the oeuvre of Shmuel Yosef Agnon, 1966 Nobel laureate in literature, through a reading that combines perspectives from economic theory, semiotics, psychoanalysis, narrative theory, and Jewish and religious studies. Sagiv outlines the vital role economy plays in the construction of religion, subjectivity, language, and thought in Agnon's work, and, accordingly, explores his literary use of images of debt, money, and economy to examine how these themes illuminate other focal points in the canonical author's work, excavating the economic infrastructure of discourses that are commonly considered to reside beyond the economic sphere.Sagiv's analysis of Agnon's work, renowned for its paradoxical articulation of the impact of modernity on traditional Jewish society, exposes an overarching distrust regarding the sustainability of any economic structure. The concrete and symbolic economies surveyed in this project are prone to cyclical crises. Under what Sagiv terms Agnon's "law of permanent debt," the stability and profitability of economies are always temporary. Agnon's literary economy, transgressing traditional closures, together with his profound irony, make it impossible to determine if these economic crises are indeed the product of the break with tradition or, alternatively, if this theodicy is but a fantasy, marking permanent debt as the inherent economic infrastructure of human existence.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="216"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Translation Table</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A MONETARY PRELUDE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Agnon’s Time in Germany</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Money was the rising star at the turn of the nineteenth century in Europe. Heralded by many contemporary economists as the symbol of economic rationality and the facilitator of a stable social order, money was considered one of the greatest institutional advances of humankind.¹ Yet in spite of such warm praises, money also gained a rather dubious reputation. Rumor had it that money was indeed something unimportant, at times even suspicious, a neutral “veil” that only obscures the “real” economic basis of society, namely, the good old practice of barter, the direct exchange of good and services.²</p>
                     <p>The idea that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reading the works of Shmuel Yosef Agnon in New York in 2008 against the backdrop of the economic crisis evolving in the United States at that time had an unintended effect: I started to think of Agnon as an economist. Encountering Agnon in high school (as every child who grows up in the Israeli education system does), and later in university, my perception of the canonical author was shaped through Gershon Shaked’s paradoxical definition of Agnon as a “revolutionary traditionalist.” Born in 1888 in Galicia, an erudite “pupil” of the Jewish sacred multi-textual tradition but also of the writings of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>THE GIFT OF DEBT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In reading<italic>And the Crooked Shall Be Made Straight</italic>(והיה העקוב למישור), Agnon’s first novella, published in 1912 in pre-state Israel, one motif stands out clearly: money. The text’s pious narrator outlines the disastrous route to bankruptcy taken by middle-class shopkeepers Menasheh Hayim and his wife Kreindel Tcharni in mid-nineteenthcentury Buczacz, Galicia. After the childless couple loses their shop and all their assets, Menasheh Hayim sets out to raise money as a beggar, with the help of a letter from the town rabbi, which lists his name and misfortunes. Failing to get enough donations, he is persuaded by a drunkard</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>TALKING THROUGH MONEY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first-person narrator of Agnon’s short story “And We Shall Not Fail” (“ולא ניכשל”), published in 1937, begins his tale with a warning. A person should never change the customary liturgy (נוסח) of his or her ancestors. This warning is immediately followed by a religious explanation: ever since biblical times, the twelve ancient tribes produced twelve different sets of prayers, each delivered to twelve heavenly gates. As a result, a person who changes the prayers of his ancestors “confuses” the gates. The narrator explains that recent generations have already been punished for confusing the prayers, hence creating chaos and altercations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>CAN’T BUY ME LOVE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“In common sense as well as in scholarship,” writes Eva Illouz, “romantic love stands above the realm of commodity exchange and even against the social order.”¹ Indeed, Illouz’s research on love in capitalist culture begins by expanding on this common divide; whereas the concept of “romantic love” is predicated on the private sphere, irrationality, selflessness, and singularity, the capitalist market is associated with the public sphere, rationality, self-interest, and interchangeability. However, working against this division, Illouz shows how the very modern construction of romantic love is paradoxically shaped by the forces of the capitalist market itself. In a similar vein,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>THE INCOMPLETE TEXT AND THE INDEBTED AUTHOR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, my reading of Agnon’s<italic>A Simple Story</italic>ended with emphasis on the closing dialogue between Hirshl and Mina. While it is true that, in the narrator’s words, “Hirshl and Mina’s story is over,” the novel itself does not conclude with their dialogue. In fact, instead of granting the reader a sense of closure, the novel ends with the narrator’s statement that Bluma’s story is<italic>not</italic>over. The narrator also promises the reader that “everything that happened to Bluma Nakht would fill another book.”¹ This promise, however, was never fulfilled. Subsequently, it only adds to the reader’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Book of Proverbs informs us that “those who trust in their riches will wither, but the righteous will flourish like green leaves.”¹ Many of Shmuel Yosef Agnon’s pious narrators and characters would happily endorse this warning. The trust in divine agency, they would say, is the only true determinant of a person’s fate, including his or her economic and material pursuits. However, the relationship between economy and religion is not such a simple story after all. If we indeed accept Nietzsche’s argument that “Setting prices, measuring values, thinking up equivalents, exchanging, this preoccupied the very first thinking of human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g2kmnj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
