<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Virginia Woolf and Being-in-the-world</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Heideggerian Study</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Simone</surname>
               <given-names>Emma</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474421676</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474421683</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Emma Simone</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1n7qhrd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Breaking fresh ground in Woolfian scholarship, this study presents a timely and compelling interpretation of Virginia Woolf's textual treatment of the relationship between self and world from the perspective of the philosophy of Martin Heidegger. Drawing on Woolf's novels, essays, reviews, letters, diary entries, short stories, and memoirs, the book explores the political and the ontological, as the individual's connection to the world comes to be defined by an involvement and engagement that is always already situated within a particular physical, societal, and historical context.</p>
         <p>Emma Simone argues that at the heart of what it means to be an individual making his or her way in the world, the perspectives of Woolf and Heidegger are founded upon certain shared concerns, including the sustained critique of Cartesian dualism, particularly the resultant binary oppositions of subject and object, and self and Other; the understanding that the individual is a temporal being; an emphasis upon intersubjective relations insofar as Being-in-the-world is defined by Being-with-Others; and a consistent emphasis upon average everydayness as both determinative and representative of the individual's relationship to and with the world.</p>
         <p>Key Features</p>
         <p>The first sustained discussion of Woolf from the perspective of the philosophy of Martin HeideggerEmphasises the thematic and conceptual links between the works of Woolf and Heidegger, so that each chapter focuses upon the explication of particular issues and aspects of Being-in-the-worldCovers a wide range of Woolf's fictional and non-fictional writing</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Referring to the work of the English writer, Virginia Woolf (1882–1941), and the German philosopher, Martin Heidegger (1889–1976), Heidi Storl suggests that a ‘discussion of the seemingly unlikely alliance between these two thinkers generates new strategies by which to “look through” much of our daily experience and discover – even if only momentarily – what it is to<italic>be</italic>human’ (2008: 303). Despite the marked variances between Woolf and Heidegger in terms of their backgrounds, experiences, vocations, nationalities and political orientations, this book proposes that at the heart of the issue of what it means to be an individual making</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Being-in-the-world</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evident throughout the various forms of Woolf’s writings – from her novels and short stories, through to her essays, reviews, memoirs, letters and diary entries – is a consistent and dominant preoccupation with the relationship between the individual and the world. Reflected in these works is Woolf’s understanding that while the ‘world’ consists of the physical environment and its tangible objects, as well as those individuals with whom we co-exist, this notion also comes to be defined by the individual’s everyday involvements and engagements; that is, ‘our<italic>experience</italic>of the world’ (Hussey 1986: xiii). As this chapter will demonstrate, for Woolf, definitive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>A Sense of Place</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As emphasised in the previous chapter, it is the average everyday lived experience of Being-in-the-world that is a central concern and preoccupation throughout Woolf’s writings. Despite the incalculable variety of everyday experiences that any individual may encounter during his or her lifetime, each is always and inevitably located in a particular place, whether it be the home, the street, a city, the countryside, the workplace or an armchair. Place provides the setting and context for all experience.¹ The inherent connection between the individual, experience and place, and how each depends upon the other for definition and actuality, is a view</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Being-at-home and Homelessness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From an existential perspective, the notion of home is arguably one of the more significant expressions of place. Not defined simply as a co-ordinate on a map, home encompasses neighbourhoods, nations, traditions, customs, narrative, myth, the tangible, the imaginable, the dream, as well as each individual’s relation to Being. Home has relevance to all humans: despite its multifarious manifestations, our diverse relationships with home – whether positive, negative, or ambivalent – can be life-long and pervasive, creating and rekindling memories, inspiring desires and the imagination, shaping who we are, and how we relate to the Other. As this chapter will elucidate, each</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Historical Dasein</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous two chapters have considered Woolf’s sense of Beingin-the-world principally from the perspective of her treatment of place. In this chapter, the focus shifts to the notion of temporality, an area of study that is granted particular emphasis in Heidegger’s<italic>Being and Time</italic>. Specifically, Woolf’s approach to history and historical discourse from the perspective of Being-in-the-world is investigated.¹ Woolf’s interest in the subject of history began at an early age under the instruction of her father, the historian, biographer and man of letters, Sir Leslie Stephen.² A willing student in terms of her adolescent submission to her father’s direction,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Moments of Being and the Everyday</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The preceding chapters have explored Woolf’s emphasis throughout her writings on the notion that the individual’s average everyday mode of Being-in-the-world comes to be defined and ‘held in place’ (‘Sketch’: 92) by the typically veiled forces, conventions and prescriptions of the social order, including the often overlapping discourses of patriarchy, religion, nationalism and history. As discussed, such an approach to the relationship between self and world may be contrasted with Heidegger’s ontological emphasis in<italic>Being and Time</italic>. In this chapter, the focus shifts to the crucial role that moods and sensations play in Woolf’s textual representations of the individual’s experience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Confluences, Divergences and Future Directions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her essay, ‘Reading Simone de Beauvoir with Martin Heidegger’, Eva Gothlin states that</p>
                     <p>Reading Beauvoir with Heidegger can deepen our understanding of Beauvoir’s view of human beings and their relation to the world and to others. This approach might be called hermeneutical in the Heideggerian sense: it reveals new meanings without assuming that a final comprehension is ever possible. (2003: 45)</p>
                     <p>Arguably, this study of the relationship between Woolf’s writings and Heidegger’s philosophy in Being and Time leads to a similar outcome, insofar as Woolf’s textual representations of the connections between self, world and the Other are afforded a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1n7qhrd.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
