<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BV823.A77 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lord’s Supper</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History of doctrines</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Middle Ages, 600–1500</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lord’s Supper</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History of doctrines</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">16th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Food</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spiritual life</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History of doctrines</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Middle Ages, 600–1500</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spiritual life</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History of doctrines</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">16th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Eating Beauty</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Eucharist and the Spiritual Arts of the Middle Ages</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ASTELL</surname>
               <given-names>ANN W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780801444661</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781501704550</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ithaca; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cornell University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7591/j.ctt18kr4nz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"The enigmatic link between the natural and artistic beauty that is to be contemplated but not eaten, on the one hand, and the eucharistic beauty that is both seen (with the eyes of faith) and eaten, on the other, intrigues me and inspires this book. One cannot ask theo-aesthetic questions about the Eucharist without engaging fundamental questions about the relationship between beauty, art (broadly defined), and eating."-from<italic>Eating Beauty</italic>
         </p>
         <p>In a remarkable book that is at once learned, startlingly original, and highly personal, Ann W. Astell explores the ambiguity of the phrase "eating beauty." The phrase evokes the destruction of beauty, the devouring mouth of the grave, the mouth of hell. To eat beauty is to destroy it. Yet in the case of the Eucharist the person of faith who eats the Host is transformed into beauty itself, literally incorporated into Christ. In this sense, Astell explains, the Eucharist was "productive of an entire 'way' of life, a virtuous life-form, an artwork, with Christ himself as the principal artist." The Eucharist established for the people of the Middle Ages distinctive schools of sanctity-Cistercian, Franciscan, Dominican, and Ignatian-whose members were united by the eucharistic sacrament that they received.</p>
         <p>Reading the lives of the saints not primarily as historical documents but as iconic expressions of original artworks fashioned by the eucharistic Christ, Astell puts the "faceless" Host in a dynamic relationship with these icons. With the advent of each new spirituality, the Christian idea of beauty expanded to include, first, the marred beauty of the saint and, finally, that of the church torn by division-an anti-aesthetic beauty embracing process, suffering, deformity, and disappearance, as well as the radiant lightness of the resurrected body. This astonishing work of intellectual and religious history is illustrated with telling artistic examples ranging from medieval manuscript illuminations to sculptures by Michelangelo and paintings by Salvador Dalí. Astell puts the lives of medieval saints in conversation with modern philosophers as disparate as Simone Weil and G. W. F. Hegel.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1:</label>
                     <title>“TASTE AND SEE”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Eating of Beauty</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eating beauty. The title of this book is intentionally ambiguous. It carries, on the one hand, a sinister meaning, for the eating of beauty denotes its frightening, mythic consumption, whether by cunning serpents, monstrous beasts, cannibals, or machines. It recalls the vicious abuse of food and drink and the concomitant destruction of health and humanity, emblematically represented in the gaping glutton and the drunkard sprawled on the sidewalk. Finally it evokes the devouring mouth of the grave, the sepulcher that swallows every beautiful person and thing (in Latin,<italic>pulcher</italic>), and the horrific mouth of Hell. On the other hand, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2:</label>
                     <title>THE APPLE AND THE EUCHARIST:</title>
                     <subtitle>Foods for a Theological Aesthetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the beauty of the world as one knows it is lost through some personal or communal catastrophe, be it a crippling accident, the death of a loved one, betrayal by a trusted and idealized friend, or some more far reaching disturbance—a terrorist attack that ends in mass destruction, an epidemic, a genocidal uprising, a world war—the ancient question arises anew: How is this possible? What went wrong in the beginning to allow this to happen? How can the beauty that was lost be restored?</p>
                     <p>In the Judeo-Christian tradition, the question concerning what went wrong is always answered</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3:</label>
                     <title>“HIDDEN MANNA”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bernard of Clairvaux, Gertrude of Helfta, and the Monastic Art of Humility</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his continuation of William of St. Thierry’s unfinished Life of St. Bernard, Arnold of Bonnevaux so vividly describes the scene of Pope Innocent II’s visit to Clairvaux that it invites (and has received) pictorial representation:¹</p>
                     <p>Returning from Liege, the Pope now wished to see for himself what Bernard’s famed monastery at Clairvaux was really like. And there he met the poor of Christ coming out to meet him, not with gilded Gospels and purple robes, but all of them ragged men, bearing a rough cross, and greeting him with the quietest and most affectionate of voices, instead of high</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4:</label>
                     <title>“ADORNED WITH WOUNDS”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Saint Bonaventure’s Legenda maior and the Franciscan Art of Poverty</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For St. Bonaventure (1221–1274), the stigmatization of St. Francis of Assisi (1182–1226) gave new meaning to the Augustinian question of the beauty of<italic>Christus deformis</italic>—so much so that the “unprecedented miracle,”¹ whereby the wounds of Christ were imprinted on the hands, feet, and side of the<italic>Poverello</italic>, became a key that unlocked the beauty of the universe and brought into relief the artistic pattern and providential design of history. Identifying original sin with concupiscence or covetousness in its various forms, Bonaventure discovered a remedy for the restoration of the world’s microcosmic and macro cosmic beauty in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5:</label>
                     <title>“IMITATE ME AS I IMITATE CHRIST”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three Catherines, the Food of Souls, and the Dominican Art of Preaching</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Depending on which virtue is brought to the fore, a different Christian form of life appears, and the beauty of the church as a whole is thus variegated and enhanced. The early Dominicans found in the book of the prophet Zachariah a metaphoric and allegorical verse that foretells the establishment of the mendicant orders and characterizes the difference between the Franciscans and the Dominicans. Speaking as a shepherd who guides his flock by means of sweetness and strictness, the Lord declares: "And I will feed the flock…. And I took unto me two rods; one I called Beauty, and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6:</label>
                     <title>THE EUCHARIST, THE SPIRITUAL EXERCISES, AND THE ART OF OBEDIENCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Saint Ignatius of Loyola and Michelangelo</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Rome on October 6, 1554, in the presence of Ignatius of Loyola (1491–1556), Michelangelo Buonarroti (1475–1564) went down into the newly excavated foundation to set with his own hands the cornerstone for the Gesù, the mother church of the fledgling Society of Jesus.¹ Michelangelo, the master architect, had constructed a model of the church that he hoped soon to build. In a letter Ignatius enthusiastically endorsed Michelangelo’s plans: “Taking charge of the work is the most celebrated man known here, Michelangelo—who also has charge of St. Peter’s—and for devotion alone, without any other consideration.”²</p>
                     <p>Due</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7:</label>
                     <title>WEIL AND HEGEL:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Eucharistic “Ante-/Anti-Aesthetic” Aesthetics?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Protestant challenges to Catholic eucharistic beliefs during the early modern period were implicitly tied to the covering of Michelangelo’s nudes and explicitly connected to an often violent iconoclasm that resulted in the destruction of works of religious art —paintings, statues, books, buildings.¹ What, if anything, does this historical rift within Christianity have to do with modern, Hegelian reflections on the imminent “end of art”?</p>
                     <p>The extraordinary reflections on the Host by the modern, mystic philosopher Simone Weil (1909–1943) provide a key to her aesthetic theory and help to account for the manifest differences between her doctrinally Catholic (and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8:</label>
                     <title>TO (FAIL TO) CONCLUDE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eucharists without End</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Simone Weil died in England in August 1943, Edith Stein (1891–1942) was already dead, a Jewish victim of the Nazis in Auschwitz. Stein, one of Edmund Husserl’s most brilliant students, had become Catholic in 1922. For ten years she had lived a devout life as a teacher and scholar, practicing an intense, eucharistic piety. In 1933 she entered the Carmelite cloister in Cologne, choosing for herself a name, “Sister Teresa Benedicta of the Cross,” that evoked the names of Carmel’s two great sixteenth-century reformers, Saints John of the Cross (1542–1591) and Teresa of Ávila (1515–1582), whose</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ILLUSTRATION CREDITS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18kr4nz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PLATES</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
