<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Scots Imagination and Modern Memory</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Blaikie</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748617869</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748679737</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Andrew Blaikie</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1r2cd5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>All memories invoke imagined pasts, but do the ways we remember share a common imaginary? In seeking to interpret Scottish culture in the recent past as a series of encounters with modernity, this study draws on a wide range of sources to explore relationships between perceptions of place, belonging and identity in one nation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Scotland and the places of memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>A fictional Scots detective gives fleeting pause for thought, stubs out his Silk Cut, moves on quickly to more pressing, practical matters, the conundrum lingering only as long as the pause in his conversation with a disagreeable colleague. The plot moves on. I finished the novel, but marked the page, wanting to dwell some more on the frisson where ‘loss and permanence had mingled and become some new entity’. What, quite, could this ‘something extraordinary’ be and what was new about that ‘new entity’? A momentary reverie points to a difficult issue: memories link people with places in enigmatic ways.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Before and after modernity:</title>
                     <subtitle>the legacy of Adam Ferguson</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In 1766, James Boswell, having returned from a Grand Tour accompanied by Rousseau’s mistress, left London for his native Edinburgh, where he took his final law examination and joined the Scottish bar. Meanwhile, ensconced in the Advocates Library, the Professor of Pneumatics and Moral Philosophy, Adam Ferguson, was completing his pioneering work, shortly to appear (despite David Hume’s misgivings) as <italic>An Essay on the History of Civil Society</italic> (1767). These were heady days in the precincts of the Scottish Parliament Building, when cultural conversation in the Old Town was as high as the odours of its teeming streets. On 16</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>The eyes of modernity:</title>
                     <subtitle>John Grierson’s sociology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In embracing the need for a sociological vision as central to the interpretation of culture and place, a number of Scottish scholars may be cited in the early twentieth century, Patrick Geddes and Robert MacIver among them. But it was a film director, rather than an academic – and one who ‘spent almost his entire adult life outwith Scotland’² – who was to have perhaps the most profound and lasting effect upon the nation’s social imagination. John Grierson finds his place in the Scots Myth by dint of being a classic example of the Great Man: an individual who rose from a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Among the wee Nazareths:</title>
                     <subtitle>myths of moral community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Both Ferguson’s image of an ideal civil society and the Griersonian figure of the industrious citizen celebrate social participation. Yet the ‘spaces’ in which virtuous behaviour can flourish are rather different. For Ferguson, civil society constitutes an intermediate realm between the family and the state that in the modern context requires communication among strangers; for Grierson, model citizens effectively become <italic>träger</italic> of a top-down discourse of statist democracy. In each case, the cultural validity of the moral sphere of local – that is, place-bound – society is diminished, relegated to being the vestige of a past social order. Recently, scholars have argued</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Retrieving ‘that invisible leeway’:</title>
                     <subtitle>landscapes, cultures, belonging</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The conventional logic of landscape evaluation is that the Romantic Movement was a conservative response to the onset of modernity, emphasising the need to develop ‘culture’ as moral salvation against the instability of urbanisation and industrialisation. Its legacy has seen a supposedly preexisting Arcadia touted as ‘authentic’ for a public that misrecognises fabrication for historical fact. Arguably, alienated from their own acts of creation, cultural producers have reified their own constructions, believing likewise that these reflect a sacred essence of ‘natural beauty’. Icons abound. What more can be said about the social construction of the Scottish landscape?</p>
                     <p>One of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>A pattern of islands:</title>
                     <subtitle>photographs in the cultural account</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Torgovnick’s literary analysis of primitivism in Freud, Malinowski and Mead suggests that the impulse to record ‘other’ cultures represents a means of ‘handling, through displacement, the series of dislocations that we call modernity and postmodernity’.¹ While archivists have collected and classified, the better to re-present the past for contemporary consumption, the socio-historical critique of heritage and ‘museumry’ has properly castigated selective and ethnocentric interpretation.² Cultural studies includes among its nostrums the need to ‘honour the plurality of perspectives’³ in a world where ‘above all, and directly contrary to the form in which they are constantly invoked, identities are constructed through,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Remembering ‘The Forgotten Gorbals’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Bert Hardy’s ‘Gorbals Boys’ is an iconic image.¹ It depicts two lads aged about ten, strolling arm-in-arm and glancing pertly at the camera. From their clothing and hairstyles, the rain-washed pavement and tall buildings framing them, the casual spectator would conclude that they are working-class, the period is sometime between 1930 and 1950 and the setting is an industrial city with a cool climate. Rendered ‘sepia’, the picture adorns the cover of the first volume of an autobiography by Ralph Glasser, as it does the front of a monograph about Hardy, and it is also available from numerous outlets as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Finding ways home</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>
                        <italic>The station is in the middle of a moor. There appears to be no habitation around. In the distance are some hills.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The train stands at the station.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>As it pulls away, Renton, Spud, Tommy and Sick Boy are left standing on the platform, looking around.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>SICK BOY</p>
                     <p>Now what?</p>
                     <p>TOMMY</p>
                     <p>We go for a walk.</p>
                     <p>SPUD</p>
                     <p>What?</p>
                     <p>TOMMY</p>
                     <p>A walk.</p>
                     <p>SPUD</p>
                     <p>But where?</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Tommy points vaguely across the moor.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>TOMMY </p>
                     <p>There.</p>
                     <p>SICK BOY</p>
                     <p>Are you serious?</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>They step across the tracks toward the vast moorland. They stop. All but Tommy sit down on rocks or clumps of heather.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>TOMMY</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2cd5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
