<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Double Vision Hermeneutic</book-title>
         <subtitle>Interpreting a Chinese Pastor's Intersubjective Experience of Shi Engaging Yìzhuàn and Pauline Texts</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ooi</surname>
               <given-names>Samuel Hio-Kee</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174821</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902929</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Samuel Hio-Kee Ooi</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf4zg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The aim of this thesis is to unfold the multilayered intersubjective experience of the author himself, a Chinese pastor. The author postulates himself as the subject in whom the said experience was evident, so that it can be analyzed and interpreted. The author argues for a cultural-linguistic experience of shì as the locus at which the intersubjective experience takes place. He then shows that such experience embodies a Chinese Christian’s ‘two texts’ inheritance, and argues that it is through unfolding or revealing of such experience that the nature of his relationship with them can be demonstrated.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="284"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lists of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Editoral Conventions, Use of Sources, and Research Matters</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abstract</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This thesis arose from my personal experience as a Chinese Christian. Before the purpose of the thesis can be stated and appreciated, I will give a brief description of my background as a Chinese Christian and the formation of a Chinese Christian intersubjective experience of<italic>shì</italic>—with<italic>yì</italic>(grip or grasp) on the top and<italic>lì</italic>(power or force) the<italic>radical</italic>, a Chinese word implying not only power but also used to mean a situation, a circumstance, a tendency, and a tension that is about to be triggered off—and how it is related to my reading of<italic>Yìzhuàn</italic>and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Surveying Chinese Indigenous Theological Approaches</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story told in the introduction shows an indigenous Christian experience that invites further theological reflection. It involves a self, the subject, within which the Chinese culture and tradition and biblical teachings both form their respective effects. In terms of my double identity, as a Chinese Christian who has inherited Chinese tradition as well as Judaic-Christian tradition, I have many predecessors who have reflected on the dialog and integration of two traditions and two texts. This chapter intends to provide a context within which my own double vision hermeneutics will be compared. The earliest and most remarkable attempts in this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Constructing a Double Vision Hermeneutic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction, I have proffered myself and my experience as the locus of my double vision hermeneutics. In chapter 1, dissatisfaction was expressed with the doctrinal approach and interest shown in developing Archie lee’s “Two Texts” concern and K. K. Yeo’s cross-cultural and intersubjective hermeneutics. I accept the call for an exegesis that seriously considers both the literary and historical context of the texts seriously and will apply this exegetical principle to my study of<italic>Yìzhuàn</italic>and Pauline texts. I find the reflection of my personal experience to be in line with Chinese Christians who wrestle with their inheritance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Text A1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Shì as a Cultural-linguistic and Traditionary Text</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word<italic>shì</italic>appears frequently in current Chinese terms, for example:<italic>xíngshì</italic>, the propensity (tendency) or dynamic of the situation;<italic>shìlì</italic>, to judge someone’s status based on one’s power (<italic>shì</italic>);<italic>caíshì</italic>, the power of the wealthy; dìshì , the terrain or geographical area judged to be advantageous or disadvantageous; or as<italic>shì zaì bì xíng</italic>, to say that something to be done is imperative (as being forced). Without exception, the key word that determines the meanings reflected in these various combinations is<italic>shì</italic>which first became widely used in pre-Qín china.</p>
                     <p>It has been noted that<italic>shì</italic>(tendency) was a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Interpreting Text A1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Shì with Text A2: Yìzhuàn</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the double vision hermeneutic I delineated in chapter 3, I had emphasized the intersubjective factor, i.e. the intersubjective experience of<italic>shì</italic>. Developing from the hermeneutic of Gadamer, I have drawn attention to the cultural-linguistic effect of<italic>shì</italic>as part of the larger body of Chinese traditionary texts, and<italic>shì</italic>as culturally inborn and subjectively experienced within myself, which together form an intersubjective experience. Thus,<italic>shì</italic>is something that is external to me, the interpreting subject but yet simultaneously exists as an intrinsic element in me. in other words, with<italic>shì</italic>as part of my inner world acting as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Text B1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Principalities and Powers: A Survey on Contemporary Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous two chapters, I have shown the intersubjectivity between texts A1 and A2. On the one hand, they are intersubjectively related because they have both been appropriated by me, the interpreting subject; on the other, although appropriated by me they are self-subsistent. Here there are two layers of intersubjective relationship, one between the texts: Text A1 in or through Text A2 and vice versa, and the other between the texts and me. The texts and the meanings produced in the intersubjective interpretation help make sense of my initial experience of<italic>shì</italic>which was designated as text 0 in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Power in Text B2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pauline Text I: Galatians</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The aim of this and the following chapter is to interpret the Pauline notion of “principalities and powers” in Text B1 intermingling with Text b2—a reading of power relations in Galatians and 1 Corinthians. While chapters 3 and 4 prepared the “Chinese vision” for the execution of a double vision hermeneutics in the conclusion, this chapter and the next prepare the ‘Christian vision’. Both Texts A and b are appropriated texts, embedded in the Chinese Christian double vision. To see the fusion of A and b, one has to first see the fusion within each vision, in other words</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Power in Text B2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pauline Text II: Corinthians</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter, a continuation of chapter 6, serves as the second part of the discussion aimed at interpreting the Pauline account of “principalities and powers” as Text b1 intermingled with Text b2. While the last chapter focused on Galatians, this chapter will focus on 1 Corinthians. The purpose is to identify the power symbols that had a strong influence on the Corinthian church, attempt to consider them within the Corinthian social context and interpret them with an awareness of the Pauline critique of “principalities and powers.” This intermingling of Texts b1 and b2 (as 1 corinthians) will again serve to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Double Vision Hermeneutics of a Chinese Pastor’s Intersubjective Experience of Shì Engaging Yìzhuàn and Pauline Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter aims to present the result and evaluate the claim of the double vision hermeneutic, i.e., its efficacy in interpreting the intersubjective experience of<italic>shì</italic>and the multilayered intersubjective relationships between Texts A1 + A2 and Texts b1 + b2 and between these texts and the subject. In this regard, an assessment of a double vision hermeneutics as a preferable interpretive framework for the simultaneous handling of both concerns alongside the intersubjective experience of<italic>shì</italic>, needs to be undertaken.</p>
                     <p>Additionally, this conclusion will answer how this thesis has responded to the call for an indigenous Chinese theology which highly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix I:</title>
                     <subtitle>64 Hexagrams</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix II:</title>
                     <subtitle>English Names of 64 Hexagrams</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary of Chinese Expressions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf4zg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>270</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
