<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccm4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS2615.52.J65 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. N.T. John</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jesus Christ</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historicity</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>John, Jesus, and History, Volume 3</book-title>
         <subtitle>Glimpses of Jesus through the Johannine Lens</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Anderson</surname>
               <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Just</surname>
               <given-names>Felix</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Thatcher</surname>
               <given-names>Tom</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884140849</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884140832</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cx3vmb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A critical analysis of the historicity of the Gospel of John</p>
         <p>Since it began in 2002, the John, Jesus, and History Project has assessed critically the modern disparaging of John's historicity and has found this bias wanting. In this third volume, an international group of experts demonstrate over two dozen ways in which John contributes to an enhanced historical understanding of Jesus and his ministry. This volume does not simply argue for a more inclusive quest for Jesus-one that embraces John instead of programmatically excluding it. It shows that such a quest has already indeed begun. Contributors include Paul N. Anderson, Jo-Ann A. Brant, Peder Borgen, Gary M. Burge, Warren Carter, R. Alan Culpepper, James D. G. Dunn, Robert T. Fortna, Jörg Frey, Steven A. Graham, Colin J. Humphreys, Craig Keener, Andreas Köstenberger, Tim Ling, William Loader, Linda McKinnish Bridges, James S. McLaren, Annette Merz, Wendy E. S. North, Benjamin E. Reynolds, Udo Schnelle, Donald Senior, C.P., Tom Thatcher, Michael Theobald, Jan van der Watt, Robert Webb, Stephen Witetscheck, and Jean Zumstein.</p>
         <p>Features</p>
         <p>A state-of-the-art analysis of John's contributions to the quest for the historical Jesus, including evaluative responses by leading Jesus scholars•An overview of paradigm shifts in Jesus scholarship and recent approaches to the Johannine riddlesDetailed charts that illuminates John's similarities and differences form the Synoptic Gospels as well as the gospel's contributions to the historical Jesus research</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="524"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction and Overview</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clark-Soles</surname>
                           <given-names>Jaime</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In November 2010, Professor Gregory Sterling opened the joint session between the John, Jesus, and History Group and the Historical Jesus section of the Society of Biblical Literature by correctly acknowledging that the two disjunctions levied by David F. Strauss of Tübingen a century and a half ago were largely accepted by jesus researchers and New Testament scholars in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. First, Strauss argued that the Jesus of history must be divorced from the Christ of faith. Second, given some irreconcilable differences between the synoptics and John, and the three-against-one reality, one must choose between the Synoptics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Last Days of Jesus in John:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction to the Issues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The passion narrative—recounting the last days of Jesus’s life—has the greatest continuity and overlap between the four canonical Gospels, including the Gospel of John. In fact, nearly half of John’s close parallels with Mark and the other Synoptics can be found in John 18–19, tracing the events from the arrest of Jesus to his burial. When the larger outline of parallels between John and the three Synoptic Gospels regarding the last days of Jesus is listed, the particulars are impressive. Therefore, the passion narratives of the Gospels serve as a fitting place to begin when investigating glimpses</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>History and Theology in the Johannine Presentation of the Causes for the Death of Jesus:</title>
                     <subtitle>John 11:45–53 as Convergence Point</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Senior</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The attempt to find at least “glimpses” of the historical Jesus in the Gospel according to John is a topic of growing interest for biblical scholarship, and this study of a unique Johannine passage is intended to be a modest contribution to that perspective. The Johannine account of the deliberations of the “council” in 11:45–53 is an interesting example of the convergence of historical, literary, ethical, and theological dimensions of the causes and meaning of Jesus’s death in the Fourth Gospel.¹</p>
                     <p>This scene is a key transition point between the climax of the public ministry of Jesus in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jesus and Pilate:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memories in John’s Gospel?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carter</surname>
                           <given-names>Warren</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Might explicit attention to John’s presentation of the scene between Pilate and Jesus contain some historical data of significance for understanding the historical Jesus’s death and life’s work and for answering questions about why jesus was killed by crucifixion (see fredriksen 2007 and powell 2007a)?</p>
                     <p>Central to engaging these matters are three related but complex issues that need some brief discussion: the genre of John’s Gospel, the question of the Gospel’s sources, and the task of recovering “historical” data.</p>
                     <p>Concerning genre, the central question concerns whether the frequently (if not misleadingly) identified “spiritual” Gospel is capable of yielding any information</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“What is Truth?”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pilate’s Perspective on Jesus in John 18:33–38</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keener</surname>
                           <given-names>Craig S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does the scene in John 18:33–38 reflect historical information? John offers no eyewitnesses to substantiate the content of the interview in 18:33–38, and it rings with Johannine theology. At the same time, the use of private scenes would not move this Gospel outside the realm of biography, a genre that, unlike some other narrative genres, was interested in information where it was available. Sometimes biographers may have had sources unknown to us for information in these scenes; but as we shall observe further below, ancient historians and biographers also could construct scenes based on plausible inferences.</p>
                     <p>If the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Hour of the Lamb?</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Remarks on John 19:14 and the Hour of Jesus’s Condemnation and/or Crucifixion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Witetschek</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has become a piece of textbook knowledge that the Synoptic Gospels and the Gospel of John differ on the chronology of Jesus’s passion. While the Synoptics present Jesus’s last supper as a regular passover meal (and apparently have him tried, sentenced, and crucified on the first passover holiday), John’s account of the Last Supper implies nothing at all about a Passover meal, and Jesus is indeed, according to John, tried, sentenced, and crucified on the “Day of Preparation,” just before the passover feast begins (see esp.John 18:28; see also matson 2009). moreover, there is also a difference regarding the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Story, Plot, and History in the Johannine Passion Narrative</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zumstein</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Both narrative analysis as practiced by paul ricoeur (1983–1985) and the new approach to history as seen in Hayden White (1999) have emphasized the decisive hermeneutical role of plot in the construction of a story. In particular, the shaping of the plot in historiographical works allows the narrator to structure and contextualize the story and place it in a certain perspective (Bauckham 2007a; Luz 2009; Schmeller 2009). The creation of the plot is a central moment in the creation of meaning.</p>
                     <p>The plot analysis of the Johannine passion narrative confirms this theoretical statement. Even if the Johannine and Markan</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Points and Stars:</title>
                     <subtitle>John and the Synoptics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>North</surname>
                           <given-names>Wendy E. S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We may never know who the Fourth Evangelist was, but there is no mistaking the distinctiveness of his contribution to the New Testament witness to the life of Jesus of Nazareth. From the slow-moving, authoritarian Greek style, the cosmic scale of the setting, and the theological self-awareness of the central character, to the layering of irony, the often blistering polemic, and the ever-present parentheses to guide his readers, we know him well enough, do we not? In other words, we are aware that what dominates this account from beginning to end is the powerful and creative mind of its author.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Traces of Jesus in a Pre-Johannine Passion Narrative</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fortna</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As to the possibility of discovering “what actually happened,” my doctorfather, J. Louis Martyn, has often said that every would-be historian should repeat, each day three times before breakfast, slowly and solemnly, the words: “We do not know.” History is, broadly speaking, a myth: neither some ultimate truth, nor necessarily something untrue, but perhaps something unattainable.</p>
                     <p>Nevertheless, I believe that we must try, and I believe that the Jesus Seminar, of which I have been a loyal member almost from the start over thirty years ago, has indeed erred in “de-Johannizing” the historical jesus. Reasons for this are several (see</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Passion of Jesus and the Gospel of John:</title>
                     <subtitle>Progress and Prospects</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thatcher</surname>
                           <given-names>Tom</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Fourth Gospel’s account of the final events of Jesus’s life, including the causes and circumstances of his death, offers both special promise and special problems as a source for reconstructing his career. The Johannine passion narrative is<italic>promising</italic>simply because this material enjoys substantial parallels with other canonical and early noncanonical Christian documents. Unlike most of the Johannine signs and sayings, the causes and events of Jesus’s trials and death are recorded, or at least alluded to, in all three synoptic Gospels, the Johannine and Pauline Epistles, a variety of noncanonical Christian texts (most significantly the Gospel of Peter),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Works of Jesus in John:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction to the Issues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The works of Jesus are described in a number of ways in the canonical Gospels. Some of them are common to John and the Synoptics, while others are only in the Synoptics or only in John. John’s riddles include the fact that many of the Synoptic features of Jesus’s works are missing from John: Jesus’s baptism, his temptation in the wilderness, calling twelve disciples, exorcisms, healing lepers and women, dining with sinners, tax collectors, and Pharisees, sending out disciples on service trips, ministering in Nazareth, feeding the four thousand, the transfiguration on the mount, and making a long and momentous</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Who Were the First Disciples of Jesus?</title>
                     <subtitle>An Assessment of the Historicity of the Johannine Call Narrative (John 1:35–51)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Köstenberger</surname>
                           <given-names>Andreas J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early 1990s, while completing my PHD at Trinity Evangelical Divinity School in Deerfield, Illinois, I experienced a fairly precipitous drop in my ability to see. I procrastinated as long as I could before finally going to see a doctor. When, at long last, I got around to visiting an ophthalmologist, my eyesight had gotten so bad I was in desperate need of new glasses (or, as it turned out, special contact lenses). You might argue that something similar has happened in historical Jesus studies which, for centuries, have heavily tilted toward the Synoptic portrait of Jesus while giving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Perspective of a Jewish Priest on the Johannine Timing of the Action in the Temple</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McLaren</surname>
                           <given-names>James S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Discussion of the Fourth Gospel, Jesus, and history invariably incorporates consideration of the temple incident. In general, the Synoptic Gospel version of the positioning of the incident has been given priority over that of the Fourth Gospel. In effect, we have an either/or discussion, a choice between the Fourth Gospel and the Synoptic Gospels as<italic>the</italic>record of when the incident actually took place. My intention here is to argue for an alternative approach to be adopted when our concern is historical reconstruction. The Johannine version and the Synoptic version of the incident should be placed on equal footing, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jesus in Relation to John “the Testifier” and not “the Baptizer”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fourth Gospel’s Portrayal of John the Baptist and Its Historical Possibilities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Webb</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Fourth Gospel presents a distinctive picture of John the Baptist in relation to Jesus. This essay is a high-level overview of this distinctive picture, with the purpose of considering to what extent and with what level of probability elements of this picture may be judged historical. The focus of the Society of Biblical Literature John, Jesus, and History Group at this point in its research agenda is on the works of Jesus, and so that is the focus of this essay. It does require us, however, to begin more broadly and also examine the fourth Gospel’s picture of John</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Signs in the Gospel of John</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schnelle</surname>
                           <given-names>Udo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Johannine miracle stories are of decisive importance for the interpretation of Johannine Christology, because, according to John 10:41, the working of signs is the distinguishing feature of Jesus as Messiah. Moreover, the miraculous signs are extremely important for an understanding that the Gospel as a whole, since πcιεϊν σημεϊα (“doing signs”) marks the beginning (2:11), the turning point (12:37), and the end (20:30) of Jesus’s activity in the Gospel of John. Only John tells his readers how they are to understand the miracles/signs: “Now Jesus did many other signs in the presence of the disciples, which are not written</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Geopolitics of Water and John 4:1–42</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brant</surname>
                           <given-names>Jo-Ann A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A man, Jesus, meets a woman, the Samaritan, at a well: it must be a betrothal type-scene. But wait! a Jew, Jesus, meets a Samaritan, the woman: this is an entirely different scenario. When two people of different tribes or nations have an encounter at a well, one drinks; the other dies.¹ The inspiring stories in Genesis of Abraham and Isaac’s renunciation of well rights in the interest of peace (Gen 21:25–34; 26:17–22). Dead bodies at wells provide iconic shots in Western film. Perhaps the most familiar examples appear in<italic>Lawrence of Arabia</italic>(David Lean, 1962), 2001:<italic>A</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Siloam, Bethesda, and the Johannine Water Motif</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burge</surname>
                           <given-names>Gary M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The recent discovery of the Second Temple Siloam Pool in Jerusalem has drawn marked interest from the archaeology community, but it also bears important implications for our work in the historicity of the Fourth Gospel. The connection between John and Siloam is well known and was summarized in the John, Jesus, and History Group of the Society of Biblical Literature in 2005 by Urban von Wahlde.¹ In John 9 Jesus heals a blind man, places a mud plaster on his eyes, and then tells him to “go wash in the pool of Siloam.” For John, as every commentary will report,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>John, Jesus, and Virtuoso Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ling</surname>
                           <given-names>Tim</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In November 2009, somewhere over the Atlantic Ocean on a flight to Dallas International Airport, I found myself having a conversation with a fellow passenger. She was returning home from Northern Sudan, where she had been working for an aid organization. She told me about the profound restrictions on the freedom of women to participate in any form of public life that for her characterized life in Sudan. She also, without noting the irony, told me about her work, which involved leading project teams and advocacy, including liaising with local political leaders. Her experience was both real and exceptional. We</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Last Days of Jesus in John and the Synoptics:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Evidence from Astronomy and Chronology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Humphreys</surname>
                           <given-names>Colin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How certain can we be that an event described in John’s Gospel really happened? In science we can often have certainty (despite it frequently being said that this is not the case). For example, if astronomers calculate that a solar eclipse should occur at a particular time in the future, we would be astonished if this did not happen. Similarly, astronomers can run their calculations backwards in time and verify whether eclipses recorded in ancient texts really did occur at the time described. In this essay, I will include science in the armory of techniques available in order to help</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response to the Essays in Part 2</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Merz</surname>
                           <given-names>Annette</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a scholar deeply devoted to research into the historical Jesus, I have been interested in the activities and reflections of the John, Jesus, and History Group for years now. While I am delighted to give my critical thoughts on the articles in part 2 of this interesting volume, I do not intend to point out all stimulating contributions the articles provide to the scholarly debate. Instead, I will strictly confine myself to questions regarding the methodologies applied and the findings obtained with regard to historical-Jesus research. The reader will observe that in some cases the articles have challenged me</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Message of Jesus in John:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introduction to the Issues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The words of Jesus pose the greatest challenge to scholars seeking to identify the message of Jesus within his ministry. If the historical Jesus indeed spoke in parables about the kingdom of God—a near-certain likelihood—why does John’s narrative include no Synoptic-like parables, and why is the kingdom of God mentioned only in John 3:3,5? There Jesus declares access to the kingdom requires being born from above, and in John 18:36–37 he describes the character of his kingdom as one of truth; but unlike the teachings of the Synoptic Jesus, John’s kingdom sayings are contrastive statements (the kingdom</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Aphorisms of Jesus in the Fourth Gospel:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Look at John 4:35</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bridges</surname>
                           <given-names>Linda McKinnish</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literary genre “aphorism” finds full expression in the Gospel of John. Vestiges of the world of orality, aphorisms invite intense reflection and response as they illumine not only the literary landscape of the Gospel but also provide a lens for viewing Jesus tradition in the Gospel of John. This study is indebted to the research of John Dominic Crossan, author of<italic>In Fragments</italic>(1983), who has written the definitive work on the aphorisms of Jesus in the Synoptics. More exploration, however, is needed on the aphorisms of Jesus in John’s Gospel. Although the aphorisms of Jesus in John were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jesus Sayings in the Johannine Discourses:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Proposal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Culpepper</surname>
                           <given-names>R. Alan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Gospel of John poses unique and formidable problems for those interested in identifying traditional sayings of Jesus. The Jesus Seminar, for example, found only one authentic saying of Jesus in the Gospel of John (John 4:44—the dishonored hometown prophet; see Funk, Hoover, and the Jesus Seminar 1993, 412). The difficulty in using traditional criteria for identifying Jesus sayings in John was aptly stated by Norman Perrin.</p>
                     <p>As far as our present knowledge and methodological resources go, the gospel of John is not a source of knowledge of the teaching of Jesus … until we can write a history</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Johannine Dominical Sayings as Metatexts of Synoptic Sayings of Jesus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections On a New Category within Reception History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Theobald</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There’s no denying that the Johannine Jesus speaks entirely differently from the Synoptic Jesus. Whereas the latter proclaims the kingdom<italic>of God</italic>, the former continuously speaks of<italic>himself : “I</italic>am the bread of life” (John 6:35); “<italic>I</italic>have come that you might have life” (John 10:10); “<italic>I</italic>have come from the Father into the world,<italic>I</italic>will leave the world again and go to the Father” (John 16:27).¹ This persistent, penetrating “I” seems to have little to do with the simple statements about God by the Synoptic Jesus, which scholars have taken to be more likely to be historical.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Semitic Language and Syntax within the Speech of the Johannine Jesus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Graham</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the fact that the Fourth Gospel was finalized in a Hellenistic setting, its cultural background and thought forms remain thoroughly Jewish.¹ Recognizing Semitic terms and syntax within the Johannine narrative provides a distinctive window into the Evangelist’s presentation of Jesus. While scholars have tended to assume with varying degrees of certainty that none of the Evangelist’s words go back to the historical Jesus, the presence of this Semitic material nonetheless requires an accounting for its origin. Such an inquiry cannot claim to verify a primitive recollection of the Galilean rabbi within the memory of Johannine tradition, yet it still</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Observations on God’s Agent and Agency in John 5–9:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tradition, Exposition, and Glimpses into History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Borgen</surname>
                           <given-names>Peder</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Gospel of John is the product of expository activity. The most important components are the life of Jesus and the scriptures, transmitted as traditions and subject to applications and other forms of interpretation. The expository activity followed certain methods. Thus a dynamic process was at work, so that the metaphor of “biology” seems more adequate than the metaphor of “anatomy” (Culpepper 1983) as a descriptor for the Fourth Gospel’s character and structure.</p>
                     <p>In my book<italic>Bread from Heaven</italic>(1965), I studied the Old Testament text quoted in John 6:31b, “as it is written, ‘He gave them bread from heaven</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the “Kingdom of God” to “Eternal Life”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Transformation of Theological Language in the Fourth Gospel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frey</surname>
                           <given-names>Jörg</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>439</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is the aim of the John, Jesus and History Project to reinvestigate the historical value of the Fourth Gospel and to question the allegedly critical consensus by which Johannine interpretation has been “dehistoricized” while the quest for the historical Jesus has been “de-johannified” (Anderson 2006b, 43– 100; 2007a, 3). A new search for elements of historical value in John appears warranted in view of the history of research, at least since the beginning of the twentieth century. Back then, the so-called “critical consensus” in Johannine studies was established, with the effect that John was excluded from the quest for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Johannine Son of Man and the Historical Jesus:</title>
                     <subtitle>John 9:35 as a Test Case</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                           <given-names>Benjamin E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>459</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What does the Johannine Son of Man have to do with the historical Jesus? In modern critical scholarship, the answer is: Absolutely nothing. The sentiment of the majority of scholars can still be summed up in the statement of Ernst Käsemann (1964, 32): “We must admit that nowhere in the New Testament is the life story of Jesus so emptied of all real content as it already is here [in the Gospel of John], where it seems to be almost a projection of the present back into the past.” Normally, when John’s Gospel is allowed at all as a source</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What Happened to “Good News for the Poor” in the Johannine Tradition?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Loader</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>469</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the spectrum of possibilities and probabilities in constructing an image of the historical Jesus, the message of “good news for the poor” usually lies at the probability end of the authenticity scale. That Jesus emphasized the poor has the support of source texts and coheres with his social context. As James Dunn (2003, 517) observes, “the proclamation of the good news to the poor evidently ranked at the forefront of Jesus’s conception of his mission.” Key texts include the Beatitudes, in what is generally agreed to be their earlier form, in which Jesus declares, “Blessed are you who are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Some Reflections on the Historicity of the Words “Laying Down Your Life for Your Friends” In John 15:13</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van der Watt</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>481</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Did Jesus utter these words, or were they placed in the mouth of Jesus as nothing more than a figment of the Johannine imagination? This question will be addressed by analyzing these words within their present context in the Gospel and then considering their possible historical value.</p>
                     <p>There are several varied references to “friendship”² or “friends” in John’s Gospel (3:29; 11:11; 15:13,14,15; 19:12; see scholtissek 1996, 209).³ Apart from the Lazarus episode (John 11), John the Baptist refers to himself metaphorically as the “friend of the bridegroom” (3:29; see Coloe 2009, 45–61), and Pilate is called a “friend of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>John and the Historical Jesus:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Response</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dunn</surname>
                           <given-names>James D. G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>493</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The complaint that john’s Gospel has been neglected as a possible, perhaps even highly valuable, source for and contributor to the quest of the historical Jesus is a legitimate one. The issues include: (1) whether the lateninteenth century judgment that John’s Gospel was too different from the Synoptic Gospels to be counted as a historical source for Jesus should be wholly discounted or discounted in significant degree; and (2) whether, despite these differences, the character and details regarding Jesus of Nazareth still shine through John’s Gospel with sufficient clarity to substantiate, qualify, or add to whatever picture of Jesus is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributions of This Volume and the De-Johannification of Jesus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>507</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the essays in this volume demonstrate, the evidentiary basis for excluding the Gospel of John from the historical quest for Jesus is extensively flawed, critically. Many dozens, perhaps hundreds, of instances in which the Fourth Gospel arguably contributes to a fuller understanding of the life and ministry of the prophetic figure from Nazareth require renewed consideration if the fuller database of historical information about Jesus is to be consulted. The question, of course, is how to do so. While it might be safer and less likely to err to exclude John from the quest, such a conservatively reductionistic approach</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>537</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>587</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Ancient Sources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>595</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cx3vmb.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>629</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
