<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ7118.M49 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and history</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Mexico</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music and history</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Mexico</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mexican literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mexican literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Mexico in Verse</book-title>
         <subtitle>A History of Music, Rhyme, and Power</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>NEUFELD</surname>
               <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MATTHEWS</surname>
               <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BEEZLEY</surname>
               <given-names>WILLIAM H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780816531325</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780816501731</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Arizona Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>TUCSON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Arizona Board of Regents</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183p8n6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The history of Mexico is spoken in the voice of ordinary people. In rhymed verse and mariachi song, in letters of romance and whispered words in the cantina, the heart and soul of a nation is revealed in all its intimacy and authenticity.<italic>Mexico in Verse</italic>, edited by Stephen Neufeld and Michael Matthews, examines Mexican history through its poetry and music, the spoken and the written word.Focusing on modern Mexico, from 1840 to the 1980s, this volume examines the cultural venues in which people articulated their understanding of the social, political, and economic change they witnessed taking place during times of tremendous upheaval, such as the Mexican-American War, the Porfiriato, and the Mexican Revolution. The words of diverse peoples-people of the street, of the field, of the cantinas-reveal the development of the modern nation. Neufeld and Matthews have chosen sources so far unexplored by Mexicanist scholars in order to investigate the ways that individuals interpreted-whether resisting or reinforcing-official narratives about formative historical moments.The contributors offer new research that reveals how different social groups interpreted and understood the Mexican experience. The collected essays cover a wide range of topics: military life, railroad accidents, religious upheaval, children's literature, alcohol consumption, and the 1985 earthquake. Each chapter provides a translated song or poem that encourages readers to participate in the interpretive practice of historical research and cultural scholarship. In this regard,<italic>Mexico in Verse</italic>serves both as a volume of collected essays and as a classroom-ready primary document reader.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="360"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beezley</surname>
                           <given-names>William H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Blaring sounds have accompanied life in Mexico since the Spanish arrived in 1521. The clamor of church bells, merchant squares, military drums, and encouraging shouts of mule drivers and coachmen have become increasingly shrill in later centuries with political and advertising loudspeakers mounted on VWs, screaming radios, and deafening traffic jams, with drivers who understand the green light as “Honk your horn!” This teeth-clenching stridency has captured the attention of residents and visitors, and been described by authors, journalists, and foreign travelers who emphasize dissonance as symptomatic of the multiethnic society and crushing traffic.</p>
                     <p>Yet imbricated in the panorama of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mexico in Verse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Songs and wordplay represent an everyday part of the Mexican experience. Innumerable soundscapes fill the street. The chimes of vendors, the cacophony of traffic, the susurration of conversations, they surround you. Most striking, music of all kinds let you know precisely where you stand. The whistling codes of<italic>chilangos</italic>turn slang phrases into tune, the brass trios mark the end of the day with clarion calls, the wandering singers haunt every cantina, and the matched mariachis serenade tourists. All of these present a profound facet of how we remember, experience, and know Mexico.¹ This quintessential element of identity,<italic>mexicanidad</italic>(Mexican-ness),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Sister at War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mexican Women’s Poetry and the U.S.-Mexican War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Conway</surname>
                           <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most promising areas of future research into literature and national identity in early republican Mexico is the literature of the U.S.-Mexican War of 1846–1848. Mexican literary responses to the United States’ invasion of its territory, and to Mexico’s continued defeats on the battlefield, constitute an invaluable archive for examining the emergence of Mexican nationalism. Indeed, during the war and its aftermath, Mexican writers recognized the value of national unity as they never had before, because they saw their defeat on the battlefield as a function of their political disunity. “A nation is nothing but a large</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>The Sly Mockeries of Military Men:</title>
                     <subtitle>Corridos and Poetry as Critical Voice for the Porfirian Army</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Neufeld</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The patio of the barracks rang with amateur song most ordinary nights in Mexico’s late nineteenth century. Improvised and regimental instruments accompanied the enthusiastic men and women of the army as they entertained themselves performing corridos (folk songs) about life, love, and war. Meanwhile, in small chambers some three stories above, young officers set pen to paper creating verse and poetry as an exercise in cultivation and culture. Quiet reflections of their own were nonetheless interrupted or perhaps inspired by the boisterous tunes that floated up from below. The unique mixtures of these peoples, and their verses, sheds light on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Track from Beyond the Grave:</title>
                     <subtitle>Challenges to Porfirian Policymaking in Popular Verse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Matthews</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dictatorship of Porfirio Díaz (1876–1911) marked a period of rapid and expansive railway development. The growth of the country’s transportation network, above all other infrastructural accomplishments undertaken by his regime, provided the most tangible example of material progress based on massive foreign investment. The year that Díaz came to power, the nation possessed only 640 kilometers of track. By 1884, the country witnessed that transportation grid expand to 5,731 kilometers and to 12,173 kilometers by 1898. In Díaz’s final year as president, 19,280 kilometers of tracks, with another 8,000 in trunk lines, crisscrossed the nation.¹ This remarkable achievement</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>“I’m Going to Write You a Letter”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Coplas, Love Letters, and Courtship Literacy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>French</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The preceding stanza of popular lyrical poetry serves as a brief introduction to some of the interrelated themes taken up in this chapter as well as to the source used to do so, a form of nonnarrative verse known as the<italic>copla</italic>. In contrast to its much better-known relation, the corrido—a narrative form that tells a story about an event or occurrence by means of a series of stanzas that are related to each other, and in which the story emerges out of the entire piece that forms a single coherent entity unto itself—the copla is comprised of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Singing for Cristo Rey:</title>
                     <subtitle>Masculinity, Piety, and Dissent in Mexico’s Cristero Rebellion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Andes</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen J. C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mexico’s epic civil war known as the Cristero Rebellion (1926–1929) was less than a year old when a contingent of Catholic insurgents led by Pedro Quintanar established control over the region of Huejuquilla el Alto, Jalisco. From their stronghold in Huejuquilla, cristero rebels attacked federal troops and pro-government militias (<italic>agraristas</italic>) in many of the country’s central-western states: Zacatecas, Jalisco, Nayarit, and Durango.¹ The constant raiding by Quintanar’s soldiers won praise and plaudits from cristero allies and sympathizers. However, it enraged, infuriated, and generally exasperated local anti-cristero agraristas in Valparaíso, Zacatecas, a town just thirty miles away from Huejuquilla. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>El Niño Proletario:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jesús Sansón Flores and the New Revolutionary Redeemer, 1935–1938</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Albarrán</surname>
                           <given-names>Elena Jackson</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With this stark imagery, radical poet Jesús Sansón Flores closed the introductory remarks to his volume<italic>El niño proletario: poemas clasistas</italic>(<italic>The Proletarian Child: Classist Poems</italic>). A young, self-designated “revolutionary poet” from the state of Michoacán, Sansón Flores had published widely since the 1920s on social and political issues, garnering a reputation as an ardent defender of the oppressed classes. A book of children’s poetry hardly stood to launch him into international literary fame. Little more than a cardboard-bound pamphlet of fifteen simple didactic verses for children, this collection nevertheless captured the essence of Sansón Flores’s Marxist social critique at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>“That Mariachi Band and That Tequila”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Modernity, Identity, and Cultural Politics in Alcohol Songs of the Mexican Golden Age Cinema</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Toxqui</surname>
                           <given-names>Áurea</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the late 1930s to the 1950s, Mexican cinema experienced its greatest era, known as the Golden Age. Many factors made possible the development of a truly national cinema at the time. For experts focusing on economics and politics, World War II was a catalyst. For those highlighting cultural and social reasons, the people involved in the movie industry were responsible for this blossoming. However, for the common Mexican and Latin American aficionado, the music, songs, and performers were the key element of the films produced. Many melodramas and comedy movies used popular music to emphasize their drama and romance,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Let Us Weep Among the Dust:</title>
                     <subtitle>Recycled Poems of 1968 and Operas of Earthquake</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ledwon</surname>
                           <given-names>Amanda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>298</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of<italic>los topos</italic>(the human “moles”) who dug through the collapsed buildings after the 1985 earthquake likened it to the aftermath of 1968 because of the similar echoes of devastation. Tlatelolco, the site of the student-led march, appeared again as a war zone, and although he “barely participated” in the student movement in 1968, that year Hector Méndez witnessed the birth of a new social conscience brought about by the massacre of the students at the Plaza de las Tres Culturas (Plaza of Three Cultures). That initially peaceful demonstration resulted in hundreds of students killed by the directive of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lyrics have given voice to the Mexican experience even since the earliest eras of the conquest and colony. In 1604, Bernardo de Balbuena’s voluminous poetic work<italic>Grandeza mexicana</italic>told the Empire of the land’s riches and wealth. New Spain represented a utopian potential:</p>
                     <p>For centuries scholars took this work more or less at face value. Here, they asserted, was lyrical proof of colonial optimism, pride, and potential. Contemporaries knew better. Close interpretations of the political and social context of the time now offer us a different reading from the tradition of Balbuena as lauding greatness. The tract, it seems, reflected</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p8n6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
