<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX1795.I57I52 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectual life</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christian college teachers</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious life</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Education</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>In Search of the Whole</book-title>
         <subtitle>Twelve Essays on Faith and Academic Life</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Haughey</surname>
               <given-names>John C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>EDITOR</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781589017818</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1589017811</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781589017962</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">158901796X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>WASHINGTON, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Georgetown University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2tt43w"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The contributors to this inspiring anthology meet the challenge that everyone faces: that of becoming a whole person in both their personal and professional lives. John C. Haughey, SJ, has gathered twelve professionals in higher education from a variety of disciplines-philosophy, theology, health care, business, and administration. What they have in common reflects the creative understanding of the meaning of "catholic" as Haughey has found it to operate in Catholic higher education. Each essay in the first six chapters describes how its author has assembled a unique whole from within his or her particular area of academic competence. The last six chapters are more autobiographical, with each author describing what has become central to his or her identity. All twelve are "anticipating an entirety" with each contributing a coherence that is as surprising as it is delightful.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="232"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Wholeness through Science, Justice, and Love</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Byrne</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>For as long as I can remember, I have loved science. Even before I knew that science was the category, I loved learning about the universe and just about everything within it. I think I was probably born with this love, but I was also fortunate to come of age in the late 1950s and 1960s, when science permeated the cultural atmosphere around me. The United States was then engaged in a great romance with science, and there was a rich and steady flow of scientific writing to stimulate my passion for learning about the natural world. Scientists were constantly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>From Discovery to Risk</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crysdale</surname>
                           <given-names>Cynthia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>When I was an associate dean in the School of Theology and Religious Studies at The Catholic University of America, I regularly received calls from prospective students asking, “If I come to study at CUA, can I be assured that I will be getting the true teachings of the magisterium?” What always struck me about this question was the latent concern for certainty in faith, the assumption that theology is all about correct propositions. I was also struck by the canon within a canon—most of these students did not know the full body of magisterial teachings. I often replied</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Professional Education as Transformation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deahl</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>I have been for the last thirteen years the dean of the College of Professional Studies at Marquette University in Milwaukee, Wisconsin. The college is one of eleven colleges and schools at Marquette and is committed to educating working professionals—adult, nontraditional students—throughout southeastern Wisconsin.</p>
                     <p>While writing this chapter, I have been working with my staff, faculty, and advisors in completing a strategic plan for the college as we prepare to celebrate the fifteenth anniversary in 2011. This plan is part of a university-wide effort designed to meet one of the critical needs that we face in Catholic higher</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Learning to Love the Law of the Sea</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>George</surname>
                           <given-names>William P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>For many if not most doctoral students, the choice of a dissertation topic is a matter not only of importance but, until the choice becomes clear, also of obscurity. At least it was for me. Late in my first year of doctoral studies in the mid-1980s, I had yet to settle on a general topic that would shape my remaining coursework and outside research. Having spent four years in Zambia, and with a background in philosophy and theology primarily in the Catholic tradition, I entered the University of Chicago Divinity School’s program in ethics and society with vague ideas about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Catholicity and Faculty Seminars</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liddy</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>When I was a young student in the 1950s I came across a book titled <italic>The Wisdom of Catholicism</italic>.¹ I liked it very much and bought a copy as a present for my parents. It was edited by Anton Pegis of the Medieval Institute in Toronto and contained selections from the Catholic classics: Augustine’s <italic>Confessions</italic> and <italic>City of God</italic>, Thomas Aquinas’s <italic>Summae</italic>, Dante’s <italic>Divine Comedy</italic>, the <italic>Imitation of Christ</italic>, Teresa of Avila’s <italic>Interior Castle</italic>, John of the Cross’s <italic>Ascent of Mount Carmel</italic>, Blaise Pascal’s <italic>Pensées</italic>, and John Henry Newman’s <italic>Apologia pro vita sua</italic>. There were also more recent selections: papal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>The “Real World” of Business</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stebbins</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>When I completed my doctorate in systematic theology at Boston College in 1991, I fully intended to spend the next few decades of my life teaching courses in that field in a university setting. As it turned out, the years I spent in graduate school prepared me for a somewhat different future.</p>
                     <p>At its root systematic theology is the effort to produce a fully integrated Christian worldview. It is carried out from the perspective of faith (in Anselm of Canterbury’s famous twelfth-century formulation theology is found <italic>fides quaerens intellectum</italic>, “faith seeking understanding”). Systematic theology takes as given the truth of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Attaining Harmony as a Hindu-Christian</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amaladoss</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>I am an Indian Christian and a Jesuit. I was born and grew up as an Indian. My priestly formation has been in traditional scholastic philosophy and in a theology in transformation after the Second Vatican Council. I have been a student also of Hindu philosophy, theology, and spirituality. I have lived through the aftermath of the Second Vatican Council. I have been involved in interreligious dialogue between Hindus, Christians, and an occasional Muslim for thirty-five years. All this has led me to an awareness today of being a Hindu-Christian. I am encouraged by the thought that my guru, Jesuit</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Arriving at a Christocentric Universe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Delio</surname>
                           <given-names>Ilia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>From where does a theological vision begin? What gives rise to theological insight and, in particular, to my insight? I ask these questions not only as a matter of self-reflection but out of wondrous surprise that I am a theologian because, truth be told, I never intended to be one. Unlike the typical theology student finely tuned in philosophy, theology, and classical languages, I was a hard-core student of science who took only the necessary courses in theology and philosophy to meet the requirements of my undergraduate institution. As a science major I believed that science held the key to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Le Petit Philosophe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Heelan</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>My family tells me—usually with good-humored teasing—that when I was baptized, my godfather, a lawyer and a philosopher of sorts, looked bemusedly at me in the cradle and said, “<italic>Le petit philosophe</italic>!” Given who the <italic>philosophes</italic> were, it could have been an ironic lawyerly comment on the promises just made on my behalf; but in deference to the prophetic genre, this is where my story begins.</p>
                     <p>I grew up in a pretty seaside town, Dalkey, on the south side of the River Liffey in Ireland. Dalkey was once the home of George Bernard Shaw and is today the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Toward a Catholic Christianity:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Personal Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McCarthy</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Angelo Roncalli became Pope John XXIII when I was sixteen. After eight years of parochial school and three years in a Jesuit high school, I thought I knew what it meant to be Catholic. And in one sense I did. I knew the liturgy of the Mass, the biblical stories, the seven sacraments, the Apostles’ Creed, a partial history of the Church, the importance of love and forgiveness. This early formation begun at home has never deserted me. Still, the unexpected selection of Pope John XXIII began a process of personal transformation that continues to this day. Søren Kierkegaard says</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>The Hunting and the Haunting</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Steele</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>I have written well over a hundred poems that are to one degree or another after works of art—usually paintings. When I was asked recently about the attraction of such a topic, it occurred to me that the attraction lies in part in the fact that those works are finished things: whether or not they sport actual frames, they are all in some sense framed. Another way of saying this is that they are the polar opposite of the chaotic; and for reasons in part instinctive and in part educational, I do love the manifestly coherent—a brick wall</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Attaining Harmony with the Earth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vanin</surname>
                           <given-names>Cristina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>I teach at St. Jerome’s University, a small Catholic liberal arts university in southwestern Ontario. When I returned to work after an eight-month parental leave following the adoption of our two daughters from Ecuador, I indicated to close friends that on the day that I first met Sofia and Daniela, I felt as if I had been dropped off a very, very high cliff—from the life of work and relationship that I had known and had been living for a long time, into the incredible life of parenting two little girls in another country and culture, in another language,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>These twelve essays have several things in common. For one, they are eminently original. The authors have plumbed their inimitable subjectivities in ways that make them accessible to the reader. This volume is a case of the multiplication of the loaves or, to mix metaphors, an instance of what can be produced when a haunting is moved by a hunting that can locate its catch with words. I read these authors through a theological lens and do so unapologetically. So I see their haunted hunting representing twelve unique cuts into the catholicity of the mind and its fecundity when it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt43w.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
