<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8c0t</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Year's Work in the Oddball Archive</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>EBURNE</surname>
               <given-names>JONATHAN P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROOF</surname>
               <given-names>JUDITH</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253018472</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253018519</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">025301851X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>BLOOMINGTON; INDIANAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18z4hcm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The modern age is no stranger to the cabinet of curiosities, the freak show, or a drawer full of odds and ends. These collections of oddities engagingly work against the rationality and order of the conventional archive found in a university, a corporation, or a governmental holding. In form, methodology, and content, The Year's Work in the Oddball Archive offers a counterargument to a more reasoned form of storing and recording the avant-garde (or the post-avant-garde), the perverse, the off, the bent, the absurd, the quirky, the weird, and the queer. To do so, it positions itself within the history of mirabilia launched by curiosity cabinets starting in the mid-fifteenth century and continuing to the present day. These archives (or are they counter-archives?) are located in unexpected places-the doorways of Katrina homes, the cavity of a cow, the remnants of extinct animals, an Internet site-and they offer up "alternate modes of knowing" to the traditional archive.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="448"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HISTORY OF THE COLLECTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Oddball Archive is a collection whose full range we are only beginning to explore. Culled from the sidebars of mainstream culture and thought, its holdings document the eccentricities of culture, thought, and archivization alike. There exists a nearly infinite expanse of such material: anomaly, after all, is the perpetual yield of any system. The history of cultural production is replete with abandoned prototypes, rejected models, crackpot theories, and antiquated media; the permutations are endless. We all too often discount the value of this material, however. Though it may be limitless in scope, its idiosyncrasy makes it difficult to take</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ORGANIZATIONAL NOTE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACCESS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxiv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[BOX I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the United States, even the most confidential archives become the dominion of popular culture; the more secret, the more classified or off-limits, the better. Reciprocally, all popular culture becomes archival material, finding its way into an oddball archive of one sort or another. In its perpetual accumulation of tales, artifacts, and stories about accumulating tales and artifacts, American culture enfolds itself in weirdo predilections.</p>
                     <p>Littering public consciousness in much the same way that travel stickers adorn the backs of RVS, this pervasive archive situates itself as the perpetual unearthing of material long buried in the back alleys of America’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“PAWNING, PICKING, STORING, HOARDING: ARCHIVING AMERICA ON REALITY TELEVISION”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Campana</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bale</surname>
                           <given-names>Theodore</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What kind of archive is America? Let’s ask the unforgettable Palm Apodaca (Helena Kallianiotes) in Bob Rafelson and Carole Eastman’s 1970 classic<italic>film Five Easy Pieces</italic>, in the midst of which two mismatched lovers (played by Jack Nicholson and Karen Black) on a road trip pick up a stranded lesbian couple (played by Kallianiotes and Toni Basil). As the lesbian couple unloads a heap of luggage and a conspicuous sewing machine, they complain about their unreliable car, a recent purchase. They are headed to Alaska, they reluctantly admit, which they imagine as a clean place free of garbage. Their conversation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“GERM WARS: DIRTY HANDS, DRINKING LIPS, AND DIXIE CUPS”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sattar</surname>
                           <given-names>Atia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The conflict between germs and cups first came to my attention in a laboratory at the Indiana Medical History Museum, where I stumbled across an illustration by Hoosier cartoonist Gaar Williams (1880–1935) entitled<italic>Meet Me at the Town Pump. Signed, a Typhoid Germ</italic>(figure 2.1). In this drawing, a typhoid germ appears as an amphibious creature with webbed hands and feet, sitting at the edge of a wooden tub filled with water. In his right hand is the common dipper or public drinking cup of the day, a single metal can for everyone in the town, attached by chain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“THE ARCHIVE OF THE ARCHIVE OF THE ARCHIVE: THE FEMA SIGNS OF POST-KATRINA NEW ORLEANS AND THE VÉVÉS OF VODOUN”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McCoy</surname>
                           <given-names>Beth A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Serving already as archive to the archive of the Atlantic slave trade, the city of New Orleans took on further archival depth when the levees failed after Hurricane Katrina. Throughout the flooded city appeared painted symbols: the cruciform US&amp;R (urban search and rescue) signs devised by FEMA, the Federal Emergency Management Administration enfolded after 9/11 into the Department of Homeland Security. Used by FEMA task forces, the Louisiana Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, and other private and public entities involved in search and rescue, the US&amp;R signs were to function both as symptom of and vector for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[BOX II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tinkerers or pundits, visionaries or eccentrics, oddballs sometimes make their own archives. Surprisingly, the archives of some of history’s most anomalous figures are rarely themselves anomalous but instead come to appear exemplary because their organizing figures have emerged in some way from the pack. Oddball personae collect followings; their followers, in turn, are often the ones left in charge of collecting the oddballs’ life’s work, their leavings. The Kinsey archives, no less than the papers of the Marquis de Sade or the drawings of Adolf Wölfli, may now be managed by professional librarians, but they were once gathered and conserved</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>“MARCUSE’S UNREASON: THE BIOLOGY OF REVOLUTION”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blyn</surname>
                           <given-names>Robin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“We can use the word revolution again for the first time in many years,” Douglass Kellner declared in October 2011.¹ The scene was not Tahrir Square or the streets of Tunis. Nor was it Zuccotti Park. Rather, Kellner was speaking at the University of Pennsylvania, at the Fourth Biennial Conference of the International Herbert Marcuse Society. It was clearly a moment for Kellner and his audience to savor; together, the Arab Spring and Occupy protests of 2011 seemed to vindicate the very idea of revolution and with it the work of a philosopher variously dismissed as impractical, irrational, irrelevant, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“THE MADNESS OF SLAVOJ ŽIŽEK”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Allen</surname>
                           <given-names>Dennis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are literally thousands of clips of Slavoj Žižek available on the Internet, but perhaps the most entertaining one is a YouTube excerpt from Astra Taylor’s succinctly entitled 2005 documentary,<italic>Žižek!</italic>Posted as “Philosophy from a Bed View (by Žižek),” the clip seems singularly apt for our purposes if only because, in the process of defining the project of philosophy, Žižek touches on one of the key questions that this collection of essays is intended to address: What is the relation between reason and unreason? Sliding across a series of binaries, Žižek articulates the difference between “true” philosophers and “madmen”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>“FISH KIT”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eburne</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 2000, an event billed as the New York City CowParade exhibited roughly five hundred fiberglass cow statues around the city. Decorated “by artists and schoolchildren” and displayed on sidewalks throughout the five boroughs, the statues were the trademark of CowParade Holdings, a private, for-profit development company that sponsors such “CowParades” in cities around the world.¹ As the company’s website explains, “CowParade is helping to showcase the local arts community and stimulate civic spirit and pride which ultimately raises funds for local charities that in turn benefit the community.” Though a private corporation, its interests are manifestly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[BOX III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>All archives promise – and ineluctably fail – to offer a bulwark against the passage of time. In their task of making up for lost memory – that is, for the loss of ways of thinking, as well as for the passing of successive eras – archives carry out their functions incompletely. Archives mark what has been lost in their preservation of remnants that remain incomplete in what we imagine to be their testimony to a much fuller moment. Can we think of archives as time machines that bring us into direct contact with the documents and relics of a forgotten age? Or do</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>“THE EIGHTEENTH-CENTURY ARCHIVES DU MONDE: THE QUESTION OF AGENCY IN EXTINCTION STORIES”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sweet</surname>
                           <given-names>Timothy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reckoning with the fossil remains of unfamiliar creatures, naturalists in the eighteenth century began to historicize nature. The era’s preeminent naturalist, Georges-Louis Leclerc, comte de Buffon, articulated the program for this new kind of history by conceptualizing the earth itself as an archive: “As in civil history, one consults titles, one researches medals, one deciphers antique inscriptions to determine the epochs of human revolutions and discover the dates of moral events; similarly, in natural history, one must search the archives of the world, draw old monuments from the bowels of the earth, collect their debris, and assemble in a body</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>“MODERNIST HETEROCHRONY, EVOLUTIONARY BIOLOGY, AND THE CHIMERA OF TIME”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tung</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Spencer Wells, in his PBS documentary<italic>Journey of Man,</italic>claims that there is “a time machine hidden in our genes.”¹ This Wells, unrelated to the literary figure H.G. Wells (at least in the short term), is the genetic anthropologist in charge of the Genographic Project, an international study funded by<italic>National Geographic</italic>and IBM that traces individual Y-chromosomes from all corners of the earth back to a recognizably “modern” human leaving Africa around sixty thousand years ago. The time travel central to Wells’s research is guided by two-hundred-dollar self-testing kits, tracking devices sold in large part to ancestry-obsessed Americans, and,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>“THERE IS AS YET INSUFFICIENT DATA FOR A MEANINGFUL ANSWER: INHUMANISM AT THE LITERARY LIMIT”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jaffe</surname>
                           <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among its other merits, Vilém Flusser’s strange treatise on<italic>Vampyroteuthis infernalis</italic>is a fable about information at the literary limit. Comparing “the vampire squid from hell” and<italic>Homo sapiens sapiens,</italic>Flusser proposes a fantastic convergence that links the odd existence of a tentacled life-form, complexly equipped for probing the deep ocean, to the inhuman consequences of our emerging system of new media. Humans increasingly approximate the strategies of invertebrate life, he writes: “As our interest in objects began to wane, we created media that have enabled us to rape human brains, forcing them to store immaterial information. We have built</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[BOX IV Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is it that we think we already know? If we know it, why do we gather it, ignore it, refind it as a new wonder? What kinds of forgetting do archives enable? If we put our faith in the well known, if we place confidence in common sense, to what extent do we risk credulity? Hoaxes, as Judith Roof tells us, operate through the archive of the hoax – through our unforgotten knowledge that what seems too good to be true cannot be true. Even the very commonness of such wisdom – the commonness of common sense – can, as the success</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>“PERSONIFYING LA CON, OR POST HOAX, ERGO PROPER HOAX”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roof</surname>
                           <given-names>Judith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1905 famous Bloomsbury hoaxer Horace de Vere Cole led a gang of costumed Cantabrigians to Cambridge under the guise of the sultan of Zanzibar and his entourage. The real sultan was scheduled to visit Buckingham Palace the same day. The group was greeted by the mayor of Cambridge at an official reception. No one questioned the authenticity of the group of four undergraduates plus interpreter, all wearing dark makeup and dressed in Middle Eastern garb. How could that be? How could the mayor not see through the makeup? What appearance did the five offer that overcame what the mayor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>“THE ELEVENTH COMMANDMENT”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Farred</surname>
                           <given-names>Grant</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>336</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is only one way to properly understand Thomas Paine. He is the expatriate Briton whose intense belief in radical republican politics made him, this son of Norfolk Quakers, the writer of the American Revolution. Paine is the thinker whose political imaginary led him, in the moment before the thirteen colonies became independent, to coin no less than the phrase the “United States of America.” Paine’s faith in the American Revolution led him to dedicate Rights of Man, a “small treatise in defence of . . . [the] Principles of Freedom,” to President George Washington, “that the Rights of Man</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>“THE ARCHIVE THAT KNEW TOO LITTLE: THE INTERNATIONAL NECRONAUTICAL SOCIETY AND THE AVANT-GARDE”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morton</surname>
                           <given-names>Seth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>364</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over one hundred years after the first Futurist manifesto, the historical avant-garde looks like an oddity that died long ago. Perhaps nothing has served the avant-garde better than its own death. In death, the avant-garde is memorialized and archived. Its antiart position has been absorbed by the art world, and its logics inform mass culture and high art alike. Although the historical avant-garde failed to make good on revolutionary ideals, avant-garde logics continue to evolve and diversify across our entire cultural media landscape, from Dada to Monty Python and Saturday<italic>Night Live.</italic>This is the odd thing about the avant-garde:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>“TO PROPHESY POST HOC” THE CURIOUS AFTERLIVES OF ODDBALL ARCHIVES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>David L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a curious, if not downright odd, first thing to say about<italic>The Oddball Archive</italic>that, above all else, it has spoken to me at the level of politics. After all, particularly as it is practiced in the contemporary academy, politics or political science is a discipline famed for its “seriousness”; its social-science predictive ways; its focus on institutions, structures of power, and governance; and its avoidance of the messy stuff of culture, agency, and desire. Could anything be less oddball, less hospitable to the playfulness of hoaxers and hoarders, or the incongruity of dissected fish and Dixie cups?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>409</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18z4hcm.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
