<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BR333.3.M55 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Luther, Martin, 1483–1546</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy and religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Hidden God</book-title>
         <subtitle>Luther, Philosophy, and Political Theology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MJAALAND</surname>
               <given-names>MARIUS TIMMANN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253018168</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253018205</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">025301820X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Marius Timmann Mjaaland</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt189ttzv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this phenomenological reading of Luther, Marius Timmann Mjaaland shows that theological discourse is never philosophically neutral and always politically loaded. Raising questions concerning the conditions of modern philosophy, religion, and political ideas, Marius Timmann Mjaaland follows a dark thread of thought back to its origin in Martin Luther. Thorough analyses of the genealogy of secularization, the political role of the apocalypse, the topology of the self, and the destruction of metaphysics demonstrate the continuous relevance of this highly subtle thinker.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A philosophical approach to Martin Luther allows a less doctrinal access to some of his controversial but rather original ideas and methodological insights. The challenge is that such an approach has hardly been ventured before, at least not in the English-speaking literature: to analyze the seminal work of the<italic>philosopher</italic>Martin Luther. Many studies of Luther from a comparative philosophical perspective have been written over the years, for instance, his relation to Plato or Aristotle, Kant or Heidegger; but it is difficult to find contemporary efforts at reading Luther philosophically.¹ The point of such an approach is not to reject</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>History, Hermeneutics, and Political Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Authors from the early sixteenth century have often been interpreted along confessional lines of division. In this book such differences play only a minor role, when any at all, and I have no ambitions of continuing or enhancing the old confessional discussions on Luther and Erasmus. Since Oberman, it has become more common to see both the Reformation (Lutheran, Calvinist, Radical) and Counter-Reformation as parts of a major historical and intellectual shift in the history of Europe, and thus to transcend the more narrow-minded apologetics in favor of one side or the other.¹ I even find it necessary to transcend</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Philosophy:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Grammar of Destruction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The destruction of metaphysics is a favored topic in twentieth-century philosophy, in terms of a positivist critique, an overcoming, an<italic>Abbau,</italic>a rejection, or a deconstruction of traditional metaphysical notions and concepts. But where and when does this discussion of a general destruction of metaphysics start? I argue that the<italic>Heidelberg Disputation</italic>plays a key role here.¹ In this short disputation, Luther presents forty theses giving a principal justification of his position, twenty-eight of them theological and the other twelve philosophical. In the explanation to thesis 21, he argues that the cross is a good thing, since it<italic>destructs</italic>(<italic>destruuntur;</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Topology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The questions of place and topology require separate consideration. The use of topics as an analytical approach goes back to Aristotle’s<italic>Topics,</italic>where he defines the conditions for the art of dialectics. The topological approach is reserved for arguments based on commonly held opinions, Greek<italic>endoxa</italic>. Thus, they differ from the<italic>questions</italic>that are treated by way of syllogisms. Aristotle gives no definition of a topos, but the topoi are referred to as places from where his arguments can be invented, elaborated, or discovered.¹</p>
                     <p>In the early 1520s, topics as a philosophical and theological approach was rediscovered by humanist and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Quest for Immorality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Right from the beginning, there was a remarkable moral tenor in Luther’s criticism of the church authorities.¹ From 1517 onward he criticized the church for operating with double standards and undermining the prayers of penitence.² He accused the responsible authorities of organizing the confession of sins economically through the production and sale of indulgences. Hence, the moral emphasis of his criticism is striking when he attacks the praxis of exploiting poor people and their fear of Hell to the benefit of the church, the pope, and the clergy. His attacks on immorality within the church have contributed considerably to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Quest for Destruction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luther and philosophy is a topic that requires careful consideration, since there is a certain discrepancy between Luther’s rhetoric and his actual involvement in philosophical issues. His many more or less uncouth comments on philosophers as sophists, mad, or impious, of reason as a whore, and so forth, should be treated with a grain of salt and ascribed to his image as a barbarian and simple spokesman of the truth from the northern provinces of the Roman Empire. This is an image ascribed to him by his opponents and enemies and exploited in lampoons and caricatures, but it is also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>The Quest for Clarity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of Luther’s most portentous debates was his controversy with Pope Leo X. After the<italic>Ninety-five Theses</italic>and subsequent articles had been condemned by the pope in<italic>Exurge Domine</italic>, Luther wrote an apology in the form of forty-one theses with extended explanations in the pamphlet called<italic>Assertio</italic>(1520). It was published only a few weeks before Luther was finally excluded from the Roman Catholic Church on January 3, 1521. It is written by a man who is already more outside than inside the community of the holy and the orthodox. Thus almost excommunicated he communicates back<italic>in,</italic>to those who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>The Quest for Sovereignty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Toward the end of his life, Luther warned against the danger of a collapse, of speculations, of mystifications, and of political violence inherent to this concept which is hardly a concept at all, the<italic>deus absconditus</italic>.¹ Luther had introduced the term for at least three different reasons: first, in accordance with the mystical theology of Dionysius Areopagita in his<italic>Lectures on the Psalms</italic>(1513/15); second, as a destruction of speculative theology in the<italic>Heidelberg Disputation</italic>(1518); and third, with reference to God’s majesty in<italic>De servo arbitrio</italic>(1525). There are, more precisely, two different notions of divine hiddenness in<italic>De</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>The Quest for Subjectivity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luther’s ambivalent distance to the entire framework of metaphysical discourse was polemically presented in<italic>Heidelberg Disputation</italic>. What Luther formulated there as a program of the<italic>destruction</italic>of metaphysics (regarding the “wisdom of the wise”) is now unfolded as a questioning of the metaphysical tradition to which Luther belongs, not only in order to leave it behind, but also to reformulate and thus<italic>recover</italic>the basic philosophical problems raised within that tradition. In this sense the problem of free will, which Luther rejects as illusory, is significant because it<italic>conceals</italic>a number of other questions, such as the question of necessity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Deus Absconditus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On one point Erasmus of Rotterdam and Martin Luther perfectly agree: There are too many myths circulating in society, church, and academia, and too much superstition, ignorance, and mysticism surrounding the notion of God. Malicious tongues would probably comment that things haven’t changed a lot over the five centuries that have passed. For the discussion on the hidden and mysterious god,<italic>deus absconditus,</italic>this general estimation of beliefs and superstitions turns out to be significant. Erasmus claims that the very notion of<italic>‘deus absconditus’</italic>contributes to the confusion and the speculations concerning the nature of God and distracts from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Topology of the Self in Luther</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The hidden God is to a certain extent a neglected<italic>topos</italic>of modernity, either in the form of a passive forgetfulness or an active exclusion of this topic due to its inconvenient, problematic—indeed, rather<italic>unmodern</italic>—connotations. In particular Protestant theology seems to be dominated by a rationalistic tendency up to the Enlightenment, which is strictly opposed to this crucial distinction in Luther’s thought and therefore tends to exclude it from the scope of theological inquiry.¹ The major philosophers are more apt to raise the basic questions concerning the conditions for thought, including the limits of reason and the distinction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Kant versus Luther on Self-Consciousness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whereas Heidegger draws a more or less direct line of modernity from the foundation of modern subjectivity in Descartes up to its fulfillment in Nietzsche’s will to power, Schürmann argues for a more complex analysis of the period, for instance, by including Luther as a key thinker of modernity. Within this period, there are significant changes connected to subjectivity as the<italic>site</italic>of thought, but he argues that the new site allows for different perspectives and approaches—and that the basic shift comes up already with Luther. Hence, the historical narrative of modernity as continuous<italic>progress</italic>is rejected in favor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Spacing the Hidden God:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Temporal/Spatial Divide</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If this<italic>topos</italic>of a difference between the hidden and revealed god, as discussed by Luther in<italic>De servo arbitrio,</italic>is situated prior to temporal distinctions, it remains<italic>anachronistic</italic>in its relation to the<italic>chronology</italic>of history. It is, insofar as it “is,”<italic>older</italic>than beings and prior to their coming into existence. This anachronism or, rather, anachrony of the place would then be the premise for understanding its history and its genealogy. It remains non-contemporary with us and with itself.¹ It will continuously escape our efforts at a temporal identification of it as belonging to a particular era or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>The Power of Interpretation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Controversies on the Book of Daniel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A new debate on political theology has emerged since the turn of the millennium, due to a general shift in the understanding of the relationship between religion and secularity in modern societies. After José Casanova’s<italic>Public Religions in the Modern World</italic>(1994) and Habermas’s speech on faith and knowledge (2001), where he coined the term “post-secular society,” there have been a number of controversies on the issue, including debates on this specific term.¹ Hans Joas has pointed out that the term is misguiding, since there has never been such a thing as a<italic>secular</italic>society, not even in the modern</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>Political Theology of the German Revolutions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rise of the Peasants’ War in Germany 1524–1526 is intimately connected with the events of the Reformation.¹ It was not the only uproar of peasants in fifteenth- and sixteenth-century Europe but definitely the most important one, and the only upheaval deserving the name of a revolution—in the modern, political sense of the term. It also produced one of the earliest charters in favor of more general freedom rights in Europe, the so-called Twelve Articles of Memmingen (1525). There were other manifestos before and after this one, but none of them had a similar influence on political events.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>The Hidden God of Revolution and Apocalypse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The decisive role Thomas Müntzer played during the German Peasants’ War of 1525 and his prophetic statement about the people being free later did encourage Friedrich Engels to see him as a precursor of all later revolutionaries. Engels’s interpretation is deeply influenced by the Left Hegelian historian Wilhelm Zimmermann, himself a politically radical scholar who first identified Thomas Müntzer as a revolutionary figure.¹ Engels sees the incidents during the revolution of 1525 and the following counterrevolution as paradigmatic for the historical dynamic of revolutions in general. Indeed, this also allows him to relocate the historical origin of the communist revolution</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt189ttzv.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
