<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Education</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Explorations and Encounters in French</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FORNASIERO</surname>
               <given-names>JEAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MROWA-HOPKINS</surname>
               <given-names>COLETTE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780980672336</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780980672329</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Adelaide Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>AUSTRALIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Contributors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.20851/j.ctt1sq5wjr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The essays selected for inclusion in Explorations and Encounters in French bring together many of the current research strands in French Studies today, tapping into current pedagogical trends, analysing contemporary events in France, examining the Franco-Australian past, while reviewing teaching practice and the culture of teaching.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="322"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword and Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Federation of Associations of Teachers of French in Australia is a young federation whose genesis goes back to 1996. Australia had active associations of teachers of French in every state but with relatively little contact between them, other than the exchange of newsletters. There was, however, a national link amongst the universities whose association, the Australian Society of French Studies (ASFS), held an annual conference.</p>
                     <p>1996 saw the World Congress of the Fédération Internationale des Professeurs de Français (FIPF) in Tokyo. At that time, the South Australian French Teachers Association was a member of the FIPF. Although SAFTA only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Expressions of Support</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lomax-Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Jane</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Editors’ Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Explorations and Encounters:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Uses of a Theme</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FORNASIERO</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MROWA-HOPKINS</surname>
                           <given-names>COLETTE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theme of exploration requires little explanation in terms of its relevance to the constant strivings of human life and, by extension, to the activities of learning and scholarship; indeed, with its corollary of the journey, it underlines, as do writings since time immemorial, including many a school motto, the intimate relationship between seeking and discovering; striving and finding; quest and knowledge. The title of this volume —<italic>Explorations and Encounters in French</italic>— can therefore be seen as self-evident, announcing as it does its essentially investigative nature and its position within a field of study. However, if the title</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Le choc des discours dans la presse française:</title>
                     <subtitle>de la crise des banlieues à celle des universités (novembre 2005, mars 2006)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOIRAND</surname>
                           <given-names>SOPHIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Comment se construit la réalité sociale? Comment le langage verbal, l’usage de la langue, construit, ou plutôt reconstruit, le réel? Telle est la question que l’on se pose, dans une perspective à la fois proche et différente de celle de John Ronald Searle (1995) dans<italic>The Construction of Social Reality</italic>. Proche, parce qu’il s’agit de s’interroger sur le rôle du langage dans la construction des faits sociaux, ce qui présuppose, dit Searle, “une intentionnalité collective”; différente parce qu’il s’agit ici de s’interroger sur le fonctionnement des discours des médias, et en particulier ceux de la presse écrite quotidienne. Car si</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Comment j’ai appris la littérature:</title>
                     <subtitle>morceaux choisis d’une éducation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRAUBY</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANÇOISE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Je suis venue à l’enseignement dans les années 80, en France, à l’époque où une certaine<italic>mystique</italic>du professeur régnait encore sur les classes, même si la réalité de l’éducation était bien loin de se conformer à ce rêve très III<sup>e</sup>République.</p>
                     <p>Je suis venue à l’écriture assez tard, en partie parce que j’étais encombrée par une autre mystique, celle de l’artiste, avec son relent romantique, un peu oblatif, un peu sulfureux, qui, contrairement à ce que l’on peut croire, a la vie dure.</p>
                     <p>C’est de cette double initiation que je voudrais vous parler, enseignement et écriture (un écrivain sur</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Inaugural Frank Horner Lecture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Frank Horner passed away in July 2004, it was at a time of renewed research interest both in the early French exploration of Australia and the achievements of the Baudin expedition, the very interest that he had been so influential in awakening. In July 2006, when planning a major series of public lectures to coincide with the three conferences of French language and culture that were to take place at the University of Adelaide, the organizers, in consultation with Frank’s family, considered this an opportune moment to pay homage to his pioneering work by inaugurating a series of scholarly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Writing and Rewriting the Baudin Scientific Expedition to the Southern Hemisphere, 1800-1804</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SANKEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARGARET</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Baudin scientific expedition was commissioned by Bonaparte, then First Consul, to explore the Southern Hemisphere and visit Timor and New Holland. It left Le Havre on 19 October 1800 under the leadership of Nicolas Baudin in charge of the<italic>Géographe</italic>, and Emmanuel Hamelin, captain of the<italic>Naturaliste</italic>. Baudin died on the return journey in Mauritius and the<italic>Géographe</italic>, captained now by Pierre-Bernard Milius, arrived at the port of Lorient on 24 March 1804, the<italic>Naturaliste</italic>having arrived at Le Havre on 7 June 1803.</p>
                     <p>We, a team consisting of Jean Fornasiero, John West-Sooby and myself, together with a Belgian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Doing it by the Book:</title>
                     <subtitle>Breaking the Reputation of Nicolas Baudin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FORNASIERO</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEST-SOOBY</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Nicolas Baudin left the Normandy port of Le Havre in October 1800 bound on a voyage of discovery to the Southern Lands, he set out in the expectation of attaining the status of James Cook (Horner 1987: 80; Allorge 2003: 589). Four years later, despite all that had been achieved, his expedition would return to France shrouded in disgrace. It was a dramatic reversal of fortune that was all the more remarkable considering the lofty ambitions that had inspired the voyage’s conception and planning, the large amount of money that had been invested in the expedition and, last but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Exploration of the “Other”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Teaching and Learning Socio-Pragmatic Competence through French Film Extracts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MROWA-HOPKINS</surname>
                           <given-names>COLETTE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I would like to begin with the story of Anna (not her real name); her father introduced her to French at the age of two. Although he was born in Australia, he spoke fluent French and taught her French nursery rhymes and songs. Anna went on to study French at school from reception to Yr 12, and had the opportunity to visit France on several occasions with her family. To most of us, this would seem to be an ideal situation. Yet, in spite of this, Anna disliked French as a school subject and developed a negative attitude towards the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Visions and Revisions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Language Learning for Cultural Mediation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HANNA</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TOOHEY</surname>
                           <given-names>ALICIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The approach to language teaching and learning known as intercultural language learning (IcLL) has had an undeniable influence in Australia in recent times. Associated with names such as Zarate, Kramsch, Byram, and, closer to home, Crozet and Liddicoat, it represents a turn away from the attempt to produce ersatz native speakers through institutionalized language learning and places greater emphasis on learners’ abilities to apprehend the particularities of their own culture as exposed through comparison with other cultures (see Byram et al. 2001: 5). As pointed out by Harbon and Browett, the status of IcLL “as a curriculum imperative” (2006: 28)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Les TICE:</title>
                     <subtitle>de nouveaux outils pédagogiques</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ATHERTON</surname>
                           <given-names>BÉATRICE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CZAPLINSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>IWONA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Les enseignants de langue font depuis longtemps figure de pionniers en matière de technologie. L’audio, la vidéo, les produits multimédia et autres DVD ont été progressivement intégrés dans la panoplie du professeur de langue et on s’est fréquemment interrogé sur leur rôle dans l’apprentissage. Les technologies de la communication sont venues s’y ajouter ces dix dernières années et la communication médiée par les systèmes informatiques soulève à son tour des interrogations. Ce nouvel environnement modifie certaines conditions d’apprentissage, en complexifiant les relations entre les principaux acteurs de la communication. Ceux-ci interagissent au moyen d’outils qu’ils peuvent adapter à leurs besoins.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Promoting Collaborative Learning with IdeaNet:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Francophone Literature Case Study</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THOMAS</surname>
                           <given-names>BONNIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2003, the Arts Faculty at The University of Western Australia underwent a major restructure involving the distribution of points for its units of study. In the previous model each unit was worth eight points while in the revised version units could be weighted at either 6 points or 12 points. For French Studies, this redistribution of points resulted in the creation of a new series of upper level elective units. Students must take at least two of these units over two years in order to complete a major in French. A distinguishing feature of these electives is that they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Délier la langue d’étudiants “captifs”:</title>
                     <subtitle>enjeux, écueils et fortunes d’un cours d’expression orale à l’université</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VUAILLE-BARCAN</surname>
                           <given-names>MARIE-LAURE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nous souhaitons présenter ici un cours d’expression orale organisé pour des étudiants en deuxième année de français à l’université de Newcastle. Ce module optionnel est complémentaire des cours principaux, où les quatre compétences (expression et compréhension écrites et orales) sont ciblées. Il s’inscrit dans la lignée de l’approche communicative dont H. Widdowson fut l’un des pionniers. (Widdowson 1978) Le cours tente en effet de créer des conditions favorables à l’appropriation par les apprenants de savoirfaire linguistiques, en les amenant à considérer la langue étrangère comme un outil d’expression personnelle pour qu’ils acquièrent des stratégies communicatives performantes. Notre démarche s’est inspirée</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conference History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contents of the CD-ROM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1sq5wjr.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>322</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
