<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h08gn</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">FC97.M33 2000</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nationalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Democracy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Multiculturalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civil rights</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Is There a Canadian Philosophy?</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reflections on the Canadian Identity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MADISON</surname>
               <given-names>G.B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FAIRFIELD</surname>
               <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HARRIS</surname>
               <given-names>INGRID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776616155</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776616153</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Ont., Canada</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ckpd3s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Is There a Canadian Philosophy?</italic>addresses the themes of community, culture, national identity, and universal human rights, taking the Canadian example as its focus. The authors argue that nations compelled to cope with increasing demands for group recognition may do so in a broadly liberal spirit and without succumbing to the dangers associated with an illiberal, adversarial multiculturalism. They identify and describe a Canadian civic philosophy and attempt to show how this<italic>modus operandi</italic>of Canadian public life is capable of reconciling questions of collective identity and recognition with a commitment to individual rights and related principles of liberal democracy. They further argue that this philosophy can serve as a model for nations around the world faced with internal complexities and growing demands for recognition from populations more diverse than at any previous time in their histories.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABOUT THE AUTHORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If there is one thing urgently required in nations around the world confronted with growing demands for recognition of various forms of particularity—ethnic, cultural, linguistic, gender, and so on—it is a conception of civil association that reconciles recognition of difference with respect for the rights of individuals. Many older liberal democracies are rapidly becoming multicultural societies preoccupied with collective identities while many emerging democracies face similar challenges, often while struggling simultaneously to overcome a legacy of authoritarian and/or colonial rule. The dark side of identity politics has been illustrated all too frequently in modern times, most recently by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>NATIONALITY AND UNIVERSALITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Madison</surname>
                           <given-names>G.B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the occasion of its 50th anniversary in 1995, UNESCO published a volume entitled<italic>Philosophie et démocratic dans le monde</italic>. This was part of a larger project intended to take stock of the current place of philosophy in education and culture, with the aim of promoting the teaching of philosophy throughout the world. The basic theme of the book was that, as its title suggests, the fate of democracy is intimately linked to that of philosophy: “l’enseignement philosophique … a partie liée avec les processus de démocratisation” (Droit 1995, 71). The book was based upon documentation accumulated by UNESCO and,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>NATIONALISM AND THE POLITICS OF IDENTITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fairfield</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While not an altogether new phenomenon, political argumentation in recent times has increasingly opted for a discourse of collective identity over traditional liberal discourses of utility, the common good, and individual rights. Considerations of collective identity—whether articulated along national, ethnic, linguistic, gender, or other lines—and demands for recognition are increasingly displacing vocabularies of universality, neutrality, and, perhaps most of all, individuality.¹ Political disputes between proponents of individual freedoms and collective interests, or between the requirements of universality and particularity, are in themselves nothing new. What is new is the manner and extent to which the vocabulary of identity,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>THE BEARERS OF RIGHTS:</title>
                     <subtitle>INDIVIDUALS OR COLLECTIVES?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fairfield</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is an old Canadian political impulse to seek reconciliation between apparent opposites both at the levels of political philosophy and practice. Perhaps a legacy of the historic agreement that brought together in a single nation cultures as diverse as the English, the French, and an assortment of aboriginal peoples, the practice of seeking political consensus through compromise—sometimes at the expense of principle—has long been the norm in Canadian political culture. Conciliation, accommodation, and<italic>rapprochement</italic>are commonly touted as characteristically Canadian virtues, at least in this nation, and not without some claim to truth. This pragmatic turn of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>DEMOCRACY IN CANADA:</title>
                     <subtitle>“CANADA” AS A SPONTANEOUS ORDER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harris</surname>
                           <given-names>Ingrid</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Canadian political thinkers are currently grappling with many difficult questions in the face of the need for critical existential decisions: 1) Can the Canadian federal system survive the sovereignty of Quebec and aboriginal groups? 2) Are the special rights that accompany group sovereignty necessarily divisive, and do they spell the doom of Canada as a nationstate? 3) Should immigrants to Canada enjoy the same cultural protection as aboriginal peoples and French Canadians? 4) Can community rights be accommodated within Canadian liberal-democratic institutions?</p>
                     <p>For the most part, these are not new issues. Most have been debated ever since the “non-founded founding”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>RIGHTS, SOVEREIGNTY, AND THE NATION-STATE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harris</surname>
                           <given-names>Ingrid</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sign at the side of the road reads, “Attention: You are now leaving Ontario. From here on you will be subject to the laws of the Nisga’a (or Mohawk, Cree, Inuit, etc.) nation.” The prospect of encountering such a sign frightens the daylights out of some people. After all, ethnocultural conflicts have been an increasing source of political violence around the world. Will permitting sovereignty for First Nations decrease or increase the possibility of violence? For some Canadians, it is the only measure that promises to do justice to the history of our dealings with them—the only move</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd3s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
