<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7pcxk</collection-id>
      <volume>19</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Goethe Yearbook 19</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Purdy</surname>
               <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MacLeod</surname>
               <given-names>Catriona</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>Book Review Editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781571135254</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781571138200</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Rochester, NY; Woodbridge, Suffolk</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Goethe Society of North America</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt81ph2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The ‘Goethe Yearbook’ is a publication of the Goethe Society of North America, encouraging North American Goethe scholarship by publishing original English-language contributions to the understanding of Goethe and other authors of the ‘Goethezeit’ while also welcoming contributions from scholars around the world. Volume 19 of the ‘Goethe Yearbook’ continues to investigate the connection between Goethe's scientific theories and his aesthetics, with essays on his optics and his plant morphology. A special section examines the central role that Goethe philology has had in establishing practices that shaped the history of ‘Germanistik’ as a whole. The yearbook also includes essays on legal history and the novella, Goethe ‘Lieder’, esoteric mysticism in ‘Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre’, and Werther's sexual pathology. The volume also includes three essays re-examining Goethe's aesthetics in the context of the history of deconstruction, as well as the customary book review section. Contributors: Beate Allert, Frauke Berndt, Sean Franzel, Stefan Hajduk, Bernd Hamacher, Jeffrey L. High, Francien Markx, Lavinia Meier-Ewert, Ansgar Mohnkern, Rüdiger Nutt-Kofoth, Edward T. Potter, Chenxi Tang, Robert Walter. Daniel Purdy is Associate Professor of German at Pennsylvania State University. Book review editor Catriona MacLeod is Associate Professor of German at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Towards a German Romantic Concept of the Ballad:</title>
                     <subtitle>Goethe’s “Johanna Sebus” and Its Musical Interpretations by Zelter and Reichardt</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARKX</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCIEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the midst of the political turmoil of the Napoleonic wars, the force of nature took its toll on the French-occupied lower Rhine region. On January 13, 1809, the dam near Cleve (lying today in Germany near the Dutch border) collapsed, and the icy waters of the Rhine devastated the village of Brienen and flooded several other villages nearby. A seventeen-year-old village girl, Johanna Sebus, saved her mother’s life but died herself trying to rescue her neighbors. Three months later, her body was found, and she was buried with honor near the old Gothic church in Rindern.¹ Her selfless deed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Trübe” as the Source of New Color Formation in Goethe’s Late Works<italic>Entoptische Farben</italic>(1817–20) and<italic>Chromatik</italic>(1822)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALLERT</surname>
                           <given-names>BEATE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Much has been written about Goethe’s earlier didactic and polemical works on color.¹ However, little attention has been paid to his late essays titled <italic>Entoptische Farben</italic> (1817–20) and <italic>Chromatik</italic> (1822), on which I shall focus in this essay.² Goethe’s experiments with colors and his writings on the visual occupied him almost for his entire life. Whereas one group of scholars argues for continuity and consistency in Goethe’s works, a second group argues that his oeuvre displays gaps and discontinuities, yet that these various parts represent different voices dialogically responding to each other while in the process also forming a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Myth of Otherness:</title>
                     <subtitle>Goethe on Presence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERNDT</surname>
                           <given-names>FRAUKE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Western culture is dominated by representation—however, in 1993 in a series of essays, Jean-Luc Nancy counters this paradigm of all signification processes from a culturally critical perspective with a new paradigm, and proclaims “the birth to presence.”¹ In the course of this paradigm shift from representation to presence and as a consequence of Hans Ulrich Gumbrecht’s work, contemporary literary criticism has also taken an interest in “what meaning cannot convey.”² Yet, to speak of a “new” paradigm implies a kind of mastery, since presence basically represents an outdated paradigm in two respects. In the hermeneutic tradition, whose roots are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Transformation of the Law of Nations and the Reinvention of the Novella:</title>
                     <subtitle>Legal History and Literary Innovation from Boccaccio’s<italic>Decameron</italic>to Goethe’s<italic>Unterhaltungen deutscher Ausgewanderten</italic>
                     </subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TANG</surname>
                           <given-names>CHENXI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Even prior to its publication in Friedrich Schiller’s literary journal <italic>Die Horen</italic> in 1795, Goethe’s novella cycle <italic>Unterhaltungen deutscher Ausgewanderten</italic> had already been assigned an eminent place in literary history: in a letter dated November 7, 1794, Schiller informed his friend Christian Körner that Goethe “ist jetzt beschäftigt, eine zusammenhängende Suite von Erzählungen im Geschmack des Decameron des Boccaz auszuarbeiten.”¹ Indeed, the structural borrowing from the <italic>Decameron</italic> is so undisguised in <italic>Unterhaltungen</italic> that it is undoubtedly meant to revive, under entirely new historical conditions, the genre of the novella as established by Boccaccio (1313–75). As evident as Goethe’s indebtedness</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Hear him! hört ihn!”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Scholarly Lecturing in Berlin and the Popular Style of Karl Philipp Moritz</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRANZEL</surname>
                           <given-names>SEAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In a 1779 letter, Immanuel Kant congratulates his former student marcus herz on the success of philosophical lectures held in his own home, on achieving, as Kant puts it, “durchgängiges Ansehen . . . im berlinischen Publico.”¹ Herz was one of Kant’s favorite pupils and even served as a respondent at his second dissertation disputation in 1770, a rarity for a Jewish student. Alongside a prominent medical career in Berlin, Herz held lectures on experimental science, electricity, and philosophy, the latter based on his study with Kant.² Enjoying renown amongst audiences mixed in gender and social position, Herz made the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Hypochondria, Onanism, and Reading in Goethe’s<italic>Werther</italic>
                     </title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>POTTER</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe’s pathbreaking epistolary novel, <italic>Die Leiden des jungen Werther</italic> (1774, 2nd [rev.] ed. 1787) has been the focus of an enormous amount of scholarly attention.¹ A recent analysis by Bruce Duncan of more than two centuries of <italic>Werther</italic> criticism, <italic>Goethe’s “Werther” and the Critics</italic> (2005), makes manifest the wide variety of critical approaches to this extremely rich text. Duncan discusses, among other things, contemporary late eighteenth-century reactions to <italic>Werther</italic>, biographical, religious, psychological, and political approaches to Goethe’s novel, as well as interpretations of <italic>Werther</italic> that focus on reading, writing, gender, and/or sexuality. The literary critic Michael Bell</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Judex! Blasphemy! and Posthumous Conversion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Schiller and (No) Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HIGH</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In <italic>Geschichte des Abfalls der vereinigten Niederlande von der Spanischen Regierung</italic> (1788), Friedrich Schiller (1759–1805) wrote: “Das gemeinschaftliche Ziel des Despotismus und des Priestertums ist Einförmigkeit, und Einförmigkeit ist ein notwendiges Hülfsmittel der menschlichen Armut und Beschränkung.”¹ Like Schiller, many of the foremost canonical thinkers and doers of the Late Enlightenment rose to prominence as political, philosophical, and literary enemies of coerced uniformity—despotism and priestcraft—be it in the form of feudal tyranny, foreign occupation, violation of freedom of political thought and expression; or church-state violation of freedom of, to, and from religion. Revolutions in deed are preceded</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Esoterik der “Macht, die über uns waltet und alles zum Besten lenkt”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Das Wissen vom Anderen in Goethes<italic>Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre</italic>
                     </subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAJDUK</surname>
                           <given-names>STEFAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Zu <italic>beginn der Lehrjahre</italic> mangelt es Wilhelm wie jedem jungen Mann an Erfahrung, Können und Wissen. Er ist ein Anfänger in der Liebe, erweist sich als Dilettant in der Schauspielkunst und seine Hoffnung auf ein anderes Leben führt ihn in eine Reihe von Krisen. Sein Ausbrechen aus der bürgerlichen Enge seiner Herkunft beweist jedoch Mut und sensibilisiert ihn für eine Offenheit, die neue Erfahrungen ermöglicht. Wilhelm entwickelt im Gegensatz zu seinem Jugendfreund Werner schon früh auch ein Gespür dafür, was seiner Entwicklung hin zu einem freieren Selbst gut tut. Ihm schwebt etwas von einer Entfaltung der Persönlichkeit vor, wie es</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Goethes Fortgepflanztes:</title>
                     <subtitle>Zur Unbegrifflichkeit der Morphologie</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOHNKERN</surname>
                           <given-names>ANSGAR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Mit der Veröffentlichung seiner Hefte <italic>Zur Morphologie</italic> im Jahr 1817 legt Goethe eine Sammlung von Texten vor, die ähnlich den <italic>Wanderjahren</italic> aus dem Gesamtwerk als ungewöhnlich offen und unfertig herausragt. Dabei berührt das Unfertige, das den <italic>Heften</italic> anhängt, aufs Innigste die historische Ungeschliffenheit einer morphologischen Disziplin am Beginn des 19. Jahrhunderts, die sich im Augenblick ihrer Entstehung zugleich über sich selbst zu verständigen sucht. In der Sammlung findet sich ein Stück, welches mit “Der Inhalt bevorwortet” überschrieben ist. In dem Bemühen, Anfänge der morphologischen Forschung zu beziffern, heißt es dort in bedeutsamer Unschärfe:</p>
                     <p>Mit andern Freunden unterhielt ich mich gleichfalls</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAMACHER</surname>
                           <given-names>BERND</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In der Wissenschaftsgeschichte der Germanistik wurde bereits in unterschiedlichen Zusammenhängen die Goethe-Philologie als Paradigma für die Theorie-und Methodenentwicklung in der Literaturwissenschaft insgesamt beschrieben. Nicht ausreichend aufgearbeitet ist indes, dass die Neugermanistik im 19. Jahrhundert nicht nur aus der Goethe-Philologie heraus entstanden, sondern ihre disziplinäre Gestalt noch bis in die Gegenwart hinein von diesen Entstehungsbedingungen geprägt ist. Bei einzelnen Segmenten der wissenschaftlichen Terminologie—wie etwa bei den Gattungsbegriffen oder bei Begriffen wie “Symbol”—ist evident, dass wichtige Grundbegriffe noch der heutigen (deutschen) germanistischen Wissenschaftssprache nicht ohne Rekurs auf Goethe zu definieren sind. Eher verdeckt wird durch solche punktuellen begriffsgeschichtlichen Evidenzen der</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Goethe und Goethe-Philologie als Muster der neugermanistischen Editionswissenschaft:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eine Skizze mit Blick auf literaturwissenschaftsgeschichtliche Kontexte</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NUTT-KOFOTH</surname>
                           <given-names>RÜDIGER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Dass “Goethe-Philologie” nicht nur einen spezifischen wissenschaftlichen Umgang mit Goethe in der zweiten Hälfte des 19. Jahrhunderts meint, sondern zum Paradigma der neugermanistischen Fachentwicklung seit den 1870er Jahren bis um die Jahrhundertwende werden konnte, ist inzwischen fester Bestandteil der Fachgeschichtsschreibung für die neuere deutsche Literaturwissenschaft.¹ Gefüllt wurde dieser Begriff in der Geschichtsschreibung der deutschen Literaturwissenschaft lange mit der Vorstellung von “kleinkarierte[m] Expertenwissen” und dem damit verbundenen “häufig unreflektierten Dichterkult.”² Der sich in Aufgriff der und Analogie zu den Naturwissenschaften entwickelnde literaturwissenschaftliche Positivismus, wie die Bezeichnung jener Phase der deutschen Literaturwissenschaft im Allgemeinen lautet, schien daher angetreten, jene “Mühe positiver Kleinarbeit”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Aus dieser fingierten Welt in eine ähnliche wirkliche versetzt”?:</title>
                     <subtitle>Die Theorie der Autobiografie und ein postmoderner Goethe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WALTER</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Als die Autobiografietheorie Anfang des 20. Jahrhunderts in Deutschland so richtig in Gang kam, übertraf ein Text in seiner Prägekraft für den neuen Wissenschaftszweig bei weitem alle anderen: Goethes <italic>Dichtung und Wahrheit.</italic>¹ Besonders wirkungsvoll war dabei wohl Wilhelm Diltheys Rückgriff auf Goethes Jugendautobiografie. “Die Selbstbiographie”—so Dilthey—“ist die höchste und am meisten instruktive Form, in welcher uns das Verstehen des Lebens entgegentritt.” Eine besondere “Intimität des Verstehens” ergibt sich für Dilthey daraus, dass “der, welcher diesen Lebenslauf versteht, identisch [ist] mit dem, der ihn hervorgebracht hat”—die Autobiografie ist für den Hermeneutiker Dilthey die hermeneutische Textsorte schlechthin. Goethe verhalte</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Man sucht einen Mittelpunkt und das ist schwer und nicht einmal gut”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Figurationen der Verdopplung in<italic>Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahren</italic>
                     </subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MEIER-EWERT</surname>
                           <given-names>LAVINIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Unmöglich zu beginnen, ohne selbst bereits zu verdoppeln.</p>
                     <p>Ich wünschte, versetzte Wilhelm, daß ich Ihnen alles, was gegenwärtig in mir vorgeht, entdecken könnte! Alle Vorgefühle, die ich jemals über Menschheit und ihre Schicksale gehabt, die mich von Jugend auf, mir selbst unbemerkt, begleiteten, finde ich in Shakespeares Stücken erfüllt und entwickelt. Es scheint, als wenn er uns alle Rätsel offenbarte, ohne daß man doch sagen kann: hier oder da ist das Wort der Auflösung. Seine Menschen scheinen natürliche Menschen zu sein, und sie sind es doch nicht. Diese geheimnisvollsten und zusammengesetztesten Geschöpfe der Natur handeln vor uns in seinen Stücken,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Johann Wolfgang Goethe, Briefe. Historisch-kritische Ausgabe. Im Auftrag der Klassik Stiftung Weimar Goethe- und Schiller-Archiv hg. v. Georg Kurscheidt, Norbert Oellers, Elke Richter. Band 6: Anfang 1785-3. September 1786 (Band 6 I: Text, XXI + 303 S., Band 6 II: Kommentar, XLIV + 683 S.). Hg. v. Volker Giel unter Mitarbeit von Susanne Fenske und Yvonne Pietsch. Berlin: Akademie-Verlag, 2010.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Breuer</surname>
                           <given-names>Constanze</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Astrida Orle Tantillo, Goethe’s Modernisms. New York: Continuum, 2010. 198 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carter</surname>
                           <given-names>William H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Kristina Skorniakova, Moderne Transzendenz: Wie Goethes Wilhelm-Meister-Romane Sinn machen. Leipzig: Leipziger Universitätsverlag, 2010. 423 S.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bahr</surname>
                           <given-names>Ehrhard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Günter Saße, Auswandern in die Moderne: Tradition und Innovation in Goethes Roman Wilhelm Meisters Wanderjahre. Berlin/New York: de Gruyter 2010. 284 S.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Breuer</surname>
                           <given-names>Constanze</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Johann Wolfgang Goethe, West-East Divan: The Poems with “Notes and Essays”: Goethe’s Intercultural Dialogues. Martin Bidney, trans. “Notes and Essays” translation assisted by Peter Anton von Arnim. Binghamton, NY: Global Academic Publishing, 2010. 474 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wickersham</surname>
                           <given-names>Erlis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Katharina Mommsen, Kein Rettungsmittel als die Liebe: Schillers und Goethes Bündnis im Spiegel ihrer Dichtungen. Göttingen: Wallstein, 2010. 379 S.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carone</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria Giulia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Volker Wahl, Hrsg., “Das Kind in meinem Leib”: Sittlichkeitsdelikte und Kindsmord in Sachsen-Weimar-Eisenach unter Carl August: Eine Quellenedition, 1777–1786. Veröffentlichungen aus Thüringischen Staatsarchiven, 10. Mit einem Nachwort von René Jacques Baerlocher. Weimar: Böhlau, 2004. 516 S.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bahr</surname>
                           <given-names>Ehrhard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jesko Reiling, Die Genese der idealen Gesellschaft: Studien zum literarischen Werk von Johann Jakob Bodmer (1698–1783). Berlin/New York: Walter de Gruyter, 2010. 322 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powers</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Wulf Koepke and Karl Menges, eds., Herder Jahrbuch VIII/2006. Heidelberg: Synchron Wissenschaftsverlag der Autoren, 2006. 206 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martinson</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Harald Wentzlaff-Eggebert, Weimars Mann in Leipzig: Johann Georg Keil (1781–1857) und sein Anteil am kulturellen Leben der Epoche. Eine dokumentierte Rekonstruktion. Ereignis Weimar-Jena. Kultur um 1800, Bd. 26. Mit einem Beitrag von Markus Bertsch und unter Mitwirkung von Corinne Dolling. Heidelberg: Universitätsverlag Winter, 2009. 702 S.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tschacher</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>290</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anthony Krupp, Reason’s Children: Childhood in Early Modern Philosophy. Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 2009. 261 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schindler</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephan K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>292</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Susanne Kord, Murderesses in German Writing, 1720–1860: Heroines of Horror. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 2009. 266 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schaad</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bernd Hamacher, Offenbarung und Gewalt: Literarische Aspekte kultureller Krisen um 1800. Munich: Wilhelm Fink, 2010. 437 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lande</surname>
                           <given-names>Joel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jürgen Thym, ed. Of Poetry and Song: Approaches to the Nineteenth-Century Lied. Rochester, NY: U of Rochester P, 2010. 450 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mahoney</surname>
                           <given-names>Dennis F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Adrian Daub, “Zwillinghafte Gebärden”: Zur kulturellen Wahrnehmung des vierhändigen Klavierspiels im neunzehnten Jahrhundert. Würzburg: Königshausen &amp; Neumann, 2009. 275 S.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Höyng</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>298</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Angus Nicholls and Martin Liebscher (eds.), Thinking and Unconscious Nineteenth-Century German Thought. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010. ix + 327 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cooksey</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lynne Tatlock, ed., Publishing Culture and the “Reading Nation”: German Book History in the Long Nineteenth Century. Rochester, NY: Camden House, 2010. 345 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tucker</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81ph2.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Robert Cowan, The Indo-German Identification: Reconciling South Asian Origins and European Destinies, 1765–1885. Rochester, NY: Camden House, 2010. 225 pp.</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haque</surname>
                           <given-names>Kamaal</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>304</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
