<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4vpr</collection-id>
      <volume>24</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading Rochester</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BURNS</surname>
               <given-names>EDWARD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780853230380</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781846317644</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Liverpool University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vjm6q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A collection of new essays exploring all aspects of one of the most intriguing and controversial English poets, the seventeenth-century libertine the Earl of Rochester. Different sections focus on sexual politics, on the poetry of intellect, and on Rochester and his contemporaries. The aim of the book is to read Rochester and to open up the poems to further reading. Rochester’s personal notoriety is in a complex relationship to his writing and to the personality he created for himself through that writing. These essays offer a fresh reassessment of the range and quality of a writer only recently widely available, who is currently becoming visible as one of the great writers of his century.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all the major English poets, Rochester is the most irrepressibly disruptive. The very idea of the anarchic libertine poet, as created in the gossip of his contemporaries and in the notoriety of unpublishably obscene texts, disrupts any attempt to account for his writings from within the institutions and procedures of the Academy. To submit Rochester to scholarship is to effect an even starker juxtaposition of a poet’s emotion and its eventual recollection into the tranquillity of footnotes than that of Yeats’s ‘The Scholars’:</p>
                     <p>Bald heads forgetful of their sins</p>
                     <p>Old, learned, respectable bald heads</p>
                     <p>Edit and annotate their lines</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Gender and Artfulness in Rochester’s ‘Song of a Young Lady to Her Ancient Lover’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILCOX</surname>
                           <given-names>HELEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay arises primarily out of the experience of discussing Rochester’s work with readers who possess plenty of ‘Youth, Fire, Wit and Discernment’, namely, fascinated but perplexed undergraduates. How does Rochester, they ask, achieve that astonishing rational directness, that surprisingly delicate lyric grace? Why does he so regularly challenge these, and his readers, with cynicism and obscenity? Is his wit sharpened in anger or love? Is it concerned or dispassionate? Is there a consistent perspective underlying and shaping the variety of poetic masks worn in and by the texts? More particularly, as a male author did he regard the human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>‘Something Genrous in Meer Lust’?:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rochester and Misogyny</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CLARK</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given Rochester's undisputed status as ‘one of the dirtiest poets in the canon’,¹ one might think that any sustained consideration of his work would at some point involve detailed attention to the issue of misogyny. This has not, however, proved to be the case. It is not that feminist criticism has neglected his writing: in the last 20 years Fabricant, Wilcoxon, Wintle and Nussbaum have all provided illuminating commentaries.² Yet considering the attention devoted to niceties of satiric form or problems of textual attribution, this aspect of his work has suffered at least comparative neglect, the issues involved apparently being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Obscene Libel and the Language of ‘The Imperfect Enjoyment’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McGHEE</surname>
                           <given-names>JIM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his bestselling sermon for Rochester’s funeral, Robert Parsons, chaplain to the Earl’s mother, claimed that Rochester had made a last request that ‘those persons, in whose custody his Papers were’, would ‘burn all his profane and lewd Writings, as being only fit to promote Vice and Immorality’.¹ Parsons’ image of Rochester’s shameful and blasphemous texts ablaze with the flames of Holy Religion is particularly apt in the light of their subsequent publication history. Part of the ritual of press control still current at this time was the public burning by the hangman of a symbolic copy of the banned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rochester, Lady Betty and the Post-Boy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BURNS</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An early pastoral finds Rochester in transition between fluency in a received language and an abrupt acknowledgement of his more personal concerns. The conventional language of love seems at first to spin itself out without any focused emotional reference.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Alex</italic>. There sighs not on the Plain</p>
                     <p>So lost a swain as I;</p>
                     <p>Scorcht’d up with Love, frozen with Disdain,</p>
                     <p>Of killing sweetness I complain</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Streph</italic>. If’tis Corinna, die.</p>
                     <p>(A Pastoral Dialogue Between Alexis and Strephon, 11.1–5)</p>
                     <p>But when Strephon says that ‘Like ruin’d Birds, rob’d of their Young, / Lamenting, frighted, and alone, / I fly from place to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Negativity and Affirmation in Rochester’s Lyric Poetry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DENTITH</surname>
                           <given-names>SIMON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the following essay I seek to provide some context for the particular twists and inversions that characterize Rochester’s lyric poetry. The context I suggest is not biographical, but social and therefore, ultimately, historical; that is, I seek to locate the various affirmations and debunkings that characterize these poems in the wider, class-marked discursive economy of the Restoration. But I attempt this act of location by attention to the tone of voice and shifts of register within the poetry, and to its differing rhetorical appeals. In this, my enterprise has a generally Bakhtinian inspiration; not so much the Bakhtin of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>‘Upon Nothing’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rochester and the Fear of Non-entity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>TONY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because of its knowing exhibitionism, because of its flair, because of its mock-solemn pride in its own achievement, Rochester’s poem ‘Upon Nothing’ brushes aside the kind of readerly interrogation invited by similarly impressive metaphysical displays. If Donne’s ‘Lecture on the Shadow’ or ‘A Nocturnall upon S. Lucie’s Day’ or Marvell’s ‘Definition of Love’, provide a recent generic pedigree for ‘Upon Nothing’, Rochester’s salient improvisation on non-entity requires of its readership qualitatively less imaginative effort to succumb to its arguments and admire its paradoxes. ‘Upon Nothing’ asks, supposing it asks anything of its readers, for a take-it-or-leave-it sense of delightedly amused</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Not Being a Very Punctual Subject:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rochester and the Invention of Modernity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAVIS</surname>
                           <given-names>NICK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rochester’s slightly older contemporary, Antony à Wood, makes a distinctive claim about Rochester’s commitment to study of the classics:</p>
                     <p>He was a person of most rare parts, and his natural talent was excellent, much improved by learning and industry, being thoroughly acquainted with the classic authors, both Greek and Latin; a thing very rare (if not peculiar to him) among those of his quality.¹</p>
                     <p>Samuel Johnson, coming across the claim in Wood’s standard reference work and feeling obliged to do something with it, has recourse to sarcasm: ‘He read what is considered as polite learning so much, that he is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From ‘Nothing’ to ‘Silence’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rochester and Pope</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BAINES</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1739 Alexander Pope, during the course of a ‘ramble’, stayed for one night at the Duke of Argyle’s house at Adderbury. The house had belonged to the Earl of Rochester, and the legend is that Pope was given Rochester’s bed. The occasion was celebrated in a poem ascribed to Pope and printed in three monthly magazines in August and September.</p>
                     <p>With no poetick ardors fir’d,</p>
                     <p>I press the bed where<italic>Wilmot</italic>lay:</p>
                     <p>That here he lov’d or here expir’d,</p>
                     <p>Begets no numbers grave or gay.¹</p>
                     <p>What it begot instead was a rather starchy compliment to the patriotism and familial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>‘An Allusion to Horace’, Jonson’s Ghost, and the Second Poets’ War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAMMOND</surname>
                           <given-names>BREAN S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Post-Romantic conceptions of originality make it difficult for us to regard as other than paradoxical the claim that ‘An Allusion to Horace’, the poem in which Rochester is most indebted to a precursor, is also one of his most original contributions to English poetry. If Rochester was not quite the first English poet to press a Roman satire into the service of his own times, he was the first to appreciate that this could be done systematically over the length of an entire poem, to wit Horace’s<italic>Satire</italic>1.10.¹ Doubtless, Rochester did not intuit the full potential of this new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rochester and Oldham:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘High Rants in Profaneness’</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SELDEN</surname>
                           <given-names>RAMAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rochester died on 26 July 1680. John Oldham’s pastoral elegy ‘Bion, A Pastoral . . . Bewailing the Death of the Earl of Rochester’ suggests that the Earl was his poetic mentor:</p>
                     <p>If I am reckon’d not unblest in Song,</p>
                     <p>‘Tis what I owe to all-teaching tongue:</p>
                     <p>Some of thy Art, some of thy tuneful breath</p>
                     <p>Thou didst by Will to worthless me bequeath:</p>
                     <p>Others thy Flocks, thy Lands, thy Riches have,</p>
                     <p>To me though didst thy Pipe and Skill vouchsafe.¹</p>
                     <p>The lines were written about four years after Rochester was first made aware of Oldham, when the latter was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>‘The Present Moment’ and ‘Times Whiter Series’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rochester and Dryden</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BEATTY</surname>
                           <given-names>BERNARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dryden and Rochester are the most considerable poets of their day and knowingly represent their times. Both poets are fascinated, too, by their occupancy of time but they understand and represent this in entirely different ways. This divergence is most easily marked in their reading of Charles II and his court but it controls, too, their attitude to sexuality and, finally, distinguishes the specific nature of their religious conversions.</p>
                     <p>The opposition is not difficult to see for it cuts to the centre of their interests and literary procedures. Rochester insists upon the impossibly ‘present moment’ and, as corollary and consequence,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm6q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Proper Names and Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
