<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gx2w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt183gzx9</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A History of Anthropology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Eriksen</surname>
               <given-names>Thomas Hylland</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Nielsen</surname>
               <given-names>Finn Sivert</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745333526</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781849649186</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Thomas Hylland Eriksen</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Finn Sivert Nielsen</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183gzx9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This is a thoroughly updated and revised edition of a popular classic of modern anthropology. The authors provide summaries of ‘Enlightenment’, ‘Romantic’ and ‘Victorian’ anthropology, from the cultural theories of Morgan and Taylor to the often neglected contributions of German scholars. The ambiguous relationship between anthropology and national cultures is also considered. The book provides an unparalleled account of theoretical developments in anthropology from the 1920s to the present, including functionalism, structuralism, hermeneutics, neo-Marxism and discourse analysis. There are brief biographies of major anthropologists and coverage of key debates including totemism, kinship and globalisation. This essential text on anthropology is highly engaging, authoritative and suitable for students at all levels.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Second Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eriksen</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas Hylland</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nielsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Finn Sivert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the First Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Proto-Anthropology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How long have anthropologists existed? Opinions are divided on this issue. The answer depends on what you mean by an anthropologist. People around the world have always been curious about their neighbours and more remote people. They have gossiped about them, fought them, married them and told stories about them. Some of their stories were written down. Some were later criticised as inaccurate or ethnocentric (or flatly racist). Some stories were compared with others, about other people, leading to general assumptions about ‘people elsewhere’, and what humans everywhere have in common. In this broad sense, we start an anthropological enquiry</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Victorians, Germans and a Frenchman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between the Napoleonic Wars (1792–1815) and the First World War (1914–18), we see the rise of modern Europe – and of the modern world. This was, above all, the age of the Industrial Revolution. In the 1700s, profound transformations had taken place in agriculture and manufacturing, particularly in Britain. Steam power and spinning machines had become widespread, and a growing class of landless peasants and urban labourers began to make themselves heard. But greater changes were ahead. In the 1830s, the first major railways were built; a decade later, steamships crossed the Atlantic on a regular basis; in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Four Founding Fathers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The peaceful conditions that had prevailed in the West since the Napoleonic Wars, the steady advance of democracy and culture, the growing colonial empires, the dynamic economy and the scientific breakthroughs, had done their part to make ideologies of unilinear progress seem plausible, if not inevitable. A mere glance at the world seemed sufficient to confirm evolutionism in this age, which is called Victorian, after the long-lived British monarch. As Keith Hart puts it:</p>
                     <p>The question Victorians asked was how they were able to conquer the planet with so little effective resistance. They concluded that their culture was superior, being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Expansion and Institutionalisation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jazz and Stalinism,<italic>Kristallnacht</italic>and Al Capone, blood on the horizon and bread-lines in the street, the consolidation of colonial empires and the birth of mass media, the crash of stock markets and rise of the welfare state. The 1930s quiver like an arrow waiting for release. Then war rolls across Europe and the world, a war even more terrible than its predecessor. Science gave us Hiroshima. Nationalism gave us Auschwitz. Now, if not before, the idea of the infinitely perfectible, rational individual was dead and buried. Or was it?</p>
                     <p>The war obliterated the last vestiges of the world in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Forms of Change</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The guns are silent, the bombers grounded. Millions of refugees pick their way through Germany’s ruined cities, across the scorched earth of Russia, Poland, Belarus and the Ukraine. France and Britain have been deeply shaken; their great empires will soon be only a memory. By contrast, the American economy is just settling down into superpower gear, wheeling out an ever-increasing plenitude of pink Cadillacs, TV sets, film stars and nuclear weaponry. To the East of Europe, the Soviet Union will compete successfully with ‘the free world’ in the production of military hardware, while the production of Cadillacs (pink or otherwise)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Power of Symbols</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first decades of the twentieth century, the younger generation of anthropologists carefully distanced themselves from the search for historical origins that was characteristic of the nineteenth century. They sought an anthropology based on synchronous analysis and meticulous observation. By the 1950s, a new generation was rediscovering change, either as an evolutionary movement (in the United States) or an outcome of individual action (in Britain). All the while, other anthropologists were looking for new ways to study meaning and symbolism.</p>
                     <p>Research on the meaning of symbols was nothing new. In the United States, in particular, the ‘discovery’ was not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Questioning Authority</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Cuban missile crisis, the Berlin Wall, the civil rights movement, the Prague spring; hippies in Haight-Ashbury, student riots in Paris; the Beatles, the Moon landing, Kennedy’s assassination, the Vietnam War – all this is emblematic of the ‘Sixties’, as the time is known in the West. But the radical political climate to which these events contributed did not come to bloom before the end of the decade, and belongs, strictly speaking, to the ten years<italic>following</italic>1968. Certainly this was true in academia, where students shout their slogans but tenured professors remain as the years go by. Anthropologists, always</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The End of Modernism?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If every age has its ambience, that of the 1980s is unmistakable. The decade seems to roll in on us in a heavy cloud of AIDS, black leather, urban decay and crack. The sound of The Cure from a Walkman, drifting down the street, past the pale guy on the corner with his spikes and golden mohawk. Or watch the girls in tight pastels swooning to Michael Jackson and dancing till dawn – while the first clunky personal computers hit the home market, and the pale moon shines down on you from a sky that now contains ozone holes and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Global Networks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lack of historical distance precludes a proper review of the last decades, whether of the general cultural ambience or of the specific enterprise of anthropology. In both regards, it is nevertheless obvious that some of the trends of the 1980s were consolidated towards and beyond the millennium. Uncertainty, or ambivalence, became a standard feature (some would say an affectation) of intellectual life, certainly in the humanities and social sciences; although trends representing a more positivist view, seeking less equivocal answers to the perennial questions of anthropology, were also on the rise. In particular, we have sociobiology and its successor, evolutionary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzx9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Compiled by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carlton</surname>
                           <given-names>Sue</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
