<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8b1v</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT103.C3675 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">God (Christianity)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Postmodernism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Insistence of God</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Theology of Perhaps</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CAPUTO</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253010018</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253010100</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253010101</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John D. Caputo</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzk5p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Insistence of God presents the provocative idea that God does not exist, God insists, while God's existence is a human responsibility, which may or may not happen. For John D. Caputo, God's existence is haunted by "perhaps," which does not signify indecisiveness but an openness to risk, to the unforeseeable. Perhaps constitutes a theology of what is to come and what we cannot see coming. Responding to current critics of continental philosophy, Caputo explores the materiality of perhaps and the promise of the world. He shows how perhaps can become a new theology of the gaps God opens.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Gap God Opens</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>IX</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XI</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>GOD, PERHAPS:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fear of One Small Word</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I dream of learning how to say “perhaps.” I have the same dream, night after night, of a<italic>tolle, lege</italic>experience, in which I open a book—I cannot make out the title—always to the same sentence, “<italic>Peut-être</italic>—<italic>il faut toujours dire peut-être pour</italic>. . .” In the morning I cannot remember the rest of the sentence.</p>
                     <p>I am dreaming of a new species of theologians, of theologians to come, theologians of the “perhaps,” a new society of friends of a dangerous “perhaps.” I would like to think we are, perhaps, already a little like these theologians we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>THE INSISTENCE OF GOD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Allow me to put my cards on the table right at the outset. My criterion of truth is how well we have learned to deal with the fear of one small word, “perhaps.” That, I would say, is a general problem for us all. No one gets a pass. But in this book I am singling out theology and calling for a new species of theologians, theologians of the future. That means I measure theology by the extent to which it avoids the pitfalls of a too-comforting piety—of pious prayers and pious theology portrayed on gilded postcards. I avoid</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>INSISTENCE AND HOSPITALITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mary and Martha in a Postmodern World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The name of God is the name of trouble. The insistence of God means that God calls for a response or, since God is not somebody who “does” things like call, it means that the calling takes place in the middle voice, in and under the name of God. God calls in the middle voice. The call is perfectly figured in an unexpected and insistent knocking on our door. A disturbing visitation in the night is an uncertainty in which all the sting of “perhaps” is perfectly concentrated, in which the dynamics of “perhaps” and a theology of insistence is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>THEOPOETICS AS THE INSISTENCE OF A RADICAL THEOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the end of his 1920–21 lecture course on the letters of St. Paul, the young Heidegger wrote:</p>
                     <p>Real philosophy of religion arises not from preconceived concepts of philosophy and religion. Rather, the possibility of its philosophical understanding arises out of a certain religiosity—for us, the Christian religiosity.¹</p>
                     <p>We cannot start with a stable concept of “philosophy” and a stable concept of “religion” and then “apply” “philosophy” to “religion.” We must allow what are called “philosophy” and “religion” to tremble together under the force of their mutual contact, letting each push back on the other. That contact can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>TWO TYPES OF CONTINENTAL PHILOSOPHY OF RELIGION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kierkegaard’s Johannes Climacus reports the case of one Dr. Hjortespring, who was converted to Hegelianism by a miracle on Easter morning at the Hotel Streit in Hamburg.¹ My own story is not as dramatic. Still, if truth be told, in the present work I fear I will shock my friends by declaring myself a born-again Hegelian, and this in order to distinguish myself from the Kantians. My reasoning is as follows. The event is an event of truth. The insistence of the event may also be called its insistent “truth.” The “democracy to come” means the truth that insists on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>IS THERE AN EVENT IN HEGEL?</title>
                     <subtitle>Malabou, Plasticity, and “Perhaps”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let there be no mistake. I am following Hegel where he did not quite mean to lead, marching to a drum he did not quite beat, taking up a cause he did not quite advocate. I am proposing, as Heidegger would have said, to “repeat” Hegel, to repeat not what Hegel actually said, which has already been said by Hegel, but to repeat the possible in Hegel, remaining loyal to the possibilities Hegel opened up for us by being faithfully disloyal to Hegel. To repeat Hegel in a productive way is, of course, to repeat Hegel’s own prodigious ability to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>GIGANTOMACHEAN ETHICS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Žižek, Milbank, and the Fear of One Small Word</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Žižek’s rereading of Hegel is more radical and disruptive than Malabou’s. Žižek sees the Hegel of the<italic>au revoir</italic>coming, the Hegelian Absolute inching its way home through its peregrinations through world history, and he stops it in its tracks. In its place Žižek puts a more deeply doubly negative dialectic, where the Spirit does not come home, where it never had a home, where there never really was a “Spirit.” Adieu to the Spirit, good riddance. No, we will not meet again. No, no, we never met in the first place. Stop trying to recollect something that never happened.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>THE INSISTENCE OF THE WORLD:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Chiasm to Cosmos</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We promised at the start to honor the animals of Jesus, and now we must make good on that promise, this time by honoring the animal that Jesus is, the animal that I am following (<italic>je suis</italic>),¹ whose animal needs were recognized by Martha. Indeed it is time to honor the history of the animals that we all are and are following, which I have emblematically called Martha’s world, the world to which we all belong in the most deeply material sense. Yet, despite our pledge to follow the animals of Jesus, we have in truth been focused almost exclusively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>AS IF I WERE DEAD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Radical Theology and the Real</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I object to the blackmail, to the bad choice—theism or atheism!—and to the violence of double genitive in the<italic>odium theologiae</italic>—the total contempt for religion on the part of secularists, the demonization of atheism by the theologians, which leads to outright violence by religious extremists. The whole thing is a perfect recipe for war. The current form this blackmail has taken in recent years is a new wave of “materialism,” “realism,” and “atheism” that has arisen in reaction to the so-called theological turn. These terms are used more or less interchangeably, as if theology is allergic to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>FACTS, FICTIONS, AND FAITH:</title>
                     <subtitle>What Is Really Real after All?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having thus redescribed “objectivity” as a way to think about the world in which we live as if we were dead or never born, let us now take a careful look at the words that have sparked the current critique of continental philosophy—Meillassoux’s critique of “correlation” and “fideism,” in that order. This criticism has been set in motion by the theological turn, or the return of religion, which is taken to be a regrettable consequence of continental antirealism. I think there is something to this critique of fideism but it should be put to better purpose. It should be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>A NIHILISM OF GRACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Life, Death, and Resurrection</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I return now to the hard hypothesis, that life is a passing feature of the universe, an interim phenomenon, not an ultimate or permanent part of the cosmic furnishings. An ineluctable fate lies in store for us—terrestrial, solar, galactic, and universal death in entropic disintegration, that point when there is no chiasm or poetics, no life or religion. What then of God, perhaps?</p>
                     <p>To this end we can do no better than to return to the cold, disenchanted, demythologized, disappointing, reductionistic, realistic, rationalistic world view of one of the critics of continental philosophy, best encapsulated in all of its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>THE GRACE OF THE WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So we come to stand on the ground of a certain materialism but of an odd sort, the groundless ground of a certain religious materialism. Likewise we stand on the ground of a certain religion, but it too is an odd sort of religion, a religion without religion,¹ with a weak theology not a strong, a theology of insistence not existence, of “perhaps” not of an<italic>ens necessarium.</italic>There is grace, grace happens, but it is the grace of the world. There is salvation, but we are “saved” only for an instant, in the instant, saved without salvation by a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzk5p.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
