<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccqk</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS1181.6 .B66 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">P document (Biblical criticism)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. Pentateuch</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Vision of the Priestly Narrative</book-title>
         <subtitle>Its Genre and Hermeneutics of Time</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Boorer</surname>
               <given-names>Suzanne</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884140641</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884140634</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gxxq00"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A fresh look at the Priestly narrative that places less weight on linguistic criteria alone in favor of narrative coherence</p>
         <p>Boorer explores the theology of an originally independent Priestly narrative (Pg), extending through Genesis-Numbers, as a whole. In this book she describes the structure of the Priestly narrative, in particular its coherent sequential and parallel patterns. Boorer argues that at every point in the narrative's sequential and parallel structure, it reshapes past traditions, synthesizing these with contemporary and unique elements into future visions, in a way that is akin to the timelessness of liturgical texts. The book sheds new light on what this material might have sought to accomplish as a whole, and how it might have functioned for, its original audience.</p>
         <p>Solid arguments based on genre and themes, with regard to a once separate Priestly narrative (Pg) that concludes in Numbers 27*Thorough discussion of the overall interpretation of the Priestly narrative (Pg), by bringing together consideration of its structure and genreClear illustration of how understanding the genre of the material and its hermeneutics of time is vital for interpreting Pg as a whole</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="636"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is generally agreed that it is relatively easy to distinguish Priestly material (P)¹ from non-Priestly material (non-P) in Genesis–Numbers (Joshua).² However, when it comes to identifying the overall theology of the Priestly material, or what it might be primarily about, there is much more contention. A range of views have been proposed, primarily in articles³ and sections in books whose primary concern is mostly with one section of P⁴ or with source/redactional issues or with defining the extent or possible levels within P.⁵ Philip Jenson’s statement that “there have been surprisingly few full-scale theological studies of P in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Structure of Pg</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Various views regarding the structure of P as a whole have been proposed. All have a certain merit, not least because the P narrative material seems to contain a number of structural markers or characteristics that do not necessarily all point in the same direction or indicate the same structure.¹ These will become clear in the following selective survey of attempts at structuring P, as will the way in which each view gives importance to selective characteristic(s). In exploring these various views, it must be kept in mind that the delineation of Pg by the various scholars may not coincide</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Genre and Hermeneutics of Pg</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A vital factor in any attempt to interpret Pg as a whole is the question of its nature or genre.¹ However, how exactly to describe the nature of the Priestly material (Pg) has proven to be an elusive task. The Priestly material has been described in various ways; it has been described as “<italic>Geschichte</italic>,” and specific nuances of this such as “<italic>Geschichtserzählung</italic>” or “<italic>Ursprungsgeschichte</italic>,” as “historiography,” and as “history viewed in ritual categories.”² It has also been described in terms of “paradigm,” whether as comprising “fundamental paradigmatic constellations” or being described as “paradigmatic” narrative, “paradigmatic history,” or “myth.”³</p>
                     <p>These terms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Paradigmatic Nature of the Scenarios within Pg’s Story of the Nation and Their Hermeneutics of Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In analyzing the paradigmatic nature of Pg’s story of the nation in Exod 1–Num 27*, the core trait of this material that defines it as paradigmatic, as unfolded in chapter 3, is the way in which earlier traditions are reshaped and synthesized with unique and visionary elements into a picture, or pictures, that are in a sense timeless, or transcend time, or are relevant for all time. How this hermeneutics of time or sense of timelessness is nuanced over and above this varies between components: whether through repetition of details or stereotypical patterns that suspend or mark time; or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Interpretation of the Story of the Nation within Pg as a Whole, Its Trajectory, and Parallels, in Light of Its Hermeneutics of Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In seeking to situate the story of the nation in Exod 1:13–Num 27:14* as we have analyzed it in chapter 4 in terms of its paradigmatic nature, in its context as preceded by Gen 1:1–Exod 1:7*, its historiographical nature, which is indeed inseparable from its paradigmatic nature, will become more apparent.</p>
                     <p>The historiographical nature of Pg, as discussed in chapter 3 (esp.§3.3), consists primarily in its sequential trajectory of contingent events moving toward a future goal that reflect “historical” traditions (albeit in reshaped form). Indeed, the specific sequence in Pg itself reflects in broad outline the sequence or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Embodying the World of the Text, Cognitively, Existentially, and through Ritual Praxis, or Not</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>503</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The task of this chapter is primarily to explore what the impact of Pg as a whole might have been on its original audience of the exilic/early postexilic period. However, this chapter has a double function. It also presents an integrated summary of the conclusions reached throughout this monograph concerning the meaning of Pg as a whole, interpreted in light of its genre and hermeneutics of time, as this is an integral part of unfolding how Pg might have functioned for its original audience (and indeed perhaps its ongoing readership). Exploring the possible effect Pg might have had on its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>563</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Texts Constituting the Priestly Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>583</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Biblical References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>585</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxq00.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Modern Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>613</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
