<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391c8</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.3998/mpub.9380984</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1661 .M87 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">One-act plays</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">One-act plays</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Technique</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Theater</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Production and direction</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Performing Arts</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Microdramas</book-title>
         <subtitle>Crucibles for Theater and Time</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Muse</surname>
               <given-names>John H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472073634</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472123148</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John H. Muse</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.9380984"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In<italic>Microdramas</italic>, John H. Muse argues that plays shorter than twenty minutes deserve sustained attention, and that brevity should be considered a distinct mode of theatrical practice. Focusing on artists for whom brevity became both a structural principle and a tool to investigate theater itself (August Strindberg, Maurice Maeterlinck, F. T. Marinetti, Samuel Beckett, Suzan-Lori Parks, and Caryl Churchill), the book explores four episodes in the history of very short theater, all characterized by the self-conscious embrace of brevity. The story moves from the birth of the modernist microdrama in French little theaters in the 1880s, to the explicit worship of speed in Italian Futurist synthetic theater, to Samuel Beckett's often-misunderstood short plays, and finally to a range of contemporary playwrights whose long compilations of shorts offer a new take on momentary theater.Subjecting short plays to extended scrutiny upends assumptions about brief or minimal art, and about theatrical experience. The book shows that short performances often demand greater attention from audiences than plays that unfold more predictably. Microdramas put pressure on preconceptions about which aspects of theater might be fundamental and about what might qualify as an event. In the process, they suggest answers to crucial questions about time, spectatorship, and significance.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="246"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Time Pieces</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is, in its entirety, Francesco Cangiullo’s 1915 Futurist play,<italic>Detonation: Synthesis of All Modern Theater</italic>. Detonation looks like a joke, and many have mistaken it for little more than one. This book attempts to take Cangiullo’s subtitle seriously by exploring the potential of theatrical brevity to distill lessons about modern theater and, more widely, to teach us about the ex perience of time in theater and in general. a sort of opening salvo for the theatrical avant-garde,<italic>Detonation</italic>explodes previous conventions while distilling several hallmarks of modern theater: atmosphere trumps charac ter, expectations are under attack, and an empty</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Two</label>
                     <title>The Dimensions of the Moment:</title>
                     <subtitle>Short Spaces and the Birth of the Modernist Microdrama</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The above account appeared in a Parisian daily newspaper,<italic>Le Matin</italic>, in 1906 among a list of<italic>faits-divers</italic>, sundry incidents too minor to warrant full stories. Offering only a bare description of the scene and without preface or commentary, the miniature narrative says little about the victim yet speaks volumes. nestled among other reports of accident or misfortune from across France, the anonymous story reminds the newspaper reader of shared vulnerability: even a priest is not safe from the capriciousness of fate. The tale’s swiftness reinforces the abrupt arrival of death. An event almost too insignificant to mention suggests universal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>The Future in the Instant:</title>
                     <subtitle>Futurist Synthesis in Theory and Practice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the curtain rises, a man enters the stage preoccupied, upset, and in a hurry. He removes his overcoat and hat, paces furiously, and erupts in dis belief at some unknown outrage: “Incredible!” Suddenly the audience catches his eye. Irritated, he turns to face them, walks to the edge of the stage, and announces categorically: “I . . . I have absolutely nothing to tell you. . . . Bring down the curtain!”¹ and the curtain falls. This is<italic>Negative Act</italic>, a microdrama written by Italian Futurists Bruno Corra and Emilio Setti melli in 1915 and performed along with dozens</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Shape of Time in Beckett’s Late Theater</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Samuel Beckett’s play<italic>Endgame</italic>, as Clov fervently collects a few objects littering the ground, he says, in frustration, “I’m doing my best to create a little order.”¹ Clov yearns to bring the single room that bounds his exis tence under control, to combat entropy with habit. Clov’s statement is, on one level, the complaint of a weary domestic servant employing chores as consolation to make the space he tends for three other people more tolera ble. But he is also a stage manager and property master who lifts the hand kerchief from Hamm’s face like a curtain, structures the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Long Shorts:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contemporary Micro-marathons</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The house lights fade and the audience settles before the show. A rectangle of white LED lights frames the proscenium’s four edges, creating the illu sion that a sheet of darkness hangs between them and the stage, a virtual fourth wall. As the lighted border blinks off, stage lights reveal the interior of a bright white cube, its five visible sides lined like enormous sheets of graph paper, unbroken by any opening that might facilitate entrance or exit. A conversation is already in progress between two people, one beg ging for the other to reveal a secret.</p>
                     <p>Please please tell</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.9380984.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
