<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Gift of the Other</book-title>
         <subtitle>Levinas, Derrida, and a Theology of Hospitality</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Shepherd</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>With a Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bouma-Prediger</surname>
               <given-names>Steven</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174845</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902943</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Andrew Shepherd</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0nw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>We live in an age of global capitalism and terror. In a climate of consumption and fear the unknown Other is regarded as a threat to our safety, a client to assist, or a competitor to be overcome in the struggle for scarce resources. And yet, the Christian Scriptures explicitly summon us to welcome strangers, to care for the widow and the orphan, and to build relationships with those distant from us. But how, in this world of hostility and commodification, do we practice hospitality? In The Gift of the Other, Andrew Shepherd engages deeply with the influential thought of French thinkers Emmanuel Levinas and Jacques Derrida, and argues that a true vision of hospitality is ultimately found not in postmodern philosophies but in the Christian narrative. The book offers a compelling Trinitarian account of the God of hospitality—a God of communion who “makes room" for otherness, who overcomes the hostility of the world though Jesus’ life, death, and resurrection, and who through the work of the Spirit is forming a new community: the Church—a people of welcome.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="274"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bouma-Prediger</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few today would doubt the claim that violence seems pervasive in contemporary society. Whether reading the local newspaper or the global online news, whether watching the latest film or listening to the newest music, violence of one sort or another seems omnipresent. The violence of our late-modern age, furthermore, seems embedded in competing claims about boundaries and identities and what some philosophers call our relationship to “The Other.” Some people cheerily claim that boundaries are (or soon will be) no more, since modern technologies are shrinking the walls and distances that separate us. Such shrinkage will, these optimists argue, render</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>A World for All?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We live in an intriguing period of human history. The last century has seen the exponential growth of the human population—from 1.5 billion in 1900, to 2.5 billion in 1950, to over 7 billion today. Yet, with this burgeoning growth in the human population, there is also perhaps a greater awareness than at any stage of human history of our essential interconnectivity and inter-relatedness. The collapse of both ideological and physical barriers erected during the Cold War, and the technological and economic “developments” of the last two decades mean that, notwithstanding the differences and diversity of “human civilizations” spread</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Transcendence of the Other and Infinite Responsibility:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Philosophy of Emmanuel Levinas</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Born in Lithuania in 1906, where he received a traditional Jewish education, Emmanuel Levinas began his philosophical studies at the University of Strasbourg in 1923. It was in Strasbourg that Levinas also met and began a lifelong friendship with Maurice Blanchot. In 1928, Levinas moved to Freiburg University to continue his studies in the emerging field of phenomenology being pioneered by Edmund Husserl. Here at Freibrug, Levinas also met and sat under the teaching of Martin Heidegger, whose work<italic>Sein und Zeit (Being and Time)</italic>(1927) had recently been published. In 1930, Levinas became a naturalised French citizen and with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Unconditional Hospitality, the Gift of Deconstruction?:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Philosophy of Jacques Derrida</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Levinas’ ethical philosophy has had a major impact on philosophical and religious thinking of the late 20th century. Notable amongst the number of writers who have been influenced by Levinas’ thought is well-known and controversial French philosopher, Jacques Derrida. In this chapter, we will explore the ways in which Levinas’ commendation of the priority of the ethical, manifested in concepts such as the “transcendence of the Other” and the “infinite responsibility” of the subject, are developed further by Derrida into the theme of “unconditional hospitality.” Defining and Delineating Derrida’s Deconstruction? Biographical Philosophy While clearly pivotal to the development of his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Levinasian and Derridean Hospitality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethics beyond Ontology?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In seeking to offer a theological account of the ethical practice of hospitality we have begun our journey by reflecting on the work of Emmanuel Levinas and his friend and compatriot, Jacques Derrida. The choice of Levinas and Derrida as interlocutors is not arbitrary. As well as the far-reaching influence of Levinasian and Derridean thought, not unimportant is the extent to which their respective philosophies have been shaped by their own life experiences of inhospitality, exclusion and violence. Such experiences have led them to the conclusion that not only is Western thought ill-equipped to respond to the inhospitable and unethical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Gifted, Called, and Named:</title>
                     <subtitle>Trinitarian Personhood and an Ontology of Communion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The work of Emmanuel Levinas and Jacques Derrida has been of major significance in its critique of the modern Western understanding of selfhood and identity. For both Levinas and Derrida, Western conceptions of human identity and personhood post-Descartes are deeply disturbing. In placing the<italic>cogito</italic>at the centre of his philosophy, Descartes and his successors give primacy to consciousness and conceive of the human person as a self-constituted entity. Philosophy which gives primacy to consciousness has, argue Levinas and Derrida, always given priority to the “I” and turned the Other into an object. They conclude that such philosophy leads ultimately</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A tête à tête.</title>
                     <subtitle>Wrestling with the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A few chapters after recounting the relationship between YHWH and Abraham, the Genesis narrative introduces us to Abraham’s grandson, Jacob. From the very beginning of the narrative, in the recounting of Jacob’s inter-uterine grappling with his twin brother, the reader is made aware of the struggle which will characterize Jacob’s life. Having stolen the birthright and father’s blessing from his brother Esau, and forced to flee for his life to his Uncle Laban, as Jacob’s life progresses it takes on a regular pattern. Despite receiving the blessing of the LORD (28: 10–20), for Jacob, unlike Abraham, this experience of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“LOGOS,” “Sacrificial Substitute,” and “Eikon”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Christology and the Overcoming of Hostility</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we observed that the Levinasian and Derridean stress on<italic>différance</italic>,<italic>division</italic>,<italic>separation</italic>and<italic>exteriority</italic>exists only because they seem unable to envisage a peaceful ontology in which<italic>communion</italic>and<italic>otherness</italic>mutually coexist. In contrast to these relations of<italic>différance, division and separation</italic>we have suggested that genuine hospitality is grounded in relations of love and freedom. Within such an ontology of communion, relationality is not understood as inevitably adversarial, in which power is used over the Other, hierarchy implies domination, “naming” assumes control, and subordination is understood as subjugation. Rather, within this distinct ontology, “power-over” is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A tête à tête.</title>
                     <subtitle>Seen by the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The motif of Christ as<italic>Eikon</italic>and the transformation that occurs as we look to the face of Christ is one employed by British theologian David F. Ford in his book<italic>Self and Salvation</italic>. Ford, in a Christology shaped by a close interaction with the thought of Levinas, suggests that “being faced by God” and “turning to face Jesus Christ in faith” are among the defining characteristics of Christianity.¹</p>
                     <p>While innovative, Ford’s concept of a “worshipping self”<italic>generated</italic>by its facing of the face of Jesus, does seem to revert to an exemplarist Christology. John Webster expresses disquiet at Ford’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Dwelling in Christ and the In-Dwelling Other:</title>
                     <subtitle>Forming the Ecclesial and Eschatological Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Previously, we have argued that all of creation, and humanity itself, is brought into being as a gift, its origins lying in the hospitable and ecstatic actions of the loving Triune God. However, distorted by our own desire to live<italic>distantly</italic>and<italic>separately</italic>and therefore cut off from the life of this divine<italic>communion</italic>, humanity becomes fearful of<italic>otherness</italic>. The Other is no longer perceived as one who comes offering joy, enrichment and mutual beneficence, but rather as a threat to our existence, one to be struggled against and overcome. Fear erupts into violence, hospitality gives way to hostility.</p>
                     <p>Stemming</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A tête à tête.</title>
                     <subtitle>A Drink with the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So what is the nature of the relationship with the Other shaped not by hostility? We have already noted Derrida’s skepticism regarding whether “pure” hospitality/genuine gift-giving can function in the economy of human relations. For Derrida:</p>
                     <p>Now the gift,<italic>if there is any</italic>, would no doubt be related to economy. One cannot treat the gift, this goes without saying, without treating this relation to economy, even to the money economy. But is not the gift, if there is any, also that which interrupts economy? That which, in suspending economic calculation, no longer gives rise to exchange? That which opens the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Performing a Different Script:</title>
                     <subtitle>Participation in the Practice of Ecclesial Hospitality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In contrast to our post-structuralist philosophers who have a strong aversion to the idea of<italic>community</italic>, we have contended that it is only in<italic>communion</italic>with Christ, and thus in community<italic>with</italic>others that the self finds its true identity. While it is God’s desire that all of creation should be brought into the joy of the Divine embrace, humanity, in its “sinful” desire for<italic>communion</italic>without<italic>otherness</italic>, construes the Other not as one to delight in, but rather as one to be feared, struggled against, vanquished. This hostility towards both the human Other and the Wholly Other however however</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A tête à tête.</title>
                     <subtitle>Hosted by the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jesus’ plans to create a new covenant people who through their lives will witness to the in-breaking hospitality of God’s kingdom begin in a rather inauspicious way. His choice of disciples seems somewhat unusual to say the least. Two sets of brothers hailing from Galilee whose “friendly rivalry” from their lives as fishermen spilt over into this new domain as disciples. James and John had particularly fiery tempers and liked to ensure they came out on top. Also, like other Galileans, their fierce regional loyalty was accompanied by distrust, often extending to an outright disdain, of<italic>Others</italic>who did not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Grounded Hospitality: Community, Ecological Care, and Inter-Faith Relationships</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Building relationships with the stranger has become increasingly difficult in an age where the dual discourses of the “war on terror” and “the market” hold sway. The influence of these pervasive discourses means Others come to be conceived as threats. The stranger is either to be explicitly feared—a potential “terrorist” coming to “destroy civilization” and our place in it—or, is simply another abstract commodity, at best, to be “tolerated,” or at worst, competing for limited resources, one to be struggled against.</p>
                     <p>In response to this understanding of human relations, essentially Hobbesian by nature, Emmanuel Levinas’ and Jacques Derrida’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0nw.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
