<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Foundational Theology</book-title>
         <subtitle>A New Approach to Catholic Fundamental Theology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ormerod</surname>
               <given-names>Neil</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jacobs-Vandegeer</surname>
               <given-names>Christiaan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451480412</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451480415</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506401881</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506401880</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress Publishers</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt155j2pq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Fundamental theology is traditionally viewed as the starting point for the various disciplines within Catholic theology; it is the place where solid foundations are established for the further research and engagement with the vast terrain of historical, systematic, philosophical, and sacramental/liturgical theology. In Foundational Theology, a landmark new study, Neil Ormerod and Christiaan Jacobs-Vandegeer seek to ground foundational theology in the normative drive toward meaning, truth, goodness, and beauty, appropriated by the theologian through religious, moral, intellectual, and psychic conversions. In doing so, the work maps out the implications of those fundamental orientations to the specific questions and topics of the Catholic theological tradition: God, Trinity, revelation, and an array of doctrinal points of investigation. The authors in this work provide a comprehensive approach to theological foundations for theologians while employing a new, groundbreaking approach to the discipline through the application of the insights of Bernard Lonergan, one of the foremost Catholic theologians of the modern era.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Collins</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ormerod</surname>
                           <given-names>Neil</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While the initial seeds for this work go back to my own doctoral thesis,¹ the more proximate cause for the project was a celebratory dinner in which I happened to be sitting next to the eminent Australian theologian, and recognized authority on fundamental theology, Gerald O’Collins. Though we were both aware of one another’s work (who could not be aware of his work!), it was the first time we had met, and Gerald began talking about his recently published book on fundamental theology,<italic>Rethinking Fundamental Theology</italic>. He noted that in this book he mentions Lonergan at the beginning and end</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Why Theological Foundations?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book endeavors to develop sound foundations for undertaking theological study and research. More precisely, we seek foundations for the doctrinal, systematic, and communicative work of theology—its normative phase, wherein the theologian is seeking to hand on the tradition in all its revealed authority and depth. This phase differs from theology’s historical or positive phase, wherein the theologian is seeking to recover from the past just what it is that has been revealed within that tradition. The book’s final chapter (chapter 10) explains how these two phases fit together in a comprehensive theological method. Prior to the emergence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Religious Conversion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The guiding idea of this book contends that a theologian’s personal (and communal) growth in religious, moral, intellectual, and psychic conversion marks the foundational reality of theology, and that constructing explicit theological foundations requires attention to the normative features of these conversions. This chapter focuses on religious conversion. It addresses that which strikes at the heart of who and what we are, at how we live, and toward what ends or goals our living tends. The approach to theology in this book asks that we maintain a keen awareness of the social and cultural contexts within which religious conversion takes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Moral Conversion and the Structure of the Good</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we considered religious conversion in terms of an inchoate (total) fulfillment of our conscious-intentional orientation toward meaning, truth, and goodness. It is the experience of God’s love flooding our hearts (Rom. 5:5), of being loved by God “before the foundation of the world” (Eph. 1:4). This involves a radical shift in our horizon so that in everything we do we act on a different level, with an expanded range of possibilities for meaning, truth and goodness. Still, as with the human experience of falling in love, this is only the first momentous step in our sustained</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Intellectual Conversion and Meaning, Truth, and Reality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the second century ce, Tertullian asked the question, “What indeed has Athens to do with Jerusalem?”¹ It is a question that has continued to echo through the learned books and journals, the lecture halls and classrooms of theological institutions in the ensuing centuries. What is the relationship, if any, between philosophical reason, captured by the symbol of Athens, the home of Greek philosophy, and Christian faith, captured in the symbol of Jerusalem? Whatever one might think of the question and its theoretical answers, historically there has been a strong tendency for philosophical questions and issues to arise within the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Psychic Conversion and the Question of Beauty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus far, we have considered religious, moral, and intellectual conversions and their foundational role in the life of the theologian seeking to be an authentic subject engaged in theological work. The question can arise as to whether this is an exhaustive account of the foundational theological subject. What other types of conversion might we consider? Previously we have mentioned our fundamental orientation to meaning, truth, and goodness. Goodness and values relate to moral conversion, while questions of meaning and truth relate to intellectual conversion. We have already seen how the presence and absence of these conversions may impact on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter discusses theological foundations for knowledge of God. Our approach emphasizes the conversion of the theologian and builds on previous chapters by illustrating how a theologian’s fourfold conversion determines the horizon within which discourse about God becomes meaningful. The chapter begins by identifying the main lines or themes of several major conversations about knowledge of God in the history of philosophy and theology. In this way, the reader may gain a sense of how our discussion of foundations allows us to revisit classic themes or questions about God.</p>
                     <p>The method we propose in this book contains the exigency for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Revelation and Divine Self-Communication</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the era of Vatican II, it has become a commonplace to speak of revelation as an act of<italic>divine self-communication</italic>. This terminology, derived from the work of Karl Rahner and adopted by Pope John Paul II, seeks to express the fact that God does not simply communicate various “facts” about God’s life and his relationship to us; rather God communicates God’s very self to us.¹ God is both the communicator and what is communicated. As Scripture puts it, we have become sharers in the divine nature (2 Pet. 1:4). God communicates something of the divine nature to us in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Heuristic Anticipation of Doctrines</title>
                     <subtitle>Trinity, Christology, and Ecclesiology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The task of foundations is not to preempt doctrines, but at the same time, sound foundations provide heuristic anticipations of doctrines, especially as these foundations emerge out of dialectical conflicts of interpretations of the history of doctrinal development. Without actually coming to the point of making a judgment, one can argue for the congruence of foundational categories with key doctrines such as Trinity, Incarnation, and Church. Many of the questions about the reasonableness of central doctrines are taken up in traditional fundamental theology, but in the form of apologetics and emphasizing credibility. Here, the goal is more modest, to show</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Communicative Context</title>
                     <subtitle>Secularism and Religious Pluralism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we provided a heuristic anticipation of certain positions in relation to the church, its nature and mission. In this chapter, we move from those more abstract considerations to the present and more concrete context of the church’s mission and communication, in a world of growing secularism on the one hand, and increasing exposure to religious pluralism on the other, while still drawing on the foundations developed in the first part of our work. Let us begin then with an ending:<italic>Ite missa est</italic>. These words express the dismissal declared at the end of the Roman Catholic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Theological Method</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The overall aim of this book has been the development of theological foundations, a task conceived as a specialization or stage within a functionally differentiated and collaborative theological method. However, to this point, we have said little to explain the nature of that theological method, though it has functioned throughout this book. Elements of this method appear in (later) chapters where we distinguish the task of foundations from doctrines and systematics. Now it is time to make that method more explicit. Our method distinguishes eight interrelated theological tasks, each of which makes a distinct contribution to the theological project. Following</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j2pq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>360</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
