<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Drinking from the Wells of New Creation</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Holy Spirit and the Imagination in Reconciliation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dearborn</surname>
               <given-names>Kerry</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903841</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Kerry Dearborn</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0kv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Holy Spirit, as God’s abiding presence to draw people to Christ, can cleanse wounds and bring love and hope into our hearts. Kerry Dearborn’s insightful focus on the Holy Spirit transforming our moral imagination and putting us on the path of reconciliation with Jesus Christ is both profound and encouraging. Biblical analysis, historical surveys and references to acclaimed theological authors support Dearborn’s nuanced yet practical application of imagination as a tool for awakening, recovery, and dissolving intellectual or psychological barriers that isolate us from God. She considers effectively how imagination can be connected to reality, and is able to delve deep into this vein of thought with startling clarity. Drinking from the Wells of New Creation provides spiritual guidance for dealing with oppression in society; an issue that affects people both within and outside the Christian faith. The acknowledgement of reconciliation as a creative process provides a fresh outlook and will excite those delving into both theological and psychological studies, as well as those seeking to understand God’s unification of life, regardless of tribe, tongue and nation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="170"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Why Emphasize the Holy Spirit and Imagination for Reconciliation Studies?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Phantastes</italic>, which C. S. Lewis credits with baptizing his imagination, George MacDonald tells the story of Anodos, who has just come of age and is about to receive his inheritance.² The framework with which Anodos approaches life is one of confident mastery, self-referent pragmatism, and enough curiosity to make him wonder if there is more to life than what he has experienced. Clearly a person of strong self-esteem, Anodos expresses his sense of mastery by placing things in convenient categories. When he first meets his fairy grandmother who appears to him in “tiny woman-form” wearing a Grecian dress, he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Reconciling God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much of the focus of studies and teaching on reconciliation, especially for Protestants, has been on the cross of Jesus Christ and the individual’s restored relationship with God.² It is his sacrificial death that cleanses us from sin and creates the way for a new relationship with God the Father. Acknowledging the centrality of Jesus as the good news of who God is and what God has done is a vital emphasis. Both Barth and Bonhoeffer endeavored to correct theology that was losing this center and becoming more anthropocentric than theocentric. They discovered that a message focused more on human</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Who Is the Holy Spirit and Does the Spirit Effect Reconciliation?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who is the One who now fills and transforms Jesus’ disciples for participation in the ministry of reconciliation? The following pages will highlight three prominent characteristics of the and the specific implications for each of these characteristics in the of reconciliation. Though many more qualities could be explored, for purpose of this book the focus will be on God’s Spirit as 1) universal; 2) and personal; and 3) the breath and source of life. In light of these Torrance, characteristics of the Spirit the following questions will be addressed: What does it mean to honor the Holy Spirit as God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Gifts from the Holy Spirit for Reconciliation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The nature of the Holy Spirit as universal, creative, and the source of life means there are many resources the Spirit offers to deal with painful realities and to bring to fulfillment God’s gift of reconciliation. Numerous gifts and fruit of the Holy Spirit, which are particular resources for the ministry of reconciliation, draw on the specific vehicle of the imagination for their expression. Though not an exhaustive list, three areas in particular will be explored as gifts crucial to the healing of relationships, all of which rely heavily on wise imagination: re-creation, hope, and love. Before exploring the specific</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Holy Spirit’s Work of Reconciliation through the Imagination</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What empowers people to live out lives of re-creation, hope, and love that correspond with the truth they affirm and the Holy Spirit that indwells them? What transforms approaches to reconciliation from being empty verbal niceties or guilt-assuaging “quick fixes” to dynamic expressions of the gospel? What is it that makes people empathetic, caring, compassionate, forgiving, and ultimately loving toward those who are “other”? This book has affirmed the reality that through the Holy Spirit, God’s love has flooded our hearts, uniting us with God and empowering us to participate in the reconciliation established by God through Christ’s life, death,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Imagination’s Third Way</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the imagination is a gift from God and can catalyze such change, why has it often been ignored as a resource for participation in God’s kingdom work? What specific qualities of the imagination make it such a powerful tool for the Holy Spirit’s work of transformation and reconciliation? What further role does the imagination play in helping to create a new community in which there is “neither Jew nor Gentile, slave nor free, male and female,” and yet where those distinctions are still honored as a place from which particular gifts and perspectives can be offered? David Brooks writes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Facing the Shadows</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though the Spirit imparts transformative visions to us, it is vital to acknowledge that the imagination is also a reservoir of gruesome and hideous images. The imagination, which can be a fountain of beatific visions, can also be a seabed of monsters spawned by fear, pride, hatred, despair, and even the demonic. What is it that arises within a person and thwarts the Spirit’s new creation in faith, hope, and love? What shadows arise in believers’ perceptions to obscure their vision of God’s recreation of others? Reconciliation is often thwarted because of the natural tendency to perceive the “ other”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Signposts and Oases of the New Creation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The central thesis of this book is that the Holy Spirit is God’s abiding presence to draw all people to the renewing waters of Christ’s recreating and reconciling work and life. Because of the Spirit’s universal, life-giving, and particularized presence, these waters are available even in the most turbulent and seemingly desolate places. Furthermore, I have proposed that the channels in which these waters often flow most freely, at least initially, are those of the imagination. It is through the imagination that God’s Spirit carries creativity, hope, and love into our hearts when there may be rational and psychological objections</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0kv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
