<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7pcf9</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Luis de Góngora and Lope de Vega</book-title>
         <subtitle>Masters of Parody</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KERR</surname>
               <given-names>LINDSAY G.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781855663176</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781787440548</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Woodbridge, Suffolk; Rochester, NY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Lindsay G. Kerr</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt1t6p5zq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Co-Winner of the 2014 Publication Prize awarded by the Association of Hispanists of Great Britain and Ireland Kerr traces the processes and paradoxes at work in the late parodic poetry of Luis de Góngora and Lope de Vega, illuminating the correlations and connections between two poets who have more often than not been presented as enemies.The analysis follows the parallel development of the complex parodic genre through Góngora's late mythological parody, from his 1589 Hero and Leander romance through to his culminating parody, La fábula de Píramo y Tisbe (1618) and Lope de Vega's alter ego Tomé de Burguillos, whose anthology, Rimas humanas y divinas del licenciado Tomé de Burguillos, was published a year before Lope's death, in 1634. Working from the premise that parody provides a Derridean supplément to exhausted, dominant genres (e.g. pastoral, lyric, epic), this study asks: what do these texts achieve by their supplementarity, and how do they achieve it?, and, the overarching question, why do these erudite poets turn to parody in an age of decline? Lindsay Kerr received her PhD in Spanish at Queen's University Belfast.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="219"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luis de Góngora y Argote and Lope de Vega y Carpio,<italic>príncipe de las tinieblas</italic>and<italic>monstruo de la naturaleza</italic>, respectively, are infrequently invoked together outside the realm of poetic belligerence. As the cultural landscape they inhabit bends and shapes to their gravity, these two literary forces collide in violent counteraction. This at least has been the prevailing view of criticism, bolstered by Emilio Orozco Díaz’s seminal work<italic>Lope y Góngora frente a frente</italic>(1973), in which he illuminates the poets’ divergent poetic methodologies and<italic>ethos</italic>.¹ Although Orozco admits a grudging admiration between Góngora and Lope,² my goal is to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Parodic Beginnings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Long before the complex worlds of the<italic>Polifemo</italic>or<italic>Soledades</italic>came into being, Góngora displayed a certain precocious ‘alejamiento no-conformista’ in his satirical<italic>letrillas</italic>that would prove to be the seed of a centuries-long controversy.¹ The neologisms, warped syntax, dazzling surface phenomena and many of the processes that would become intrinsic to gongorine style germinated from the young Góngora’s fascination with the precariousness of signs, with the tenuous relation between word and world. For Góngora in these ludic and occasionally vulgar<italic>letrillas</italic>, the space between signifier and signified is where play is king, where, amid the disguises and misdirections, truths</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>La fábula de Píramo y Tisbe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>La fábula de Píramo y Tisbe</italic>(1618) is, in the vein of Góngora’s Hero and Leander poems, a ludic expansion of a myth whose classical origins (Ovid’s<italic>Metamorphoses</italic>) and enduring popularity draw our poet like a moth to a flame. The 508 verses of<italic>Píramo y Tisbe</italic>tell the tale of two young lovers whose only original mode of communication is through a chink in the wall between their adjoining houses, although Góngora invents an African maid (‘fatal carabela’, v. 137) who ferries notes between them. The two agree to meet at the tomb of Ninus; however, a mountain lion,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Las Rimas de Tomé de Burguillos</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1634, the year before his death, Lope de Vega published an anthology of poetry in the parodic mode, comprising 161 sonnets, 11<italic>rimas sacras</italic>, various espinelas and canciones and the seven-<italic>silva</italic>, feline mock epic<italic>La Gatomaquia</italic>: the<italic>Rimas humanas y divinas del licenciado Tomé de Burguillos</italic>. The pseudonym was not a new creation, and the true author of the text was a thinly veiled secret, which raises some interesting questions about authorial intent and subsequent textual interpretations. Why would a poet like Lope de Vega, who sought to be taken seriously as the principal lyric poet of his age,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>La Gatomaquia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his 1935 introduction to one of the first annotated editions of<italic>La Gatomaquia</italic>, Francisco Rodríguez Marín makes the case for the relative obscurity of Lope’s burlesque masterpiece. He rails against ‘los que imaginan ser innecesaria la exégesis en cuanto a las obras de este autor’,¹ proceeding to give examples of Lope’s invented words (‘piramizar’, ‘ñifiñafe’, etc.) and phrases that the uninitiated reader might consider an obstacle to understanding. Despite Burguillos’s claims that ‘la vega es llana’ (147, v. 8),² my analysis of La Gatomaquia will show that the plain surface dissembles much deeper foundations.</p>
                     <p>Structured in seven relatively even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Last Laughs</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The parodic poetry written by Luis de Góngora and Lope de Vega at the end of their professional careers and in the winter of their years unquestionably brings forth something new, built from the bricks of ancient and contemporary poetic monuments. These poets utilise parody as a process that, paradoxically, ends and begins simultaneously in order to engage with the literary past, question its legacy, and redirect future poetics. Góngora’s mytho-parodic trajectory and comic culmination, and Lope’s final theatrical extravaganza as Tomé de Burguillos, reveal a wealth of common practices. Primarily, against the traditional critical tendency to pit our authors</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study has attempted to pose, and answer, new questions regarding the literary relationship between Luis de Góngora and Lope de Vega, particularly in the twilight of their respective careers. Neither of these poets turned to parody without precedent. That they did turn to parody, however, after their greatest career successes and at the end of their lives, establishes a correlation between lateness, decline, mastery and humour. These texts show an awareness of<italic>kairos</italic>in the midst of the endless and shapeless<italic>chronos</italic>, a moment of truth, of reflection; an event that must not simply continue on in the predictable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t6p5zq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
