<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HV9104 .S748 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Juvenile delinquency</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Juvenile delinquents</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Behavior modification</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">African American juvenile delinquents</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Massachusetts</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Boston</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">African American juvenile delinquents</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Illinois</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Chicago</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hispanic American youth</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Massachusetts</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Boston</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hispanic American youth</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Illinois</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Chicago</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Juvenile recidivists</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Law</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Dream Denied</book-title>
         <subtitle>Incarceration, Recidivism, and Young Minority Men in America</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Soyer</surname>
               <given-names>Michaela</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780520964617</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0520964616</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Oakland, California</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Regents of the University of California</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1cg4n9v"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Young minority men are often portrayed in popular media as victims of poverty and discrimination.<italic>A Dream Denied</italic>delves deeper, investigating the social and cultural implications of the "American dream" narrative for young minority men in the juvenile justice systems in Boston and Chicago. This book connects young male offenders' cycles of desistance and recidivism with normative assumptions about success and failure in American society, exposing a tragic disconnect between structural reality and juvenile justice policy. This book challenges us to reconsider how American society relates to its most vulnerable members, how it responds to their personal failures, and how it promises them a better future.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="184"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When our oldest daughter turned two, my husband bought<italic>The Little Engine That Could</italic>for her. Having grown up in Germany, I had never read the story before. The plot fascinated me. The children’s books I grew up with definitely did not include tales of overcoming one’s limitations. In the 1980s in Germany<italic>Der Struwwelpeter</italic>was still common reading material. To this day I remember what happens to poor little Suck-A-Thumb: a tailor with a giant pair of scissors storms in, catches him sucking on his thumbs, and cuts both of them off. As I have learned over the years,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Role of Agency in the Desistance Process</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While they were held in detention facilities or treatment centers, most teenagers expressed an inflated sense of agency. Relying on the cultural narrative of the “American Dream,” they believed in their ability to desist from crime, even if the odds were stacked against them. Criminologists often overlook the role agency plays in the desistance process. Structural conditions can be measured and quantified reliably. Operationalizing agency is more difficult. Direct observations of criminal acts are ethically dubious. Even if researchers were able to witness a crime in the making, it would be impossible to generalize from isolated instances. Although agency manifests</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Two Cities, Two Systems, Similar Problems:</title>
                     <subtitle>JUVENILE JUSTICE IN BOSTON AND CHICAGO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fall of 2009, when I visited the Cook County Juvenile Temporary Detention Center (JTDC) in Chicago for the first time, I was not sure what to expect. I had read about the abuse, overcrowding, and unsanitary conditions that led to an ACLU lawsuit filed against the center in the late 1990s. Would I see teenagers living in filth under deplorable circumstances, or had conditions truly improved since Earl Dunlap, a widely respected juvenile justice reformer, took over the JTDC as transitional administrator in 2007?</p>
                     <p>Unlike, for example, Chicago’s Cook County jail, the JTDC did not seem to have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Too Little Too Late:</title>
                     <subtitle>JUVENILE JUSTICE AS A SOCIAL SERVICE PROVIDER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I met Demetrius at the Healy North Alternative School in July 2010, when he was fifteen years old. He was on probation for armed robbery and had violated his home confinement. Rather than being held at the JTDC, he was sent to the Saura Center. Over the course of the two years I met with Demetrius, he was held once at the Saura Center and three times at the JTDC. Twice he was committed to St. Charles, a juvenile prison outside Chicago. During the summer of 2011, Demetrius was shot seven times in the legs. He was released from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Imagining Desistance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I always felt uncomfortable when staff members escorted me out of treatment centers or detention facilities after my interviews in Boston. Around the holidays—Thanksgiving, Christmas, and New Year’s—I felt even worse that I could go back to my suburban bubble, while the teenagers I interviewed had to spend the holidays away from their families. Most juvenile justice facilities I visited in Massachusetts did try to make the holidays more bearable for the young men. They served a turkey dinner on Thanksgiving, and in some treatment centers teenagers even received gifts for Christmas. Still, in my view such treats</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Weak Ties—Strong Emotions:</title>
                     <subtitle>CARING FOR JUVENILE OFFENDERS IN BOSTON AND CHICAGO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Darell had been angry a lot over the past few weeks. He felt misunderstood by his DCF caseworker and his probation officer. More than that, he didn’t care for the group home he currently lived in. “It’s not my home,” he said, “and these people are not my family members.” Whether they were family members or not, Darell was surrounded by people who were supposed to care for him. He had a probation officer, a DCF caseworker, and a social worker. Darell and his mother also saw a family therapist.</p>
                     <p>When I visited him at his Dorchester group home in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Uncertainty of Freedom:</title>
                     <subtitle>TEENAGERS’ DESIRE FOR CONFINEMENT AND SUPERVISION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lucas’s situation was complicated. I met him at the Eliot Detention Center, where he was being held for armed robbery. He was released fairly quickly and spent most of the year and a half during which we met regularly on the outside. While he was on juvenile probation, one of his associates pressed charges against him. His former friend claimed that Lucas had threatened him and his pregnant girlfriend. New accusations followed, and the whole case became an increasingly confusing he said–she said scenario. Lucas insisted vehemently that the allegations were unfounded. The details were far too complex to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>“I know how to control myself”:</title>
                     <subtitle>AUTONOMY AND DISCIPLINE IN THE DESISTANCE PROCESS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I moved to Boston to set up my second field site, our daughter was almost a year old and my husband had recently started an academic appointment at Wellesley College. Wellesley offered faculty housing, and we decided to settle right on the picturesque campus in a place within walking distance of his office. According to the 2010 census, the median income in Wellesley, Massachusetts, was $155,000. Eighty-five percent of the population was white, 9.8 percent Asian, 3.6 percent Latino, and 2 percent black. I always thought of Wellesley’s city center as a quintessential New England town: manicured lawns, white</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dan dreamed about leaving the South Side of Chicago, but even more than that, he envisioned his triumphant return. He imagined how his relatives were going to be surprised that the struggling teenager they knew before had become somebody. Dan wanted to be a psychiatrist. He was articulate and a good listener. Someone had told him that Arizona State University (ASU) had a good psychology program, and that’s where we wanted to go. Dan’s life had been anything but stable so far. He had moved from place to place, had stayed with different relatives, and finally ended up at the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX:</title>
                     <subtitle>Methodological Reflections</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cg4n9v.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
