<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h09qg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HQ1453.F47 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Women</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Education</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Women</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Health and hygiene</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Women</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Employment</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Volunteers</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Feminist Success Stories - Célébrons nos réussites féministes</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Blackford</surname>
               <given-names>Karen A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Garceau</surname>
               <given-names>Marie-Luce</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kirby</surname>
               <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>1999</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776615912</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776615912</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cn6rqg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Abuses by international corporations, withdrawal of social services and implementation of regressive legislation continue to impoverish women and reduce the quality of their everyday lives: women have reason to be demoralized. Recognizing this challenging and difficult situation, this volume reviews women's successes at feminizing Canadian institutions. It is intended to hearten the women's movement, and show the potential for feminist change and suggest ways to realize this potential.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="348"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                     <trans-title-group xml:lang="fre">
                        <trans-title>Remerciements</trans-title>
                     </trans-title-group>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION Celebrating Success — Célébrons nos réussites</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blackford</surname>
                           <given-names>Kttren</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garceau</surname>
                           <given-names>Marie-Luce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kirby</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The main purpose of this book is to recognize advances made by feminists in Canada. Increasing international corporate power, withdrawal of state services, and régressive législation impoverish women and ravage thé quality of their everyday lives. Women hâve reason to be demoralized. Recognizing this challenging and unfortunate situation, this text establishes as its mandate something différent. Specifîcally, it is a review of women's successes intended to hearten thé Womens Movement and to show that thé potential for feminist change still exists.</p>
                     <p>The use of both French and English throughout this text is deliberate as we want to provide opportunities for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Linda Christianson Ruffman, Francine Descarries, and Mary Lynn Stewart corne together to identify thé power of fédéral granting agencies in discouraging woman-centered research and scholarship in postsecondary institutions. The Canada Council and later thé Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) failed to acknowledge women until thé Royal Commission on thé Status of Women and thé 1975 United Nations Décade on Women. The steps which led to SSHRC’s Women and Work Stratégie Grant and thé grant’s limited success in opening research funding to women are described. This chapter is written from thé perspective of thé académie activists who initially proposed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Unfinished Story:</title>
                     <subtitle>SSHRC’s Stratégie Grant Program on Women and Work</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Christiawen-Buffinan</surname>
                           <given-names>Linda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Descarries</surname>
                           <given-names>Fntncine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stewart</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary Lynn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once upon a time — what seems like a long time ago but is really only yesterday — women were invisible — theoretically, academically, and politically.¹ From thé vantage point of thé early 1990s, it is hard to remember — and difficult to imagine — thé scholarly world without books, journals, newsletters, or courses that even mentioned women.² It is hard to recapture thé enthusiasm that greeted Maggie Benstons article on thé Political Economy of Women’s Liberation³ and Marylee Stephensons edited book, Women in Canada, in 1973.⁴ It is difficult to describe that taken-for-granted world without women⁵ and thé sudden “clicks” of récognition at first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mais où sont-elles?</title>
                     <subtitle>Fragments de l’histoire des Franco-Manitobaines de 1916 à 1947</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hébert</surname>
                           <given-names>Monique</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cet article vise à montrer à quel point les institutrices qui ont travaillé dans les écoles franco-manitobaines de 1916 à 1947 ont été présentes pendant tout le temps qu’a duré l’illégalité de l’enseignement du français, période nommée pertinemment «la traversée du désert» (Blay, 1987 : 59). Le gouvernement manitobain cherchait alors à assimiler la population franco-manitobaine au moyen de l’école. Le mouvement d’assimilation visait, il est vrai, non seulement les francophones, mais aussi tout élément non anglophone (Blay, 1987; Leblanc, 1968; Morton, 1967;Taillefer, 1979).</p>
                     <p>Nous examinerons d’abord brièvement certaines sources écrites pour vérifier la présence des femmes dans les institutions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The University’s New Clothes:</title>
                     <subtitle>Morality Tales for Feminists in Modem Academe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Epp</surname>
                           <given-names>Juanita Ross</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The original call for papers for this book asked for accounts of success stories in feminizing Canadian institutions. When that request landed on my desk, I thought it must be a joke. There seemed to be too many oxymorons in those phrases: successful feminizing? feminized institutions? I work at a university. Entire books hâve been devoted to an examination of how thé “invisible paradigm of thé académie System...marginalize(s) or trivialize(s) thé lives of ail women...so effectively that we no longer see it, notice its présence, or, most important, name it for thé determining force that it is” (Schuster and Van</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Gender Equity in the Canadian Sport Council:</title>
                     <subtitle>The New Voice for the Sport Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kirby</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper is about thé formation of thé Canadian Sport Council (CSC) in response to pressure from thé Canadian sport community and thé public to create a value based, équitable, drug-free sport System. Opportunity to create a more gender équitable System presented itself when thé whole “amateur” sport System was thrown into an intense self-examination by thé positive drug test of sprinter Ben Johnson at thé 1988 Séoul Olympic Games and thé ensuing Dubin Inquiry. A broad consultation process occurred over three years, concluding with thé establishment of thé CSC.</p>
                     <p>When opportunity knocked, worrien and other marginalized groups in sport</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Linda Briskin’s article addresses thé topic of women and unions within économie parameters. She notes events from as early as 1981, and informs us about unions and feminist leaders across Canada. Exclusion from male-dominated executive boards and educational courses has been central to oppression of women in unions, particularly at national levels. In spite of thé introduction of affirmative action policy, Briskin recognizes that complex patterns of structural discrimination continue. A feminist leader in labour studies, she emphasizes thé importance of mutual support among union women at thé local level in achieving goals important for working women. Parsons and Goggins</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Feminisms, Feminization, and Democratization in Canadian Unions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Briskin</surname>
                           <given-names>Linda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a 1981 assessment of thé situation of women in Canadian unions, Charlotte Gray concluded that thé main achievement of thé previous five years of union activity was a shift in attitudes.¹ In 1996, extensive évidence suggested that thé organizing of union women has had a dramatic impact on thé structures, policies, practices, and climate of thé union movement — a transformation that goes well beyond thé elusive change in attitudes. The 1994 Policy Statement “Confronting thé Mean Society” (Canadian Labour Congress [CLC]) underscores thé significance of thèse changes:</p>
                     <p>Equality seeking groups hâve strengthened our movement, bringing new ideas and perspectives</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Intersecting Multiple Sites of Marginalization:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Work of Feminizing within an Educational Workers’ Union</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Panons</surname>
                           <given-names>Marianne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goggins</surname>
                           <given-names>Starla</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am a Black woman of West African and American cultural héritage. Having witnessed firsthand thé Détroit riots of thé late 1960s, my politics hâve been gready influenced by thé efforts of those involved in thé Civil Rights Movement. This history, in conjunction with my own expériences of racism within Canada, give me thé particular perspective which I bring to my activist work.</p>
                     <p>I am a white woman frorn Nova Scotia. Having been raised in a région of économie disparity and in a large family with a strong commitment to grassroots community activism, I became politically aware of social inequity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>La création de nos propres institutions:</title>
                     <subtitle>une voie à emprunter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bouchard</surname>
                           <given-names>Lyne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cholette</surname>
                           <given-names>Chantai</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cet article relate notre expérience de gestion féministe qui est en constante évolution depuis 14 ans¹. Nous y discutons, tout particulièrement, de la question de la création d'institutions féministes. Les concepts et les critères de féminisation que nous présentons sont le fruit d’un processus de théorisation des pratiques de<italic>La coopérative Convergence</italic>. Cet exercice, que nous avons nommé « Peau neuve » , nous a permis de réfléchir sur nos pratiques, de raffiner notre analyse et de positionner notre expérience de gestion féministe dans un cadre théorique. Cette démarche de théorisation a marqué un point tournant dans l’évolution de la</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Girl Guides of Canada:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Feminist Promise in the “Promise and Law”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Whitney</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If woman came from Adams rib, as thé Bible claims, so thé Girl Guides came forth from thé Boy Scouts. The analogy is apt, given thé “Muscular Christianity” that imbues thé foundations of both thé Guides and thé Scouts. This particular form of Christian practice saw Victorian men living "by Gods blessing ‘a strong, daring, sporting wild man-of-thewoods’ life” while preaching “a healthful and manly Christianity, one which does not exalt thé féminine virtues to thé exclusion of thé masculine,” as thé Révérend Charles Kingsley wrote in<italic>His Letters and Memories of His Life</italic>(1877) (Houghton 1964, 204). The Boy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dancing the Road to Success:</title>
                     <subtitle>Metro Dance and Women</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gordon</surname>
                           <given-names>Jane</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To most people, dance is a féminine art because women are thé majority of performers. However, dance as a performance art has its own genderbased hiérarchies. In contrast, thé dance group I studied is run largely by and for women and girls, and has been successful and effective in maintaining a structure which is inclusive, non-hierarchical, and appréciative of work donc by women, both paid and unpaid. It has sustained thèse patterns through thé twenty-odd years of its existence and through its expansion from a small, informai group of dancers to a large educational and cultural body in its community.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Place aux actrices sociales! Les Franco-Ontariennes de 45 à 64 ans</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garceau</surname>
                           <given-names>Marie-Luce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>En Ontario français comme ailleurs, nombreuses sont les féministes qui ont montré l’androcentrisme de la recherche dans l’ensemble des disciplines. Assimilées à tout prix dans un savoir qualifié d’objectif et de général, les femmes se sont opposées à des traditions scientifiques qui les empêchent de s’ancrer dans de nouveaux modes de lecture et d’interprétation du réel. Constatant le peu de place qu’on leur accorde, les femmes de l’Ontario français s’insurgent contre l’engendrement d’un savoir masculin qui oublie leur existence.</p>
                     <p>Depuis le milieu des années 1980, les travaux scientifiques des chercheures, tout comme l’action soutenue des intervenantes féministes et des organismes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aboriginal Women’s Economie Renewal:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Project of Re-inventing Strengths from the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hare</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corbière</surname>
                           <given-names>Laura Day</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aboriginal women in First Nation communities in Canada are faced with a légal Foundation not of their making. They must also survive with économie possibilities which were not developed with Aboriginal women in mind.</p>
                     <p>This paper will describe practical methods that allow Aboriginal women to succeed in économie development. A thorough background of thé historical oppression and légal limitations imposed on Aboriginal women — and thé nature and outcomes of thèse limitations — will explain that others besides Aboriginal people are responsible for their deprivation. This review will also explain why économie renewal must be based on thé cultural and historical strengths</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART IV Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Elsy Gagné présente un texte qui oscille entre deux questions chères aux femmes canadiennes. À qui appartient-il de décider de la méthodologie à utiliser lorsqu’il s’agit de féminiser l’institution médicale «masculinisée»? À qui appartient-il de se soucier des femmes dont le corps a été amputé suite à une chirurgie majeure et mutilante ? A la première question, l’auteure répond en disant que la recherche médicale, à tendance positiviste, promeut la supériorité des approches quantitatives qui conduisent souvent à des conclusions décontextualisées du vécu des femmes. À la seconde, Gagné indique que l’institution médicale est peu apte à reconnaître les problèmes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sous le soleil féministe en théologie</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dumais</surname>
                           <given-names>Monique</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Depuis plus de 20 ans, des chercheures féministes en théologie et en sciences religieuses se préoccupent d’investir un champ de réflexion qui est notoirement patriarcal, celui de la théologie¹. Il est en effet apparu et devenu important que les femmes marquent des traces précises et visibles pour manifester qu’elles sont présentes et actives dans le monde de la pensée et de l’action religieuses. La féminisation d’institutions telles que la théologie chrétienne et l’Église catholique est un processus scientifique qui vise à créer et à promouvoir un espace d’expression, de valorisation et d’engagement du potentiel des femmes dans les domaines indiqués.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Réflexion sur les méthodes et la féminisation de l’institution médicale</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gagné</surname>
                           <given-names>Elsy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dans le domaine de la santé, le développement des méthodes de recherche est un phénomène dont les implications économiques, politiques et sociales sont telles qu’il a, jusqu’à présent, suscité des débats intéressants et passionnés. La majorité des écrits portant sur le sujet repose essentiellement sur une conception technique de la science et de ses méthodes. Les chercheurs ne sont concernés que par les effets physiques des traitements mis en oeuvre. Il ne faut donc pas s’étonner que ces analyses, s’appuyant sur des techniques de recherche objectives, attribuent au progrès scientifique une place prépondérante parmi les nombreux facteurs de succès. Mais</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Alternatives to Hierarchy in Feminist Organizational Design:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case Study</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Laiken</surname>
                           <given-names>Marilyn E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Many non-profit and social-change organizations, working to make thé world a better place, manage to create work environments that are social nightmares for their staffs. The lack of good management in thèse organizations often drives their most dedicated employées and volunteers away, frustrated and resentful” (Britell 1992, 84).</p>
                     <p>Beyond management practices, which include issues of power and particular difficulty with thé rôle of executive director (Martin 1990; Ristock 1991), there seem to be many other obstacles to thé effective functioning of such organizations. Issues of class, gender, and ethnicity challenge increasingly multi-cultural and mixed économie workforces: “The attempt to replace</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Personal and Organizational Change:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Feminist Sexual Assault Program</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Coholic</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Prévost</surname>
                           <given-names>Colette T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sexual Assault Program Women share thé common expérience of being treated “differently” from men. What many of us do not share is thé expérience of being able to articulate how oppression, inequality, and sexism détermine our “différent” treatment. In général, we are not exposed to environments which can assist us or which encourage us to learn about our unequal status. This is in keeping with a patriarchal culture which dictâtes what is “normal” for us¹. In our view, feminizing means two things. First, particular attention will be paid to thé sociological and political circumstances and context of womens lives. Feminist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Feminization of the Black Baptist Church in Nova Scotia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moreau</surname>
                           <given-names>Bernice</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I believe that any inquiry into Black Canadian womens tradition could spark controversy and debate over thé interprétation of concepts such as spirituality. This paper, an interprétation of thé religious or spiritual practices of a group of Black Canadian women in résistance to patriarchal church governance, is no exception. Be that as it may, I will argue that thèse Black womens religious or spiritual practices, until recently, were not only for their personal satisfaction and empowerment but were also stratégies for change in their spiritual community. It is worthy of note that thèse Christian Baptist women were not unique in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART V Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Feminist researchers Baukje Miedema and Nancy Clark describe thé lives of working-class women who choose to mother other peuples children. This paper leads to an interesting examination of thé family, with an exploration of mothering, childhood, and family relations. The New Brunswick foster mothers interviewed in this article must often use their own runds to meet thé needs of thé children in their care since state support is insufficient. Child care, including thé nurturing donc by thèse women, has little status in society. While thèse social relations oppress foster mothers and thé children they care for, thé authors report that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mothering for the State:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three Stories of Working Class Foster Mothers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miedema</surname>
                           <given-names>Baukje</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nason-Clark</surname>
                           <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Poster mothers are women who enter a contractual relationship with thé child welfare System for thé care of children who hâve been apprehended by thé state. Poster care can be described as “thé provision of planned, preferably short-term, substitute care for children who cannot be adequately maintained at home” (McKenzie 1989,1). In New Brunswick, thé rôle of thé foster mother and other foster family members is described as providing thé apprehended child with “stability of a substitute family” (New Brunswick Health and Community Services Information Sheet n. d.).¹</p>
                     <p>From an outside perspective, foster mothers appear to be exploited by thé</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Caring to Overcome Differences, Inequities, and Lifestyle Pressures:</title>
                     <subtitle>When a Parent Has a Disability</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blackford</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This article discusses disability and family life, arguing that living with disability can heighten ones appréciation for and practice of thé feminist principles of equity, dailiness, and respect of différence. This article is based on fmdings from a study of 18 Ontario families in which a parent has multiple sclerosis.</p>
                     <p>My personal expérience as a mother with a chronic illness initially provided thé insight that thé rights of people living with disability needs to be addressed. Disablist oppression touches ail family members and usually includes stigma, économie hardship, isolation, and inadéquate access (Abberley 1987). However, as I interviewed each family</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Implementing Principles:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Alternative Community Organization for Children</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reitsma-Street</surname>
                           <given-names>Marge</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rogerson</surname>
                           <given-names>Pat</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this article is to describe thé principles that guided thé development of a community organization serving children. The following is a brief description of thé context for thé organization. Six catégories of principles are described; thèse principles, expressed as objectives, are as follows:</p>
                     <p>To promote active participation of members;</p>
                     <p>To create egalitarian work relationships;</p>
                     <p>To nourish dailiness;</p>
                     <p>To care for thé caregivers;</p>
                     <p>To expand thé capacity to act powerfully;</p>
                     <p>To nurture partners and networks.</p>
                     <p>Examples that illustrate implementation of thèse principles are presented throughout thé article. Spécifie détail is included to reveal one effort to create a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Feminizing Social Welfare:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Needlework Guild of Canada, 1892-1995</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garrett</surname>
                           <given-names>Heather L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The formation of womens organisations was a widespread phenomenon in thé mid-nineteenth century. Many of thèse womens groups began in churches and were committed to charity work. It has been argued that toward thé end of thé nineteenth century, there was an increase in womens organizations committed to social reform (Baines 1988). Some womens groups which hâve been studied are thé Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA), thé Womens Christian Tempérance Union (WCTU), and thé National Council of thé Women of Canada (NCWC). Historians connect thé groups’ émergence with a séries of fundamental changes in thé late nineteenth century: thé entry</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Part VI</label>
                     <title>What We Have Learned</title>
                     <trans-title-group xml:lang="fre">
                        <trans-title>Leçons de nos expériences</trans-title>
                     </trans-title-group>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blackford</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garceau</surname>
                           <given-names>Marie-Luce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kirby</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In thé opening chapter of this book, we reviewed Rosemarie Tong’s (1989) idea that ferninist theory is demonstrated by action imbedded in particular locations and identifies. From this starting point, we introduced each of thé sections of thé book to highlight thé diverse identifies and locations of Canadian authors and their various approaches to creating change.</p>
                     <p>In each chapter, authors presented their explanations of why and how women are oppressed. Now, in this final chapter of Feminist Success Stories, we review where this text has taken us and identify thé collective lessons we hâve learned. Our first major lesson involves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion The Faces of Feminist Change—Les multiples visages du changement féministe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blackford</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garceau</surname>
                           <given-names>Marie-Luce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kirby</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In thé preceding chapter, we hâve analyzed what constitutes success in making feminist change. Our analysis has shown that, although some authors emphasize certain thèmes more than others, each authors work contributes in some way to our understanding of ail thé identified thèmes. In other words, there is a shared understanding of how feminism is defined across many Canadian constituencies. At thé same time, thé constituencies represented in this book vary by bodily condition/disability/ability, geographical location, class, race, âge, and ethnicity. Thus, while there is a shared sensé of what feminism is, it is not surprising to find that feminist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                     <trans-title-group xml:lang="fre">
                        <trans-title>Collaboratrices</trans-title>
                     </trans-title-group>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6rqg.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
