<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Psychology</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Grace for the Injured Self</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Healing Approach of Heinz Kohut</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cooper</surname>
               <given-names>Terry D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Randall</surname>
               <given-names>Robert L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718892586</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718840815</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Terry D. Cooper</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Robert L. Randall</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgdwgd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Grace for the Injured Self shows the reader how the 'self psychology' developed by Heinz Kohut can be an influential theory for pastoral care. The late Kohut affirmed that religion is not only an expression of the self, but can also sustain the self in the alliance between faith and grace, with self psychology and empathy. Cooper and Randall articulately explore Kohut's psychoanalytic perspective of 'self psychology', orientated towards pastoral care for parishioners. The authors ascertain how the human condition is affected by 'self injury', and the relationship between this and the traditional notions of sin. Two interviews with Kohut, never before published in the UK, give the reader unique insights into the psychoanalyst who many regard as the most important figure in psychology since Sigmund Freud.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="176"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Greetings to Our Readers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cooper</surname>
                           <given-names>Terry D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Randall</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Self Psychology Perspective</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>New creative endeavors deeply engage three aspects of the innovator’s life: their thought, their work, and their person. These three are interrelated yet separate domains. It is possible to “read” Heinz Kohut in these three ways. One way is to look at his thought. This has to do with the ideas and conceptualizations at the heart of his self psychology. Another way is to look at his work. This involves a consideration of his self psychology as a treatment approach for those suffering from disturbances of the self. A third way is to look at his person. This focuses on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Self Injury and the Human Condition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Behind every psychological theory is a vision of human fulfillment. An image of optimal health is at work when we name something “neurotic,” “sick,” or “pathological.” We cannot speak of a deficit, a fault, or a sense of brokenness without an image of human health. Or as Paul Tillich used to frequently say, every perspective on the human condition conveys a sense of what is wrong with us, how we can find healing, and how we can sustain the reality of a new life.</p>
                     <p>Kohut’s theory is certainly no exception. After a long and thorough immersion in Freudian psychoanalysis, an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Kohut and the Seven Deadly Sins</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we contrasted Kohut with a broad stream of the Western tradition that has focused on the darker dimensions of the human condition. From this darker perspective, something is inherently wrong with us. Our destructiveness, violence, and capacities for evil emerge from an inherited blueprint that is self-seeking and corrupt. In contrast to this Augustinian/Freudian emphasis on out-of-control drives, we examined the more optimistic view of Kohut. While acknowledging the human capacity for destructiveness, Kohut refused to see that destructiveness as a part of our basic nature. Instead, psychological deprivations and distortions promote the human dilemma. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A New Pastoral Care Orientation for Parishioners</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Students in seminary are taught how to “think theologically.” More is required than just a pious spirit. Clergy need a theological template, a set of perspective-giving tools by which the activities of human life (once symbolized by the newspaper) can be understood from various theological viewpoints (once symbolized by the Bible). In ongoing parish work, pastors typically need to refer to the theological template. They have to consciously apply it rather than having so thoroughly internalized the template that they automatically “think theologically.”</p>
                     <p>We believe that pastors also need to learn to “think psychologically.” More is required than just a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Pastoral Care of the Church as a Group Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A minister tells of being dissuaded in seminary from writing a dissertation on “personalities of parishes.” “you can’t apply individual psychology to complex, heterogeneous groups,” warned his sociologically minded teacher. Methodology aside for the moment, just ask any seasoned minister, denominational leader, or pastoral consultant if congregations have distinct “personalities” and you will see faces light up—or grimace—in affirmation.</p>
                     <p>Self psychology supports this general impression. One of Kohut’s important contributions was to show how a group can be understood to function as a “self” analogous to the self of an individual. The self of a group is its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>First Interview with Heinz Kohut</title>
                     <subtitle>Chicago, March 22, 1981</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Randall</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kohut</surname>
                           <given-names>Heinz</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Randall</italic>: Would you start by relating when and how your interest in religion or religious issues originated?</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Kohut</italic>: I don’t think that I could honestly say that religion is one of my foremost preoccupations. It’s really not. But since I’m interested in human beings and<italic>their</italic>preoccupations, in what makes them tick, what’s important to them, and what’s on their minds, obviously religion is a powerful force in life. It has been an essential aspect of human existence as long as there has been any knowledge of human activity at all. So, naturally I’m interested in it as a student</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Second Interview with Heinz Kohut</title>
                     <subtitle>Chicago, April 12, 1981 (Palm Sunday)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Randall</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kohut</surname>
                           <given-names>Heinz</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Randall</italic>: Our last meeting focused on religion more as a cultural selfobject that supported and encouraged man’s sense of self. I’d like to focus today on religion as an<italic>expression</italic>of man’s creative self, how it arises from man’s own personality, from within his self. You alluded a couple of times in the Heller letters to religion as both an expression of man as well as a support to his sense of self. We focused very well, you did, on religion as a cultural selfobject. What about religion as an expression of the self?</p>
                     <p>Secondly, from studying your writings I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Getting Something from Kohut’s Perspective on Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this final chapter, we will respond to the previous interviews between Randall and Kohut, as well as offer some additional reflections on Kohut’s value for understanding the psychological functions of religion. While the entire chapter represents our combined and united work, we will respond individually to these issues. We believe this will provide the reader with a broader and more comprehensive analysis of Kohut’s potential as a dialogue partner with religion. Thus, Randall’s reflections will be followed by Cooper’s.</p>
                     <p>We are pragmatists. We wrote this book convinced that Kohut’s self psychology perspective offers concrete benefits for the life of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Closing Words for Our Readers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cooper</surname>
                           <given-names>Terry D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Randall</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgdwgd.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
