<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3q38w9</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC423 .B26124 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Democracy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political geography</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Critical theory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Population Studies</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Priority of Injustice</book-title>
         <subtitle>Locating Democracy in Critical Theory</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BARNETT</surname>
               <given-names>CLIVE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">SERIES EDITORS</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Heynen</surname>
               <given-names>Nik</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Coleman</surname>
               <given-names>Mathew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Doshi</surname>
               <given-names>Sapana</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780820351506</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0820351504</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Georgia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Georgia Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pwt43v"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This original and ambitious work looks anew at a series of intellectual debates about the meaning of democracy. Clive Barnett engages with key thinkers in various traditions of democratic theory and demonstrates the importance of a geographical imagination in interpreting contemporary political change.</p>
         <p>Debates about radical democracy, Barnett argues, have become trapped around a set of oppositions between deliberative and agonistic theories-contrasting thinkers who promote the possibility of rational agreement and those who seek to unmask the role of power or violence or difference in shaping human affairs. While these debates are often framed in terms of consensus versus contestation, Barnett unpacks the assumptions about space and time that underlie different understandings of the sources of political conflict and shows how these differences reflect deeper philosophical commitments to theories of creative action or revived ontologies of "the political." Rather than developing ideal theories of democracy or models of proper politics, he argues that attention should turn toward the practices of claims-making through which political movements express experiences of injustice and make demands for recognition, redress, and re pair. By rethinking the spatial grammar of discussions of public space, democratic inclusion, and globalization, Barnett develops a conceptual framework for analyzing the crucial roles played by geographical processes in generating and processing contentious politics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>Arguing with Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is theory good for? Theories are things we argue with. They provide the resources for making validity claims, for drawing inferences, and for constructing generalizations. Arguing with the help of theory is a means of engaging in reasoned debate. And theories are things we use to score points in the midst of an argument. But theories are also things we argue with in another sense, insofar as argument entails passionate, sometimes unreasonable disagreement. Theories can make us angry and invite criticism, if not outright dismissal, because they unsettle our most cherished thoughts. In the social sciences and humanities, arguments</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>An Awareness of Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Democracy seems to have a simple enough meaning. It means “rule by the people.” Or it means “rule by the many,” to distinguish it from monarchy (rule by a single person), aristocracy (rule by the best), or anarchy (the absence of rule). It is common enough to note that the word “democracy” derives from the Greek words “demos” (the people) and “<italic>kratos</italic>” (power). But, as Philip Pettit observes, “Each of these words is ambiguous in an interesting way.”¹ Are the people a unified community or a more pluralistic and divided populace? Should power be understood as equivalent to rule, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Criteria for Democratic Inquiry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I want to elaborate further on why thinking about democracy in an ordinary way, as suggested at the end of the previous chapter, should lead us away from supposing that there is a particular form of politics that is properly political, as if grasping this form would allow lesser forms to be characterized as postpolitical. In particular, I want to consider how best to understand the problem of deriving “context-transcending” principles from the specific situations in which the meanings of democratic politics are articulated. I take it for granted that this possibility can no longer be premised</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Ontological Need</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the next three chapters I critically engage with a set of intellectual traditions that present strongly ontological interpretations of the concept of the political. I argue that ontologies of the political often define democracy in a rather one-sided way, reserving authentic democratic action for the disruption of identities, hegemonies, and settled formations. This one-sidedness derives from the splitting of politics into two aspects and then arranging the world into two layers with a clear order of priority. Obvious and routine understandings of politics are contrasted to a more difficult to discern but more fundamental layer—the site and source</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>The Scandal of Consent</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapter raised the question of how the concept of the political should be interpreted in theories of democracy. One key difference of interpretation is captured in Hannah Pitkin’s distinction between the idealist and realist dimensions of political life and also in Oliver Marchart’s distinction between associative and dissociative concepts of the political. The distinction at stake is not simply one between more consensual or more agonistic perspectives. It is, rather, a distinction that turns on different ways of understanding the dynamics of conflict and discord. Understood in this way, the difference of interpretation is closely related to another</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>The Significance of Conflict</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ascendency of ontological interpretations of political life discussed in the previous two chapters is part of a more broadly shared agreement that liberal political thought has a tendency to displace the disruptions of politics in favor of procedures for efficient administration or for reaching binding agreements.¹ In this chapter I develop the argument that the contrast found in political theory, which is in turn echoed in critical ontologies of space and spatiality, between deliberative approaches to democracy apparently oriented to consensus and agonist approaches that are open to the rigors of intractable struggle is better thought of as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Claims of the Affected</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The chapters in part 2 tracked the way in which strongly ontological interpretations of the political are used to sustain a priori models of proper politics and real democracy. These models underwrite laments about the postpolitical condition as well as excited declarations of the radical potential of dramatic protest events. From within this worldview, properly political events have no determinative content—they exceed given forms of expression and order. Political events occur when singularities that cannot be represented in current formations of political life make their presence felt. Across their variety, whether informed by readings of Spinoza or strands of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Subjects of Domination</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, I argued that debates about cosmopolitanism, environmental issues, global poverty, and transnational migration have helped to draw into view the norm of all-affectedness as the central reference point for thinking about democratic legitimacy. It is easy enough to think that the principle of all affected interests exhausts the question of<italic>who</italic>should constitute the democratic polity. But the principle of affectedness also relates to questions of effective agency, that is, to the capacity to do things. It refers to the<italic>how</italic>of democracy as well the identity of who is affected. The translation of the all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>The Sense of Injustice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The reorientation around the value of non-domination that I discussed in the last chapter is at the heart of the prioritization of injustice in critical theory. In this chapter, we will see that this involves moving away from thinking of injustice as either an empirical deficit measured against an ideal of justice or a conceptual derivative of such an ideal. Among other things, we will see that the prioritization of injustice involves reimagining the dynamics through which demands for democratization emerge in the world in a way consistent with the discussion in chapter 2. This chapter therefore seeks to demonstrate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>Profane Democratization</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have sought in this book to trace divergent ways of conceptualizing the sources of transformative political action in radical thought. In so doing, I have tried to draw into view how radical theorists’ interest in democracy is not simply driven by a concern with substantive or procedural questions of governance, participation, resistance, or rule. Democracy arises in a broad range of Left theory as a worry about the status, the legitimacy even, of the vocation of critique itself. What is at stake in assessing different theories is not simply whether they successfully identify the possibility of social transformation, perhaps</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt43v.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
