<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Retiring to Spain</book-title>
         <subtitle>Women's narratives of nostalgia, belonging and community</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ahmed</surname>
               <given-names>Anya</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781447313311</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1447313313</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bristol, UK; Chicago, IL, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Policy Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1t896fb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book is a study of nostalgia, belonging and community which provides a new theoretical framework for understanding retirement migration. It is the first account of retirement migration that focuses on the voices of retired working-class British women, who are considering either return migration to the UK or permanent/temporary settlement in Spain. Through a narrative approach, we follow their journeys as they seek, recreate and construct community in a new context and their experiences of belonging and non-belonging are unravelled. The book offers a critical perspective, challenging positivistic, essentialist definitions of community.The book offers a critical perspective, challenging positivistic, essentialist definitions of lifestyle migration. We follow the journeys of retired working class British women as they seek, recreate and construct community in a new context.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ahmed</surname>
                           <given-names>Anya</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Retiring to the Costas:</title>
                     <subtitle>British women’s narratives of nostalgia, belonging and community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book focuses on the lives of a group of women from the UK who moved to the Costa Blanca¹ in Spain in retirement. We follow their journeys as they seek ‘community’ and belonging in a world characterised by rapid social change. Imbued with nostalgic yearning, community is hailed as a panacea to the ills of modernity and as a representation of social continuity. Nostalgia denotes the mourning of a lost home or place and a lost time – and in this way – the search for community and belonging can also be understood as a quest for another epoch.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Conceptualising, theorising and narrating retirement migration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus of this chapter is on how I gain knowledge of the processes involved in constructing shifting and overlapping forms of belonging to different kinds of community and how this illuminates experiences of retirement migration. I begin by presenting a discussion of my conceptualisation of retirement migration and then unravel my approach to theory, explaining how women’s experiences and agency are placed within wider structural contexts. I explore how understanding of retirement migration is gained through a thematic and structural narrative analytic approach centring on plot, time, identity or positionality and an analysis of linguistic devices employed. An important</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Locating the women:</title>
                     <subtitle>macro, meso and micro contexts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter I explained my approach to gaining knowledge of the processes involved in constructing shifting and overlapping forms of belonging to different kinds of community. I argued that a thematic and structural narrative approach can illuminate how retired women experience the structural contexts in which their migration takes place, how this shapes agency,¹ and how structures and agency are mediated by their multiple and shifting positionalities. In this chapter I discuss the macro contexts framing retired women’s agency in migration in terms of ‘upper structural layers’ and ‘more proximate structural layers’ (O’Reilly, 2012). The focus then shifts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Boundary spanning and reconstitution:</title>
                     <subtitle>retirement migration and the search for community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Well, purely and simply because someone has had to come up with a word – the word “community” – there has to be such a thing.’ (Deidre)</p>
                     <p>Arguably, all migration is about improving one’s life in some way and the women featured here moved to Spain to enjoy a new lifestyle in retirement. For them, a ‘better life’ involved regaining community and a sense of belonging which had been lost in the UK. Community has been identified as a factor that influences the quality of later life (Conway, 2003) and lamenting the loss of community is a key theme underpinning</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Leaving the UK:</title>
                     <subtitle>motives, agency and decision-making processes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter I suggested that thinking with community and how – and to what – people construct belonging illuminates processes of social change and continuity from particular social locations or positions. Retirement migration was presented as a form and consequence of social change, involving both boundary spanning and reconstitution. The important role of nostalgia as a cultural resource in constructing belonging to different forms of community, evoking an imagined lost place or time, particularly for older people was also considered. In this chapter, I explore the reasons for women’s dislocation in and from the UK, and the decision-making</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Living in Spain:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘idyllisation’ and realisation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter I focused on how my research participants felt dislocated from and in the UK and how their sense of belonging was fractured. Women experienced disengagement from the UK as a place, or space, and also as temporal disjuncture since they also rejected the UK in the present. Age and ethnic positionalities, too, shaped feelings of disruption regarding being on the margins through retirement and the presence of ‘others’ through immigration to the UK. I unravelled the multiple motivations for women’s migration, taking account of structural forces, their unique biographies and agency and positionalities through structurally analysing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Belonging to networks:</title>
                     <subtitle>reconciling agency and positionalities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter I focused on how the women featured experience and narratively construct belonging and non-belonging to Spain and the complex relationships they have with place(s), highlighting that such associations can be imagined and pragmatic, shaped by social ‘locations’, and also contingent on experiences and intentions, or the end point of plot movement (Bakhtin, 1981). In this chapter, the core theme is networks and their connection with spatial, temporal and social locations. I explore how geographical location – where one is from and where one is located – is significant in shaping belonging to networks and how women’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Renegotiating family relationships:</title>
                     <subtitle>managing intimacy from a distance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is now becoming clear that the relationship between place – being from the UK and living in an urbanisation in Spain – shapes the kind of networks that women form and is also influenced by their translocated positionalities. For Cynthia, Celia, Mabel, Margot, Mabel, Agatha and Myra, fulfilling the quest’s goal was possible because they were able to overcome a number of obstacles. Bernice and Viv were satisfied by living a heterolocal life, enjoying the best of both worlds, spending part of the year in the UK and part of the year in Spain, while Enid, disillusioned by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Locating ‘home’ and community:</title>
                     <subtitle>the end point of plot movement</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout this book we have followed women’s migration journeys across space and time as they spanned and reconstituted boundaries. Beginning with their pre-migration lives – characterised for many by fractured belonging in the UK – upper and more proximate structures enabled and facilitated their agency in moving to Spain in retirement. We have also seen that women’s positionalities and unique biographies are also significant in shaping migration choices, decision-making processes and their post-migration lives. I framed divergent migration trajectories in relation to two plot typologies: the quest and voyage and return. Those women who ultimately chose to remain in Spain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>Nostalgia, belonging and community: linking time and space</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I premised at the outset that the idea of community is often romantic and utopian, idealising and evoking a bygone age. Often considered to have been ‘lost’ through modernity, community has also been hailed as the solution to social ‘problems’ by successive governments in the UK. From the New Right to the present Conservative-led coalition government, community has become synonymous with a relinquishment of responsibility by the state (Hoggett et al, 1997). When the women made their move to Spain, community in policy circles was presented by the then government, as a panacea to the lack of social cohesion among</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Vera and Deirdre moved back to Yorkshire in 2005, and Agnes and her husband moved back to Norfolk in the same year. Enid and her husband sold their holiday home in the Costa Blanca in 2006, and bought one in Florida. In 2006 Jenny left her husband and returned to the UK and rented a property close to where her daughter lived. Lillian and her husband bought a house further inland in southern Spain and kept the house in the Costa Blanca as a holiday home.</p>
                     <p>Throughout this book I have emphasised that knowledge is contextually and temporally specific and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1t896fb.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
