<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kw28fz</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr62h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Forgiveness to Come</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Holocaust and the Hyper-Ethical</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Banki</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">series editors</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cornell</surname>
               <given-names>Drucilla</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Berkowitz</surname>
               <given-names>Roger</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823278657</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823278671</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0823278670</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xhr62h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book is concerned with the aporias, or impasses, of forgiveness, especially in relation to the legacy of the crimes against humanity perpetrated by the Nazis and their collaborators during World War II. Banki argues that, while forgiveness of the Holocaust is and will remain impossible, we cannot rest upon that impossibility. Rather, the impossibility of forgiveness must be thought in another way. In an epoch of "worldwidization," we may not be able simply to escape the violence of scenes and rhetoric that repeatedly portray apology, reconciliation, and forgiveness as accomplishable acts.</p>
         <p>Accompanied by Jacques Derrida's thought of forgiveness of the unforgivable, and its elaboration in relation to crimes against humanity, the book undertakes close readings of literary, philosophical, and cinematic texts by Simon Wiesenthal, Jean Améry, Vladimir Jankélévitch, Robert Antelme and Eva Mozes Kor. These texts contend with the idea that the crimes of the Nazis are inexpiable, that they lie beyond any possible atonement or repair. Banki argues that the juridical concept of crimes against humanity calls for a thought of forgiveness-one that would not imply closure of the infinite wounds of the past. How could such a forgiveness be thought or dreamed? Banki shows that if today we cannot simply escape the "worldwidization" of forgiveness, then it is necessary to rethink what forgiveness is, the conditions under which it supposedly takes place, and especially its relation to justice.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>To Forgive the Unforgivable</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a scene composed by Ingeborg Bachmann for her unfinished novel<italic>Franza</italic>(1965–66), the protagonist, Franza, visits a “doctor” who had taken part in medical experiments at Dachau and in the Nazi euthanasia program at Hartheim. He now lives as a free man in Cairo, Egypt. After having confronted him, by telling him that she has read all the documents and knows who he is, she is surprised by the words she then says to him:</p>
                     <p>Forgive me [<italic>Verzeihen Sie</italic>], she said. The two of them stood there; he no longer pressed at her and she also didn’t move.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Survival of the Question:</title>
                     <subtitle>Simon Wiesenthal’s The Sunflower</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1969, Simon Wiesenthal, already internationally recognized for his work in the Documentation Center of the Association of Jewish Victims of the Nazi Regime in Vienna, published an autobiographical narrative based on an exceptional encounter between himself and a dying, repentant Nazi soldier. On his deathbed this soldier confessed to Wiesenthal that he had participated in the murder of hundreds of Jews (including children) and asked Wiesenthal—at the time himself a prisoner in a concentration camp in Poland—for his forgiveness. Responding at the time with silence, Wiesenthal confessed nonetheless to being haunted by the dying man’s request, unable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Reading Forgiveness in a Marrano Idiom:</title>
                     <subtitle>(Jacques Derrida)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many recent studies have focused on the contemporary proliferation around the world of requests and offers of apology, reconciliation, and forgiveness. Eliza Barkan, notably, has spoken of an “age of apology,” referring to the impressive number of heads of state, leaders of the ecclesiastical hierarchies, and even multinational companies, who over the last twenty-five years have been asked to—and in some cases have made—public confessions, offers of apology, and requests for forgiveness.¹ It is to the detriment of many of these studies that they have not been informed by a careful reading of the work of the philosopher</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Crimes against Humanity or the Phantasm of “We, Men”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction, I analyzed in what sense the invention of a concept of “crimes against humanity” in international law may be interpreted as a sign of moral progress, a sign of history (<italic>Geschichtszeichen</italic>) in the Kantian sense. By virtue of this concept, the international community recognizes—at least in principle—a crime whose seriousness is such that it remains universally and eternally open to prosecution. In this chapter, I shall analyze in what senses the concept of “crimes against humanity” remains, despite this moral advance, bound to a humanist metaphysics whose limits today more than ever need to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Hyper-Ethics of Irreconcilable Contradictions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Vladimir Jankélévitch</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Until recently the work of French philosopher and musician Vladimir Jankélévitch (1903–1985) has been scarcely acknowledged in the English-speaking world. Over the last few years, some of his texts have appeared in English translation, in part because of the growing recognition of the importance of his moral philosophy for figures such as Paul Ricoeur, Emmanuel Levinas, and Jacques Derrida.¹ It is little known, for example, that Emmanuel Levinas acknowledged Jankélévitch as a source of the notion of the “absolutely” or “wholly other” (<italic>le tout autre</italic>).² Born of Russian Jewish émigrés, a student of Henri Bergson, about whom he wrote</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Forgiveness as a Jewish Joke</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is no doubt significant that on the sole occasion (to my knowledge) where Derrida provides an affirmative characterization of what forgiveness is or might be, it is by means of the interpretation of a joke. Forgiveness is a joke perhaps: an object of ridicule and scepticism; or, following Freud’s famous argument, a mechanism by which repressed psychic energy, for example, aggressive or sexual urges, are discharged without fear of social sanction:</p>
                     <p>Two Jews, long-time enemies, meet at the synagogue, on the Day of Atonement [<italic>le jour du Grand Pardon</italic>]. One says to the other [as a gesture, therefore, of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>What an Art of Living!</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dear Professor,</p>
                     <p>Part of me would love to be finished with this book and move onto the next chapter of my life. Not finishing holds me back, etc. But, as you know from wherever you are, there’s no being finished with this … You didn’t like to talk too much about the Holocaust, reminding people that much of what is usually said about it is not specific to it, and that one need not to refer to this event to make many of the same arguments about memory, responsibility, testimony, and so on. Provocatively, you even used the word “holocaust”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr62h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
