<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR428.D4 A53 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Early modern, 1500–1700</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Death in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Metaphor in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Analogy in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Allegory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Light and Death</book-title>
         <subtitle>Figuration in Spenser, Kepler, Donne, Milton</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Anderson</surname>
               <given-names>Judith H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823272778</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823272808</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1h1hww3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Light figures being; darkness, death. Bridging mathematical science, semantics, rhetoric, grammar, and major poems, Judith H. Anderson seeks to negotiate writings from multiple disciplines in the shared terms of poiesis and figuration rather than as cultural opposites. Analogy, a type of metaphor, has always been the connector of the known to the unknown, the sensible to the infinite. Anderson’s study moves from the figuration of light and death to the history of analogy and its pertinence to light in physics and metaphysics, from Kepler to Donne, Spenser, and Milton. Topics proliferate: creativity, optics, the relation of literature to science, the methodology of thought and argument, and the processes of narrative, discovery, and interpretation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues of Death, Light, and Analogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Introducing this book, the word<italic>issue</italic>, derived from Latin<italic>exire</italic>, “to go out” or “go forth,” embraces a range of meanings, among them “outflows,” “questions,” or “problems,” which in turn suggest “results,” “departures,” “developments,” or even “extensions.”¹ English<italic>issues</italic>is itself a historical extension of<italic>exire</italic>, one issuing from this verb over time. For readers of early modern texts,<italic>issues</italic>and its implied Latin root hold a haunting memory of Donne’s play on it in<italic>Deaths Duell</italic>, famously his own funeral sermon, which examines the issues from, in, and through death—Latin<italic>à</italic>(<italic>ab</italic>),<italic>in</italic>, and<italic>per</italic>death—and charges</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>“The Body of This Death”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Donne’s Sermons, Spenser’s Maleger, Milton’s Sin and Death</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Romans 7:24, Saint Paul, lamenting the conflict between his enlightened mind and his sinful flesh, utters a cry that has echoed down the centuries: “O wretched man that I am! Who shall deliver me from the body of this death?” Almost predictably, Paul’s moving outcry attracted the sustained attention of the poets of early modern England, conspicuous among them Spenser, Donne, and Milton—predictably, not only because of Paul’s anguish but also because of its unusual phrasing and figuration. Popular English translations of the Bible, such as Geneva and King James, in accord with the Latin Vulgate and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Mutability and Mortality in The Faerie Queene</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Spenser’s Mutabilitie Cantos engage the subjects of sin and death from start to finish—from the introduction of Mutability herself through the end of her pageant. Descended from Mother Earth and the rebellious Titans, Mutability desires “Rule and dominion” over Earth, her maternal inheritance, “That as a Goddesse, men might her admire, / And heauenly honours yield” (VII.vi.4). To this end, she has perverted the order of Nature, quite altered “the worlds faire frame,” and made all those “accurst / That God had blest” (vi.5):</p>
                     <p>Ne shee the lawes of Nature onely brake,</p>
                     <p>But eke of Iustice, and of Policie;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Satanic Ethos:</title>
                     <subtitle>Evil, Death, and Individuality in Paradise Lost</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The organization of this chapter on<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>might be considered a diptych. The first of its panels—Part I—shows the origin of evil, hence sin, in Satan’s envy when the Son is exalted, an envy that underlies Satan’s self-authoring pride.¹ This panel focuses primarily on negation and death. Part II, the second panel, which examines God’s terms of exaltation in greater detail, focuses on the inseparable questions of individuality, allness, and pride, each of which, even pride, has a more positive potential.² My argument in both panels grows out of two crucial speeches in Book V, examining them</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Connecting the Cultural Dots:</title>
                     <subtitle>Classical to Modern Traditions of Analogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Changing focus, this chapter engages the history and structure of analogy. The change is pronounced—from sin and death to rhetoric, from poetry and belief to science and methodology. In manner, the chapter is historical, analytical, and abstract, in effect a further shift. These changes threaten to confirm the very chasm between science and the humanities against which I argue. Yet my first three chapters have treated matters that relevantly recur in this one, such as physical and intellectual vision, body and mind, imagination, knowledge, figurative illumination, and Neoplatonism. More importantly, the argument of this chapter enables a theorized broadening</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Proportional Thinking in Kepler’s Science of Light</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Light is at the center of Kepler’s optics, astronomy, and cosmology. Verbal and mathematical analogy, whether as concept, proportion, or both, is crucial to his methodology and, indeed, to his habits of thought. In addition to these thematic and methodological reasons, Kepler plays an exemplary role in my study because he is an intellectual hybrid who combines ideas about light, deriving especially from Neoplatonist and perspectivist traditions, with mathematical and physical discoveries anticipating those of Descartes and Newton, both of whom number among his debtors. The longstanding debate as to whether Kepler’s work is the culmination of medieval perspectivism or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Analogy, Proportion, and Death in Donne’s Anniversaries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ample evidence exists that Donne read at least one, and possibly two, of Kepler’s earlier writings on astronomy, that he actually met Kepler, and that he probably knew, or heard, at some point about Kepler’s experiments concerning vision. Eventually, he was at least aware of Kepler’s<italic>Harmonice mundi</italic>. My Introduction has treated these observations in greater detail. I reemphasize here, however, that my present concern is with the larger cultural pertinence for Donne’s<italic>Anniversaries</italic>of Kepler’s thinking, which is broadly representative of a large body of thought “at the dawn of modern science,” rather than with the direct influence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Milton’s Twilight Zone:</title>
                     <subtitle>Analogy, Light, and Darkness in Paradise Lost</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Culturally, associatively, and naturally, light brings with it reference to darkness, as day to night and life to death. The symbolic valences of night and light, together with their phonic likeness, occupied Milton throughout his writing, but especially after his blindness, as his blind protagonist eloquently testifies in<italic>Samson Agonistes</italic>. Various half-lights, such as twilight, dusk and dawn, shade and shadow, enter the picture, too. These belong neither to light nor to darkness, neither exclusively to day nor to night; in them, light and dark combine suggestively. In<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>, Milton’s figure of Death is recurrently called a shade or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hww3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
