<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h097q</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P92.5.M24A8 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">McLuhan, Marshall, 1911-1980</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>At the Speed of Light There is Only Illumination</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Reappraisal of Marshall McLuhan</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moss</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Morra</surname>
               <given-names>Linda M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776615431</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776615432</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Ont. Canada</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ckpd28"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>At the Speed of Light There is Only Illumination</italic>collects a dozen re-evaluative essays on Marshall McLuhan and his critical and theoretical legacy; from intellectual adventurer creating a complex architecture of ideas to cultural icon standing in line in Woody Allen's Annie Hall. Given McLuhan's prominent status in many academic disciplines, the contributors reflect a multi-disciplinary background. John Moss and Linda Morra chose the essays from a gathering of McLuhan's academic devotees. The contribution - from "McLuhan as Medium" and "McLuhan in Space" to "What McLuhan Got Wrong" and "Trouble in the Global Village" - to provide a kaleidoscope of new views. As Moss writes of the collected essays: "Some are big and some are small, some exegetic and some confessional, some stand as major statements and others are sidelong glances; some resonate with the concerns of public discourse and others are private or privileged or impious and provocative. Each consists of many parts, each a design on its own. They speak to each other…they may have come together as one version of what happened."</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="250"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOSS</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Labour day evening, 2001; the CBC is rebroad-casting a mosaic of interviews from “This Hour Has Seen Days,” originally televised in 1966. There is Pierre Trudeau, a slightly effete and nervous intellectual coaxing the Liberal Rene Levesque into admitting the inefficacy of Quebec separation; actually, Larry Zolf conducts most of the interview, but history intervenes, and the viewer sees the nearly silent Trudeau as key player in the discourse. There is Leonard Cohen making love to the camera, making love to the smitten interviewer, loving himself, making the viewer voyeur. And there is Marshall McLuhan, introduced by Patrick Watson with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Move to the Glebe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOSS</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I stopped reading books when i turned fifty. Under the aegis of Marshall McLuhan, I determined that the impact of print on my life was antithetical to living well. Not being a zealot, I have not given up reading in dailies or weeklies the captions under photographs, or print on signs or cereal boxes, or printed texts emblazoned on screens; nor, when I made the conversion from print to experience, did I consign my library to a ceremonial pyre. I am neither a fanatic nor given to grandiloquent gestures. Instead, I boxed up the vast collection of leatherbound books I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>McLuhan as Medium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DILWORTH</surname>
                           <given-names>TOM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By 1964, when marshall mcluhan was already an international culture star, I was an undergraduate at the college in the University of Toronto where he taught English literature. He was pointed out to me as he strode across campus, tall, lanky, in what looked like an orange suit. Various people who knew him remarked that he was colour blind, but he was not—he was simply unconcerned with matters sartorial. He took vast strides, his long legs pushing slightly to the outside, as if he were trying to cover as much ground as possible in all directions, even as he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>McLuhan and Canadian Communication Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BABE</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marshall mcluhan was, if anything, enigmatic, paradoxical, and seemingly self-contradictory. Most famously, he exalted the “global village” for “retribalizing” humankind—that is, for restoring wholeness and cooperation to a humanity fragmented by print. He even likened it to the mystical body of Christ—as the fulfilment of human destiny and purpose.¹ He also warned against the global village, however, claiming it to be totalitarian, full of spite, and devoid of privacy. “It never occurred to me,” McLuhan intoned, “that uniformity and tranquillity were the properties of the global village. It has more spite and envy.”² Similar-seeming contradictions pertain to his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Marshall McLuhan and the Modernist Writers’ Legacy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LAMBERTI</surname>
                           <given-names>ELENA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After almost two decades of more or less oblivion, Marshall McLuhan is back in vogue. Looking through the rear-view mirror of knowledge, the new generation of media scholars has finally decided to resurrect him, turning the “media guru” into a powerful icon, enhancing new hightech speculations: today, the gospel of Marshall McLuhan, the “Patron Saint” of the “Information Era,” is evoked to support new theories, interpretations, and ideas. To a skeptical observer, the proselytes of the World Wide Web look like the new prophets eager to explain what McLuhan said, what McLuhan foresaw, and even what McLuhan would say if</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Retracing the Labyrinth of Modernism:</title>
                     <subtitle>McLuhan and the Aesthetic Moment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MANGANIELLO</surname>
                           <given-names>DOMINIC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marshall mcluhan sounds a keynote of his literary criticism with a description of modern art as a process of recovery by retracing. Landmark works such as<italic>Ulysses</italic>and<italic>The Waste Land</italic>move simultaneously forward and backward in a timeless present, he argues, providing the reader with a discontinuous or cubist perspective from which to view various stages of aesthetic apprehension. This modernist method of composition in reverse was made possible by the shift in focus from exterior to interior landscape, a<italic>paysage intérieur</italic>, that occurred after Edgar Allen Poe, Charles Baudelaire, Rimbaud, and Stephane Mallarme. The period spanning the early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Shall I Say, It Is Necessary to Restore the Dialogue?”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wilfred Watson’s Encounter with Marshall McLuhan, 1957-1988</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TIESSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between 1991 and 1999, the Bruce Peel Special Collections Library at the University of Alberta made available, in three successive instalments, the thousands of pages of unpublished manuscripts that the avant-garde play-wright and experimental poet Wilfred Watson had donated to the University of Alberta archives.³ Central to the collection are many dozens of notebooks that Watson kept and wrote in, often daily, from the mid-1940s on. The notebooks are a kind of private intellectual journal. They range in content and include everything from drafts of Watson’s plays and letters to playful experiments with poetry to Picasso-esque drawings and watercolours. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>McLuhan, Media, and Hybridity:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Revaluation in the Postcolonial Context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AJAYAKUMAR</surname>
                           <given-names>P. P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marshall mcluhan’s theory of “hybrid energy” adopts, almost self-evidently, a hybrid structure. Although he develops and refines this concept in association with his revelations regarding various forms of media, he also links this concept with larger cultural experiences. Connecting the interplay of media with civilians, relating society to the human psyche, and juxtaposing fission and fusion, McLuhan crosses the boundaries of diverse disciplines and concepts to reveal the interaction among them. When he observes that “everybody notices how coal and steel and cars affect the arrangements of daily existence,” he seems to assert not only the interrelationship between apparently unconnected</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Does the Space Make Differences?</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Geographical Remarks about Spatial Information between Harold Innis and Marshall McLuhan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NEVE</surname>
                           <given-names>MARIO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since what I will try to probe and uncover is part of research in progress, many questions will probably remain unanswered. First, I will briefly outline, with the aid of Harold Innis’s concept of “bias,” some features of a possible definition of<italic>spatial information</italic>that meet the present crisis in the traditional concept of territory. Second, I will show how Marshall McLuhan gestures toward the cartographic origins of nation-states—that is, the way in which map, as medium, really<italic>processed</italic>the world. Finally, I will suggest a possible and very general frame of reference for further research. My intention is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>McLuhan in Space</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAVELL</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1973, marshall mcluhan made a film for the<italic>Great Minds of Our Times series</italic>called<italic>Picnic in Space</italic>.¹ The film begins with static and a voice-over of McLuhan speaking about several kinds of space—visual, acoustic, Greek, Roman, enclosed, open, and so forth. Then we see the tide, against a blue background, which cuts to McLuhan walking in a parking lot set against a backdrop of buildings in the Gothic academic style. McLuhan enters an automobile and is filmed as reflected in its rearview mirror. He speaks of how the Greeks never thought of the world as coming in²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Making Sense of McLuhan Space</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOW</surname>
                           <given-names>GORDON A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Metaphor is a polestar in the work of Marshall McLuhan: everything revolves around it. His journey through media, culture, and mind was guided largely by means of metaphor, since his thoughts on technology, his method, and his mode of presentation were all intimately oriented toward it in some form or another. Yet the contemporary study of metaphor in McLuhan’s work is made difficult precisely because it is so pervasive. This paper is an initial attempt to chart some of the contours of a persistent<italic>form</italic>of metaphor in McLuhan’s work—namely, that of space. Spatial metaphor, as I will demonstrate,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What McLuhan Got Wrong about the Global Village and Some Things He Didn’t Foresee</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FAWCETT</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In may 2000, I accepted an invitation from the University of Ottawa to investigate Marshall McLuhan’s mistakes and over-sights at a commemorative conference. I was invited, at least in part, because in the realm of McLuhan studies I have become “the troll”—as one critic put it years ago—who lives under the bridge that leads to the information superhighway, the metaphor for the street system of the “Global Village.” I confess to liking this role, which has been evolving since my book<italic>Cambodia: A Book for People Who Find Television Too Slow</italic>(1986) portrayed Marshall McLuhan variously—on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Wychewode Parke</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FAWCETT</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>#3, (the house number) is of brass—probably from Thailand and of recent manufacture—fixed to a tree at the end of the driveway that overlooks a pond, which is older than the brass or the tree even though probably artificial, the possibly accidental product of road-building.</p>
                     <p>At which road the pond ends, although its waters run beneath the road and likely straight into the storm sewers so as not to risk undermining valuable real estate when rains doth fall,</p>
                     <p>This deducible because it rains on this day in early May,</p>
                     <p>not injurious to real estate</p>
                     <p>rather a genteel making</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Panel Discussion:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Trouble in the Global Village”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHADE</surname>
                           <given-names>LESLIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KROKER</surname>
                           <given-names>ARTHUR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BABE</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FAWCETT</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Leslie Shade: Welcome to this session, “Trouble in the Global Village.” My name is Leslie Shade, and I am a professor here in the Department of Communication Studies at the University of Ottawa. For this panel, we have three esteemed members who are going to address the various problems in the “Global Village.” Starting from my immediate left, we have Canadian author Brian Fawcett, then Professor Robert Babe, followed by Professor Arthur Kroker.</p>
                     <p>First, a few introductory remarks. What did McLuhan mean by the term “Global Village,” and how has it altered and been appropriated into the twenty-first century? Popular</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpd28.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
