<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccm4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS2665.52 .R625 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. Romans, VIII, 1-17</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Metaphor in the Bible</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holy Spirit</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Biblical teaching</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Metaphor, Morality, and the Spirit in Romans 8</book-title>
         <subtitle>1–17</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Robinson</surname>
               <given-names>William E. W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884141877</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884141860</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1h4mhzd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Engage compelling arguments that challenge prominent positions in Pauline studies</italic>
         </p>
         <p>In this innovative book, William E. W. Robinson takes the reader on a journey through Romans 8:1-17 using Conceptual Metaphor Theory and Conceptual Integration Theory. Robinson delineates the underlying cognitive metaphors, their structure, their function, what they mean, and how Paul's audiences then and now are able to comprehend their meaning. He examines each metaphor in the light of relevant aspects of the Greco-Roman world and Paul's Jewish background. Robinson contends that Paul portrays the Spirit as the principal agent in the religious-ethical life of believers. At the same time, his analysis demonstrates that the conceptual metaphors in Romans 8:1-17 convey the integral role of believers in ethical conduct. In the process, he addresses thorny theological issues such as whether Spirit and flesh signal an internal battle within believers or two conflicting ways of life. Finally, Robinson shows how this study is relevant to related Pauline passages and challenges scholars to incorporate these methods into their own investigation of biblical texts.</p>
         <p>Features:</p>
         <p>Sustained argument that sheds new light on how Paul communicates with his audiencesSubstantial contribution to current debates about central theological conceptsConceptual Metaphor Theory and Conceptual Integration Theory applied to the metaphors in Romans 8:1-17</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robinson</surname>
                           <given-names>William E. W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the title of this book indicates, my project centers on what I contend are three essential components of Paul’s thought in Rom 8: 1–17: metaphor, morality, and the Holy Spirit. In this introduction, I address these three elements in turn, as each provides a window into the purpose, scope, and thesis of the present monograph.¹ This opening chapter also includes an explanation of the choice of Rom 8:1–17 as the textual focus for this study and an overview of the book’s structure. In the past thirty years or so, scholars have become more attentive to the metaphors</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Metaphor Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As indicated in the introduction, the purpose of this chapter is to provide an overview of metaphor theory and an orientation in particular to Conceptual Metaphor Theory and Conceptual Integration Theory. My overview of metaphor theory begins with an examination of Aristotle’s understanding of metaphor because of its lasting influence on and prevalence in Western culture to this day. Indeed, people in both academic circles and the general population usually view metaphor through an Aristotelian lens.¹ Thus, like Aristotle (and other classical rhetoricians after him), they regard it as a rhetorical trope, an artistic figure of speech, or a decorative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Metaphorical Walk and the SPIRIT-LIFE IS A JOURNEY Metaphor in Romans 8:1–17</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Rom 8:1–17, Paul uses the verb περιπατέω (“walk”) metaphorically to depict the religioethical conduct of believers. Indeed, the most common way that Paul talks about believers’ religious and moral behavior in his epistles is in terms of the human experience and knowledge of walking.¹ Paul’s figurative use of περιπατέω occurs in all of the letters that are attributed to him except Philemon, the briefest, and the pastorals, the most disputed.² In the present chapter, I will deploy concepts and principles of Conceptual Metaphor Theory and Conceptual Integration Theory introduced in chapter 2 in my examination of the constructions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>YOU ARE IN THE SPIRIT AND THE SPIRIT DWELLS IN YOU:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONTAINER Image Schema Metaphors in Romans 8:1–17</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the more puzzling expressions in paul’s letters is the prepositional phrase ἐν Χριστῷ Ἰησοῦ (“in Christ Jesus”), which occurs twice in Rom 8:1–17 (in vv. 1 and 2). As puzzling to Pauline interpreters is the similar construction ἐν πνεύματι (“in the Spirit”) in Rom 8:9. For centuries, biblical scholars have disputed the meaning of these two prepositional phrases, particularly ἐν Χριστῷ Ἰησοῦ. Regarding ἐν πνεύματι, does Paul mean that believers are<italic>literally</italic>“in the Spirit”? If so, how is that possible, and what does that mean? If the expression is instead metaphorical, what is its meaning then?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>From Commerce to Courtroom, “Gallows” to Household:</title>
                     <subtitle>Other Moral Metaphors in Romans 8:1–17</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As indicated in the title to this chapter, I will identify and elucidate four additional moral metaphors in Rom 8:1–17. The first of these is the MORAL ACCOUNTING IS FINANCIAL ACCOUNTING metaphor, a complex conceptual metaphor that is the product of other moral accounting metaphors. Before explicating this metaphor in §5.2.2, I briefly explain its experiential basis in §5.2.1. With an understanding of this particular metaphor in hand, I then show in §5.2.3 how it is manifest in Rom 8:1–17 through one of its moral schemas, the REWARD AND PUNISHMENT schema. The second metaphor I examine (in §5.3)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this book I have examined three essential components of Paul’s thought in Rom 8:1–17: metaphor, morality, and the Holy Spirit. In this concluding chapter I summarize major arguments, findings, and implications of this study with regard to each of these three elements.¹ I close by identifying several areas for further research.</p>
                     <p>In my overview of metaphor theory and in my orientation specifically to Conceptual Metaphor Theory and Conceptual Integration Theory in chapter 2, I demonstrated that the common view of metaphor today is wedded more or less to the thought of Aristotle. Aristotle essentially believed that metaphors are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Modern Authors Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhzd.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
