<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tvq1z</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">RA564.8.W69 1995</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aged</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Medical care</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aged</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Medical care</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Government policy</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aged</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Medical care</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Health Sciences</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A World Growing Old</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Coming Health Care Challenges</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Callahan</surname>
               <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ter Meulen</surname>
               <given-names>Ruud H. J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Topinková</surname>
               <given-names>Eva</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>1996</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781589012271</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1589012275</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>WASHINGTON, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Georgetown University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1q8jj8k"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>For much of the developed world, health care for a surging elderly population looms as one of the most daunting problems of the coming decade. In this book, contributors from diverse disciplinary backgrounds and countries discuss resource allocation for the elderly and debate plans for the years ahead. Essays focus on five general issues: the meaning of old age, the goals of medicine and health care for the elderly, the balance between the needs of the young and old, the pressures of other social priorities, and the role of families, especially the burden on women, in long-term care.</p>
         <p>In consideration of the difficult moral and practical issues involved, the editors conclude the volume with a special report containing policy recommendations from representatives of eight countries (the United States, Belgium, the Czech Republic, Germany, Hungary, the Netherlands, Sweden, and the United Kingdom). This important volume will be of interest to policymakers and a broad spectrum of health care professionals, as well as to anyone interested in the fate of the elderly or in coming health care challenges.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="190"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Callahan</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ter Meulen</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruud H. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Topinková</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is hardly news any longer that health care for the elderly looms as one of the most daunting problems in the decades ahead. Demographic projections in every developed country point to a great increase in the number and proportion of the elderly, particularly after 2005, together with a corresponding decline in the number and proportion of younger people—those who will have financial and social responsibility for the old. The projected increase in the elderly is particularly notable for those over the age of eighty-five.</p>
                     <p>While a majority of elderly people, particularly those in their late sixties and seventies,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How We Care for the Elderly</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is said that the greatness of a nation is measured by how it treats its people. In many nations, the elderly are not given their due respect. But a survey of country reports from the Hastings Center–Maastricht Institute for Bioethics project on care for the elderly makes it clear that not only are the number of elderly growing rapidly but also the way countries care for them is an issue that none will any longer be able to take lightly.¹ The British report refers to a “demographic explosion,” the German report describes “fundamental shifts” that will require new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Meaning of Old Age:</title>
                     <subtitle>Scenarios for the Future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moody</surname>
                           <given-names>Harry R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does old age have any meaning? Does the prolongation of life really amount to a benefit either for individuals or for society? Or on the contrary have recent gains in human life expectancy been instead a prolongation of decrepitude, frailty, and a meaningless existence? No topic seems less promising for productive public debate than a discussion about the “meaning of life.” Talk about “meaning” is notoriously difficult and divisive. Yet without confronting questions about the meaning of old age, we risk impoverishing public discussion of choices that we all must face.</p>
                     <p>Over a decade ago Bernice Neugarten noted the trend</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aging and the Life Cycle:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Moral Norm?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Callahan</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aging poses a peculiar puzzle for medicine.¹ As a biological reality, aging is an inherent part of organic life, affecting humans no less than animals, plants, and microorganisms. It is in that sense beyond the realm of medicine, a permanent backdrop to all of life. But aging is also ordinarily accompanied by disease, bodily decline, and disability. It is thus well within the realm of medicine, whose historical mission has been the cure of disease and the relief of pain, each much desired by those who grow old.</p>
                     <p>Yet is it necessarily true that aging as an inherent part of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Life Extension and the Meaning of Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van Tongeren</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay I will present some philosophical reflections on the desire for life extension, a desire that most gerontological literature as well as public discussion—for example, on resource allocation—seem to take for granted. Although life extension generally is taken as a statistical concept, I will consider it transposed to individual experience.</p>
                     <p>I will ask whether people really desire to extend their life and why exactly we think they do. For this purpose I will first distinguish between different kinds of desire; second, I will reflect upon the concept of a natural life span; and third, I will</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Will There Be a Scarcity of Resources?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Future Demand for Care by the Elderly</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van den Berg Jeths</surname>
                           <given-names>Anneke</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thorslund</surname>
                           <given-names>Mats</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the major issues in the debate about the future of care is how to keep costs under control while meeting the growing demands for care. Addressing that, especially on an international scale, is far from easy. How are we to determine what the demands for care will most likely be? Even if it is not possible to estimate the future number of dependent elderly persons with any precision, it is hard to ignore the most probable scenario: a substantial increase in the number of the oldest old.</p>
                     <p>What factors—demographic, cultural, economic—will shape the future use of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Effects of Population Aging on Health Care Expenditure and Financing:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Illustrations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leidl</surname>
                           <given-names>Reiner</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Europe the impact of population aging has become a popular threat to the health care systems. Recently, 2,700 European “opinion leaders” working in the health field were asked to identify the most significant problem contributing to the growth of health care expenditure. The survey reported population aging to be the number one issue.¹ Much of the popularity of this response may be related to the fact that it is hard to blame someone in the health field for this problem.² But in contrast to this broad agreement on the significance of the population aging issue in the health field,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Caring for the Elderly:</title>
                     <subtitle>Priorities for an Aging Population</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thorslund</surname>
                           <given-names>Mats</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parker</surname>
                           <given-names>Marti G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In most industrialized countries, the needs and demands for medical care and social services for elderly people are increasing. There are several reasons for this. One factor these countries have in common is that the number and the proportion of elderly persons is increasing. This is especially true for persons over eighty years of age. The increase is expected to continue into the next century. Since it is the oldest groups that have the greatest need for care and services, this development is creating a challenge for welfare states.</p>
                     <p>Another factor is advances in technology that provide new possibilities for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Solidarity with the Elderly and the Allocation of Resources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ter Meulen</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruud H. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the cornerstones of European health care systems is the principle of solidarity. The care of the elderly, including health care and social care, is in many respects based on this principle: the young contribute to the costs of care for the old, who have a greater risk of disease and handicaps. But the increasing demand for care by the elderly—resulting from epidemiological changes as well as various social processes—is putting solidarity between the young and the old under strain. Particularly the medicalization of old age, which is draining away resources from long-term care, is an important</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Elderly and High-Technology Therapies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jennett</surname>
                           <given-names>Bryan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are conflicting signals about the benefits and burdens of high-technology therapies for the elderly. Some are concerned that the routine application of cardiopulmonary resuscitation and intensive care for elderly patients in acute crises may serve only to prolong the dying process and deprive the patient of death with dignity. A<italic>New England Journal of Medicine</italic>editorial stated: “The very high suicide rate in older Americans is due partly to concern that they may be unable to stop treatment if hospitalized. Some people now fear living more than dying, because they dread becoming prisoners of technology.”¹</p>
                     <p>Others are more concerned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Meaning of Old Age Impeded by Chronic Disease</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Allert</surname>
                           <given-names>Gebhard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sponholz</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerlinde</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baitsch</surname>
                           <given-names>Helmut</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keller</surname>
                           <given-names>Frieder</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Increasing life expectancy and decreasing birthrates are responsible for a significant demographic change in the industrial nations. In Germany, the proportion of people who are sixty years and older is about 20 percent of the total population; this is similar to other Western nations. Demographic projections show that by the year 2025 about one-third of our population will be over sixty. Already by the year 2000, Germany will have the highest rate of people over sixty compared with the other European countries, the United States, Canada, and Japan.¹</p>
                     <p>This tremendous increase in the number of elderly people in the coming</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Family Caregiving for the Elderly:</title>
                     <subtitle>Are There Ways to Meet the Need?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Topinková</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of filial obligation is an ancient one, and every society and even generation creates its own ideal of the biblical “Honor thy father and mother.” Care for old members of the family was always a moral norm in European culture. It came out of the Judeo-Christian moral premise that it is human and moral to care for the old and helpless in the family and in the whole society and that the young and able have responsibility for those who cannot care for themselves. Relationships in the family based on intimacy and mutuality should be fulfilled with mutual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Adult Daughter Caregivers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosophical Analysis and Implications for Health Care Policy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brakman</surname>
                           <given-names>Sarah-Vaughan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As part of the discussion on resource allocation for the aged, it is crucial to ask not only who the family caregivers are and whether they need assistance but also how the conceptual underpinning of obligations of caregiving can contribute to a more just allocation. This chapter examines only one type of family caregiving, that of adult children to parents. It focuses particularly on the experience of adult daughters as caregivers. A conceptual analysis of the basis of filial obligations is provided in an attempt to deal with some of the dilemmas experienced by these caregivers.</p>
                     <p>The stereotype that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Institutional Care of the Elderly:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lessons from Hungary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blasszauer</surname>
                           <given-names>Bela</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no reason to doubt that a society can indeed very well be judged on the basis of how it takes care of its elderly. By assuring high-quality care, whether by providing it directly in public institutions or by supporting private caregivers, society could demonstrate its appreciation to a whole generation. High-quality care is an ethical concern in at least two senses: providing good care for the elderly is itself an ethical obligation; and care must be provided in an ethical manner, that is, the human dimensions of care ought to take the central place.</p>
                     <p>Both the elderly themselves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From Generation to Generation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Why U.S. Health Care Reform Is So Difficult in the Twentieth Century</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Achenbaum</surname>
                           <given-names>W. Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Health care reform now heads the U.S. domestic agenda. This generation of policy makers may be less successful than its predecessors, however, in effecting major changes. Current players now have different priorities in mind. Some see government as the only institution capable of providing universal coverage for all Americans—a goal that has eluded U.S. reformers for nearly a century. Others have made the containment of rampant inflation in the health care industry their primary objective. Since they embrace divergent policy assumptions, protagonists rarely use the same calculus in figuring costs, fiscal and otherwise.</p>
                     <p>And yet, despite all of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What Do We Owe the Elderly?</title>
                     <subtitle>Allocating Social and Health Care Resources</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ter Meulen</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruud H. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Topinková</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Callahan</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>1.<italic>The highest future goal of medicine for the elderly should be a reduction in morbidity and disability and not an explicit effort to reduce mortality or increase average life expectancy. Old age is an inevitable human condition, one that should not be defined as a medical problem to be conquered or as a set of problems wholly amenable to medical or scientific solutions. Human beings will continue to age, to get sick, and to die</italic>.</p>
                     <p>2.<italic>The maintenance of a firm sense of moral solidarity between the generations has—in the face of competing and fragmenting pressures and uncertainty about the</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Project Participants</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q8jj8k.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
