<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Music, Analysis, Experience</book-title>
         <subtitle>New Perspectives in Musical Semiotics</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Maeder</surname>
               <given-names>Costantino</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Reybrouck</surname>
               <given-names>Mark</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789462700444</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789461661869</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Leuven University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Leuven/Louvain (Belgium)</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Leuven University Press</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Presses Universitaires de Louvain</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Universitaire Pers Leuven</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt180r0s2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Transdisciplinary and intermedial analysis of the experience of music Nowadays musical semiotics no longer ignores the fundamental challenges raised by cognitive sciences, ethology, or linguistics. Creation, action and experience play an increasing role in how we understand music, a sounding structure impinging upon our body, our mind, and the world we live in. Not discarding music as a closed system, an integral experience of music demands a transdisciplinary dialogue with other domains as well. Music, Analysis, Experience brings together contributions by semioticians, performers, and scholars from cognitive sciences, philosophy, and cultural studies, and deals with these fundamental questionings. Transdisciplinary and intermedial approaches to music meet musicologically oriented contributions to classical music, pop music, South American song, opera, narratology, and philosophy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="356"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maeder</surname>
                           <given-names>Costantino</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reybrouck</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part One. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This part reflects on the nature of music. It broadens its definition as a mere description in terms of a sounding structure by comparing it to language and speech. By stressing their roles in action and performance, both music and language in action establish social bonds that afford listeners and performers the feeling of a genuine and shared experience. The figure of the performer who acts as a mediator between music and audience is a crucial element in understanding the mutual relationship between theoretical approaches to music and its possible, actual performances. Ethnomusicology, popular music studies, new musicology and (post-)semiotics,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Music, Speech and Meaning in Interaction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cross</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Music and language seem, in our western conceptions, distinct spheres of human activity. Each has features that the other does not: language can refer, and is of paramount importance in our transactions with each other; music lacks any referential exactness and seem limited to the domain of affect, having powers to elicit emotions and their concomitant personal memories and meanings to a degree to which language, outwith the domain of poetry, rarely aspires. But seen, heard and understood from the perspective of cultures other than our own, the distinctness of music and language blurs. Music, for us primarily an aesthetic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Capturing the Music:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Thin Line Between Mediation and Interference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chueke</surname>
                           <given-names>Zelia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chueke</surname>
                           <given-names>Isaac</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past years, performance studies have brought up many aspects present in music making. The theme is being explored by numerous domains of research implied in the process of building an interpretation and performing it.</p>
                     <p>On the other hand it has also to be considered that perceiving and understanding music doesn’t necessarily involve performance; while the latter is dependent on these first two premises, the contrary is neither always possible nor mandatory. For this paper’s purpose, our focus is the performer and his/her particular approach to the music as a mediator.</p>
                     <p>Adorno summarizes the main difference between theoretical and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Performativity Through(out) Media:</title>
                     <subtitle>Analyzing Popular Music Performance in the Age of Intermediality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corbella</surname>
                           <given-names>Maurizio</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this paper I will focus on performance analysis in popular music from the standpoint of intermediality. Furthermore, I will trace some methodological trajectories that, to be truly tested, should be substantiated by a wide selection of case studies. Since there is no room to extensively concentrate on case studies, this contribution should be considered as a methodological introduction to upcoming new chapters. I claim that the study of how ideas of performativity are translated throughout the web of media in the process of the production, circulation and consumption of a musical artifact can contribute to point out common traits</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part Two. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contributions to this part deal with reception as a crucial part of the communication process: they stress the issue of internal experience as an integral part of musical understanding. As such, the contributions move from semantic to semiotic and hermeneutic questions: what does music mean and how does it mean? Starting from music’s so-called<italic>inability</italic>to function referentially, it could be claimed that music expresses nothing but itself. But what does music represent? How do we read the musical work and what are the levels of sense-making in the imposition of meaning on the music? Contrary to the centrifugal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reading a Work of Music from the Perspective of Integral Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tomaszewski</surname>
                           <given-names>Mieczysław</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I think one can agree with the idea that the primary task of the theory of music, its foundation and its point of departure irrespective of its methodological orientation consists in interpreting a work of music as a result of its<italic>reading</italic>. A work of music is thus understood as a human product for humans, its task being to delight, to stir emotions and to convey meanings and senses. In this system, the interpreter functions as a competent mediator who, by reading the work in the entirety of its inimitable features, helps others to open their ears and eyes, awakens</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>La musique au second degré:</title>
                     <subtitle>on Gérard Genette’s Theory of Transtextuality and its Musical Relevance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Castro</surname>
                           <given-names>Paulo F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of intertextuality was originally developed in the context of poststructuralist literary theory by Julia Kristeva, who introduced the term (ca. 1966) in the wake of her engagement with Mikhail Bakhtin’s notion of dialogism. At around the same time, in<italic>L’archéologie du savoir</italic>, Michel Foucault was writing about the open borders of the book and the way every book is caught up in a system of references to other books (or texts), comparing it to a node within a network (Foucault, 1969, p. 34). The term<italic>intertextuality</italic>, quickly seized upon and given wide currency by Roland Barthes among other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Semiotic Narrativization Processes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marty</surname>
                           <given-names>Nicolas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fludernik (2002) talked about narrativization as the imposition of narrativity by a receiver on an object. Roughly, this means that narrativity is not a stable characteristic of an object, but rests on the receiver’s<italic>experience</italic>of the object.</p>
                     <p>This point of view can prove somewhat fruitful when applied to the study of acousmatic music listening. In fact, it allows for the distinction between a narrative as a recountal of events and narrativity as the quality of anything<italic>that might be made into a narrative</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Fludernik (2002) emphasized that for something to be made into a narrative, there needs to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Musical Understanding:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wittgenstein, Ethics, and Aesthetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chagas</surname>
                           <given-names>Paulo C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ludwig Wittgenstein (1889-1951) is an intellectual myth of the 20<sup>th</sup>century and certainly one of the most original thinkers that Western culture has ever produced.¹ The philosophy of Wittgenstein reflects on issues of logic, mathematics, language, psychology, ethics, aesthetics, religion, etc. His philosophical method combined the rejection of metaphysics and the scientific spirit with clarity and a simple, colloquial-like language, however pushed to such a level of logical precision that it seems to stretch the limits of thinking. The unorthodoxy of Wittgenstein emerges as much in his life as in his thought. For the reader unfamiliar with him, his writing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Where to Draw the Line?</title>
                     <subtitle>Representation in Intermedial Song Analysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wierød</surname>
                           <given-names>Lea Maria Lucas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Musicology has always been puzzled with semantic questions: does music have meaning? The difficulty lies in music’s inability to function referentially. One might say that literature suffers from the opposite problem: verbal texts contain a centrifugal tendency to direct the recipient’s attention away from their artwork character (form) in favor of their referential message (content) (Kyndrup, 2011, p. 87). However, the specific case of poetry (as opposed to prose) often displays a certain quality that maneuvers attention toward the form of the message itself; a move notably termed<italic>the poetic function</italic>by Jakobson (1987, p. 69). This can be understood</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part Three. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The next three contributions explore the biological and ethological sources of musical meaning and affect. They deal with aspects of musical experience and interpretation by going beyond a mere acoustic description of the sound. Music-as-heard calls forth expressive interpretations and emotions. This is the case for the recognition of tonality and tonal melodies, which are not merely sequences or successions of pitches. Being rooted in biological evolution, they can be linked to the transmission of meaning by establishing a kind of specific connection between perception of sounds, memory function and emotional assessment. The biological foundation of tonality can be related</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Ability of Tonality Recognition as One of Human-Specific Adaptations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Podlipniak</surname>
                           <given-names>Piotr</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tonality is understood by musicologists and musicians in many different, often mutually exclusive senses. Sometimes it is regarded as a distinctive characteristic of solely Western music (e.g. Dahlhaus, 1988), but sometimes this understanding is applied to the features of non-Western music too (e.g. Krumhansl, 1990). Even as a term restricted to the features of Western music it is assigned a variety of meanings such as an aspect of melodic relations (Thomson, 1999) or an exclusive trait of harmonic organization (Lowinsky, 1990). Also in the psychological sense,<italic>tonality</italic>is defined by scholars both as the hierarchical arrangements of pitch phenomena in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Musical Semiotics and Analogical Reference</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zbikowski</surname>
                           <given-names>Lawrence M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I should like to begin my consideration of the relationship between musical semiotics and analogical reference with a musical example drawn from Joseph Haydn’s oratorio<italic>The Creation</italic>, which had its premiere in April of 1798. The text for the oratorio comes from one reportedly assembled for but never used by Georg Friedrich Handel, and which was translated and abridged for Haydn’s use by Baron Gottfried van Swieten. The text is a compilation of familiar quotations from the books of Genesis and Psalms with lines reworked from Milton’s<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>, and offers any number of opportunities for pictorial representation. The instance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Other Semiotic Legacy of Charles Sanders Peirce:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethology and Music-Related Emotion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Huron</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Charles Sanders Peirce was a remarkable scholar with broad ranging interests in many areas of philosophy, logic, and metaphysics. The influence of Peirce’s ideas in the modern field of semiotics is well known. Less well known is the influence Peirce had on another discipline, the field of ethology (the study of animal behavior). Largely a European undertaking, the founders of ethology—notably Konrad Lorenz and Nico Tinbergen—were influenced by semiotic concepts in their studies of animal displays and calls. This presentation pays tribute to the achievements of ethology by returning insights from animal behavior back to the humanities and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part Four. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Intermedial and transdisciplinary investigations are of the utmost importance in contemporary research on theoretical musicology. The next four contributions are illustrative of these developments. They deal with the analysis of<italic>medial</italic>properties in terms of perception and analyze the borders between media and possibilities of “intermedial” referencing. This is especially true for musical performance and movie productions, which need a theoretical framework for a complex analysis that takes into account elements from the fields of the visual, advertising and web semiotics. The broadening of the field and scope of musicology by including music, pop culture, gender issues, rhetoric, advertisement and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Death of Klinghoffer:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Stage to Screen</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nellestijn</surname>
                           <given-names>Maarten</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The opera<italic>The Death of Klinghoffer</italic>, by composer John Adams, librettist Alice Goodman, and director Peter Sellars, from the moment of its US première in 1991 in the Brooklyn Academy of Music on, has led to an intensive debate in both the newspapers and the scholarly domain. Central to these debates are its supposed merits and shortcomings regarding its representation of sensitive political issues. This precariousness was heightened after 9/11, shortly after which a performance of the two opening choruses was canceled in an act of self-censorship at the hand of the Boston Symphony Orchestra. It is not unthinkable that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Perception of Art Songs Through Image:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Semiotic Approach</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Pádua</surname>
                           <given-names>Mônica Pedrosa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the current panorama of music research, the researcher/interpreter is faced with the need to develop tools to understand, appreciate and take ownership of the repertoire. It is his or her responsibility to create his or her own reading mechanisms for the production of meaning, and, ultimately, the production of knowledge.</p>
                     <p>Thus, in this paper, I present a proposal of a transdisciplinary methodology for studying Art Song, which consists in the integrated study of music and literature, using image as the transversal concept that pervades both disciplines. This proposal can be considered transdisciplinary inasmuch as it articulates analytic tools of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“What Kind of Genre Do You Think We Are?”</title>
                     <subtitle>Genre Theories, Genre Names and Classes within Music Intermedial Ecology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marino</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabriele</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While single genre histories have been quite explored (e.g., Charlton, 1994; Borthwick &amp; Moy, 2004; F. Fabbri, 2008), the notion of<italic>musical genre</italic>is not very much studied in itself, as a theoretical entity (cf. F. Fabbri, 1982, 2012; Hamm, 1994; Moore, 2001; Marx, 2008). This is not that surprising, as it is a crucial notion (possibly, the highest level of abstraction we can deal with as we talk about music), but, at the same time, a very ambiguous one.¹</p>
                     <p>In this paper, the notion of<italic>intermediality</italic>is employed in a broad and non-plurimedial (Wolf, 2002) sense. Intermediality is here considered</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part Five. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The interaction between analysis and extramusical interpretation brings together five contributions by Pawłowska, Martinelli, Liddle, Hatten, and Thumpston, which explore aspects of musical experience and interpretation by transcending a mere acoustic description of the sound. They all combine theoretical groundings with musical analyses, proposing a type of hermeneutics that relies on the concepts of musical topic, musical allusions and anthropomorphic conceptions of music in terms of musical agency and narrativity.</p>
                     <p>Małgorzata Pawłowska discusses the concept of narrative in an opera by Dusapin. Starting from the current disbelief in narrativity she discusses transformations of the concept. She elaborates on the distinction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Story or Not a Story?</title>
                     <subtitle>Pascal Dusapin’s Opera Roméo &amp; Juliette and New Ways of Musical Narratives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pawłowska</surname>
                           <given-names>Małgorzata</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no doubt that a narrative has been subject to transformation throughout the history of literature and art. In 1979 Jean-François Lyotard claimed that people no longer believed in the so-called<italic>grand narratives</italic>(Lyotard, 1979). In the 1980s, Paul Ricœur asked himself a question, whether the narrative function as such was going to die. Eventually he hoped it was not when he wrote:</p>
                     <p>Perhaps we are witnesses […] of death of a certain kind […] It cannot be ruled out that metamorphosis of the plot will approach a barrier beyond which it will not be possible to recognize a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Authorship, Narrativity and Ideology:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Lennon-McCartney</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martinelli</surname>
                           <given-names>Dario</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The authorial partnership between John Lennon and Paul McCartney, during the 1960s (or afterwards, as individual songwriters), has been the subject of several forms of categorization, not rarely confining with uncritical<italic>clichés</italic>: some of them were based on solid grounds (e.g., Lennon gave more importance to lyrics, McCartney to music), others were facile stereotypes (e.g., Lennon was the rocker, McCartney the balladeer, an insight dismissed by several songs).</p>
                     <p>In the present essay, I intend to offer a semiotic analysis of the two songwriters’ approach and strategies for lyrics composition. In doing that, I hope to fill two particular gaps left</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Sublime as a Topic in Beethoven’s Late Piano Sonatas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liddle</surname>
                           <given-names>Jamie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the last two decades several studies (Bonds, 1997, 2006; Brown, 1996; Sisman, 1993; Webster, 1997) have discussed the relationship between music and the sublime in pre-Romantic aesthetics, examining the evocation of the sublime in the music of the late 18<sup>th</sup>century. These writers have naturally focused on the two most influential conceptions of the sublime within that cultural context, those of Burke (<italic>A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful</italic>, 1757) and Kant (<italic>Critique of Judgment</italic>, 1790). The Burkean sublime begins with “whatever is in any sort terrible, or is conversant about terrible</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Melodic Forces and Agential Energies:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Integrative Approach to the Analysis and Expressive Interpretation of Tonal Melodies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hatten</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Melody is not merely a sequence of pitches in a certain rhythm often found in the upper voice. When we hear, and follow, the melody of a tonal composition, we are experiencing an emergent quality that I call<italic>melos</italic>, which I define as the<italic>foregrounded and continuous expressive focus associated with the principal musical discourse of a virtual human agent</italic>. Following the<italic>melos</italic>may lead us from one voice-leading to another, and even from one line in the texture to another, regardless of register (Pierce, 2007, pp. 46-49) or even timbre (Webern’s<italic>Klangfarbenmelodie</italic>).<italic>Melos</italic>may at times be enhanced or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Embodiment of Yearning:</title>
                     <subtitle>Towards a Tripartite Theory of Musical Agency</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thumpston</surname>
                           <given-names>Rebecca</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The closing line of Alfred, Lord Tennyson’s dramatic monologue<italic>Ulysses</italic>is among the most famous statements of striving in English poetry (1972, p. 646). The poem ends with a heroic statement about moving forward, yet the enduring sense of the prose is one of loss. The poem speaks of Ulysses’ spirit yearning and his goal “To sail beyond the sunset, and the baths/Of all the western stars” (p. 646) until he dies. A beautiful meditation on age, Tennyson’s words are tinged with sadness built on the knowledge that the things for which we yearn are often not achieved: “We are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Editors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt180r0s2.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
