<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">K627.M56 1990</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Status (Law)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Interpretation and construction</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Personality (Law)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Interpretation and construction</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Equality before the law</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Interpretation and construction</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sociological jurisprudence</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social groups</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Law</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Making All the Difference</book-title>
         <subtitle>Inclusion, Exclusion, and American Law</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MINOW</surname>
               <given-names>MARTHA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781501705106</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1501705105</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ithaca; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1990</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cornell University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7591/j.ctt1tm7j8t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Should a court order medical treatment for a severely disabled newborn in the face of the parents' refusal to authorize it? How does the law apply to a neighborhood that objects to a group home for developmentally disabled people? Does equality mean treating everyone the same, even if such treatment affects some people adversely? Does a state requirement of employee maternity leave serve or violate the commitment to gender equality?</p>
         <p>Martha Minow takes a hard look at the way our legal system functions in dealing with people on the basis of race, gender, age, ethnicity, religion, and disability. Minow confronts a variety of dilemmas of difference resulting from contradictory legal strategies-strategies that attempt to correct inequalities by sometimes recognizing and sometimes ignoring differences. Exploring the historical sources of ideas about difference, she offers challenging alternative ways of conceiving of traits that legal and social institutions have come to regard as "different." She argues, in effect, for a constructed jurisprudence based on the ability to recognize and work with perceptible forms of difference.</p>
         <p>Minow is passionately interested in the people-"different" people-whose lives are regularly (mis)shaped and (mis)directed by the legal system's ways of handling them. Drawing on literary and feminist theories and the insights of anthropology and social history, she identifies the unstated assumptions that tend to regenerate discrimination through the very reforms that are supposed to eliminate it. Education for handicapped children, conflicts between job and family responsibilities, bilingual education, Native American land claims-these are among the concrete problems she discusses from a fresh angle of vision.</p>
         <p>Minow firmly rejects the prevailing conception of the self that she believes underlies legal doctrine-a self seen as either separate and autonomous, or else disabled and incompetent in some way. In contrast, she regards the self as being realized through connection, capable of shaping an identity only in relationship to other people. She shifts the focus for problem solving from the "different" person to the relationships that construct that difference, and she proposes an analysis that can turn "difference" from a basis of stigma and a rationale for unequal treatment into a point of human connection. "The meanings of many differences can change when people locate and revise their relationships to difference," she asserts. "The student in a wheelchair becomes less different when the building designed without him in mind is altered to permit his access." Her book evaluates contemporary legal theories and reformulates legal rights for women, children, persons with disabilities, and others historically identified as different.</p>
         <p>Here is a powerful voice for change, speaking to issues that permeate our daily lives and form a central part of the work of law. By illuminating the many ways in which people differ from one another, this book shows how lawyers, political theorist, teachers, parents, students-every one of us-can make all the difference,</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Minow</surname>
                           <given-names>Martha</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Making a Difference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The children’s television show<italic>Sesame Street</italic>instructs with animation, skits, and songs. One song asks, “Which one of these things is not like the others?” The screen depicts a group of items, perhaps a chair, a table, a cat, and a bed. By asking young viewers to pick out the items that do not belong with the rest of the group, the song helps them sharpen their vocabulary, perception, and analysis of objects in the world.</p>
                     <p>I often tell people that if you master this<italic>Sesame Street</italic>episode, you have started to think like a lawyer. For much of legal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>The Dilemma of Difference</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>All the teachers in the San Francisco public schools during the 1960s taught their classes in English, just as they always had. But by the end of the decade a group of parents sought out a lawyer to object that this instruction deprived their children of the chance for an equal education. Their children, who spoke primarily Chinese, were falling far behind in classes taught only in English. The parents pushed the courts to consider whether according the same treatment to people who differ—to the students who speak English and those who speak Chinese—violates commitments to equality.</p>
                     <p>Ultimately,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Sources of Difference</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dilemmas of difference appear unresolvable. The risk of nonneutrality—the risk of discrimination—accompanies efforts both to ignore and to recognize difference in equal treatment and special treatment. Difference can he recreated in color or gender blindness and in affirmative action;¹ in governmental neutrality and in governmental preferences; and in discretionary decisions and in formal constraints on discretion. Why does difference seem to pose choices each of which undesirably revives difference or the stigma or disadvantage associated with it? In this last question lies a clue to the problem. The possibility of reiterating difference, whether by acknowledgment or non acknowledgment,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Ways Out</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The difference dilemma is a symptom of a particular way of looking at the world. The problem arises only in a culture that officially condemns the assigned status of inequalities and yet, in practice, perpetuates them. This ambivalence is itself sustained by a set of usually unstated assumptions. “Different” traits are regarded as intrinsic to the “different” person, and the norm used to identify difference is assumed to be obvious, needing neither statement nor exposure to challenge. Differences are presumed identified through an unsituated perspective that makes other perspectives irrelevant and sees prevailing social arrangements as natural, good, and uncoerced.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>When Difference Has Its Home</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Art restorers use the word<italic>pentimento</italic>to refer to what happens when one painting has been painted over another: the earlier painting, over time, may begin to show through.¹ Perhaps it is not surprising that similar reminders of the past appear in legal arguments: lawyers and judges routinely reuse materials from the past in constructing the new. Yet the reappearance of earlier patterns of thought in legal arguments does not always reflect deliberate design.</p>
                     <p>While I was researching historical legal conceptions of the “law of persons” and the “law of abnormal persons,” the Supreme Court of the United States heard</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Different Histories</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many observers have described Western intellectual and legal histories as moving from notions of fixed and assigned status to notions of individual freedom and rights. Sir Henry Maine’s famous dictum defined progress as the movement from status to contract.¹ Such broadly gauged summaries risk oversimplification and insensitivity to the variety and contestability of understandings of the past. Nonetheless, the contrast between legal orders premised upon status and those premised upon state-guaranteed rights helps to locate notions of abnormal persons and rights analysis as ways for dealing with differences. And as a historical matter, rights analysis in some ways is a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Rights Theories and Contemporary Legal Debates</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As developed by lawyers and theorists during the mid-twentieth century, rights analysis itself cannot remedy the exclusion and degradation of people defined as different by experts and majorities in this society. Despite its liberatory rhetoric of inclusion and fundamental entitlement, the analysis of rights, developed in constitutional and statutory judicial doctrines in this country, runs aground on the shoals of the two-track system of legal treatment. One track offers basic rights to self-determination and participation for those who satisfy the criteria of rational thought and independence; the other offers special treatment and, quite often, social and political exclusion. Those treated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>The Emergence of the Social-Relations Approach</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The limitations of rights analysis were not unknown to the reformers who challenged the institutional treatment of mentally retarded people. They worked within a rights framework but also looked to other disciplines to reimagine the legal entitlements of marginalized people. Litigators developed an argument that the label of mental retardation is a stigma that deprives individuals of their liberty; therefore, the right to due process applies before the label can be assigned.¹ To build this argument, the critics of labeling drew on a theory developed by sociologists and shifted the focus from the deviant person to the process by which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Problems in Relationship:</title>
                     <subtitle>Today’s Feminism and Yesterday’s Progressivism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a Chinese fable about two men who were walking along the river. One said to the other, “Look how happy the fish are as they swim in the river!” The other said, “You are not a fish. How do you know whether the fish are happy?” The first one said, “You are not me. How do you know whether I know what the fish think?”</p>
                     <p>Thinking we are close enough to another to understand poses a risk of presumption. We may wrongly think we know another, yet we may also wrongly doubt anyone’s ability to know, or care</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Rights and Relations:</title>
                     <subtitle>Families and Children</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Progressive reformers and sympathetic theorists at the turn of the century criticized liberal rights for permitting an abusive capitalism and for rendering poor and working-class people vulnerable to urban, industrial hazards and onerous working conditions. Contemporary critics cite the impoverished vision of human community implicit in liberal rights.¹ Something was lost through the triumph of liberal rights, some sense of community and mutual obligation.</p>
                     <p>But Progressivism had problems, too. Its reformers and their spiritual progeny—New Dealers, Great Society staffers, and advocates of social welfare and judicial programs throughout the twentieth century—defined their objective as caring for those in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Dying and Living</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because of changes in medical technology, the birth of a baby born with severe defects now signals a moment of decision.¹ It is a decision about medical treatment; it is also a decision about what meanings the family and society want to give to the life of the infant. It is a decision that cannot be answered by reference to rights—or without them. finally, it is a decision about patterns and qualities of relationships beyond that one family.² Babies who in earlier times would have died may now be rescued through surgery and other medical intervention, but the intervention</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Knowing and Judging</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The case of Phillip Becker is special. It brought together a remarkable judge who felt unusually connected to the people in the litigation, a developmentally disabled youngster, and two volunteers who offered him a better life. What’s more, the unfolding of the case can be described, retrospectively, as a series of challenges to the unstated assumptions common to other cases about mentally retarded persons and about the role of the courts. For example, Judge Fernandez compared the Beckers’ assumption that Phillip’s differences were intrinsic and immutable with the Heaths’ view that Phillip is more like than unlike “normal” people and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Different Beginnings: Making All the Difference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The use of anesthesia in surgery spread quickly once it had been discovered.¹ Nineteenth-century doctors who adopted anesthesia selected which patients needed it and which deserved it; they thought some people’s pain more serious than others; some people were thought to be hardy enough to withstand pain. Both the medical literature and actual medical practices during the nineteenth century distinguished people’s need for painkillers on the basis of race, gender, ethnicity, age, temperament, personal habits, and economic class. Women, for example, were thought to need painkillers more than men; the rich and educated more than the poor and uneducated. How</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Cases</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j8t.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
