<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1fzhg7w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Edinburgh Critical History of Nineteenth-Century Philosophy</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Stone</surname>
               <given-names>Alison</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748635665</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748647019</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748647015</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Edinburgh University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0b1vg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This volume begins with the rise of German Idealism and Romanticism, traces the developments of naturalism, positivism, and materialism and of later-century attempts to combine idealist and naturalist modes of thought.</p>
         <p>Written by a team of leading international scholars this crucial period of philosophy is examined from the novel perspective of themes and lines of thought which cut across authors, disciplines, and national boundaries. This fresh approach will open up new ways for specialists and students to conceptualise the history of 19th-century thought within philosophy, politics, religious studies and literature.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Editors’ Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Caygill</surname>
                           <given-names>Howard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Webb</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosophy in the Nineteenth Century</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stone</surname>
                           <given-names>Alison</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nineteenth-century philosophy can be broadly characterised by several themes: the conflict between metaphysics and religious faith on the one hand and the empirical sciences on the other; a new focus on history, progress and evolution; new ideas of individuality, society and revolution; and ever-increasing concerns about nihilism.¹ This volume provides a re-examination of nineteenth-century philosophy in terms of these and other themes distinctive of the period.</p>
                     <p>It is worth remembering that this was the period in which much of the fundamental structure of modern society took shape in Europe, North America and beyond. At the beginning of this development, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The New Spinozism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>di Giovanni</surname>
                           <given-names>George</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1935 Paul Hazard famously spoke of a ‘crisis of the European mind’ to describe the transition from the earlier confessional era – when reason was still taken to be subservient to faith and political power to the rule of God and the Church – to the Enlightenment, when reason reversed that relation by asserting its autonomy with respect to religious belief and philosophers began to look to reason’s rule for the authentication of political power. Hazard himself dated that transition to around 1680 (Hazard [1935] 1953: xv–xvi). Recent scholarship has pushed this date back to 1650 and has also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Absolute in German Idealism and Romanticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nassar</surname>
                           <given-names>Dalia T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most obscure, yet significant, concepts in early nineteenth-century philosophy is that of the Absolute. As a word, the Absolute came into philosophical discourse with Schelling to mean the ontological ground of and point of identity between subject and object. In this sense Hegel adopted the term in his early works, while in his later writings he came to identify the Absolute with the process and final conclusion of reason. Although it is these figures who employed the words ‘the Absolute’ (<italic>das Absolute</italic>), the idea of the Absolute as the ontological ground in which subject and object are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Question of Romanticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Norman</surname>
                           <given-names>Judith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Welchman</surname>
                           <given-names>Alistair</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Romanticism’ is one of the more hotly contested terms in the history of ideas. There is a singular lack of consensus as to its meaning, unity and historical extension and many attempts to fix the category of Romanticism very quickly become blurry. In his<italic>Conversations with Eckermann</italic>, Goethe says that the concept of Romanticism ‘is now spread over the whole world and occasions so many quarrels and divisions’ (Goethe [1836] 1984: 297) and this situation has not rectified itself in the 180 years since then. But the term was poorly defined from the start. Friedrich Schlegel, frequently claimed as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Hermeneutic Turn in Philosophy of Nature in the Nineteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Huneman</surname>
                           <given-names>Philippe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the nineteenth century the natural sciences underwent a radical transformation. The paradigms of many of the disciplines that we know today, such as geology, chemistry, thermodynamics, cell biology or evolutionary biology, were established in this period. Prior to this period, knowledge of nature was a part of philosophy, as the examples of Leibniz or Descartes show. Moreover, the Kantian critique of metaphysics from the<italic>Critique of Pure Reason</italic>onwards had a profound impact on philosophers, especially in Germany. Kant dismissed the traditional objects of philosophical inquiry such as God, the world and the soul, which for Kant were to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Idealism and Naturalism in the Nineteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gardner</surname>
                           <given-names>Sebastian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The nineteenth century may be regarded as comprising the first chapter in the story, as it must appear to us now, of idealism’s long-term decline and of the eventual ascent within the analytic tradition of a confident and sophisticated naturalism.¹ The chief landmarks of both developments are fairly clear. The former begins with Kant’s Critical Philosophy and the great systems of Fichte, Schelling and Hegel, a rich legacy which is re-explored continuously over the course of the century and provides the basis for myriad novel positions, leading in the final quarter of the nineteenth century to a renaissance of absolute</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Darwinism and Philosophy in the Nineteenth Century:</title>
                     <subtitle>The ‘Whole of Metaphysics’?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More than twenty years before the publication of<italic>The Origin of Species</italic>, Charles Darwin was already certain that his embryonic hypothesis would have far-reaching consequences and not just in biology. ‘My theory’, he wrote in 1837, ‘would give zest to recent and fossil comparative anatomy; it would lead to the study of instinct, heredity and mind-heredity, [the] whole [of] metaphysics’ (Darwin 1887: 1: 370). By emphasising mutability and struggle instead of stability and harmony, by banishing the last intellectually respectable vestiges of supernaturalism, by asserting a genealogical continuity between humanity and the rest of the animal kingdom that shone light</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Faith and Knowledge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pattison</surname>
                           <given-names>George</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first decade of the twenty-first century, religion once more became a prominent topic of public discourse and the language of religion, and of atheism, became the lingua franca in which key issues of the day were formulated. Whatever might be thought of the general level on which it has been taken up in our contemporary debates, this resurgence of religion facilitates the leap of historical imagination required to take us back to the intellectual climate of the nineteenth century, especially its first half. Then, as now, religion offered a crucial focus for debating fundamental issues of human identity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Philosophising History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Distinguishing History as a Discipline</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Connelly</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter focuses on key themes, problems and concepts in the thinking of historians and philosophers about the nature and status of historical thought, practice and self understanding in the nineteenth century. It covers the concept of history in relation to Hegel and German idealism, the British idealists, the development of historicism and the issues surrounding the<italic>Methodenstreit</italic>. This story is also that of the other disciplines, such as psychology, sociology, economics and theology, with which history stands in relation.</p>
                     <p>Until the twentieth century, the term ‘philosophy of history’ usually denoted not an epistemological inquiry but systematic claims concerning the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Genealogy as Immanent Critique:</title>
                     <subtitle>Working from the Inside</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Guay</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of the distinctive terminology of nineteenth-century thought, perhaps no word has been more widely adopted than ‘genealogy’.¹ ‘Genealogy’, of course, had a long history before Nietzsche put it in the title of a book, but the original sense of pedigree or family tree is not the one that has become so prominent in contemporary academic discourse.² Nietzsche initiated a new sense of ‘genealogy’ which, oddly, has become popular despite a lack of clarity about what it is.³ My aim here is to clarify this sense of genealogy by situating it in the context of nineteenth-century narrative argument and identifying its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Embodiment:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conceptions of the Lived Body from Maine de Biran to Bergson</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sinclair</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In contemporary philosophy the phenomenological movement has offered a compelling challenge to the mind–body dualism that was instituted by Descartes amongst others in the seventeenth century. This challenge, perhaps most notably in the work of the French phenomenologist Maurice Merleau-Ponty, does not consist in the reduction of one of the opposed terms to the other in the manner of a thoroughgoing or ‘eliminative’ materialism but rather rests on a broader critique of both terms. The self, it is argued, is not originally an isolated thinking subject, certain of its own thoughts and separable from the body, whilst the body is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The Unconscious in the German Philosophy and Psychology of the Nineteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gödde</surname>
                           <given-names>Günter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated from the German by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cronin</surname>
                           <given-names>Ciaran</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The adjective ‘unconscious’ designates a quality that can be found in psychical processes such as imagining, remembering, thinking, feeling, desiring, wishing and acting. The processes which exhibit this quality differ from those with the quality ‘conscious’ in that the former are not present in the current field of consciousness but nevertheless remain psychologically effective, indeed, often far more so than the processes which have the quality of being conscious. The substantive, the ‘unconscious’, expresses the fact that psychological phenomena are not confined in principle to conscious experiences but are profoundly shaped by unconscious forces. In psychoanalysis, this concept also designates</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Individuality, Radical Politics and the Metaphor of the Machine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zakaras</surname>
                           <given-names>Alex</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of individuality expresses an ideal of personal emancipation and selfrealisation. For many philosophers of the late eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, individuality was the highest end, the<italic>telos</italic>, not only of human life but also of social and political organisation. Its attainment, however, often seemed a distant goal: virtually all of the philosophers who defended individuality believed that it was endangered, if not entirely stifled, in their own societies. Individuality was, for them, a way of imagining a modern world worth living in. It gave ethical content to their imagined utopias; it also served as the normative foundation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Rise of the Social</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Outhwaite</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter will examine social philosophy in the nineteenth century in terms of three interrelated processes: the consolidation of a conception of society or the social; the reformulation of issues of poverty and inequality in the form of ‘the social question’ and related attempts at social regulation; and the emergence of the social sciences ‘between literature and science’ (see Lepenies [1985] 1988). Although the term ‘rise’ may seem to suggest an inevitable or desirable process, we shall see that the status of the social sciences and the relation between the social and the political were no less contentious at the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Theory and Practice of Revolution in the Nineteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blackledge</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word ‘revolution’ was first used in an unmistakably modern sense in the eighteenth century to describe the American and French Revolutions. And although it had begun to gravitate towards something like this modern meaning in England in the wake of her seventeenth-century revolutions (Williams 1976; Hill 1991; Hobsbawm 1962: 74–5), John Dunn is right that ‘in a few short months, in the year of 1789, the people of France set their stamp ineffaceably on a political idea which has loomed over the history of the world ever since’ (Dunn 2008: 17). In fact, as Krishan Kumar points out,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Nihilism in the Nineteenth Century:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Absolute Subjectivity to Superhumanity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gillespie</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term ‘nihilism’ has been used to denote a philosophical concept or position, a psychological or sociological state or mood, a doctrine or agenda for political action and a cultural condition or movement. Moreover, the connotations of the term within each of these areas are multiple, complicated and contested. It is thus not easy to define the term or to determine the nature of the phenomenon that the term describes. This difficulty is exacerbated by the fact that the term has been principally used as a pejorative by opponents to characterise a condition, doctrine, or movement that they fear, disagree</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Repetition and Recurrence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Putting Metaphysics in Motion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carlisle</surname>
                           <given-names>Clare</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Difference and Repetition</italic>, Gilles Deleuze writes that Kierkegaard and Nietzsche ‘are among those who bring to philosophy new means of expression’:</p>
                     <p>They want to put metaphysics in motion, in action. They want to make it act and make it carry out immediate acts. It is not enough, therefore, for them to propose a new representation of movement; representation is already mediation. Rather, it is a question of producing within the work a movement capable of affecting the mind outside of all representation; it is a question of making movement itself a work … (Deleuze [1968] 1994: 8)</p>
                     <p>In identifying</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Nineteenth-Century Philosophy in the Twentieth Century and Beyond</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bowie</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>314</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reflections on the relationships between one period of philosophy and another raise important methodological issues which first emerge in their modern form in the wake of Kant, Herder and other thinkers in the second half of the eighteenth century. This is the period in which the ramifications of the idea that philosophy is bound up with the historical circumstances of its production begin to be apparent. In the light of these ramifications, the apparently obvious aim of identifying anticipations or echoes of twentieth-century forms of philosophy in the nineteenth century is by no means as straightforward as it might at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>330</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0b1vg.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
