<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="ita">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7gw</collection-id>
      <volume>XXVI-2</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Theodor W. Adorno: Truth and Dialectical Experience / Verità ed esperienza dialettica</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">a cura di</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Matteucci</surname>
               <given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Marino</surname>
               <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9788822900296</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9788874629572</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Quodlibet</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Macerata</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Quodlibet</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gr7dw2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>TOC: Giovanni Matteucci, Stefano Marino, Presentazione • Stefano Marino, Giovanni Matteucci, The Dark Side of the Truth. Nature and Natural Beauty in Adorno • Josef Früchtl, Tell Me Lies, and Show Me Invisible Images! Adorno’s Criticism on Film – Revisited • Tom Huhn, The Enigma of Experience; Art and Truth Content • Giuseppe Di Giacomo, Form, Appearance, Testimony: Reflections On Adorno’s Aesthetics • Samir Gandesha, Adorno’s Reading of Endgame: Between Autonomy and Authenticity • Fabrizio Desideri, Ratio, Mimesis, Dialectics: On Some Motifs in Theodor W. Adorno • Giovanni Zanotti, Contingent Antagonism. A Key to Adorno’s Dialectic • Paolo A. Bolaños, The Promise of the Non-Identical: Adorno’s Revaluation of the Language of Philosophy • Filippo Costantini, Cosa mostra la dialettica? Contraddizione, negazione e non identità in Hegel e Adorno • Giacomo Fronzi, Dialettica negativa, metafisica e intersoggettività. Una lettura relazionale del pensiero di Th.W. Adorno • Pietro Terzi, Critica e decostruzione dell’immediato. Adorno e Derrida di fronte a Husserl</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>ita</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Presentazione</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Matteucci</surname>
                           <given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marino</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A partire dagli anni Ottanta del secolo scorso, nel pieno della estenuante diatriba tra analitici e continentali, il pensiero dialettico sembrava per lo più incamminato verso l’oblio o, nel migliore dei casi, destinato a diventare oggetto di studi filologici. Non molto tempo dopo, però, esso è stato oggetto di una ripresa di interesse che è via via cresciuta. Un contributo forse inatteso a questa rinnovata considerazione è venuto dalla cultura angloamericana, grazie agli studi di filosofi contemporanei di grande importanza quali John McDowell e Robert Brandom.¹ Inoltre, la dialettica sembra godere attualmente di una certa fortuna anche in ambiti particolari</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Dark Side of the Truth.</title>
                     <subtitle>Nature and Natural Beauty in Adorno</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marino</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Matteucci</surname>
                           <given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this paper refers to the peculiar and indeed special role played by the concepts of nature, in general, and natural beauty, in particular, in Adorno’s philosophy. In fact, since Adorno’s early works of the 1930s up to his mature works of the 1960s, nature seems to represent what has been systematically repressed in the course of civilization. Hence, if observed from a dialectical point of view and expressed in somehow Pinkfloydian terms, nature appears as something like “the dark side of the truth” (or, in a more Springsteenian fashion, the “darkness” that lies “at the edge of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tell Me Lies, and Show Me Invisible Images! Adorno’s Criticism on Film – Revisited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Früchtl</surname>
                           <given-names>Josef</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Enlightenment as Mass Deception”. This is the subtitle of the chapter “The Culture Industry” in Adorno and Horkheimer’s<italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic>. Their theory is as follows: while culture in bourgeois society cannot be free from the contradictions which characterise this society in accordance with Hegel and Marx, nevertheless at the same time, capturing the moment of the negative and critical in its “affirmative character”, as Hork-heimer and then Herbert Marcuse put it, industrially produced culture loses even this last element of the critical and becomes completely affirmative. Thus, culture industry loses its immanent dialectic. However, the culture industry still claims</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Enigma of Experience; Art and Truth Content</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Huhn</surname>
                           <given-names>Tom</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The enigma of the work of modern art is also the name for its constitutive character. The character of this self-contradicting existence is what makes the work of art into the occasion for a baffling and befuddling encounter. The complement to enigma in the work of art is its truth content. Key to engaging the work of art’s enigma and truth content is the mimetic relation between experience and the work of art. The misalignment between the work of art and human experience is an opportunity for encountering what exists as objective contradiction. The ongoing dance between the mimetic misalignments</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Form, Appearance, Testimony:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections On Adorno’s Aesthetics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Di Giacomo</surname>
                           <given-names>Giuseppe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction</italic>(1936), Walter Benjamin claims that an work of art’s “cult value” excludes the possibility of its replication or reproduction, while the culture of printing copies of original works, which begins during the Renaissance, replaces this “cult value” with “exhibition value”. As a result, these copies are clearly distinct from the work of art, whose uniqueness is what Benjamin calls “aura”. Industrialisation brought about a radical change in the conditions of production, meaning that a series of objects could be produced from one mould, as the completely mechanical production process</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“In Sympathy with the Ephemeral Life”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Adorno’s Reading of Beckett’s Endgame</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gandesha</surname>
                           <given-names>Samir</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I have suggested elsewhere (Gandesha 2017), there are two models that understand the problem of reification as a kind of “forgetting”(Horkheimer, Adorno 1988, p. 230). The first stems from the Idealist tradition and, via a detour through Feuerbach’s “transformative critique” of religion, forms the basis for Marx’s analysis of the commodity form in the famous fourth section of the first chapter of<italic>Capital</italic>, Volume I. It is developed further in Georg Lukács’ (1986) epochal essay “Reification and the Consciousness of the Proletariat”, published as a chapter of his 1923 book<italic>History and Class Consciousness</italic>. It could be said to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ratio, Mimesis, Dialectics:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Some Motifs in Theodor W. Adorno</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Desideri</surname>
                           <given-names>Fabrizio</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From<italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic>to<italic>Aesthetic Theory</italic>: these two book titles somehow sum up the entire development of Adorno’s philosophy. From a meditation (together with his friend and colleague Horkheimer) on the unavoidable polarity in the Modern between the dynamics of rationalization and the persistence of myth, to an arduous analysis of the relationship between the work of art and philosophy. His posthumous and unfinished<italic>Aesthetic Theory</italic>has often been read as nothing more than an outcome to which Adorno was led by the internal aporias of a “critical theory” of the late-capitalist society understood as an “administered world” in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contingent Antagonism.</title>
                     <subtitle>A Key to Adorno’s Dialectic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zanotti</surname>
                           <given-names>Giovanni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although often overlooked, a passage from Marx’s<italic>Manuscripts of 1844</italic>represents an important turning point in the history of dialectical philosophy. In this work, a theoretical perspective is opened, which I define as the “contingency of antagonism” – an Adornian concept. I will argue: (a) that this is an original perspective, irreducible to any previous philosophical positions, (b) that Marx’s intuition finds a more sophisticated reformulation in Adorno, and (c) that the idea of a contingent antagonism can provide a key to overcome the apparently antinomical outcome of negative dialectic. My aim here is to offer some preliminary clarification about the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Promise of the Non-Identical:</title>
                     <subtitle>Adorno’s Revaluation of the Language of Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bolaños</surname>
                           <given-names>Paolo A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theodor W. Adorno’s preoccupation with language is gleaned from the context of his theory of knowledge, particularly his critique of identity thinking. He tackles the problem of conceptual reification genealogically, that is, he traces conceptual reification via an analysis of the structure of language. My aim in this paper is to argue that Adorno’s engagement with the nature of language is informed by an implicit attempt at a revaluation of the language of philosophy, a revaluation that has significant consequences for a global understanding of how we conceive the world of objects, in general, and how philosophy’s configurative use of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cosa mostra la dialettica?</title>
                     <subtitle>Contraddizione, negazione e non-identità in Hegel e Adorno</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Costantini</surname>
                           <given-names>Filippo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Il rapporto che Adorno intrattiene con Hegel è un rapporto ambivalente, dialettico, non nel senso banale e scontato che entrambi fondano le loro rispettive filosofie sulla dialettica, ma nel più profondo senso per cui Adorno vede in Hegel colui che più di qualsiasi altro ha colto l’irruenza del nonidentico all’interno del pensiero identificante, e tuttavia non ha saputo essere all’altezza di tale comprensione, riconducendo il non-identico nelle trame dell’identità.</p>
                     <p>Il significato di una riforma negativa della dialettica hegeliana si trova tutto qui: si tratta di salvare la scoperta fatta da Hegel dall’esito affermativo del suo sistema. Bisogna, cioè, utilizzando gli</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dialettica negativa, metafisica e intersoggettività.</title>
                     <subtitle>Una lettura relazionale del pensiero di Th. W. Adorno</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fronzi</surname>
                           <given-names>Giacomo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nella trama di ramificazioni del pensiero filosofico del Novecento, ci sono alcune tendenze che spesso vengono considerate opposte, conflittuali, in via definitiva. Tra queste, vi è quella tra la costellazione speculativa di Theodor Wiesengrund Adorno, da una parte, e l’esistenzialismo, la fenomenologia o qualsiasi filosofia della coscienza e/o dell’essere, dall’altra. A tal riguardo, a partire dagli anni Ottanta è emersa la necessità di ripensare la contrapposizione tra il pensiero dialettico-negativo e quello ontologico, in particolare di matrice heideggeriana.¹ Un’analoga possibilità di “messa in dialogo” di direttrici di pensiero costitutivamente collocantesi su piani epistemologici e metodologici diversi è offerta, a mio</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Critica e decostruzione dell’immediato.</title>
                     <subtitle>Adorno e Derrida di fronte a Husserl</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Terzi</surname>
                           <given-names>Pietro</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>C’è un libro che Derrida avrebbe voluto scrivere, ed è quello che egli può solo immaginare quando, il 22 settembre 2001, gli viene conferito il Premio Adorno. Nel testo letto durante la cerimonia di consegna, a distanza di undici giorni dall’attacco al World Trade Center, le preoccupazioni etiche e politiche prendono decisamente il sopravvento su ogni altro aspetto filosofico che possa in qualche modo congiungere il suo itinerario con quello di Adorno. Ancor più, la prolusione attribuisce maggior spazio a Walter Benjamin e a un sogno che egli raccontò in una lettera alla moglie di Adorno, Gretel Karplus. Derrida si</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gr7dw2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
