<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Close Encounters</book-title>
         <subtitle>Essays on Russian Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JACKSON</surname>
               <given-names>Robert Louis</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781936235568</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781618116772</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Academic Studies Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Brighton, MA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Academic Studies Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxshr0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Close Encounters: Essays on Russian Literature combines discussions of ethical, esthetic, and philosophical interest raised by Pushkin, Gogol, Turgenev, Dostoevsky, Tolstoy, and Gorky, with close analyses of their texts. This book focuses on four thematic configurations: first (“Chance and Fate"), issues of freedom and responsibility, the necessity of free individual expression and yet the limits of will, or self-will; second (“Two Kinds of Beauty"), the unity of moral, esthetic, and spiritual categories, and the quest for the ideal; third (“Critical Perspectives"), examples of the type of commentary that approaches art with a unified ethical and spiritual perspective (Dostoevsky, Gorky, V.I. Ivanov, and the partially dissenting Bakhtin); and fourth (“Poems of Parting"), three poems (works by Tyutchev, Severyanin, and Pushkin) involving parting, loss, and recovery.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VI</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introductory Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gerigk</surname>
                           <given-names>Horst-Jürgen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>IX</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This collection of essays is neither a history of Russian literature in disguise nor is it a collection of separate interpretations of great Russian books.<italic>Close Encounters</italic>is an answer, a new answer to the old question of what to look for in Russian literature. Years ago we had Aaron Copland’s What to Listen for in Music ; and, with quite similar intentions, our author now presents his approaches to “Russian fiction” which, as William Lyon Phelps of Yale University once put it, “is like German music—the best in the world.” The categories are “Freedom and Responsibility” (eight essays</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Glance at the Essays</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XII</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Close Encounters: Essays on Russian Literature,</italic>a selection of writings on Russian prose, poetry, and criticism in four parts, covers the period from my second book,<italic>Dostoevsky’s Quest for Form: A Study of his Philosophy of Art</italic>(1966), to the present. For reasons of space, I have omitted selections from my earliest period of writing, notably, from<italic>The Underground Man in Russian Literature</italic>(1958). Yet that study, with its core focus on<italic>Dostoevsky’s Notes from the Underground</italic>(1864)—a work that both defends free will and criticizes self-will, while pointing to a spiritual path out of the underground—laid the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Moral-Philosophical Subtext in Pushkin’s The Stone Guest</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>2</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The beginning is always decisive,” German novelist Theodor Fontane observed well over a hundred years ago. “If one hits it off right, then what follows succeeds through a kind of inner necessity.”² One may add that that necessity sometimes carries with it a hint of the inner content of the work. That is eminently the case with the beginning of The Stone Guest (<italic>Kamennyi gost</italic>’, 1830) where Pushkin projects a major concern of his play: the question of Don Juan’s identity.</p>
                     <p>The four opening lines of<italic>The Stone Guest</italic>, in contrast to the opening lines of Pushkin’s<italic>Mozart and Salieri</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Turgenev’s “Knock… Knock… Knock!..”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Riddle of the Story</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we know, even such an appreciative critic of Ivan Turgenev’s writings as Pavel V. Annenkov (1813–1887) placed the Russian writer’s “Knock… Knock… Knock!.. A Study” (<italic>Stuk….. stuk…. Stuk...! Studiia,</italic>1871) among his “weak pieces.”² On the contrary, “Knock… Knock… Knock!..” belongs to the strongest works of Turgenev and of Russian literature. Complex in its design and brilliant in artistic execution, it is a work of psychological and philosophical depth.³ Turgenev several times stressed the importance of his story, though not without his usual admixture of apology and self-deprecation where his works were concerned. Although he found it “a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Polina and Lady Luck in Dostoevsky’s The Gambler</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a letter written to the literary critic and philosopher Nikolai N. Strakhov (1828–1898) from Rome in September 1863, Dostoevsky projected the idea of a story that was to evolve later into the novel,<italic>The Gambler</italic>(<italic>From the Notes of a Young Man</italic>) (1866). The story, he wrote, would reflect the “contemporary moment (as far as possible, of course) of our inner life.” The central character would be “a certain type of Russian abroad”: Dostoevsky’s comparison of this story with his<italic>Notes from theHouse of the Dead</italic>is of particular interest. The link between<italic>The Gambler</italic>and the earlier</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Pierre and Dolokhov at the Barrier:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Lesson of the Duel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus of our discussion is the duel between Dolokhov and Pierre (book 2, part 1, chapter 5) in<italic>War and Peace.</italic>We will present what happens in the duel; consider its outcome against the background of the psychology of the protagonists; and finally, ask what bearing the duel has on the general theme of chance and design in<italic>War and Peace.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>The duel takes place at a moment when the wounded Prince Andrei, in Austria, has been declared a “hopeless case” by Napoleon’s physician, Dr. Larrey. Pierre, in Moscow, also appears to be a hopeless case: not so much</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Chance and Design:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anna Karenina’s First Meeting with Vronsky</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 18, part 1 of<italic>Anna Karenina</italic>, some seventy pages from the beginning of the novel, Tolstoy introduces Anna to the reader for the first time in person. The scene is a Moscow railroad station. Stepan Oblonsky is there to meet his sister Anna who is arriving from St. Petersburg; Vronsky, to meet his mother who is arriving on the same train. All four meet, exchange amenities, and prepare to leave the station; momentarily, a disturbing incident draws their attention: a railroad guard has been crushed by one of the cars. After a brief delay (Vronsky leaves some money</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Breaking the Moral Barrier:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anna Karenina’s Night Train to St. Petersburg</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anna’s night journey to St. Petersburg (part 1, chapter 29) is one of the great transitional moments in her drama. Her experience dramatizes a state of intense moral and psychological conflict in which a powerful passion crashes through a barrier of will and conscience. Tolstoy’s account of this internal experience is remarkable for its representation of Anna’s epic crisis. The battle engages her entire being, physical, psychological, moral, and spiritual, drawing in her immediate surroundings and nature in the broadest sense of the term.</p>
                     <p>In Tolstoy’s view, we are never separate from the world around us. We are in extricably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Uzhas in the Subtext:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tolstoy’s The Death of Ivan Ilych</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Andreyev says, ‘Boo!’ but I am not afraid,” Leo Tolstoy once remarked apropos of some of Leonid Andreyev’s tales of horror and death. Tolstoy had a very keen sense of the distinction between melodrama and drama. His<italic>Death of Ivan Ilych</italic>(<italic>Smert’ Ivana Il’icha,</italic>1886) is a case in point. There are disturbing moments in this tale’s treatment of illness and death, but the elements of horror or terror (<italic>uzhas</italic>)² in the story do not belong to melodrama. Tolstoy’s purpose is not to say “Boo!” to the reader, that is, to frighten him to death, but rather to wake him</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“What Time Is It? Where Are We Going?” Chekhov’s The Cherry Orchard:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Story of a Verb</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The train has arrived,” “They’re coming!” “They’re coming!” “They’re coming!” “Let’s go and meet them,” “Come through here . . . the nursery!” “Time is marching on!” “Sleep well. There’s a way out. The railroad passed nearby.” “Go to sleep,” “I’m going, I’m going,” “Let’s go to bed . . . Let’s go.”(Act 1) “Our’s [our children] are coming,” “Epikhodov is coming,” “Somebody is coming,” “Can I go through here directly to the station?” “Let’s go, everybody, it’s time for supper,” “To avoid [literally, “go around,” or “bypass”] everything petty and illusory that interferes with being free and happy, that’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Two Kinds of Beauty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Beauty will save the world. Two kinds of beauty,” Dostoevsky observes without further explanation in one of his notebooks to<italic>The Idiot</italic>.² This condensed set of idea-signals points not only to the problem content of<italic>The Idiot</italic>, but to the complex dialectic of Dostoevsky’s esthetic thought. The first phrase, “Beauty will save the world,” is a model of syntactic precision and order; it promises direct, unimpeded action. But the second phrase is disruptive; it shatters the integrity of the beauty-savior and bogs down the action in ambiguity and enigma. “Is it true, Prince, that you once said that ‘beauty will</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Sentencing of Fyodor Karamazov</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two short scenes, “Over the Brandy” and “The Sensualists,” one following the other, occupy a pivotal place in the destiny of Fyodor Karamazov. In the first scene, the theme of desecration (crime), as it relates to Fyodor, attains its sharpest and most comprehensive expression. In the second scene, the theme of retribution (punishment) surfaces as the inexorable response to his desecration. Both the crime and punishment of Fyodor, in the poetics of Dostoevsky, belong to the realm of “bezobrazie (the morally and esthetically “monstrous” or “shapeless”) and involve the disfiguration of man made in the image and likeness of God.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Defiled and Defiling “Physiognomy” of Fyodor Pavlovich Karamazov</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a discussion some years ago entitled “The Sentencing of Fyodor Karamazov,” I focused on the way in which the theme of<italic>defilement</italic>reached its culmination in “Over the Brandy” (<italic>Za kon’iachkom</italic>). Fyodor Pavlovich, in the presence of Alyosha and Ivan, recalls spitting on Sofia Ivanovna’s icon of the Mother of God and saying to her, “Just take a look, you think this is [a miracle-making] icon, well right now before you I’m spitting on it, and nothing will happen to me!” In “Over the Brandy,” as early in the novel, the theme of esthetic-religious defilement is linked with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dostoevsky’s “Anecdote from a Child’s Life”:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case of Bifurcation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sketch entitled “An Anecdote from a Child’s Life” (“Anekdot iz detskoi zhizni”) constitutes the first section of chapter 2 of the December 1876 issue of<italic>Diary of a Writer</italic>(<italic>Dnevnik pisatelia</italic>).² In length it is about 2,000 words. The story centers on a twelve-year-old girl who decides not to come home after school and to spend the night in St. Petersburg. Its focus is the psychology of a preadolescent girl at the moment of passage from innocence to a “knowledge of good and evil” and the predatory world this girl faces in the dark Petersburg night. The theme of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Triple Vision:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dostoevsky’s “The Peasant Marey”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In “The Peasant Marey” (<italic>Diary of a Writer</italic>, February 1876, chapter 1, section 3), Dostoevsky recalls how as a convict in a Siberian prison, early in Easter week, 1850, he recoiled in horror before the depravity and violence of his fellow convicts. The words of a Polish political prisoner addressed to him on this occasion, “Je hais ces brigands,” seem to express his own sense of disgust, hatred, and despair. Dostoevsky writes that he lay down on his bunk in the barracks a few moments later and recalled, in a daydream, a childhood encounter with the kindly peasant Marey.² As</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Making of a Russian Icon:</title>
                     <subtitle>Solzhenitsyn’s “Matryona’s Home”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alexander Solzhenitsyn’s tale “Matryona’s Home” (“Matrenin dvor,” 1963),² consisting of three little chapters, begins with a prologue that is brief, factual, yet tense with significant drama.</p>
                     <p>One hundred and eighty-four kilometers from Moscow, and a good half year after it happened, all trains slowed down their course almost to a crawl. The passengers pressed to the windows, went out into the vestibule: were they repairing the tracks, or what? Was there a change in schedule? No. Past the crossing, the train again picked up speed and the passengers settled back.</p>
                     <p>Only the engineers knew and remembered what it was all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dostoevsky’s Concept of Reality and Its Representation in Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“By the word reality we understand everything that is,” observed Belinsky in 1840, “the visible world and the spiritual world, the world of facts and the world of ideas.”² Belinsky’s definition—which belongs to his middle or so-called Hegelian period of rationalization of reality— comes close to characterizing Dostoevsky’s omnibus view of reality. We shall not encounter a single binding concept of reality in Dostoevsky’s thought; rather, his notion of reality is a syncretism.³ Reality for him embraces concrete, historical reality with its classes, its immediate problems and conflicts, and its social and national types which give expression to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>In the Interests of Social Pedagogy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Maxim Gorky’s Polemic with Dostoevsky</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three things may be said about the lifelong polemic of Maxim Gorky (1868–1936) with Dostoevsky. First, it had deep psychological roots in a confrontation with aspects of his own nature; overcoming Dostoevsky, for Gorky, was a process of self-overcoming. Second, this process of self-overcoming became linked with a central effort of Gorky’s literary and cultural writings—the task of overcoming Russian history, the painful legacy of violence and disorder in Russian man and life, all that he once called “our most implacable enemy—our past.”² And third, this overcoming ultimately took on the dimensions of a struggle between worldviews,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bakhtin’s Poetics of Dostoevsky and “Dostoevsky’s Christian Declaration of Faith”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“God can get along without man,” Mikhail M. Bakhtin wrote in “Towards a Reworking of the Dostoevsky Book” in 1961, “but man cannot get along without Him.”² How does Dostoevsky get along with God? Vyacheslav Ivanov answers this question in his Dostoevsky book (1932): “Dostoevsky has long since made his choice: his surety and pledge for it is the figure of Christ shining upon his path.”³ The “infallible criterion” for this claim, Ivanov insists, is “the accord between what Dostoevsky had to teach and the living artistic imagery in which he clothed it.”⁴ For Ivanov, “the investigation of Dostoevsky’s religious</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Vyacheslav I. Ivanov’s Poem “Nudus Salta!” and The Purpose of Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ivanov’s untitled poem “Nudus salta! Tsel’ iskusstva” (“Dance naked! The Purpose of Art”) appears in his<italic>Roman Notebook</italic>(<italic>Rimskii dnevnik</italic>, 1944) and is dated February 18, 1944.² Three earlier versions of the poem date from February 15 through February 17, 1944.³ In those few days, the poem underwent some small, but significant, changes.</p>
                     <p>“Nudus salta!” consists of four stanzas of five lines each. On the semantic plane, the poem may be divided into two parts, each consisting of two stanzas (referred to in this discussion as parts one and two). The first two stanzas of the poem appear in quotation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Intimations of Mortality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fyodor I. Tyutchev’s “In Parting there is a Lofty Meaning”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>318</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Here are some bad verses expressing something even worse,” Fyodor I. Tyutchev (1803–1873) wrote to his wife with reference to his poem of August 6, 1851.² The poem is in no sense a bad one; on the contrary, it is a masterpiece in miniature. Whether it expresses something on the somber or pessimistic side is a question. In any case, Tyutchev’s subjective reaction to his poem does not alter the poem’s independence or its rich poetic and philosophical texture.</p>
                     <p>“In Parting there is a Lofty Meaning” (“V razluke est’ vysokoe znachen’e,” 1851) is a philosophical poem about the pathos</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Poetry of Memory and the Memory of Poetry:</title>
                     <subtitle>Igor Severyanin’s “No More Than a Dream”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Igor Severyanin’s poem consists of a title, “Ne Bolee Chem Son” (“No More Than a Dream”), and two quatrains, each one numbering twenty-four words. In the first quatrain, the narrator-dreamer relates that he has dreamed a “remarkable” dream. He lists five discrete dream sequences beginning with the scene of his riding in a carriage with a girl who is reading Blok.³ In the second quatrain, the narrator dwells on the profound impact the dream has had on him and how increasingly moved he was by the thought that the “the strange girl had not forgotten Blok.” “No More Than a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Supremum Vale:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Last Stanzas of Pushkin’s Eugene Onegin. Goethe, Zhukovsky, and the Decembrists</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The last stanza of<italic>Eugene Onegin</italic>(<italic>Evgenii Onegin</italic>, 1833) by Alexander S. Pushkin begins with an allusion to the Decembrists,” wrote Dmitry Chizhevsky in 1953 in his critical edition of Pushkin’s masterpiece, “for they were the only group of Pushkin’s friends of whom one could say, ‘inykh uzh net, a te daleche’” (Some are no more, others are distant).⁵ That Pushkin was alluding in the opening four lines of the last stanza to the Decembrists has long been affirmed by scholars.⁶ In this connection, his reference to the thirteenth century Persian poet Muslih-ud Din Saadi as author of the above-cited</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Other Shore:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nabokov’s Translation into Russian of Goethe’s “Dedication” to Faust</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preceding chapter we began our discussion of the last stanza of Eugene Onegin with Nabokov’s search for the source of Pushkin’s socalled Saadi line, “Some are no more, others are distant” (Inykh uzh net, a te daleche), and begin this one with a question: Why did Nabokov pass over specific allusions to Goethe’s “Dedication” (<italic>Zueignung</italic>) to Faust and to Zhukovsky’s “Imitation of Goethe”? Nabokov had composed a verse translation of Goethe’s poem into Russian in 1923. He published that poem in 1932 on the occasion of the 100th anniversary of Goethe’s death.² He was thoroughly familiar with Zhukovsky’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>366</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxshr0.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>374</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
