<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN45.S854 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Books and reading</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Language and languages</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Deed of Reading</book-title>
         <subtitle>Literature * Writing * Language * Philosophy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>STEWART</surname>
               <given-names>GARRETT</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780801454219</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781501701702</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ithaca; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cornell University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7591/j.ctt1h4mhkq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Garrett Stewart begins<italic>The Deed of Reading</italic>with a memory of his first hesitant confrontation, as a teenager, with poetic density. In that early verbal challenge he finds one driving force of literature: to make language young again in its surprise, coming alive in each new event of reading. But what exactly happens in the textual encounter to make literary phrasing resonate so deeply with readers?</p>
         <p>To take the measure of literary writing,<italic>The Deed of Reading</italic>convenes diverse philosophic commentary on the linguistics of literature, with stress on the complementary work of Stanley Cavell and Giorgio Agamben. Sympathetic to recent ventures in form-attentive analysis but resisting an emphasis on so-called surface reading, Stewart explores not some new formalism but the internal pressures of language in formation, registering the verbal infrastructure of literary prose as well as verse. In this mode of "contextual" reading, the context is language itself. Literary phrasing, tapping the speech act's own generative pulse, emerges as a latent philosophy of language in its own right, whereby human subjects, finding no secure place to situate themselves within language, settle for its taking place in, through, and between them.</p>
         <p>Stewart watches and hears this dynamics of wording played out in dozens of poems and novels over two centuries of English literary production-from Wordsworth and Shelley to Browning and Hopkins, from Poe and Dickens through George Eliot, Conrad, James, and on to Toni Morrison.<italic>The Deed of Reading</italic>offers a revisionary contribution to the ethic of verbal attention in the grip of "deep reading."</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FORE WORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literary ethics or verbal ethic? There is of course no reason to choose. But many a distinction to be made. We have come to this: “It is not unusual in literary studies to treat language as transparent, and thus irrelevant.”¹ Thus writes a professional linguist, in the year 2012, from her institutional base in an English department at a major Canadian university. It is in fact very common lately not to “treat language” at all in the analysis of literature, as if it were no more than the readily legible conveyance of expressed ideas, whether urgently identitarian, ideologically suspect, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>INDUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I go back in memory, then, to my hometown’s well-stocked and long-gone local bookshop, with its fuss-budget and anything but avuncular owner, at least as inquisitive as his patrons, who was always seeming to scope out your roving interests over his bifocals. It was the California of the Beach Boys, not yet the Beatles. And there in Laguna Beach, a newly transplanted and misfit high school student from the other coast, I began my first sustained bookstore romance, a few blocks walking distance from the family house—and continents away. A rather desperately compensatory romance? Sublimated teen solitude and angst?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>SECONDARY VOCALITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Concerning the ductile music of literary language, all “inductions”—like mine long ago—are renewable. It’s not that “you had to have been there,” once and back when, falling untaught under the spell of words and finding in them, as the undertext of their lettering, the waiting sounds they never quite seem to have left behind. Instead, you are always there again in reading. With an emphasis on meter and lineation (rather than phonetics per se) as the aural prompt and structuring “end” of poetry in its destined repetition, Italian philosopher and poetician Giorgio Agamben, so we’ll find, gives us</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>ERRANDS OF THE EAR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Phonic not sonic. Latent in literary writing, not mystified by it. Secondary vocality: registering hinted aural undertones in poetry’s descriptive overtones, the phonematic beneath the semantic—and certainly before the thematic, though often cycled back through it in response. That’s how—once moving beyond the referential foreclosures of deixis—the last chapter took up as central English example the “composed lines” of<italic>Tintern Abbey</italic>and their enunciated syncopations. Even without anticipating in Stanley Cavell’s work the skepticism that poetry and prose alike, that the fictive world in general, faces up to and stares down, we can say so far, with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>IMP-AIRED WORDS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First Giorgio Agamben, now Stanley Cavell: on the “ends” of literary writing as performed language—or say, in Agamben’s genitive swivels, on “the idea of language” and “the thought of voice.” In the redoubtable line of Ludwig Wittgenstein and J. L. Austin, Cavell participates in an ordinary language philosophy bent on excavating, from within the prosaic cadences of everyday speech, their evidence of philosophical pressure points. In adapting this approach to a literary prosaics of formative reading, my effort is to extend his method in general (while following his example in certain specific cases) to the eccentric phonic and syntactic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>SPLITTING THE DIFFERENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A vocabular conundrum can, I hope, be readily cleared away. “You say eether and I say eyethere.” I said zeugma and now say syllepsis. Knee there, nigh there: it’s only the difference internal, not terminological, that matters. The Gershwins’ lyric to “Let’s Call the Whole Thing Off” also speaks quite accidentally, in the lead-in of its often unsung verse, not just to the matter of variant lexical usage but to the particular concerns of this chapter with grammatical compounding in the accusative case: “You like this and the other / While I go for this and that.” Imagine, with either</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>TALKING ROOM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literature’s script makes room for its own kind of back talk: that’s one way of evoking the vocal undertow of certain inscribed turns in the prose as well as poetry we’ve surveyed. In general, as I began by regretting, there is no disciplinary tautology (far from it) in thinking of “literature writing language,” let alone its “writing language philosophy.” For language is often forgotten in cultural estimates of what is too causally termed literary<italic>writing</italic>and its effects. Whenever in evidence, any attention to the disclosure, rather than sheer service, of language within a work of words tends to educe</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTER WORDING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After the words are laid out, if no longer in cold type but in laser jet or backlight, how does reading revive them as immanent speech act? And what—this book has gone on to ask—is implied there, there in the deed of reading, for a philosophy of the subject as<italic>homo loquens</italic>? Where, in fact, is<italic>there</italic>, exactly? And how often does the phonetic aftermath of a given word seem to generate its own virtual alternative as part of the serial coming-to-be not just of a verbalized world elsewhere but of a newly channeled linguistic gesture? Phonetic aftermath</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h4mhkq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
