<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Back to Modern Reason</book-title>
         <subtitle>Johan Hjerpe and Other Petit Bourgeois in Stockholm in the Age of Enlightenment</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JARRICK</surname>
               <given-names>ARNE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>1999</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780853235835</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781846312632</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Arne Jarrick</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vjm4r"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A revised and translated edition of Mot det moderna förnuftet, published in 1992. Utilising the diaries from the 1780s of Johan Hjerpe, the study focuses on the specific world of Hjerpe in terms of trade, social conditions and contemporary social life in Stockholm.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Johan Hjerpe and Enlightenment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Johan Hjerpe was born in Stockholm in 1765 and died sixty years later. The son of a poor Moravian master tailor, he eventually became a member of the evangelical brotherhood, the Moravian brethren.</p>
                     <p>In his youth, Johan Hjerpe served in the linen shop of the wholesaler Anders Kjellstedt in the Old Town. Like others he started at the bottom but did better than most, rising in time above his humble beginnings.² An industrious and decent man, in 1801 he eventually acquired a small workshop for the production of silk thread and camel hair, by which time he was already thirty-five</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Johan Hjerpe and the artisan uprising in support of the king’s war</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On Monday 27 April 1789, the artisan journeymen of Stockholm demonstrated through the Old Town. They had most likely spent the night, not with their masters as they should have, but in hostelries, drunk and up to no good. At about half past eleven in the morning, they occupied the Riddarhustorget outside the House of the Nobility, where they continued their uproar until four o’clock in the afternoon, ‘at which time a heavy downpour, combined with the flexed batons of the police officers, helped to disperse the drunken mob’.¹</p>
                     <p>It was the last day on which parliament was in session.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>The coherence of the inconsistent self:</title>
                     <subtitle>some reflections on mentality, identity and historiography</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Towards the end of the preceding chapter, I attempted to explain what led the artisan journeymen of Stockholm and Johan Hjerpe to take part in Gustavus III’s showdown with the nobility in the spring of 1789, an episode worthy of a war novel. Although this was not stated, my interpretation was based on a set of general hypotheses about the human mind. The hypotheses underlay the text as its analytical precondition, which perhaps made the interpretation difficult to follow, and possibly also more provocative than it would otherwise have been. At the same time, fuller explanations would have been even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Burghers, common folk and books</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As there is no easy road to popular culture and mentality, one must take the byways: speeches of welcome, for example, books in the estates left by the poor, broadsheets, biographies and the odd diary. Or, basically, through eyewitness accounts, mementoes and various literary artefacts.</p>
                     <p>Actions occupied the centre of the preceding diptych. Things will be less eventful here, for I nowwant to get at the structure of a gradual unfolding of events. First of all, I will try to clarify certain aspects of the change in people’s relationship to the printed word, above all during the eighteenth and early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>New cultural history and old history of mentalities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preceding chapter, I tried to build up a picture of a certain change in mentality among merchants and artisans in eighteenth-century Stockholm. The picture that emerged demonstrated that a shift was taking place in the cultural frames of reference. But because the change was very slow, it must have been difficult for those involved to notice it, however much they themselves contributed to it. In time, however, its effects became evident to all, and it is conceivable that, in retrospect, the change can be registered with the help of statistics, for instance.</p>
                     <p>But can it? What do quantitative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Johan Hjerpe and the culture of Enlightenment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the relativistic framework of Enlightenment philosopy, a number of coherent thematic groupings stand out more than others: a secularised deismor atheism, an expanded awareness of the value of foreign cultures, and the transformative idea that history will never return to its starting point – a notion that for some like Fontenelle, Turgot or Condorcet was elevated to a belief in progress.</p>
                     <p>What concerns me in this chapter is how these attitudes were remoulded when they reached the man in the street. Indeed, the discussion is even more narrowly focused, as it largely concerns a single person who has already made</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>The individual and history</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The preceding chapter focused its attention almost entirely on one person. Despite the insistent presence of Jacques-Louis Ménétra, it mostly concerned the world according to Johan Hjerpe, the artisan son alone with his thoughts, protected both from the throng of people and from statistical intrusions. And even if Hjerpe had also made an appearance in the second chapter, it was only in the last one that he was dealt with as the central personality.</p>
                     <p>Studying one individual is no easier and can be done no more quickly than research into many. Even if it is occasionally more entertaining, it produces</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>In retrospect</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why write a book about Johan Hjerpe and Enlightenment when no successful meeting ever took place between them? It is easy to give an answer.</p>
                     <p>One reason is that Enlightenment had a very strong presence in the social debate of the Gustavian period, and that many of its ideas also experienced a breakthrough as a practical reform programme, within the spheres of, for example, the administration of justice and legislation on freedom of the press. Another reason is that Hjerpe could not side-step the notions of Enlightenment however much he disliked them: they challenged him as obviously and permanently as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjm4r.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
