<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ffjnxw</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1xhr5j8</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Migrant Nation</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Arthur</surname>
               <given-names>Paul Longley</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">Series Editors</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bode</surname>
               <given-names>Katherine</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moore</surname>
               <given-names>Nicole</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781783087204</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781783087211</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Anthem Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London, UK; New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Paul Longley Arthur</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xhr5j8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Description not available.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>TRANSCULTURAL STUDIES IN AUSTRALIAN IDENTITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arthur</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul Longley</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a former colony of Great Britain, Australia has faced the dual challenge experienced by all settler colonies of forging an identity that allows it to distinguish itself from its ‘parent’ culture at the same time deal with its complicity in the colonization of the new land and the treatment of its original inhabitants. In the case of Australia, this situation has been further complicated by the fact that the land was simply taken – without a war, without a treaty and without negotiation. Throughout its European history, Australia has needed to perpetuate its founding myth of being a previously</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>REMEMBERING ABORIGINAL SYDNEY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Read</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aboriginal Sydney has two histories. The first is well known, centred in Redfern, and includes the history of the Aboriginal Legal Service, the Medical Service and the radical housing plan known as the Block. The second is much less known, and of much less interest to historians. This is the history of those who have always lived in Sydney, who would be known now, if they lived in northern or central Australia, as Traditional Owners. In Sydney, they know themselves, and are respected by some, as the Traditional Custodians. They have formed legal entities known as Local Aboriginal Land Councils</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>FILES AND ABORIGINAL LIVES:</title>
                     <subtitle>BIOGRAPHIES FROM AN ARCHIVE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haebich</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anthropologist and historian Ann Stoler (2009, 1) describes archives as ‘active, generative substances with histories[, …] documents with itineraries of their own’. She urges scholars to engage with them as ‘cultural artifacts of fact production, of taxonomies in the making, and of disparate notions of what made up colonial authority’ (Stoler 2002, 91).</p>
                     <p>This chapter takes up her challenge in a study of the archive of the West Australian Department of Indigenous Affairs (DIA) archive. This sprawling collection is a storehouse of stories documenting 74 years of state power over Aboriginal people. This chapter traces the archive’s history of development</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>WRITING, FEMININITY AND COLONIALISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>JUDITH WRIGHT, HÉLÈNE CIXOUS AND MARIE CARDINAL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ravenscroft</surname>
                           <given-names>Alison</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How to write of a white feminine<italic>I</italic>so as not to tell – once more – the story of the woman we already know, the woman we take ourselves to be? The answer might lie in a kind of writing that gives a formal place to uncertainty. This would be a writing practice that aims at a writer’s doubts about herself and others, rather than closing them over, and which works with an<italic>aesthetics</italic>of uncertainty and not just a<italic>vocabulary</italic>. Such a writing practice would also aim at the production of doubt in a reader. If aesthetics is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>THE STAGING OF SOCIAL POLICY:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE PHOTOGRAPHING OF POST-WAR BRITISH CHILD MIGRANTS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ely-Harper</surname>
                           <given-names>Kerreen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A large number of photographs were taken in the late 1940s and 1950s by the Department of Information (later Australian News and Information Bureau) to promote post-war migration to Australia. These photos were of new arrivals, family groups, single adults and sponsored child migrants from the United Kingdom. With the increase in unaccompanied minors coming to Australia, the federal government enacted the Immigration Guardianship of Children Act of 1946, which ensured that the Minister for Immigration and Citizenship (then Arthur Calwell) would assume legal guardianship of unaccompanied children under 21 years of age. The child migration schemes were operated by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>WRITING HOME FROM CHINA:</title>
                     <subtitle>CHARLES ALLEN’S TRANSNATIONAL CHILDHOOD</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bagnall</surname>
                           <given-names>Kate</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In June 1910 Frances Allen received a letter from her 13-year-old son, Charles. ‘Dear Mother’, it began, ‘I received your letter to-day and was very pleased to hear from you. I don’t like been here at all. I want you to try and bring me home’.¹ Lonely and homesick, Charles was in China, far from the familiar sights and sounds and smells of Sydney, where he had grown up and where his mother remained. After nearly a year in China, Charles noted, ‘I can talk the China talk now so it is all right’ – a brief reassurance for his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>AUSTRALIAN?</title>
                     <subtitle>AUTOBIOGRAPHY? CITIZENSHIP, POSTNATIONAL SELF-IDENTITY AND THE POLITICS OF BELONGING</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bowers</surname>
                           <given-names>Jack</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last week of March in 2011, Mohammed Asif Atay took his own life while at the Curtin Detention Centre in Western Australia (ABC 2011). A 19-year-old refugee from Afghanistan, Mohammed had withdrawn unobtrusively from the group of men who were sitting around outside talking together. He went to his room, locked the door and hanged himself. Despite the efforts of journalists and refugee advocates, we know little else about Mohammed. We do know that he was from the Hazara community, a minority religious and ethnic group in Afghanistan that has endured ongoing persecution from other Afghani groups. He</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>A NIKKEI AUSTRALIAN STORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>LEGACY OF THE PACIFIC WAR</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nagata</surname>
                           <given-names>Yuriko</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Diaspora’ is a useful umbrella term under which we can discuss large-scale migration, but it can lead to homogenized representations of migrants and may fail to reflect the individual pressures or dreams that motivated the migrants to leave their homelands. As part of a broader interest in how the Pacific War affected the Japanese diaspora, in this chapter I attempt to personalize and re-examine the notion of diaspora through the life story of Joseph Clement Kisaburo Murakami, an Australian-born ethnic Japanese who holds an Australian passport and has permanent residency in Japan. Joe is one of the few surviving<italic>Nikkei</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>DISPLACED PERSONS (1947–52) IN AUSTRALIA:</title>
                     <subtitle>MEMORY IN AUTOBIOGRAPHY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Persian</surname>
                           <given-names>Jayne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Almost 171,000 post-war Displaced Persons (DPs) – predominantly Central and Eastern Europeans – arrived in Australia between 1947 and 1952 as International Refugee Organisation–sponsored refugees.¹ These DPs came to Australia with little documentary evidence of their lives in Europe. They also soon found that telling their stories was not encouraged in an Australian society intent on assimilation. DP narratives were either co-opted to fit into government publicists’ and media’s representations or ignored, or became part of a diasporic literature. DP experiences have been retrospectively self-represented – ‘remembered’ – through mainstream media such as novels and memoirs. The advent of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>BETWEEN UTOPIA AND AUTOBIOGRAPHY:</title>
                     <subtitle>MIGRANT NARRATIVES IN AUSTRALIA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Williams</surname>
                           <given-names>Katarzyna Kwapisz</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The genres of autobiographical writing and utopian writing have little in common. While an autobiography is an account of the life of an individual written by that individual, utopian narrative offers a vision of an ideal place and social system for a collective. In fact, according to Robert F. Sayre, autobiography and utopia indicate polarities: between experience and prophecy, self and society, private and public or emotional unity and rational order (Sayre 1972, 21, 23). Both forms have firmly marked their presence in the culture and history of Australia. Autobiography, as Joy Hooton writes, has always been a prolific genre</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>VIETNAMESE–AUSTRALIAN LIFE WRITING AND INTEGRATION:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MAGAZINE FOR MULTICULTURAL AND VIETNAMESE ISSUES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jacklin</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Vietnamese–Australian stories have attracted significant public interest in the last few years, particularly with the success of Anh Do’s<italic>The Happiest Refugee</italic>(2010). When this book won a raft of Australian literary awards in 2011, it quickly became a bestseller and was selected for book-group discussions across the country. By the end of 2011 Do had been engaged by the Australian government’s Department of Immigration to deliver a motivational speech to selected detention centre staff – with the view that his family’s story of escape from Vietnam, their subsequent adaptation to migrant life and their eventual making good in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>HEROES, LEGENDS AND DIVAS:</title>
                     <subtitle>FRAMING FAMOUS LIVES IN AUSTRALIA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fox</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stories of shady characters are among the most popular biographies on the<italic>Australian Dictionary of Biography (ADB)</italic>website.¹ Between 1 July and 3 November 2011, the biographies of brothel-keeper Tilly Devine and fellow underworld figure Kate Leigh were the most frequently viewed on ADB Online, with a total of 85,983 page views between them. Gangster Squizzy Taylor was the second most popular in the 1 April to 30 September 2013 period, reaching 47,444 page views. It may be that these statistics reflect a temporary high point of visibility for these early-twentieth-century criminals, attributable to the popular television series<italic>Underbelly</italic>, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xhr5j8.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
