<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1081.S9</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Addresses, essays, lectures</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Addresses, essays, lectures</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion and poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Addresses, essays, lectures</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Symposium of the Whole</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Range of Discourse Toward an Ethnopoetics</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited with Commentaries by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rothenberg</surname>
               <given-names>Jerome</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rothenberg</surname>
               <given-names>Diane</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780520293113</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780520966345</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0520966341</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Berkeley; Los Angeles; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1983</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt1bmzkq4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Symposium of the Whole</italic>traces a discourse on poetry and culture that has profoundly influenced the art of our time, with precedents going back two centuries and more. Beginning with a reassertion of the complexity of poetry among peoples long labeled "primitive" and "savage," many recent poets have sought to base a new poetics over the fullest range of human cultures. The attempt to define an ethnopoetics has been significantly connected with the most experimental and future-directed side of Romantic and modern poetry, both in the Western world and, increasingly, outside it. As a visionary poetics and as a politics, this complex redefinition of cultural and intellectual values has involved a rarely acknowledged collaboration between poets and scholars, who together have challenged the narrow view of literature that has excluded so many traditions.In this gathering, the Rothenbergs follow the idea of an ethnopoetics from predecessors such as Vico, Blake, Thoreau, and Tzara to more recent essays and manifestos by poets and social thinkers such as Olson, Eliade, Snyder, Turner, and Baraka. The themes range widely, from the divergence of oral and written cultures to the shaman as proto-poet and the reemergence of suppressed and rejected forms and images: the goddess, the trickster, and the "human universe." The book's three ethnographic sections demonstrate how various poetries are structured and composed, how they reflect meaning and worldview, and how they are performed in cultures where all art may be thought of as art-in-motion.Among the poetries discussed are the language of magic; West African drum language and poetry; the Huichol Indian language of reversals; chance operations in African divination poetry; picture-writings and action-writings from Australia and Africa; and American Indian sacred-clown dramas and traditional trickster narratives. The cumulative effect is a new reading of the poetic past and present-in the editors' words, "a changed paradigm of what poetry was or now could come to be."</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="522"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PRE-FACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rothenberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Jerome</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>D. R.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Magic Words</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>NALUNGIAQ</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Material reworked from The Netsilik Eskimos (1931), representing field work by Knud Rasmussen (1879–1933), Danish explorer and ethnologist, of Eskimo ancestry on his motherʹs side. Nalungiaq, ʺjust an ordinary womanʺ (she says), learned it from an old uncle, Unaraluk the shaman, whose helping spirits—his dead father and mother, the sun, a dog, and a sea scorpion—enabled him to ʺknow everything about what was on the earth and under the earth, in the sea and in the sky.ʺ</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The idea of ʺmagic wordsʺ will be running through these pages (see especially Malinowski, p. 107, below), and the convergence</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Age of the Gods and the Origins of Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VICO</surname>
                           <given-names>GIAMBATTISTA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>4</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The ʺPrinciples of New Science of Giambattista Vico concerning the Common Nature of the Nationsʺ (first edition:1725) is a model work (comparative, evolutionary) for later history and anthropology: a view of the history of all societies as the account of their birth and development. But itʹs also a virtual speculative ethnopoetics in which the poetry of the ʺNationsʺ (= gentiles/gentes = Gk. ethnoi) already looms large. The core of the work, an extended section called ʺPoetic Wisdom,ʺ sets out a kind o f aboriginal creativity-writ-large that comes back full circle into the projected ʺnew science.ʺ Of that interplay between the</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From a Correspondence on Ossian and the Songs of Ancient Peoples</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HERDER</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHANN GOTTFRIED</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>With Herder we get the outlines for an actual and still viable ethnopoetics—a concept of poetry ʺemancipated from rationalist or Christian context and strictures, opening to world horizons, the dimension of time and cultural relativism, and deepening its meaning as a profound mode of truthʺ (Feldman, Modern Mythology, p. 225). But the universal poetics Herder creates has a new and strict regard for cultural autonomies and particularities—allowing the reentry of the outcast European (ʺfolkʺ) past and the more distant poetries of peoples then falling to European domination. Herderʹs Volkslieder (1778) is a first anthology with ethnopoetic scope: ʺnot</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From The Marriage of Heaven &amp; Hell</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BLAKE</surname>
                           <given-names>WILLIAM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>As does his very different contemporary Goethe, Blake appears today as one of the first of the new poets to revive in his own work a more-than-literary role as (ʺvisionaryʺ) shaper-of-the-real. (See Vico, above, p. 4.) Of the prevalence of such a mythopoetic mode in a larger human history, he wrote: ʺThe antiquities of every Nation under Heaven, is no less sacred than that of the Jews. They are the same thing as Jacob Bryant, and all antiquaries have proved. How other antiquities came to be neglected and disbelieved, while those of the jews are collected and arranged, is an</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>In Wildness is the preservation of the World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THOREAU</surname>
                           <given-names>HENRY DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Thoreau brings the ʺwildernessʺ side of the proposition into focus: what the nineteenth century would have subsumed under the word ʺnatureʺ and the later twentieth century under ʺecology.ʺ The emphasis is in fact characteristically American, and the view of wilderness and wildness brings together ideas (social and personal) of place, of language, of body, and of mind. In the American instance, also, the persistent presence is that of the Indian (ʺthe vengeful ghost lurking in the back of the troubled American mindʺ—G. Snyder), as one remembers the word ʺIndianʺ spoken by Thoreau on his death bed—or his vision</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Rise of Bourgeois Rule and the Origin of World Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARX</surname>
                           <given-names>KARL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ENGELS</surname>
                           <given-names>FRIEDRICH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>In Stanley Diamondʹs summation of a primitivist/Marxist ʺclaim that our sense of primitive communal societies is the archetype for socialism,ʺ he writes: ʺPrimitive cultures were for [Marx and Engels] the ground of all future movement. Moreover, Marx indicated that they served as the paradigm for the idea of socialism; socialism would achieve ʹthat which men had always dreamed aboutʹ Marx believedʺ (Diamond 1974: 106, 108). The opening image of The Communist Manifesto—ʺa specter is haunting Europe: the specter of communismʺ—is, therefore, not only the classic statement of a revolutionary European politics but an implicit argument toward a radical</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From “Mauvais Sang” [Bad Blood]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RIMBAUD</surname>
                           <given-names>ARTHUR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The center of an ethnopoetics in Rimbaudʹs work is his recovery (circa 1870 at age 16) of the shaman-like poet who ʺmust become a seer, make oneself a seer … by a long, prodigious &amp; systematic derangement of the senses.ʺ (Compare, e.g., the Copper Eskimo word for the shaman/songman [= poet]: ʺone who has eyes.ʺ) But along with that comes an early internalization of the once distant ʺsavageʺ—a ferocious play, in Rimbaudʹs case, that fuses his imagined Gallic/pagan ancestors (ʺthe race that sang under tortureʺ) with those contemporary outcasts and criminals (local and colonial) who become for him a kind</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Ritual and Theater</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DURKHEIM</surname>
                           <given-names>EMILE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Durkheim (1858–1917) has exerted a major and continuing influence on contemporary social theory (structural-functionalism, structuralism, etc.) through his investigations of the relation of social to mental structures. In ʺnon-alienatedʺ simple societies, he viewed this relationship as an instance of ʺcollective mindʺ—as when he and Marcel Mauss wrote: ʺLogical relations are in a sense domestic relations … and the unity of knowledge is nothing else than the unity of the collectivity extended to the universeʺ (1963:84). Durkheim brings to the present context an emphasis on the</italic>collective<italic>nature of tribal ritual and art, leading, from our perspective, toward later</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From The Chinese Written Character as a Medium for Poetry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FENOLLOSA</surname>
                           <given-names>ERNEST</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Fenollosaʹs long essay, written circa 1908, is the outstanding instance of the impact on contemporary practice not simply of another poetry but of the inherent poetics of another language—its written as well as spoken form. Ezra Pound, who had translated Japanese Noh plays with Fenollosa, arranged for the essayʹs posthumous publication, writing in introduction: ʺIn his search through unknown art, Fenollosa, coming upon unknown motives and principles unrecognized in the West, was already led into many modes of thought since fruitful in ʹnewʹ Western painting and poetry…. The later movements in art have corroborated his theories.ʺ In spite of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on Negro Poetry/Oceanian Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TZARA</surname>
                           <given-names>TRISTAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>As an avant-garde extremist and co-founder of the Dada movement—Zurich 1916 in the midst of World War I—Tzara called for ʺa great negative work of destructionʺ against the European nation-state as a ʺstate of madness, the aggressive complete madness of a world left in the hands of bandits who vandalize and destroy the centuries.ʺ But the constructive side of the work included a project to recoup the model of a primal art and poetry, toward which he assembled, using numerous scholarly sources, a first anthology of tribal/oral poems from a fiercely modernist perspective—poèmes nègres, never published in</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reality at White Heat</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RADIN</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Born in Lodz, Poland, Radin (1883–1959) became a leading figure in the Boasian school o f American anthropology. His special genius lay in revealing and asserting the dominance of the individual in the stateless communal cultures of the aboriginal world. Not only that but ʺan individualism run riot,ʺ a ʺruthless realism,ʺ and a high imagination, in a human nexus he summarized as follows:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>If one were asked to state briefly and succinctly … the outstanding positive features of aboriginal civilizations, I, for one, would have no hesitation in answering that there are three: the respect for the individual, irrespective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Paideuma</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FROBENIUS</surname>
                           <given-names>LEO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>One of the first Westerners to recognize the actual achievement of traditional African art, Frobenius (1873–1938) spent many years in Africa, gathered and translated African oral traditions, and founded the Institute for Cultural Morphology in Frankfurt as a repository for (largely facsimiles of) prehistoric and African paintings and engravings. He was, in anthropological terms, a leading German diffusionist who advocated a complex, multifactorial approach to the analysis of cultural transmission, but in British and American anthropology, for example, his reputation is by now minimal. At the same time, he has profoundly influenced at least two major and largely unrelated</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Value of Leo Frobenius</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>POUND</surname>
                           <given-names>EZRA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Poundʹs gift to a possible ethnopoetics comes largely from his idea of culture and mind as ʺvortexʺ—opening the poem to a range of historical and cultural particulars: Chinese and Japanese, Egyptian, Provençal, gnostic and subterranean, contemporary U.S. and European, as well as a gesture toward the Euro-African bridge via Frobenius. Of the vortex in general, Pound wrote, manifesto fashion, in 1914: ʺAll experience rushes into this vortex. All the energized past, all the past that is living and worthy to live. All MOMENTUM, which is the past bearing upon us.ʺ With this end in view, Frobeniusʹs idea of</italic>Paideuma,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Duende</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LORCA</surname>
                           <given-names>FEDERICO GARCÍA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Lorcaʹs poetry of the late 1920s/early 1930s fuses Surrealist concerns with that sense of native culture (Andalusian and Gypsy), a true Paideuma (see above, p. 36), which permeates this essay. ʺCharacteristically,ʺ writes Arturo Barea, ʺLorca took his Spanish term for daemonic inspiration from the Andalucían idiom. While to the rest of Spain the</italic>duende<italic>is nothing but a hobgoblin, to Andalucía it is an obscure power which can speak through every form of human art, including the art of personalityʺ (</italic>Lorca: The Poet and His People<italic>). The</italic>duende<italic>essay, originally a lecture, followed a year in New York City (1929–</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Negritude</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CÉSAIRE</surname>
                           <given-names>AIMÉ</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DEPESTRE</surname>
                           <given-names>RENÉ</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺNegritudeʺ was—from one of its directions—a culmination of Surrealist concepts of an alternative consciousness ʺopposed to the values of Europeʺ and ʺviolently departing once and for all from the ways of thinking and feeling which have made life no longer bearable.ʺ (Thus: André Breton, the master of French Surrealism, in his preface—1943—to the Martinican poet Aimé Césaireʹs</italic>Notebook of a Return to the Native Land.)<italic>The young French-speaking black poets (Césaire, Senghor, et al.) who launched the movement in the 1930s tied all that to</italic>this<italic>particular culture or network of cultures—ʺA frica,ʺ then colonized—</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The White Goddess</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRAVES</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The ʺreturn of the goddessʺ is one of the central events of a poetics of recovery, a symposium of the whole, etc. From Blake on (ʺThe Eternal Female groand! it was heard all over the Earthʺ), her image accompanies many of our most radical language experiments, summoning up past images (e.g., Shekinah, Sophia, Kali), leading to a male-centered vision of the muse, as with Graves in what follows, and to a revitalized feminism exploring its own numinosity. But the goddess is linked as well with a geocentric/Gaiacentric vision (ʺthe earth as a religious formʺ [Eliade]) and thus with contemporary stabs</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From Tristes Tropiques</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LÉVI-STRAUSS</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAUDE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The founder of ʺstructural anthropologyʺ Lévi-Strauss globalizes Durkheimʹs ʺcollective mindʺ and here carries it into the heart of the city—the contemporary world of the new wilderness. Beneath the primitive-civilized dichotomy, he asserts a deep structure, a principle of psychic unity that offers a way out of the anomie caused not only by a breakdown of the social bond but by rejection of the underlying unity of mind and nature. The resultant proposition is a new science—based like that of Vico (see above, p. 4) on the reshaping of a primary ʺpoetic wisdomʺ—and a recognition of the actual</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Epilogue to Shamanism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ELIADE</surname>
                           <given-names>MIRCEA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>An experimental novelist earlier along (his objective, in the Rumanian phrase, to ʺsabotage historyʺ), Eliade became a historian of religion and the greatest living reinterpreter of the sacred dimensions of religion and thought, setting these against a contemporary ʺdesacralization of natureʺ through an impressive sweep of disciplines and cultures (shamanism, yoga, alchemy, etc.). His large work on shamanism is still the best guide to the subject, reinforcing an intuition long held of the shaman as artist and thinker as well as ʺmedicine man, priest and psychopompus.ʺ In the present co-editorʹs book, Technicians of the Sacred (the title itself is a</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Human Universe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLSON</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺWe are estranged from that with which we are most familiar,ʺ wrote Olson, quoting ancient Heraclitus, and he set out on a search through the American and human past—Pleistocene, pre-Biblical Mediterranean (Sumerian, Hittite, etc.), Norse, Mayan, and American Indian—with a conviction ʺthat the reality the Trobriand Islanders hearken toʺ (at least the process of getting at it, reenacting it as myth)ʺ is not at all a local or primitive one, is as much our own as theirs, whatever the differencesʺ (Olson 1978: 67). And on a local level—and here was his major contribution—he put a renewed</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Plato and the Definition of the Primitive</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DIAMOND</surname>
                           <given-names>STANLEY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>At the heart of Diamondʹs engaged and committed anthropology is the image of a ʺsearch for the primitiveʺ—as ʺan attempt to define a primary human potential,ʺ to transcend thereby the ʺprimitive-civilized dichotomyʺ that he traces back to the origins of the political state, with its antagonism to ambivalence and to the concrete instance in favor of a ʺPlatonic abstraction, the essence of civilized modalities of thoughtʺ (Compare Olsonʹs ʺwe have lived long in a generalizing time,ʺ p. 63, above.) More than any contemporary anthropologist of note, with the possible exception of Victor Turner, Diamond insists on an internalized poetics</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Poetry and the Primitive:</title>
                     <subtitle>Notes on Poetry as an Ecological Survival Technique</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SNYDER</surname>
                           <given-names>GARY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺAs a poet I hold the most archaic values on earth. They go back to the Paleolithic: the fertility o f the soil, the magic of animals. The power-vision in solitude, the terrifying initiation and rebirth, the love and ecstasy of the damned, the common work of the tribe.ʺ</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>More than most poets, Snyder has been a model of these values put into practice, engaged with experimental and traditional religion and with an experimental—still tentative—communal life. ʺForming the New Society / Within the shell of the Old,ʺ he writes (quoting the old Wobbly motto) in his first book,</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Pre-Face to Technicians of the Sacred</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROTHENBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>JEROME</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺTherefore, in outline: (1) the traditions in question add to any reconsideration of poetry as ʹvisionʹ &amp; ʹcommunionʹ a series of authentic instances (historical &amp; cultural) in which such functions were realized; (2) they provide the idea of the oral &amp; mythic as self-corrective tellings, &amp; the evidence of how it works; (3) they give a functional dimension to ʹmeaningʹ or ʹsignificanceʹ in the poetic act: the evidence that even apparently minimal forms may have a great complexity of function (ʹthe smallest things can turn you onʹ—P. Blackburn) … but at the same time, an expanded notion of alternative poetic &amp; linguistic structures; (4)</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Meaning of Meaningless Words and the Coefficient of Weirdness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MALINOWSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>BRONISLAW</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Malinowski lays down one major line of British functionalism, as A. R. Radcliffe-Brown lays down the other (structural-functionalism). But if Radcliffe-Brownʹs version has the greater theoretical carry-over at present, Malinowski has set a model for anthropological fieldwork and its attendant theory and has had an extraordinary impact as a teacher of later anthropologists and on a range of Western and Third World thought outside of anthropology itself. His principal writings in this regard come out of his extended work in the Trobriands and other islands off the southeast tip of New Guinea (1912–1916), and include such books as Argonauts</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Born Tying Knots</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NORMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>HOWARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The concern with names and naming enters our poetics with Whitmanʹs exultant assertions (in An American Primer) that ʺnames are magicʺ and that ʺno country can have its own poems without it have its own namesʺ (1949:577, 583) and even more emphatically in Gertrude Steinʹs later description of names as the key to the origins of poetry:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nouns are the names of anything. Think of all that early poetry, think of Homer, think of Chaucer, think of the Bible and you will see what I mean you will really realize that they were drunk with nouns, to name to know</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How the Names are Changed on the Peyote Journey</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SILVA</surname>
                           <given-names>RAMÓN MEDINA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The poetry of reversals described by the maraʹakáme (shaman), Ramón Medina Silva, of San Sebastian, Mexico, is part of the Huichol peyote hunt and ritual (see below, p. 225). The tactic is common to the languages, acts, and dream-work of shamans and sacred clowns throughout the world. Its Crow Indian manifestation, for example, took the form of warrior societies of ʺcontrariesʺ (Crazy Dogs) whose behavior included ʺsaying the opposite of what you mean &amp; making others say the opposite of what they mean in returnʺ (Rothenberg 1972: 195). As a more deeply rooted philosophy of contradictions, it reentered Western thought through</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Speech and Image:</title>
                     <subtitle>An African Tradition of the Surreal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SENGHOR</surname>
                           <given-names>LÉOPOLD SÉDAR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Emerging from the Negritude movement of the 1930s (see above, p. 52), Senghor became the first and long-reigning president of Senegal from the time of its independence in 1960. His poetics drew from a base in African oral tradition, illuminated by and in turn illuminating the explorations of European Surrealism, etc. For the ʺsurreal imageʺ per se, the reader might turn to Pierre Reverdyʹs classic ʺdefinition,ʺ circa 1918, often cited by the French Surrealists:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Image is a pure creation of the mind.</p>
                     <p>It cannot spring from a comparison but from the bringing together of two more or less distant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Koyukon Riddle-Poems</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAUENHAUER</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The riddle in verbal culture is part of the stock-in-trade of academic folklore, but its relation to the poetic image (see above, p. 119) has rarely been explored. The workings presented here were originally published in the Riddle and Poetry Handbook, developed by Richard Dauenhauer as a project of the Alaska Native Education Board in Anchorage. With Nora Dauenhauer, a native Tlingit speaker, Dauenhauer has for some years engaged in translation projects (Tlingit into English, English into Tlingit) aimed at Tlingit-speaking audiences</italic>.</p>
                     <p>In 1913, Father Julius Jetté, S.J. published a two-part article on the riddles of the Koyukon Indians, an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Izibongo:</title>
                     <subtitle>Zulu Praise-Poems</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COPE</surname>
                           <given-names>TREVOR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The praise-poem as a stringing-together of new or inherited praise-names (e.g., Yoruba oriki, Zulu izibongo, Basuto lithoko, Hausa kirari) is found throughout much of Africa. ʺSuch words or phrases,ʺ writes Ruth Finnegan, ʺoccur frequently within the more complex form of a complete poemʺ (1970: 111), and the praise-poem itself can become extremely complex and diversified. But the basic method holds—a kind of ʺcollagingʺ in which the individual poet takes off from the work of the collectivity, adding to it as last in a line of makers. His art therefore is one of creation and assemblage—the weighing of line</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Drum Language and Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FINNEGAN</surname>
                           <given-names>RUTH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺOf very great interest and importance is the possibility of transferring the whole system of speech symbolism into other terms than those that are involved in the typical process … a transfer, direct or indirect, from the typical symbolism of language as spoken and heard…. The ease with which speech symbolism can be transferred from one sense to another, from technique to technique, itself indicates that the mere sounds of speech are not the essential fact of language, which lies rather in the classification, in the formal patterning, and in the relating of conceptsʺ (Sapir 1921: 19–21).</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The process</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Guruwari Designs</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MUNN</surname>
                           <given-names>NANCY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Munnʹs instance of a traditional tie between oral and visual language is from the Walbiri of northwestern Australia. The visual side (hand and eye) of ethnopoetics has generally been ignored in favor of the oral side (mouth and ear). Fundamental relations between writing/drawing and speaking/singing, although clear enough within such cultures as the Walbiri, have received little real attention from without. A series of propositions in this regard has come from the French philosopher, Jacques Derrida, whose elevation of other-than-alphabetic forms of writing should simultaneously help establish the equality of oral modes of poetry. Of the universality of his grammatology</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Written Face</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARTHES</surname>
                           <given-names>ROLAND</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Barthesʹs essay is presented here as an extension, by ethnopoetic means, of the ʺquestion of writingʺ discussed in the previous headnote.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Japanese theatrical face is not painted (powdered), it is written. This unforeseen movement occurs: though painting and writing have the same original instrument, the brush, it is not painting, however, which seduces writing with its decorative style, its sprawling, caressing touch, its representative space (as no doubt would have happened with us in the West, for whom the civilized future of a function is always its esthetic ennoblement); on the contrary, it is the act of writing-which subjugates</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Divination Poetry of Ifa</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FINNEGAN</surname>
                           <given-names>RUTH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Though divination as such has had minimal impact on contemporary poetry, the underpinnings of divination in systematic chance procedures relate closely to processes used by experimental poets and artists, from the Dada work of Duchamp, Arp, and Tzara to its fuller development by Jackson Mac Low and John Cage. For this, the traditional system most drawn from is that of the Chinese I Ching, as modified by Carl Jungʹs speculation on ʺsynchronicity,ʺ the ʺacausal connectionsʺ between things happening at the same time (Wilhelm/Baynes 1950). But itʹs in the widespread African practices that we find a still actively creative, large, and</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>First Person Voice in Ainu Epic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PHILIPPI</surname>
                           <given-names>DONALD L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The device presented here—of a projective first person narration on a possibly shamanistic base—points to a linkage of the male and female singers with other ʺnon-human entitiesʺ in what Philippi calls ʺa form of inter-species communication in which gods or humans speak of experiences to members of their own or other species.ʺ In saying this, he reveals a traditional way not only of knowing but of experiencing and projecting a total natural environment—as Gary Snyder describes it in his ʺforewordʺ to these songs: ʺThe life of mountains and rivers flowed from their group experience, through speech and</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Songs and the Song</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LORD</surname>
                           <given-names>ALBERT B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The distinction made by Lord and his predecessor, Milman Parry, is between poems ʺmemorized,ʺ in a transcriptional writing system, and poems ʺremembered,ʺ in an oral or word-of-mouth tradition. The latter are never absolutely fixed as text or reference (ʺthe oral poem even in the mouth of the same singer is ever in a state of changeʺ [Parry 1932: 14]) and are finally inseparable from their performance (i.e., the idea here presented, that performance = composition). In focusing on surviving European oral epics, Lord and Parry put great stress on the use of traditional ʺtagsʺ and ʺepithetsʺ (formulas) that the epic</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Some Ewe Poets</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AWOONOR</surname>
                           <given-names>KOFI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>A major African poet and himself a native Ewe-speaker, Awoonorʹs first-hand assessment of the individuality of the Ewe song-poets puts to rest the common view of the anonymous/collective nature of all tribal poetry. His own work in English, he tells us, has ʺattempted to incorporate the features of the Ewe dirgeʺ and other forms of oral poetry, ʺborrowing liberally from [such poets as] Akpaluʺ in what Awoonor calls ʺa deliberate act of falling back upon a tradition which has been ignored in our missionary education and whose practice has been labeled paganistic by our Christian mentorsʺ (1975: 202, 208).</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Meaning of Everyday Objects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FIRE</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>What Lame Deer says here of the resonance and meaning of ʺordinary, common thingsʺ among the Lakota (Sioux) had burst into Western consciousness as well—if not as the common practice he implies, then as a central issue of poetics from the first Romantics to the later modernists and ʺpostʺ-modernists. Thus Blake, for example, in 1802 (ʺA Letter to Thomas Buttsʺ), writes:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>What to others a trifle appears</p>
                     <p>Fills me full of smiles or tears</p>
                     <p>For double the vision my Eyes do see</p>
                     <p>And a double vision is always with me</p>
                     <p>With my inward Eye ʹtis an old Man grey</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Sacred Hoop:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Contemporary Indian Perspective on American Indian Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALLEN</surname>
                           <given-names>PAULA GUNN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Born in Cubero, New Mexico, and affiliated with Laguna Pueblo, Paula Gunn Allen is one of the Native American poets concerned with the question of sources and survivals into the industrial/postindustrial world. The issue of traditional continuities (and discontinuities)—and the meanings derived therefrom—has been central to Third and Fourth World cultures and to others threatened by internal imperialisms and the movement toward a global monoculture.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>For more on Lame Deer, frequently mentioned herein, see the excerpt and commentary immediately preceding.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Literature is a facet of a culture. Its significance can be best understood in terms of its culture,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Mushrooms of Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SABINA</surname>
                           <given-names>MARÍA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Of the use of the psychedelic Psilocybe mushroom in pre-Conquest Mexico, an early Spanish chronicler wrote: ʺThey pay a sorcerer who eats them [the mushrooms] and tells what they have taught him. He does so by means of a rhythmic chant in full voice.ʺ The practice is continued today by shamans (ʺWise Onesʺ) among the Mazatec Indians of northeastern Oaxaca. But it isnʹt the shamans who speak directly; itʹs the mushrooms, called ʺsaint children,ʺ and ʺlittle ones,ʺ and ʺflesh of god.ʺ that give them language. ʺIf you ask a shaman where his imagery comes fromʺ—Henry Munn tells us in</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>An American Indian Model of the Universe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WHORF</surname>
                           <given-names>BENJAMIN LEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The ways in which the structure of a language may shape the reality of its speakers are nowhere more elegantly set down than in Whorfʹs studies of Hopi and other American Indian languages. ʺWe dissect nature along lines laid down by our native language,ʺ he writes of the differences in linguistic pattern from language to language—and the consequences (= ʺthought worldsʺ) arising therefrom. Or, summarizing the enterprise shared with linguists such as Edward Sapir (the so-called Sapir-Whorf hypothesis):</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Actually, thinking is most mysterious, and by far the greatest light upon it that we have is thrown by the study</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Fertilizing Word</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>OGOTEMMÊLI</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRIAULE</surname>
                           <given-names>MARCEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The conversations between Ogotemmêli, an elder of the Dogon in the Western Sudan, and the ethnographer, Marcel Griaule, took place over thirty-three successive days in October 1946. During that time, according to Griaule, Ogotemmêli ʺlaid bare the framework of a world system: … a cosmogony as rich as that of Hesiod, poet of a dead world, and a metaphysics that has the advantage of being expressed in a thousand rites and actions in the life of a multitude of living beingsʺ (1965: 3). That ʺsystemʺ—or the part of it presented to Griaule—sets up a vast web of correspondences</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Dreaming</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STANNER</surname>
                           <given-names>W. E. H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺExistence is elsewhere,ʺ wrote André Breton and pointed to the reintroduction of dream into everyday life, toward ʺthe future resolution of these two states, dream and reality, which are seemingly so contradictory, into a kind of absolute reality, a surrealityʺ (The First Surrealist Manifesto, 1924). A projection of Surrealist yearning, the idea of a process, an ʺact of dreamingʺ by which ʺthe mind makes contact with whatever mystery it is that connects the Dreaming [the Eternal Dream Time] and the Here and Now,ʺ is fundamental to mythic thought throughout the world and is at its most developed in the traditions</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On the Psychology of the Trickster Figure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JUNG</surname>
                           <given-names>CARL G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>A near-universal figure, Trickster appears both as human and animal—Raven, Coyote, Rabbit, Jaguar, Spider, Fox, and so on: as the creator of the world and the source o f its confusion. In his prefatory note to his gathering and translation of the Winnebago ʺtrickster cycle,ʺ for which Jungʹs essay serves as commentary, Radin writes:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Few myths have so wide a distribution as the one known by the name of The Trickster…. Among the North American Indians, Trickster is at one and the same time creator and destroyer, giver and negator, he who dupes the others and who is always</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>God the Father/God the Mother</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PAGELS</surname>
                           <given-names>ELAINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>In an important synthesizing essay, ʺPassage to More than India,ʺ the poet Gary Snyder wrote:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>My own opinion is that we are now experiencing a surfacing (in a specifically ʺAmericanʺ incarnation) of the Great Subculture which goes back as far perhaps as the late Paleolithic. This subculture of illuminati has been a powerful undercurrent in all higher civilizations. In China it manifested as Taoism … and the Zen Buddhists up till early Sung. Within Islam the Sufis; in India the various threads converged to produce Tantrism. In the West it has been represented largely by a string of heresies starting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Return to Wirikuta:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ritual Reversal and Symbolic Continuity in the Huichol Peyote Hunt</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MYERHOFF</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The following piece explores and illuminates ways in which this kind of traditional poetry and ritual has been able to ʺsustain contradictionsʺ (S. Diamond) and to participate thereby in aspects of reality not recoverable by ordinary means. A Huichol summary, by Ramón Medina Silva, of the accompanying language of reversals, appears above on pages 116 to 118.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>God is day and night, winter summer, war peace, satiety hunger—all opposites, this is the meaning.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>—<italic>Heraclitus</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rituals of opposition and reversal constitute a critical part of a lengthy religious ceremony, the peyote hunt, practiced by the Huichol Indians of north-central Mexico.¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Return of the Symbol</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ELIADE</surname>
                           <given-names>MIRCEA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The headnote on the place and work of Mircea Eliade appears on page 59, above.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>The surprising popularity of psychoanalysis has made the fortunes of certain key-words: image, symbol and symbolism have now become current coin. At the same time, systematic research devoted to the mechanisms of “primitive mentality” has revealed the importance of symbolism in archaic thinking and also the fundamental part it plays in the life of any and every primitive society. The obsolescence of “scientism” in philosophy, the revival of interest in religion since the first world war, many poetic developments and, above all, the researches of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From “On the Balinese Theater”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ARTAUD</surname>
                           <given-names>ANTONIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Artaudʹs efforts ʺto break through language in order to touch lifeʺ placed him, finally, among the truly radical poets of the twentieth century and among those who pioneered a necessary ethnopoetics toward such ends. An actor by profession, he pursued a new overview of art and life, first as the director of the Paris-based Bureau of Surrealist Research and, after his break with the Surrealists, through his thwarted experiments with theater and film, his writings such as The Theater and Its Double (from which the present excerpt), and his collapse into a personal agony he could yet project through language.</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Aesthetics of the Sounding of the Text</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LANSING</surname>
                           <given-names>J. STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Whatʹs ʺmissingʺ from Artaudʹs spontaneous take on Balinese theater (see above, p. 235) is the awareness of a self-conscious body of discourse, an indigenous and fully formulated Balinese poetics, behind the work observed. This poetics—following from what Stephen Lansing, on a Southeast Asian model, calls ʺthe aesthetics of the ʹsounding of the textʹ ʺ—illuminates not only Balinese performance per se but the nature of performance art in general. Such an ʺillumination in generalʺ is, of course, what weʹve always posited for forms of Western discourse—the assumption, for example, that Aristotleʹs equally localized, Athenian Poetics is the basis,</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.51</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From “Shamanistic Theater: Origins and Evolution”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KIRBY</surname>
                           <given-names>ERNEST THEODORE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The relation of shamans and their works to art, dance, music, poetry, performance—and, above all, to vision and healing—traces back to the Dancing Sorcerers of Europeʹs paleolithic caves. ʺRain kings, magic protectors, chiefs, artisans and ambassadors,ʺ the shamans, now rediscovered, have become the prototypical ʺculture heroes … of all the European artsʺ (La Barre 1970: 422). Weston La Barre stresses the shamanʹs ʺsecret magic, musicʺ through ʺthe harpsinging shaman Apollo … leader of the muses,ʺ but the shaman has also emerged as a kind of protopoet—ʺvery much,ʺ writes Peter Furst, ʺRadinʹs own PRIMITIVE MAN AS PHILOSOPHER.ʺ (See</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.52</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Sacred Clown</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ORTIZ</surname>
                           <given-names>ALFONSO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>270</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺ[Among] the oldest pure performers in the history of settled human life,ʺ notes Alfonso Ortiz (1977 ms: 4–5), the sacred clowns in their Pueblo form ʺwere around at least by the end of the 1st millennium, a.d., because petroglyphs and other representations of them are traceable to that period.ʺ As E. T. Kirby indicates (above, p. 266), the clownʹs ʺsacredness,ʺ like the shamanʹs, hooks into an extraordinary initiatory/visionary experience and rebirth. Ortiz terms this rebirth ʺa new, omnipotent mode of existenceʺ (1977 ms: 22)—what Mircea Eliade speaks of as the ʺdivine election,ʺ and Black Elk, with specific reference</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.53</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From The Sorrow of the Lonely and the Burning of the Dancers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHIEFFELIN</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The interaction between performer and spectator has been an issue of performance theory—Western and other—from Aristotleʹs catharsis to contemporary experiments with participatory theater, etc. (see below, p. 311). In the Papua New Guinea instance following, the projection and expulsion, here of grief and anger, works through a language-centered, basically social and nonmystical exploitation of human feelings—a cathartic geography, a primal poetry of name and place. ʺMoving and violent,ʺ in Schieffelinʹs words, the Gisaro Ceremony is itself part of a larger series of ceremonial events involving ritual exchanges between kinsmen who are living at some distance from each</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.54</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Nsibidi/Action Writing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THOMPSON</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT FARRIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Writing of African performance art, Robert Farris Thompson suggests that performance puts objects and words in motion toward a highly unified, even total art ʺin which one medium is never absolutely emphasized over othersʺ (1974: xii). (Compare this with contemporary ideas of ʺintermedia,ʺ etc.) And again:</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Icon defines itself in act south of the Sahara. Things done, sculpture and dress, combine with things happening, music and dance. A fundamental principle is made manifest: action is a superior mode of thought. Movement serves long-term knowledge with sensuous uprush and spontaneity, answering to the imperatives of life. There is no turning back.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.55</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Poetry without Sound</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KLIMA</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BELLUGI</surname>
                           <given-names>URSULA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Even in its early, tentative stages, the signing poetry emerging as an aspect of the ʺculture of the deafʺ challenges some of our cherished preconceptions about poetry and its relation to human speech. Ameslan (American Sign Language) represents, literally, a poetry without sound and, for its practitioners, a poetry without access to that experience of sound as voice that weʹve so often taken as the bedrock of all poetics and all language. In the real world of the deaf, then, language exists as a kind of writing in space and as a primary form of communication without reference to any</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.56</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Kabbalistic Ritual and the Bride of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHOLEM</surname>
                           <given-names>GERSHOM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The ʺgreat subcultureʺ (see above, p. 217) emerges as well in</italic>kabbalah:<italic>the last of the Jewish oral traditions, connected at its source to what Scholem speaks of elsewhere as ʺJewish gnosticism.ʺ A catchall term ʺfor the esoteric teachings of Judaism and Jewish mysticism, especially the forms which it assumed in the Middle Ages from the 12th century onwardʺ (Scholem 1974: 3), kabbalah was often carried on by mystics who were themselves extraordinary poets—Abraham Abulafia, Isaac Luria, Moses de Leon (author of ʺThe Zoharʺ), and others—ʺverbal alchemists,ʺ in Rimbaudʹs phrase. This virtual poetics made an approach to reality</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.57</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From Ritual to Theatre and Back:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Structure/Process of the Efficacy-Entertainment Dyad</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHECHNER</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>In the late 1960s Richard Schechner, as director of the New York-based Performance Group and a leading shaper of contemporary ʺperformance theory,ʺ pioneered a so-called ʺenvironmental theaterʺ that could draw on all elements in and around the performance space, including the actor-audience nexus and that between both and ʺthe larger environments outside the theatre.ʺ Schechnerʹs deliberate use of models to ʺstimulate [the environmentalistsʹ] creativityʺ turned from familiar Western sources to ʺAmerican Indian, Oceanic, African, Siberian, or Eskimo societies,ʺ or back in history ʺto Altamira and the other caves, and then forward to Egypt, the Near and Middle East, Asia, and</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.58</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From “Rites of Participation”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DUNCAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>ʺA multiphasic experience sought a multiphasic form,ʺ wrote Robert Duncan (D. Allen 1960:435) toward a poetics, rich in influences and sources, that could set the work of an avant-garde alongside both the Western ʺmainstreamʺ (Dante, Whitman, the Romantics) and those subterranean traditions (Kabbalah, Gnosticism, etc.) that had long been ʺneglected, even scornedʺ but ʺin which one begins to find the Gnosis o f the modern w orld.ʺ Duncan is also, in both his poetry and poetics, a principal reinterpreter of myth as an ongoing human process, so crucial to him that he writes: ʺThe meaning and intent of what it</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.59</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Review of “Ethnopoetics”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TURNER</surname>
                           <given-names>VICTOR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Victor Turner has been a major and highly influential anthropologist since the late 1950s. His contributions to symbolic anthropology and to a unified theory of performance include concepts of liminality and</italic>communitas,<italic>social drama, reflexivity, and symbolic process, applicable to a wide range of human cultures but developed from particular situations such as that of the Ndembu of eastern Africa. In the present article, he reviews the proceedings of ʺthe first international symposium on ethnopoeticsʺ as gathered by Michel Benamou and Jerome Rothenberg in a special issue of</italic>Alcheringa<italic>(Benamou 1976). Principal works:</italic>The Forest of Symbols, The Ritual Process,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.60</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Some North Pacific Coast Poems:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Problem in Anthropological Philology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HYMES</surname>
                           <given-names>DELL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>343</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>As a major anthropological linguist, Hymesʹs early and ongoing contribution to an ethnopoetics has been a practical ʺstructuralismʺ that attempts to examine and represent ʺways in which narratives [or, as here, songs] are organizations of linguistic meansʺ—a work he has pursued not by ʺleaping to universalsʺ but by ʺthe development of theories adequate and specific to each tradition.ʺ Beginning with the present essay—a criticism and virtual ʺdeconstructionʺ of earlier translation work—Hymes later focused on the performative side of traditional oral poetry (i.e., on its ʺrealization in performanceʺ) in ways akin to the proposals and practice of Dennis</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.61</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Tell It Like It’s Right in Front of You”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TEDLOCK</surname>
                           <given-names>DENNIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>366</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Tedlockʹs breakthrough—for which his essay, ʺOn the Translation of Style in Oral Narrativeʺ (1971), was a first declaration—involves a recognition of the full dynamics of voice in oral narration, along with the development of new means of transcription and translation to bring it across on the page and in performance. To do this, he typically uses line and stanza breaks to note the natural pauses of</italic>all<italic>human speech, and he adapts such typographical devices as capital letters, reduced type-size, jagged lineation, and vowels followed by long dashes, to indicate such voice qualities as loudness, softness, (chanted) pitch</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.62</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Total Translation:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Experiment in the Presentation of American Indian Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROTHENBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>JEROME</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Jerome Rothenberg has worked for two decades toward the enlargement of poetics by ethnopoetic and other means (ʺtotal translation,ʺ poetics of performance, etc.) involving a spectrum of assemblages and translations from multiple sources (see above, p. 99). The ethnopoetic aspects of the work are to be found in his own poetry (</italic>Poland/1931, A Seneca Journal<italic>), in anthologies such as the present one</italic>, Technicians of the Sacred, Shaking the Pumpkin, America a Prophecy,<italic>and</italic>A Big Jewish Book,<italic>and in magazines such as</italic>Alcheringa<italic>and</italic>New Wilderness Letter.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>At the time o f this writing (1969), the other key works toward</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.63</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Tenth Horse Song of Frank Mitchell</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McALLESTER</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Among the great American ethnomusicologists, David P. McAllester has had an eminent sense of the possibilities of an actual poetics emerging from the verbal materials with which he has dealt. His principal area of ethnographic concern has been Navajo, and he has worked with Navajo music and poetry (and their complex interworkings) for close to thirty-five years. The present essay was originally published alongside Jerome Rothenbergʹs experimental translations of the Navajo horse-songs (see above, pp. 381, 387), for which McAllester served as transmitter and adviser. Though their strategies for translation diverge significantly, McAllesterʹs view, circa 1966, of the spirit of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.64</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Song/Poetry and Language—Expression and Perception</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ORTIZ</surname>
                           <given-names>SIMON J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>A poet of Acoma Pueblo (New Mexico), Ortizʹs English writings have provided a significant continuity between old and new modes, with a strong sense of the possibilities and losses involved therein. To the questions, ʺWhy do you write? Who do you write for?ʺ he replies: ʺBecause Indians always tell a story. The only way to continue is to tell a story and thatʹs what Coyote says. The only way to continue is to tell a story and there is no other way. Your children will not survive unless you tell something about them—how they were born, how they came</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.65</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fragments from the Prayers Made on Behalf of Nathaniel Tarn by the Tzutujil-Maya Priest Nicolas Chiviliu Tacaxoy, Santiago Atitlan, Guatemala, 1953, 1959</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TARN</surname>
                           <given-names>NATHANIEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>408</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Nathaniel Tarnʹs early work as an anthropologist (contemporary Mayan culture, popular Buddhism in Burma) informs the richness of reference in his later poetry (pre-Conquest and early post-Conquest themes in</italic>A Nowhere for Vallejo,<italic>Inuit [Eskimo] observations in</italic>Alashka,<italic>etc.). He founded, in the 1960s, the Cape Coliard poetry series and the influential Cape Editions, a series of small books which forged significant links between poetics and contemporary social theory. Principal works:</italic>Beautiful Contradictions, A Nowhere for Vallejo, Lyrics for the Bride of God, Alashka<italic>(with Janet Rodney)</italic>, Rabinal Achi (Act IV).<italic>Among recent writings on ethnopoetics is ʺThe Heraldic Vision:</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.66</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Man Made of Words</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOMADAY</surname>
                           <given-names>N. SCOTT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>414</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Author of the Pulitzer Prize novel</italic>, House Made of Dawn,<italic>N. Scott Momaday is the most prominent of the American Indian novelists and is a poet in the tradition of his teacher, Yvor Winters. His personal and familial works—drawing from his Kiowa Indian background and from the sense of a poetics offered in the present piece—include</italic>The Way to Rainy Mountain<italic>and</italic>The Names.</p>
                     <p>When I was a child, my father told me the story of the arrowmaker; and he told it to me many times, for I fell in love with it. I have no memory that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.67</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Neo-HooDoo Manifesto/The Neo-HooDoo Aesthetic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>REED</surname>
                           <given-names>ISHMAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Ishmael Reed has long been a prolific and active poet and novelist, whose language and concerns reflect the particular and universal poles of a genuine ethnopoetics. As editor of the influential magazine</italic>, YʹBird,<italic>and as a founder (with Bob Callahan, Frank Chin, Victor Hernandez Cruz, David Meltzer, and Simon Ortiz) of the San Francisco-based Before Columbus Foundation, he writes: ʺWe welcome a time in history when ʹAmericanʹ is no longer interchangeable with rudeness, grossness and provincialism, but has begun to stand for a society where all of the cultures of the world may co-exist and in which cultural exchange is</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.68</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Expressive Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARAKA</surname>
                           <given-names>IMAMU AMIRI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>422</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>By the mid-1960s, Baraka had become one of the major figures (poetry, fiction, theater) of the ʺnew American poetry.ʺ His contribution to an ethnopoetics was the articulation (both in theory and practice) of black cultural and linguistic values within a highly charged social/political context in which he participated notably from a home base in Newark, New jersey. Changing over the years, his cultural writings are marked by early warnings of ʺcultural imperialism,ʺ etc. (see above, pp. 12, 340) and by a recent return to a universalism along Marxist-Leninist lines but drawing from the black instance still central to his poetry.</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.69</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From “The Incredible Survival of Coyote”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SNYDER</surname>
                           <given-names>GARY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Gary Snyderʹs researches, which form a part of his own work, go back to the early 1950s and a thesis</italic>, He Who Hunted Birds in His Fatherʹs Village: The Dimensions of a Haida Myth,<italic>only recently published as a book. A key contributor to the ethnopoetic discourse (see above, p. 90), his principal works include</italic>Myths and Texts, Regarding Wave,<italic>and</italic>Turtle Island<italic>(poetry);</italic>Earth House Hold<italic>and</italic>The Old Ways<italic>(essays); and</italic>The Real Work<italic>(talks and interviews)</italic>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Coyote figure discussed herein is, of course, only one instance of the widely diffused Trickster—for which, see above, page</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.70</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coyote Poems</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ORTIZ</surname>
                           <given-names>SIMON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CLOUD</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER BLUE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MacADAMS</surname>
                           <given-names>LEWIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The emergence of Coyote as trickster-saint of the ʺnew American poetryʺ—a primary event of ethnopoesis—is documented and discussed in the preceding piece by Cary Snyder. Three examples follow: from Acoma poet Simon Ortiz (see above, p. 399), who came at it from childhood, and from Mohawk poet Peter Blue Cloud and Texas-born poet Lewis MacAdams, who came at it in wanderings through the U.S.A. and through related adventures in poetry, etc. (But see also Diane di Primaʹs intuition of a female Loba (wolf) figure [below, p. 441], which is certainly related to the rest; or, at a still</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.71</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Birth of Loba</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DI PRIMA</surname>
                           <given-names>DIANE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The work of Diane di Prima—poetry, theater, autobiography—relates not only to European but to non-Western folklore and mythology: her anthology</italic>, Various Fables from Various Places;<italic>her projected worldwide gathering on ʺthe goddessʺ; her early staging of new ritual performances; and her long-running auto-mythological poem</italic>, Loba,<italic>to which the present lecture excerpt refers. The selection given here can be read in relation to the two preceding sections on Coyote, or to the Ainu version of the wolf goddess (see above, p. 156), or to the various discussions herein on the suppression and reemergence of the goddess figure (p. 36</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.72</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The hinges of civilization to be put back on the door</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLSON</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>444</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Charles Olson was one of the major figures between Ezra Pound and the present in opening up American poetry to a range of ancient and contemporary/Western and non-Western cultures. (See above, p. 62.) His principal ʺethnopoeticʺ works, as such, are</italic>The Mayan Letters, Causal Mythology, The Special View of History,<italic>and the various lectures and writings assembled posthumously in</italic>Muthologos—<italic>but the same impulse is present throughout his cumulative masterwork</italic>, The Maximus Poems.</p>
                     <p>otherwise the present will lose what America is the inheritor of: a secularization which not only loses nothing of the divine but by seeing process in reality</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.73</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Preface to Hades in Manganese</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ESHLEMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAYTON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>446</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>From 1967—1973, Clayton Eshleman was the editor of</italic>Caterpillar,<italic>a seminal magazine of the new poetry in which some of the early ethnopoetic discourse first appeared. His own work draws from travels to Peru (ʺOn Mule Back to Chavinʺ) and Japan (</italic>The House of Okomura, etc.<italic>)—an interplay in mind and at first hand with those and other cultures—and from extensive translations of such poets as Vallejo, Neruda, Artaud, and Césaire. The vision of the ʺpaleolithic imaginationʺ and what he calls ʺthe construction of the underworldʺ marks his distinctive contribution to an expanded ethnopoetics—pursued over the last</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.74</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Talking to Discover</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ANTIN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>450</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>As an early participant in the ethnopoetic discussion, David Antin has explored a radically ʺnewʺ source for poetry in speech and discourse. This has involved, as here, a tension with the idea of poetryʹs origins in song, and an intensification, touched on in the pieces that follow and elsewhere in this book, of the old dichotomy between the oral and the written. Antinʹs own poetry over the last decade has taken a form sometimes indistinguishable from ʺtalkingʺ per se, culminating in an ongoing series of written and elaborated poem-transcriptions. (See below, p. 469.) His principal works in this genre are</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.75</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From “DiaLogos: Between the Written and the Oral in Contemporary Poetry”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>QUASHA</surname>
                           <given-names>GEORGE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>461</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>George Quashaʹs wide-ranging magazine</italic>, Stony Brook,<italic>provided a first forum, 1968–1969, to renew the discourse about ethnopoetics as such. (The term itself was first used here—by Jerome Rothenberg, who also acted as ʺethnopoetics editor.ʺ) Quasha has also been co-editor of</italic>America a Prophecy<italic>(Quasha and Rothenberg 1973), editor of two anthologies of contemporary work</italic>, Open Poetry<italic>and</italic>Active Anthology,<italic>and author of the ongoing long poem</italic>, Somapoetics.<italic>His contribution to the issues of voicing/writing as mapped in this anthology has been to expand the idea of a poetics in a variety of ways (metapoetics, parapoetics, somapoetics, etc.) and</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.76</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Writing in the Imagination of an Oral Poet</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MUNN</surname>
                           <given-names>HENRY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>474</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The following essay by Henry Munn presents a necessary complication of the ʺoralityʺ issue in ethnopoetics (see above</italic>, passim)—<italic>the location of a concept of ʺbookʺ and ʺwritingʺ at center of the genuine ethnopoetics of a major oral poet (see above, p. 187). The interested reader can relate it to the proposal of an archécriture (or primal writing)—the idea of writing itself as, in David Antinʹs term, a ʺnatural genreʺ co-equal with speech, etc.—presented in the workings of such a contemporary philosopher as Jacques Derrida (see above, p. 139). Henry Munn is the author of an important introduction</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.77</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Death of Sedna</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CARPENTER</surname>
                           <given-names>EDMUND</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Edmund Carpenterʹs field studies and media experiments range from the Canadian Arctic and Siberia to Southeast Asia, Borneo, and New Guinea. His early collaboration with Marshall McLuhan gave the latter his principal link to areas of anthropological concern. A significant part of Carpenterʹs own work involves the impact of the new technology and its resultant monoculture on the worldʹs surviving software cultures. Principal works:</italic>Eskimo Realities, They Became What They Beheld, Explorations in Communication<italic>(ed., with Marhsall McLuhan), and</italic>Oh, What a Blow that Phantom Gave Me!</p>
                     <p>In cigar stores, art galleries &amp; museum shops across Canada, Eskimo stone art is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.78</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>485</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzkq4.79</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
