<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8bk4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN649.M65E54 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Fieldwork</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Morocco</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropologists</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Morocco</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Morocco</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Intercultural communication</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Morocco</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Encountering Morocco</book-title>
         <subtitle>Fieldwork and Cultural Understanding</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CRAWFORD</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>NEWCOMB</surname>
               <given-names>RACHEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>Afterword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dwyer</surname>
               <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253009043</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253009197</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253009197</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gh8g5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Encountering Morocco introduces readers to life in this North African country through vivid accounts of fieldwork as personal experience and intellectual journey. We meet the contributors at diverse stages of their careers-from the unmarried researcher arriving for her first stint in the field to the seasoned fieldworker returning with spouse and children. They offer frank descriptions of what it means to take up residence in a place where one is regarded as an outsider, learn the language and local customs, and struggle to develop rapport. Moving reflections on friendship, kinship, and belief within the cross-cultural encounter reveal why study of Moroccan society has played such a seminal role in the development of cultural anthropology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CRAWFORD</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NEWCOMB</surname>
                           <given-names>RACHEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book introduces readers to Morocco by showing how anthropologists have come to understand it. Each essay takes us into a specific part of the country through the unique voice of the writer. Each delivers a very local story, a vignette of how a particular individual has done fieldwork in a specific context. And each stands as a personal meditation on cross-cultural understanding, the way that one person came to appreciate an alien social world. Together the chapters build a richly textured portrait of the Kingdom of Morocco-a key site in the development of the discipline of anthropology.</p>
                     <p>As the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Arabic or French?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Politics of Parole at a Psychiatric Hospital in Morocco</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VAN DEN HOUT</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLOTTE E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is Thursday morning, and the patients and doctors of the open women’s ward at a Moroccan psychiatric hospital are gathering in the lounge for the weekly<italic>ijtimʿ</italic>, an hour or so of sharing stories, experiences, and impressions of life at the hospital. As the women take their seats on the couches—made in a traditional design, but with a modern twist—the hum of excited whispers hangs in the air. There’s been conflict in the corridors this week, and the patients are expecting the issue to come to a head at today’s meeting.</p>
                     <p>This morning I sit next to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Time, Children, and Getting Ethnography Done in Southern Morocco</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RIGNALL</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When ethnographies assume polished form, the process of selecting a field site usually appears to have been a serendipitous alignment of intellectual commitments and affective attachments. The “arrival narrative” begins to take shape in those first days at the field site. As the narrative becomes fixed in the published ethnography, the anthropologist’s cultural connection—that commitment to people and place—becomes naturalized. In retrospect, the relationship can appear inevitable, even foreordained. My choice of field sites had more to do with day care than serendipity.</p>
                     <p>Perhaps I can admit my pragmatic concerns because my affective attachments had already been established.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Thinking about Class and Status in Morocco</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McMURRAY</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A barber worked directly across the street from the front door of our apartment in the late 1980s in Nador, a gritty boomtown in the Berber north that was exploding with the repatriated wealth of emigrants away in Europe as well as the revenues from goods smuggled in from Spain and hash smuggled out of Morocco.¹ The barber’s shop was decorated with posters of stylish men, all of them models advertising various hair care products. He had hired another barber—a poorer man, judging by his attire—to help out during busy times, such as early evening hours and Fridays.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Forgive Me, Friend:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mohammed and Ibrahim</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SPADOLA</surname>
                           <given-names>EMILIO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Morocco I tend—like many American anthropologists—to seek rapport with a smile. Retailers in Fes refer to American tourists by the code word<italic>miska</italic>—chewing gum—meaning they are all teeth and lips. (British tourists, in contrast, are<italic>ad-dam al-barid</italic>, which means cold blood.) Yet a Moroccan acquaintance of mine characterized Americans as tragically sad friends. The United States is so enormous, he said, and everyone so mobile, that “you Americans are always ready to drop a friend.” He’s right, in my experience. The friendly first steps of rapport are, if not the opposite of friendship, a firm</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Suspicion, Secrecy, and Uncomfortable Negotiations over Knowledge Production in Southwestern Morocco</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOFFMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>KATHERINE E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Power relations inherent in the encounter between anthropologist and informant engaged the advocates of reflexive anthropology working in Morocco (Crapanzano 1980; K. Dwyer 1982; Rabinow 2007 [1977]). Their analyses have reconfigured the practice and writing of ethnography over the last three decades. Questions of truth, disclosure, and suspicion shape not only anthropologists’ relationships in the field, but also the data that can be collected and the forms in which it can be presented to outsiders. Irfan Ahmad remarks in regard to ethnographic informants’ frequent suspicion of the state that perhaps we should “also talk—after Geertz’s ‘theatre state,’ Dirks’s ‘ethnographic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Activist and the Anthropologist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SILVERSTEIN</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his afterword to Paul Rabinow’s<italic>Reflections on Fieldwork in Morocco</italic>(2007 [1977], 166–67), Pierre Bourdieu cites Jean Piaget’s famous dictum, “it is not so much that children don’t know how to talk: they try out many languages until they find one their parents can understand,” and concludes, “Ethnology will have taken a giant step forward when all ethnologists understand that something similar is taking place between informants and themselves.” This is a striking yet curious statement. Curious because it portrays anthropology as an improvable, developmental discipline, in spite of Bourdieu’s critique several pages earlier of the “positivist conception</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>A Distant Episode:</title>
                     <subtitle>Religion and Belief in Moroccan Ethnography</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NEWCOMB</surname>
                           <given-names>RACHEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was a bright June day in Fes, with perfect blue skies, just before the heat of summer would lie on the Ville Nouvelle¹ like an unquiet conscience. Today my Moroccan mother-in-law, Jamila, had been promising to take me to the tomb of Sidi Bou Ghalib in the medina. For weeks I had been interviewing medical doctors, herbalists, midwives, and women about reproduction, but this would be my first visit to the tomb of a saint known for his<italic>baraka</italic>(the spiritual power a dead person once possessed) and his abilities to heal those who could not have children. My</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Shortcomings of a Reflexive Tool Kit; or, Memoir of an Undutiful Daughter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARGACH</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMILA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bougainvilleas of multiple colors—burgundy, yellow, rose, and white—draped the walls of what seemed to be a timeless corner villa and separated it from the small streets paved with a puzzle, hard bricks that made a funny buzzing sound when cars drove on them. Past imposing metal doors, a tiny cemented walkway led up the stairs to the inside of this art-deco villa where there was practically no garden, except for the branches of the bougainvilleas shooting outside. This was the main headquarters of the nongovernmental organization (NGO) Solidarité Féminine, SolFem for short. The villa had been built around</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Reflecting on Moroccan Encounters:</title>
                     <subtitle>Meditations on Home, Genre, and the Performance of Everyday Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAPCHAN</surname>
                           <given-names>DEBORAH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I encountered Morocco when I was twenty-four years old. It was, in a sense, an accidental or at least a serendipitous encounter—but then again, it may have been fate. Before leaving New York in 1981, I was in music school studying flute performance. I was working on my second BA, begun after my graduation from the English Department at New York University (with a minor in French literature), and although I was feeling too old to be a freshman for a second time, I didn’t know what else to do. My only directive was a tired but workable cliché:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Power of Babies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CRAWFORD</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Children are of obvious importance to farmers in the High Atlas Mountains of Morocco, as the main source of farm labor and as a preeminent cultural value. Villagers expect to have children, pity those who do not, ask about having them, pray to have them, and consider any equivocation about the desirability of parenthood to be a weird misunderstanding or a form of mental illness. For most of my time in Morocco, I was a researcher without children, so I existed in kind of bizarre, liminal state. I had the material resources and apparent capabilities of a man, but I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anthropologists among Moroccans</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DWYER</surname>
                           <given-names>KEVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essays in this volume address topics that, for a long time, were present only at the margins of academic anthropological discourse, if they appeared at all. Issues like the anthropologist’s “identity”—the implications of the anthropologist’s origins and how anthropologists construct themselves in the field; the attractions and perils of friendship; the impact of the anthropologist’s family on fieldwork; suspicion of and hostility toward the anthropologist and competition between the anthropologist and others in the field; the tensions among the many aspects of an anthropologist’s humanity, and between the roles of researcher and judge, between “scientific” observation and judgmental</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gh8g5.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
