<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>In the Archive of Longing</book-title>
         <subtitle>Susan Sontag's Critical Modernism</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mitrano</surname>
               <given-names>Mena</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474414340</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474414357</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1474414354</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Mena Mitrano</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1bh2kv9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This adventurous critical inquiry into Sontag's archive illuminates the intimate link between modernism and theory while also providing a fascinating reintroduction to these two movements and concepts.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Archival Relation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Interest in Susan Sontag has grown in recent years. As I complete this book, two new books on her have just come out: the first, an intimate portrait, the second, a biography translated from the German.¹ Not surprisingly, her life draws attention. It is a fascinating example of the formation of the public intellectual in modernity. With the publication of two volumes of her journals we have been given access to an extraordinary document of that formation.² The conflicting desires for knowledge and experience, which for Sontag the woman translated into a constant oscillation between the mind and the body,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Thoughts about Thinking:</title>
                     <subtitle>Approaching Sontag</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Susan Sontag’s critical production shows a preference for unfinished form, for notes and fragments (‘Notes on Camp’, ‘Fragments of an Aesthetic of Melancholy’) or for the cumulative sequence of meditations on or regarding a topic (<italic>On Photography</italic>,<italic>Regarding the Pain of Others</italic>). What has become known as her ‘epigrammatical mode’ (Sayres, ‘Susan Sontag’ 595) combines with a tendency to protect the object of inquiry rather than explicate. The combination of unfinished form and opacity has fascinated her readers.</p>
                     <p>For her most perceptive readers, silence is a key term in Sontag’s critical canon. Cary Nelson first noticed the ‘deep, sweet silence’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Aesthetic Experience and Critical Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The new role for the critic beyond solitary exegesis implies a transition from criticism to the notion of critical theory: ‘The great task which remains to critical theory is to examine in detail the formal function of subject-matter’ (‘On Style’ 20). As we have seen, one of the reasons why Sontag took her stand ‘against interpretation’ was its standard treatment of the works of art as ‘statements’ (21). Against this long-established trend, she contends: ‘A work of art encountered as a work of art is an experience, not a statement or an answer to a question. Art is not only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>The Public Intellectual</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sontag’s rise as a public intellectual in the 1960s is so legendary that anyone writing about her is compelled to revisit the story. This chapter will consider the consequences of the loss of philosophy, discussed in the previous chapter, on Sontag’s performance of the public intellectual. Philosophy’s metamorphosis into an incomplete critical discourse that resists the ‘spectral and mortuary cosmos’ of total reproduction¹ both enhanced and questioned her public image. Progressively, she realised that the public intellectual is pinned to a scene of utterance that produces assenting crowds, and therefore is thrown into question. The second part of this chapter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Modernism and Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last section of Chapter 3 I suggested that Sontag and modernism are two interconnected intellectual objects. From the perspective of her visual persona, melancholia transfigures Sontag into a beautiful modernist ruin. This chapter explores the connection from the vantage point of the archive. We shall see how, in the archive, Sontag’s fidelity to modernism becomes, in fact, her relation to theory, and she re-emerges as a mind among the theorists. The chapter illuminates the understudied role and place of Sontag in the critical movement called ‘theory’.</p>
                     <p>In her early essays Sontag had raised the question of a more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Iconologies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Certain New York School artists played a decisive role in Sontag’s acceptance of the post-philosophic metamorphosis of philosophy into a formally heterogeneous discourse. They helped her embrace the precariousness of a cultural expanse, symbolised by the city environment, where the philosopher is one with the archetype of the solitary artist lost in the crowd, where thinking and writing are experienced as a pressure coming from the outside: ‘I write what I can: that is, what’s given to me and what seems worth writing, by me’ (‘Singleness’ 259)</p>
                     <p>Paul Thek (1933–88) was the first decisive influence in this transition. Sontag</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Aura, Dread and the Amateur</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sontag’s progression towards Benjamin is strange, fascinating. More than finding him, she finds herself. Encountering Benjamin translated into a clear sense of belonging to a theoretical tradition; above all, it gave her a more nuanced narrative of the critical act.</p>
                     <p>Sontag had earned her place as a literary critic by emancipating herself from firmly held beliefs in the critical establishment. This, however, took some time. Despite her youthful rebellion, in her first book of essays she was still working with a rather traditional notion of interpretation. She thought that ‘great art induces contemplation’ and that ‘the reader or listener or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Interlocution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sontag became aware of Benjamin’s work in the early 1960s. The first mention of his name occurs in a thin spiral notebook dated on the cover September 1963. Inside, however, the entries show abrupt chronological leaps from 1963 to March 1965; the entries continue to April 1965, then jump back to 1964. Tucked between a cluster of pages dated 1964 and an entry for April 1965 is the first reference to Benjamin. We find his name written next to ideas from<italic>The Antiquiertheit des Menschen</italic>(1957) by philosopher Günther Anders. The fragment expands on ‘the technique of reproduction’, on ‘a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda (to the Gentle Reader)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>UCLA, 26 August 2011. Something happened to my notes on Box 175, the box containing the research materials for<italic>Regarding the Pain of Others</italic>. All the notes have gone. The Leica ads, Fenton and First World War photography materials, the Elizabeth Bishop poem … the anthropological gaze – everything gone. I am trying to reconstruct the notes, but it is not simple. In the attempt to remember, I realise that Sontag’s research relied above all on newspaper and magazine articles, in particular<italic>The New Yorker</italic>and<italic>The New York Times</italic>. But there was also an article in Italian bearing in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kv9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
