<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9dgg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">E415.7.P64 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and government</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1815–1861</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Slavery</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                     <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
                  </subj-group>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Conspiracies</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chase, Salmon P. (Salmon Portland), 1808–1873</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Language</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Language</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Language</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                     <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
                  </subj-group>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English language</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Discourse analysis</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political culture</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Political Style of Conspiracy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Chase, Summer, and Lincoln</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pfau</surname>
               <given-names>Michael William</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780870137600</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781609170868</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Michigan State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>East Lansing</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michael William Pfau</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.14321/j.ctt13x0p8c"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The turbulent history of the United States has provided a fertile ground for conspiracies, both real and imagined. From the American Revolution to the present day, conspiracy discourse-linguistic and symbolic practices and artifacts revolving around themes, claims, or accusations of conspiracy-has been a staple of political rhetoric. Some conspiracy theories never catch on with the public, while others achieve widespread popularity. Whether successful or not, the means by which particular conspiracy theories spread is a rhetorical process, a process in which persuasive language, symbolism, and arguments act upon individual minds within concrete historical and political settings.Conspiracy rhetoric was a driving force in the evolution of antebellum political culture, contributing to the rise and fall of the great parties in the nineteenth century. One conspiracy theory in particular-the "slave power" conspiracy-was instrumental in facilitating the growth of the young Republican Party's membership and ideology.<italic>The Political Style of Conspiracy</italic>analyzes the concept and reality of the "slave power" in the rhetorical discourse of the mid-nineteenth-century, in particular the speeches and writing of politicians Salmon P. Chase, Charles Sumner, and Abraham Lincoln. By examining their mainstream texts, Pfau reveals that, in addition to the "paranoid style" of conspiracy rhetoric that inhabits the margins of political life, Lincoln, Chase, and Sumner also engaged in a distinctive form of conspiracy rhetoric that is often found at the center of mainstream American society and politics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Problems of Interpretation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Approaching Conspiracy in Text and Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Conspiracy, the secret cooperation for the achievement of some base design, has been a frequently recurring topic of political discussions since ancient times. But it has been the turbulent history of the United States that has provided the most fertile ground for conspiracy discourse. From the time of the Revolution to the present day, conspiracy discourse—that is, linguistic and symbolic practices and artifacts revolving around themes, claims, or accusations of conspiracy—has pervaded diverse forums and genres of American political discourse. For many critics and commentators, the ubiquity of conspiracy theories in American history and the increasing appeal of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Slave Power According to Salmon P. Chase:</title>
                     <subtitle>Entering the Mainstream of Partisan Rhetoric, 1845–1854</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rhetorical texts of Salmon P. Chase are an ideal place to begin a consideration of slave power conspiracy discourse in the political mainstream, for Chase has been credited with fundamentally altering the nature of the antislavery movement: ʺThe American anti-slavery movement, which began as a moral crusade, eventually found that it would have to turn to politics to achieve its goals…. No anti-slavery leader was more responsible for the success of this transformation, and none did more to formulate an anti-slavery program in political terms than Salmon P. Chase of Ohio.ʺ Crucial to this transformation was Chaseʹs development of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Charles Sumner’s “Crime Against Kansas”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conspiracy Rhetoric in the Oratorical Mold</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Charles Sumner was a latecomer to politics. While he had established a reputation as a philanthropist and reformer in the 1830s and early 1840s, he was not politically active until the Texas annexation controversy of the mid-1840s. As is evident by his July 4, 1845, oration, ʺThe True Grandeur of Nations,ʺ Sumnerʹs sudden entrance into politics was inspired largely by his pacifism and his belief that the measure to annex Texas was the work of the slave power and designed to expand slavery westward. At the time, Massachusetts Whigs in Congress were themselves engaged in a vigorous opposition to annexation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Lincoln, Conspiracy Rhetoric, and the “House Divided”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Assessing the Judgment of History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any study purporting to examine slave power conspiracy rhetoric in the political mainstream must consider the case of Abraham Lincoln. Salmon Chase and Charles Sumner were important national and local Republican leaders in their own right, but even they were deemed too radical to be serious presidential candidates in 1860. In contrast to comparative radicals like Seward, Chase, and Sumner, by 1860 Lincoln appeared to be a quite moderate candidate who was likely to appeal to the broadest spectrum of voters. Lincoln, in sum, was the ʺembodiment of availability.ʺ¹ As such, Lincolnʹs conspiracy texts are worthy of serious attention in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Lessons of the Slave Power Conspiracy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conspiracy Rhetoric at the Center and Fringe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is unfortunate that at a juncture in history when conspiracy theories of various sorts increasingly populate the diverse locales of public spheres around the world, the study of conspiracy discourse continues to be hobbled, rather than enabled, by the legacy of the paranoid style. Too many scholars studying conspiracy still conceive of conspiracy discourse as uniformly deranged and dangerous. While a number of scholars have attempted to move beyond the oversimplifications and pejorative assumptions of the paranoid style in their engagements with mainstream conspiracy texts, few have brought to the issue Hofstadterʹs critical sensitivity and concern with discursive form.¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0p8c.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
