<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Border Crossing</book-title>
         <subtitle>Russian Literature into Film</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Burry</surname>
               <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>White</surname>
               <given-names>Frederick H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474411424</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474411431</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1474411436</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Alexander Burry</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Frederick H. White</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1bh2kpq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Applying the metaphor of the 'border crossing' from one temporal or spatial territory into another,<italic>Border Crossing: Russian Literature into Film</italic>examines the way classic Russian texts have been altered to suit new cinematic environments.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Filming Russian Classics—Challenges and Opportunities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burry</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Russian literature has occupied a special position as an object of cinematic adaptation in the hundred-year-plus history of film. The invention and development of the medium closely followed a period of robust literary and cultural achievements rare for any nation. Early in the 1800s, Aleksandr Pushkin, Nikolai Gogol, and Mikhail Lermontov launched the so-called Golden Age of poetry and prose. In the latter part of the century, Ivan Turgenev, Fedor Dostoevskii, and Lev Tolstoi established the international dominance of the Russian novel through compulsively readable narratives that featured bold generic experimentation and a nearly obsessive focus on what the critic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Across the Russian Border</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leitch</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Adaptation, the process by which texts are transformed to suit them to new media (novels made into films) or historical periods (updated theatrical versions of<italic>The Seagull</italic>) or languages (translations from Russian to English or English to Russian), is essentially a metaphorical concept that is defined and understood, though often without acknowledgment, with reference to the biological processes whereby organisms and species survive by adapting to new environments. The metaphorical valence of the term has only been intensified by the range of synonyms commentators have offered to help understand it. Robert Stam has suggested that we can think about “adaptation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Dostoevskii’s “White Nights”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Dreamer Goes Abroad</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Ronald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fedor Dostoevskii’s short story “White Nights” (1848), subtitled a “sentimental love story (from the notes of a dreamer),” has been adapted for the screen more than any other of his short works. A staggering twelve feature films have been mounted on the basis of this early short story, though only two Russian entries and Luchino Visconti’s<italic>Le notti bianche</italic>(1957) carry Dostoevskii’s title.² Perhaps even more surprising than the sheer number of adaptations, half of which were released in the twenty-first century, is the language distribution: Russian and Hindi tie for the most with three each, followed by two in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>On Not Showing Dostoevskii’s Work:</title>
                     <subtitle>Robert Bresson’s Pickpocket</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hasty</surname>
                           <given-names>Olga Peters</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How does French filmmaker Robert Bresson, who minimizes affect and expressivity on the screen and rejects psychological realism in filmmaking, connect with the Russian novelist Fedor Dostoevskii, a master of psychology whose works burst with emotional turmoil and scandal? The question is an important one because underlying these obvious stylistic differences are ideational ties with Dostoevskii that are vital to Bresson’s films. Allen Thiher observes that “[i]n nearly all his works, […] Bresson’s narrative turns in one way or another on isolation and humiliation, on estrangement and the impossibility of a desired community.”² It is precisely these quintessentially Dostoevskian concerns,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Stealing the Scene:</title>
                     <subtitle>Crime as Confession in Robert Bresson’s Pickpocket</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Orr</surname>
                           <given-names>S. Ceilidh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Robert Bresson’s 1959 film<italic>Pickpocket</italic>, ostensibly based on<italic>Crime and Punishment</italic>, begins with the declaration, “This is not a detective story.”¹ And it is not. The titular thief, Michel (Martin LaSalle), confesses in the opening scene, so that viewers learn “whodunnit” before ever witnessing a crime. The only mystery left is motive: What drives Michel to steal, and to pick pockets, in particular? And how does it become so compulsive that he will drop everything, even romance, when a stranger with a handsome watch walks by? Studies of Bresson and<italic>Pickpocket</italic>are full of references to the inscrutability of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>The Eye-deology of Trauma:</title>
                     <subtitle>Killing Anna Karenina Softly</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leving</surname>
                           <given-names>Yuri</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How did it happen that world directors turned out to be so susceptible to<italic>Anna Karenina</italic>? First of all, from the standpoint of early Russian producers, this particular novel by Lev Tolstoi was a perfect candidate for a film adaptation because it enjoyed the status of a bestseller immediately upon its publication—it was even more successful than<italic>War and Peace</italic>.¹ Popularizing literary classics was done in Russia in conjunction with the very democratic spirit of cinema—“its popular appeal, its educational and cultural orientation”—the features that were emphasized by early Russian producers and later by film historians.² Turning</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>“A Vicious Circle”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Karen Shakhnazarov’s Ward no. 6</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burry</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anton Chekhov’s “Ward no. 6” (1892) has inspired a large and varied body of hypertexts in the twentieth and twenty-first centuries. The story’s basic premise of a psychiatric doctor who is incarcerated in the same mental hospital he used to run proved extraordinarily generative for Russian writers in the following century, especially given the notorious Soviet practice of labeling political dissidents insane. Valerii Tarsis and Venedikt Erofeev, among others, reflect this aspect of the story in their works.¹ Other major themes of “Ward no. 6,” such as the unstable boundary between madness and sanity, psychological isolation from other people, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>A Slap in the Face of American Taste:</title>
                     <subtitle>Transporting He Who Gets Slapped to American Audiences</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>White</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederick H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1915, the author and playwright Leonid Andreev debuted his play<italic>He Who Gets Slapped</italic>at the Moscow Art Theater. In the following years, this dramatic work about a vanquished intellectual-turned-circus-clown, more than any of his twenty other plays, achieved spectacular success among American audiences, first as a play in English translation, then when adapted for the silver screen, then as a novel and, finally, as an opera. Andreev had argued in his “Letters on the Theater” that cinema would become the place for action and spectacle, diminishing the popularity of the realist theater. Not surprisingly then, a love affair,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Against Adaptation?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Strange Case of (Pod) Poruchik Kizhe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Renfrew</surname>
                           <given-names>Alastair</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rise of the so-called “formal method” in the immediate post-revolutionary years has been associated almost exclusively with questions of literary specificity, and with the search for a methodology that would not only exceed various forms of intentionalism and/or determinism, but would also destroy the pretensions of a general aesthetics to account for the presumably transgredient “essence” of art.³ As a consequence, the logical corollary of any claims for the specificity of the literary, namely that this implies also the formal specificity of the other modes of art from which literature is differentiated, has been just as consistently neglected: What</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Chasing the Wealth:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Americanization of Il’f and Petrov’s The Twelve Chairs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mulcahy</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout his film career, US comedian, director, and producer Mel Brooks has engaged an amazingly varied assortment of cinematic genres in an irreverent vein:<italic>The Producers</italic>(1968) is a musical comedy about Adolf Hitler;<italic>Blazing Saddles</italic>(1974) satirizes the Western;<italic>Young Frankenstein</italic>(1974) spoofs the horror genre;<italic>Silent Movie</italic>(1976) takes on the silent film genre, especially its slapstick comedy; and<italic>High Anxiety</italic>(1977) parodies Hitchcockian suspense films.¹ Through no-holds-barred parody, as well as gags and slapstick humor, Brooks undermines expectations as he lampoons sundry venerable forms institutionalized in American society of the late 1960s and 1970s.</p>
                     <p>As an outsider</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Fassbinder’s Nabokov—From Text to Action:</title>
                     <subtitle>Repressed Homosexuality, Provocative Jewishness, and Anti-German Sentiment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ioffe</surname>
                           <given-names>Dennis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rainer Werner Fassbinder’s film<italic>Despair</italic>was shot in 1977 and was proudly premiered at the Cannes International Film Festival in 1978.¹ The film is based on one of Vladimir Nabokov’s major Russian novels,<italic>Despair</italic>.² The eminent British playwright Tom Stoppard prepared the screenplay for Fassbinder, carefully adapting Nabokov’s text for cinematic staging. The hypotext<italic>Despair</italic>was originally published in 1934 in<italic>Contemporary Letters</italic>, a major Russian–Parisian literary journal of the pre-war emigration, and further issued as a separate book in Berlin (by Petropolis) in 1936. The original storyline was set in Berlin at the beginning of the 1930s.</p>
                     <p>Fassbinder’s<italic>Despair</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>“The Soviet Abroad (That We Lost)”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fate of Vasilii Aksenov’s Cult Novel A Starry Ticket on Paper and on Screen</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boele</surname>
                           <given-names>Otto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One piece of information with which we like to startle our students when teaching film and adaptation theory is that at least half of all films produced worldwide can trace their origin to some literary text. Statistically, one out of two movies we watch is not a “film,” but a “book-to-film adaptation.”¹ Usually, we like to add another piece of information that is equally revealing, namely that quite often successful and popular films are based on mediocre and forgotten novels. How many people are aware of the fact that it was a short story by Daphne du Maurier (1952) that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Passport Control—Departing on a Cinematic Journey</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>White</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederick H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Russian literature has inspired film directors at home and abroad for over a century, and continues to do so today. American, British, French, German, and Italian cinema all have important film classics that were drawn directly from Russian literature. Some, such as French filmmaker Robert Bresson or Japanese filmmaker Akira Kurosawa, turned to Russian writers more than once in creating their own distinctive cinematic style. Kurosawa reimagined Fedor Dostoevskii’s<italic>The Idiot</italic>(<italic>Hakuchi</italic>, 1951); Maksim Gor’kii’s<italic>Lower Depths</italic>(<italic>Donzoko</italic>, 1957); incorporated elements of Dostoevskii’s<italic>The Insulted and Injured</italic>in his film<italic>Akahige</italic>(1965); and animated Vladimir Arsen’ev’s autobiographical work<italic>Dersu Uzala</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Filmography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2kpq.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
