<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR878.I3W4 1984</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Identity (Psychology) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mind and body in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Semantics of Desire</book-title>
         <subtitle>Changing Models of Identity from Dickens to Joyce</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Weinstein</surname>
               <given-names>Philip M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400857395</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400857392</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1984</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zvwf7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This work examines the dialectic of desire and value, as it affects the protagonist's identity, in fiction from Dickens and George Eliot through Hardy and Conrad to Lawrence and Joyce. Philip Weinstein describes the growing sexualization of the imagined body--the transformation of the protagonistic self from a figure defined by semantics, signification, and cultural value to one characterized by desire, force, and natural impulse.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1984.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="326"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on Bibliographical Procedures and Primary Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study explores the changing relation between desire and value, as they affect the protagonists’ identity, in English novels between 1850 and 1928. I examine the imaginative predilections of two mid-Victorians, two late-Victorians, and two Modernists. Each chapter seeks to identify the novelist’s characteristic stance toward desire by interrogating in detail a pair of is novels.¹ The study moves from narratives of repression and disguise in Dickens and Eliot to narratives of release and celebration in Lawrence and Joyce.</p>
                     <p>Seen synoptically, my book inquires into the novelistic imagination of freedom. It does so by examining a range of protagonists’ capacities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART ONE Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The chapters on Dickens and Eliot move, in their respective ways, laterally and downward. They seek to convey the imaginative geography of each writer’s world—its norms of characterization, plot sequence, and setting—as well as to identify within each world, beneath the surface, a cluster of latent confusions. I attend to Dickens and Eliot in the measure that their work reveals an internal resistance to its own premises. Indeed, one formulation of Dickens’ more capacious achievement is that his work manages (as Eliot’s does not) to assimilate—by out-maneuvering, by disguising, by blinking—its own fissures.</p>
                     <p>To be more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>One</label>
                     <title>The Nocturnal Dickens</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As often, he was suffering from insomnia. Restless, certain that sleep would not come before morning—if at all—he dressed quickly, pocketed his notebook and pencil, and headed toward the river. Perhaps he would come across the inspector, and together they could survey the sinister traffic on the water that night. He was making his way briskly along the empty streets when, to his surprise, he came upon a young prostitute standing in the middle of the road about fifty yards away, alone and energetically swearing. Curious, he listened to the unbroken stream of oaths, and he began to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Two</label>
                     <title>George Eliot and the Idolatries of the Superego</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The foregoing chapter has sought to address two of Dickens’ novels on their own terms, and this has occasioned two somewhat differing analyses. The<italic>David Copperfield</italic>commentary centers on the phenomenon of misnaming: the movement, beneath the univocal rubric of the earnest whole self, of discrepant and disowned psychic energies. Four of the novel’s major relationships reveal the implicating play of desire (or the traces of desire repressed) even as they clamor to be seen in terms of altruistic discipline.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Little Dorrit</italic>, by contrast, is abreast of its own transactions; yet these remain sharply conflicted. This novel is Dickens’ most</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Three</label>
                     <title>Hardy:</title>
                     <subtitle>“Full-Hearted Evensong”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The simplest way to orient my commentary on<italic>Tess of the d’Urbervilles</italic>is to juxtapose it against Lionel Johnson’s well-known stricture (at the conclusion of his study of Hardy):</p>
                     <p>. . . the world was very strong; her conscience was blinded and bewildered; she did some things nobly, and some despairingly: but there is nothing . . . to suggest that she was wholly an irresponsible victim of her own temperament, and of adverse circumstances. . . .Like Maggie Tulliver, Tess might have gone to Thomas à Kempis: one of the very few writers, whom experience does not prove untrue.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Four</label>
                     <title>Conrad:</title>
                     <subtitle>Against Nature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The collapse of human structures, when subjected to unremitting natural forces, troubles Conrad’s imagination more than it does Hardy’s. Despite the bleakness of Hardy’s outlook—his view of life as an inherently unsanctioned process, an empty sequence of happenstances—he retained an enabling attachment (however complicated) to his native Dorset countryside. He absorbed its legends, its history, its customs, its landscape; and these absorptions may account for the modulated tone of even his darkest utterances. He is not surprised, his tone keeps repeating, because what is human history if not the immemorial story of expectation drained dry by time’s passage?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART THREE Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Late-Victorian tragic encounters: the subject stymied or annihilated by the incompatible mix of nature and culture within his own identity. In Hardy and Conrad, “become who you are” is a calamitous and unwanted pronouncement. What these protagonists want is immaculate self-fulfillment, achieved in the idiom of their culture’s prescriptions. Tess would be pure, Jude would be learned, Jim would be a hero, Nostromo would be admired. They are unfree exactly in the measure that their incarnate propensities—the fears and desires that they carry into every activity—are anathema to the models of behavior and achievement they propose for themselves:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Five</label>
                     <title>“Become Who You Are”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Optative World of D. H. Lawrence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“God is the flame-life in all the universe; multifarious, multifarious flames. . . . Whichever flame flames in your manhood, that is you, for the time being” (“The Novel,” 426). Lawrence seeks to center identity on flame-life (he even sees the surrounding world of matter, the sun and the moon, as derived from flame-life),¹ and the goal of the Lawrentian protagonist is as simple as it is elusive: to achieve the mobile flame-life of pure being. In each of his novels, in the course of his life, the struggle to center takes different forms, but it remains recognizably the same:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Six</label>
                     <title>New Heaven, New Earth:</title>
                     <subtitle>Joyce and the Art of Reprojection</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Born into a church, family, and country that devour their own progeny, Joyce spent the first twenty years of his life doing something that others in less inimical circumstances do with less urgency and self-consciousness. He spent those years finding and then defending his identity from his culture’s claims upon it.¹ His culture conspired to make him other, to coerce him into signing its testimonials. He was to be the child of the Catholic Church, the son of an Irish gentleman, the citizen of a ghostly Gaelic community. Each of these identities reinforced the others, and together they proposed for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Stephen Dedalus is right. All thinking is bound by its own laws, but those laws are neither given nor known in advance. I knew when I began, roughly, what I hoped to show, as well as, in each chapter, where I wanted to come out. Yet this book was essentially created twice: once when it first came into being, again when (through several revisions) I sought to find out more fully the bearing of what I had originally written.</p>
                     <p>The central lines of inquiry, as well as the further implications, came into focus only gradually. The issue of desire (repressed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvwf7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
