<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1njjmz</collection-id>
      <volume>83</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Signifying Self</book-title>
         <subtitle>Cervantine Drama as Counter-Perspective Aesthetic</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Henry</surname>
               <given-names>Melanie</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781781880029</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781880456</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Modern Humanities Research Association</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Modern Humanities Research Association</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2jc86q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Signifying Self: Cervantine Drama as Counter-Perspective Aesthetic offers a comprehensive analysis of all eight of Cervantes's Ocho comedias (published 1615), moving beyond conventional anti-Lope approaches to Cervantine dramatic practise in order to identify what, indeed, his theatre promotes. Considered on its own aesthetic terms, but also taking into account ontological and socio-cultural concerns, this study compels a re-assessment of Cervantes's drama and conflates any monolithic interpretations which do not allow for the textual interplay of contradictory and conflicting discourses which inform it. Cervantes's complex and polyvalent representation of freedom underpins such an approach; a concept which is considered to be a leitmotif of Cervantes's work but which has received scant attention with regards to his theatre. Investigation of this topic reveals not only Cervantes's rejection of established theatrical convention, but his preoccupation with the difficult relationship between the individual and the early modern Spanish world. Cervantes's comedias emerge as a counter-perspective to dominant contemporary Spanish ideologies and more orthodox artistic imaginings. Ultimately, The Signifying Self seeks to recuperate the Ocho comedias as a significant part of the Cervantine, and Golden-Age, canon and will be of interest and benefit to those scholars who work on Cervantes and indeed on early modern Spanish theatre in general.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="180"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>Cervantes: Writing Drama On The Margins</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Miguel de Cervantes (1547–1616) has long been considered a ‘literary giant’, an accolade attributed to him on account of his<italic>magnus opus</italic>,<italic>Don Quijote de la Mancha</italic>.¹ First published in 1605 and followed by a second volume in 1615, Cervantes’s creation of<italic>el ingenioso hidalgo</italic>is credited with the birth of the modern novel and has achieved iconic status in Spanish cultural history.² In his lifetime, as today, the novel eclipsed the writer’s broad range of work in verse, prose and drama; to the extent that, in relative terms, critical appraisal of Cervantes’s other literary endeavours has been minimal.³</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Encuentro con Lope en el Camino:</title>
                     <subtitle>La entretenida, El laberinto de amor and La casa de los celos y selvas de Ardenia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Canavaggio has commented that: ‘No se puede hablar de Cervantes sin encontrar a Lope en el camino’, a view substantiated by the fact that critical attention concerning Cervantes’s<italic>Ocho comedias</italic>has prioritised the playwright’s unease with Lope’s highly popular theatre.¹ Canavaggio’s observation, however, is particularly reflective of studies of<italic>La entretenida</italic>,<italic>El laberinto de amor</italic>and<italic>La casa de los celos</italic>. Each of these plays has been identified as a Cervantine reaction to dominant contemporary theatrical practise and all have been subject to analysis vis-à-vis Lope to varying degrees. This is especially true of<italic>El laberinto de amor</italic>and<italic>La</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Staging Libertad in Cervantes’s Comedias de Cautivos</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cervantes’s<italic>comedias de cautivos</italic>have been considered by one critic as ‘el resultado literario de una experiencia vital insoslayable, imposible de olvidar, que había marcado para siempre su biografía y su quehacer literario’.¹ Herein lie the two areas of investigation which have so concerned Cervantistas: the events of Cervantes’s 1575–80 North African imprisonment and the impact that such a traumatic experience has exerted on his literary production. Critical interest has resulted in copious biographies and articles and the general consensus that Cervantes’s experience as captive left an indelible mark on his work. Nonetheless, as George Camamis has noted, there</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Shaping the Self in El rufián dichoso and Pedro de Urdemalas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cervantes’s<italic>El rufián dichoso</italic>and<italic>Pedro de Urdemalas</italic>are<italic>comedias</italic>which ‘sit outside’ easy categorisation.<italic>El rufián</italic>has traditionally been perceived as a<italic>comedia de santos</italic>and<italic>Pedro de Urdemalas</italic>as a pseudo-picaresque play. Nonetheless, as this chapter will elucidate, they have more in common than has been realised. What connects these plays, in particular, is their protean<italic>pícaro</italic>protagonists. Despite the fact that scholarship has conventionally viewed Cervantes and the picaresque as incongruous, something with which I will engage more fully in the analysis which follows, it is in the characterisation of the plays’ protagonists that<italic>El rufián dichoso</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this study I have aimed, via an analysis of freedom, to draw conclusions regarding Cervantes’s<italic>Ocho comedias</italic>as a counter-perspective to contemporary Golden-Age drama. Despite the fact that the dramatist’s writings for the stage clearly flout conventional Lopean parameters, it is not indicative of a theatre which is deficient or inferior. Rather, Cervantes constructs an aesthetic which permits free expression of seditious voices and an alternative stage for those discourses normally quashed by prevailing dramatic monopoly. It is precisely because of the restrictive nature of seventeenth-century Spanish theatre that Cervantes advocates a strategy of authorial liberty. For instance, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jc86q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
