<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hj9w7s</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DA926.M3M3 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Collective memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social conditions</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ireland</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching (Higher)</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Memory Ireland</book-title>
         <subtitle>History and Modernity, Volume 1</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Frawley</surname>
               <given-names>Oona</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780815651505</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0815651503</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Syracuse University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Syracuse, New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Syracuse University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j1w050"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Despite the ease with which scholars have used the term "memory" in recent decades, its definition remains enigmatic. Does cultural memory rely on the memories of individuals, or does it take shape beyond the borders of the individual mind? Cultural memory has garnered particular attention within Irish studies. With its trauma-filled history and sizable global diaspora, Ireland presents an ideal subject for work in this vein. What do stereotypes of Irish memory—as extensive, unforgiving, begrudging, but also blank on particular, usually traumatic, subjects—reveal about the ways in which cultural remembrance works in contemporary Irish culture and in Irish diasporic culture? How do icons of Irishness—from the harp to the cottage, from the Celtic cross to a figure like James Joyce—function in cultural memory? This collection seeks to address these questions as it maps a landscape of cultural memory in Ireland through theoretical, historical, literary, and cultural explorations by top scholars in the field of Irish studies. In a series that will ultimately include four volumes, the sixteen essays in this first volume explore remembrance and forgetting throughout history, from early modern Ireland to contemporary multicultural Ireland. Among the many subjects addressed: Guy Beiner disentangles "collective" from "folk" memory in "Remembering and Forgetting the Irish Rebellion of 1798," and Anne Dolan looks at local memory of the civil war in "Embodying the Memory of War and Civil War." The volume concludes with Alan Titley’s "The Great Forgetting," a compelling argument for viewing modern Irish culture as an artifact of the Europeanization of Ireland and for bringing into focus the urgent need for further, wide-ranging Irishlanguage scholarship.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRAWLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>OONA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The field of “memory studies” has been growing steadily in recent decades, fueled by multidisciplinary interest in the ways in which a variety of social groups remember. Among humanities-based scholars, those with a stake in this area include sociologists, historians, literary critics, art historians, and anthropologists, while outside of the humanities, psychologists, neuroscientists and biologists all have the potential to contribute valuably to the field. The net cast by memory studies is so wide, in fact, that in forums like the journal<italic>Memory Studies</italic>(established in 2008), attention is often paid to describing the useful limits of a field that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Memory and History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MISZTAL</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paradoxically, despite the fact that contemporary society is commonly conceptualized as “terminally ill with amnesia” (Huyssen 1995, 1), memory has established itself as a major discourse; interest in memory in the last thirty years has been unprecedented. This interest accounts for the discovery of ethnic and local roots as well as for the construction of common pasts to bind communities and give meaning to their collective fates. The intensification of a memory discourse can be illustrated by the epidemics of public commemoration, the growing recognition of memory as both a constitutive component of political culture and an important base of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Toward a Theory of Cultural Memory in an Irish Postcolonial Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRAWLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>OONA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While terms like “memory,” “cultural memory,” and their variants frequently occur in the discourses of Irish literature, culture, and history, “memory” has remained largely undefined, addressed laterally. That the field of Irish studies has thus far failed adequately to define memory is hardly surprising, since those who have made memory their lifework experience similar problems. Memory, as the neuroscientist Antonio Damasio points out, is particularly elusive. “We are not conscious,” he writes, “of which memories we store and which memories we do not; of how we store memories; of how we classify and organize them; of how we interrelate memories</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“the memorye of their noble ancestors”</title>
                     <subtitle>Collective Memory in Early Modern Ireland</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>IVIC</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTOPHER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Oxford Companion to Irish Literature</italic>defines “Anglo-Irish Chronicles” as “the body of political writings about Ireland written in English during the Tudor and Stuart periods and primarily concerned with justifications for the expropriation of the country by the English Crown, its administration by Crown agents, and the recalcitrance of the Irish in the face of the supposed benefits of that regime” (Welch 1996, 97). As examples of “Anglo-Irish Chronicles,”<italic>the Oxford Companion</italic>lists a number of texts written in the late sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries, including Edmund Campion’s<italic>Two Bokes of the Histories of Ireland</italic>(c. 1571), Richard</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Harp as a Palimpsest of Cultural Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THUENTE</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY HELEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The harp image encompasses distinct and sometimes conflicting iconographical histories and cultural “memories” that influenced the complex formation of Irish identity. Long recognized as an iconic site of Irish identity, the harp is also a palimpsest of cultural memory. The origins of the harp icon’s meanings extend well beyond Ireland and can be traced to a variety of ancient and modern sources, in fact and in cultural memory. The broad range of historical periods and subjects outside of Irish tradition in Edward Bunting’s extensive commentary on the history of harp music and harp iconography in his three influential collections of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Modes of Memory</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering and Forgetting the Irish Rebellion of 1798</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BEINER</surname>
                           <given-names>GUY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ninety-Eight” is a quintessential Irish<italic>lieu de mémoire</italic>. The Great Rebellion of 1798, which was the bloodiest outburst of violence in late-modern Irish history and inflicted lingering traumas, stands out in the commemorative culture of modern Ireland as a landmark that cast long shadows. Although the leadership of the United Irishmen, the revolutionary secret society behind the Rebellion, were lionized as the iconic founding fathers of Irish republicanism, militant republicans did not have a monopoly on the interpretation of the historical events. Subject to continuous contestations, the memory of the Rebellion was repeatedly revived and evoked. The year 1798, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Women and the Survival of Archaeological Monuments in Nineteenth-Century Ireland</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHEALLAIGH</surname>
                           <given-names>MÁIRÍN NÍ</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1840s, while famine and disease gnawed at the lives of large sections of Ireland’s poor, Irish antiquarians increasingly turned their attention to the study of prehistoric and other archaeological remains. Inspired by the visit of the Danish antiquarian Worsaae and his account of the development of the chronological framework known as the “Three Age System” (Worsaae 1845–7, 312–14), members of learned societies and students of the past visited and described a variety of mounds and megalithic constructions. They may also, consciously or unconsciously, have been mirroring Worsaae’s observation that “It was immediately after great national calamities,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Memory, Modernity, and the Sacred</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SEN</surname>
                           <given-names>MALCOLM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The current proliferation of analyses dealing with memory does not signal a temporary fascination or a provisional critical turn. The sustained interest in multiple aspects of memory, remembrance, and various forms of amnesia is the product of the psychological, sociocultural, and historical denominators that have decidedly transformed our lives in the last two or three decades. The advent and global dissemination of the Internet’s ephemeral forms of knowledge and its technologization of memory as the storage capacity of digital media are themselves causes enough to review the spatial and temporal dimensions of cognition, memory, and being. Despite such a transformative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>“In a Landlord’s Garden”</title>
                     <subtitle>Synge and Parnell</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MATHEWS</surname>
                           <given-names>P. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is curious that the subject of “Synge and Parnell” has received very little critical attention, despite the many compelling reasons for throwing these two giants of Irish culture and politics into relief. Among these one could list the shared experience of being prominently unconventional Anglo-Irish gentlemen at pivotal moments in Irish history; their courting of international controversy over matters of sexual morality; the divisive nature of the legacies of both men; and the Wicklow connection. Of further significance is the fact that both of them loom large in the cultural memory of the Irish Revival as expressed in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Embodying the Memory of War and Civil War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOLAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1925 Timothy Mullane of Annahalla, County Cork, began a brief correspondence with J. P. Gutherie of Kircaldy, Scotland. In July he wrote:</p>
                     <p>Dear Sir,</p>
                     <p>With reference to your letter dated 2nd July re the burial of your son Lieutenant Guthrie [<italic>sic</italic>] and particulars of how he died. Lieutenant Guthrie was the only man of his party who escaped from the scene of the ambush and was uninjured. He seemed to bear a charmed life. He had to retreat through an open country on foot under the full concentrated fire of the opposing party. He got within</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>De Valera’s Historical Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DALY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eamon de Valera is the most important political figure of twentiethcentury Ireland. His political career is unprecedented in terms of a longevity unlikely to be exceeded by any future Irish politician. The only surviving commandant in the Easter Rising of 1916, he was still active in public life as president when Ireland celebrated the Golden Jubilee of the Rising in 1966 and the fiftieth anniversary of the founding of Dáil Éireann in 1969. His personal papers, now held in University College Dublin Archives,¹ testify to an abiding interest in history. His correspondence is peppered with letters from fellow-veterans of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Coming Clean?</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering the Magdalen Laundries</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PINE</surname>
                           <given-names>EMILIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 11 May 1999 the Irish<italic>taoiseach</italic>, Bertie Ahern, convened a press conference at which he delivered a public apology to the children who had been abused while in the care of the state: “On behalf of the State and of all the citizens of the State, the Government wishes to make a sincere and long overdue apology to the victims of childhood abuse for our collective failure to intervene, to detect their pain, to come to their rescue.” Although the family is enshrined in the Irish constitution as “a moral institution possessing inalienable and imprescriptible rights” which the state</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Producing Memory</title>
                     <subtitle>A History of Commemoration and the Abbey Theatre</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAPLES</surname>
                           <given-names>HOLLY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Radical changes to Irish society at the end of the nineteenth and beginning of the twentieth centuries helped shape notions of Irishness in the century to come. The emergence of the Celtic Revival at the end of the nineteenth century encouraged the foundation of numerous community-led societies such as the Gaelic League and the Gaelic Athletics Association, while the early twentieth century witnessed major events of political and social upheaval such as the First World War, the Easter Rising, the founding of the Republic, and the subsequent Irish Civil War. One hundred years on, the Irish Republic has experienced equally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Remembering to Forget</title>
                     <subtitle>Queer Memory and the New Ireland</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CREGAN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mainstream public memory is traditionally understood as an intentional recollection of quantifiable facts of the historical past that then constitute collective identity. Because of its suppressed nature, queer memory is flimsier: while mainstream public memory is solidly supported institutionally by politics and history, queer memory is more symbolic, derived from what is implied by exclusion rather than inclusion. By uncovering previously hidden gay and lesbian experiences, queer historians have initiated a type of cultural rebellion, juxtaposing queer memory with hetero-normative histories. The production of this alternative history has evoked a renewed engagement with memory because more traditional methodological approaches to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>9/11, the War on Terror, and the Irish Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CONCHUBHAIR</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN Ó</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Fourth of July in 2002 was anything but another routine celebration of Independence Day in the United States of America. Nine months earlier on 11 September, Al Qaeda operatives had rammed a passenger jet plane into the north tower of New York’s World Trade Center at 8:45 A.M. and a second airplane into the south tower eighteen minutes later. At 9:40 A.M. a third plane crashed into the Pentagon Building in Washington D.C.; a fourth plane—Flight 93—later crash-landed at Shanksville, Pennsylvania. Killing approximately three thousand people, this attack terrified a country and traumatized a nation. The date</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Multiculturalization and Irish National Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RYAN</surname>
                           <given-names>LORRAINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Irish cultural memory was, until recently, a monolithic entity, constituted of exclusively “Irish” experiences such as the Famine, the war of independence, emigration, and the symbiotic relationship of church and state, while its<italic>lieux de mémoire</italic>consisted of the churches and shrines that dotted the Irish landscape and the ballads that extolled the bravery of heroes such as Sean Treacy and Dan Breen. Despite the fact of significant minority populations in Ireland,¹ this “national” memory centered on white Catholics and was thus a highly biased narrative that implicitly ignored minority experience. However, Ireland’s recent multiculturalism and the iconoclasm of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>The Great Forgetting</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TITLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>ALAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some time in the early 1930s, the great Irish folklorist Séamus Ó Duilearga, or James Delargy, was investigating the spoken Irish of northwest Clare. He was interested in old sayings, or prayers, or words, or whatever he could find. Although Irish was still the language of the older generation, it had not been passed on, and it was effectively dead as a community language. During the course of his enquiries, he was told that there was a man living on his own out the road, and that he was a good Irish speaker. He hoped to collect some items from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1w050.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
