<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6t9j6w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B105.A8 P53 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Authenticity (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Performance</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sincerity</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Theater</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kant, Immanuel, 1724–1804</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kierkegaard, Søren, 1813–1855</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Levinas, Emmanuel</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Rethinking Sincerity and Authenticity</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Ethics of Theatricality in Kant, Kierkegaard, and Levinas</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PICKETT</surname>
               <given-names>HOWARD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813940168</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813940168</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>CHARLOTTESVILLE; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1wvwdtb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"This above all: To thine own self be true," is an ideal-or pretense-belonging as much to Hamlet as to the carefully choreographed realms of today's politics and social media. But what if our "true" selves aren't our "best" selves? Instagram's curated portraits of authenticity often betray the paradox of our performative selves: sincerity obliges us to be who we actually are, yet ethics would have us be better.</p>
         <p>Drawing on the writings of Immanuel Kant, Søren Kierkegaard, and Emmanuel Levinas, Howard Pickett presents a vivid defense of "virtuous hypocrisy." Our fetish for transparency tends to allow us to forget that the self may not be worthy of expression, and may become unethically narcissistic in the act of expression. Alert to this ambivalence, these great thinkers advocate incongruent ways of being.<italic>Rethinking Sincerity and Authenticity</italic>offers an engaging new appraisal not only of the ethics of theatricality but of the theatricality of ethics, contending that pursuit of one's ideal self entails a relational and ironic performance of identity that lies beyond the pure notion of expressive individualism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ethics of Theatricality/The Theatricality of Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“All the world’s a stage, / And all the men and women merely players” is a sentiment that neither debuts nor disappears with Shakespeare.¹ Plato, Seneca, and Saint Paul, among others, adopt the<italic>theatrum mundi</italic>(theater of the world) analogy to highlight resemblances between human existence and theatrical performance.² More recently, dramaturgical sociologists (Erving Goffman) have analyzed social roles and interactions using theatrical metaphors.³ Psychologists and advocates of drama therapy (Jean Piaget) have af-firmed imitation’s formative role in cognitive and moral development.⁴And philosophers (Judith Butler) have emphasized the performative aspects of identity.⁵Clearly, whatever their differences, these examples (modern, premodern, and postmodern) reveal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What Cosby’s joke reveals, if crassly, is that there is a problem with self-congruence.¹ As I come to argue, there are three main problems with making an unqualified virtue of the agreement between what I seem to be and what I actually am. The first, considered in this opening study of Immanuel Kant, is the ”Problem of Imperfection.” Modernity’s esteem for self-congruence—especially, but not exclusively, between inner thought and outer expression—assumes that the inner self is worthy of congruence and the externalization of ”Sincerity” in particular. What we too often forget, however, is that the self may be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>THE TROUBLE WITH LYING:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kant, Character, and Self-Congruence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Immanuel Kant’s preoccupation with self-congruence reveals itself most famously—or infamously, depending on your point of view—in his absolute prohibition against lying. However, as this first chapter demonstrates, Kant mounts a passionate, repeated, and multidimensional endorsement of self-congruence that encompasses more than the conformity between what I think and what I say. Reading through Kant’s practical philosophy—from the early ethics lectures (1762) through<italic>The Metaphysics of Morals</italic>(1797) and beyond—one finds Kant’s repeated affirmation of (1) truthfulness, (2) sincerity, (3) autonomy, and (4) character.¹ To clarify Kant’s views, the following discussion focuses on these specific forms of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>VIRTUOUS HYPOCRISY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Incongruence in Kant’s Quest for Character</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Immanuel Kant’s commitment to the self-congruence of character, with its pervasive impact on his moral thought in particular, may surprise some readers. Much more surprising, however, is his belief that the cultivation of character also requires incongruence. Despite his well-known prohibition against lying and a related distaste for hypocrisy, Kant often recommends something strikingly similar to both. Specifically, he recommends both<italic>dissimulation</italic>(concealing one’s thoughts and feelings) and<italic>simulation</italic>(pretending to be something one is not). Just as surprising—and just as revealing of his ambivalence toward self-congruence—is the subject of this chapter’s latter half: Kant’s occasional recommendation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What Iago’s taunt reveals, if gruesomely, is a second problem with self-congruence and sincerity.¹ Beyond the ”problem of imperfection” lies the ”problem of inexpressibility.” Even if the self were worthy of externalization, externalization is no simple matter. Iago’s villainous example reminds us that appearances (including of sincerity) are often deceptive. In effect, sincerity’s advocates forget the very realization that led them to value that virtue in the first place: people lie. Worse, we cannot tell when people lie.</p>
                     <p>The next two chapters examine the extent to which the self defies congruence, especially the congruence of self-expression. For some (Jean-Paul Sartre),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>INEVITABLE INSINCERITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Inwardness and Outwardness in Kierkegaardian Ethics and Faith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like Immanuel Kant before him, Søren Kier kegaard exhibits modernity’s acute ambivalence toward self-congruence. Kierkegaard’s opposition to incongruence reveals itself in his career-long indictment of hypocrisy. Caught in the crosshairs of much of Kierkegaard’s work are the pretentious ambitions of Hegelian philosophy, whose practitioners claim to know more than they do,¹ and the insincere conformity of the Danish state church, whose members claim to believe more than they do.² Kierkegaard’s works (published and unpublished, pseudonymous and signed, philosophical and religious) exhort the reader to shun incongruence. Instead, they encourage the reader to be true to the actual, existing “single individual,”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>HIDDEN LIVES, IRONIC SELVES:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kierkegaard and the Rise (and Fall) of Authenticity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kierkegaard’s deep-seated ambivalence toward self-congruence and theatricality extends beyond his pseudonymous works, and into his signed religious discourses, written, as the title page to each indicates, by ”S. Kierkegaard.” What’s more, the career-long oscillation between pseudonymous and nonpseudonymous works (published in a more or less alternating pattern from 1843 to 1849) dramatizes the depths of that ambivalence. While pseudonymity—what Kierkegaard elsewhere calls ”polyonymity” (<italic>SV</italic>7:545/<italic>CUP</italic>625)—cautions readers against the assumption of sincerity (i.e., that any particular claim is necessarily Kierkegaard’s own), nonpseudonymity renews questions about sincerity. One rightly wonders if a signed work represents Kierkegaard’s own sincerely held</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What Celan’s line reveals, if paradoxically, is that there is at least one more problem with self-congruence.¹ Specifically, ”Sincerity and the Problem of Individualism” recognizes that the modern obsession with self-congruence may often be less virtue than vice. Despite Polonius’s advice, life (the moral aspect of it, in particular) involves being true not so much to myself as to the others who surround me. An uncompromising commitment to self-congruence, therefore, stands at odds with the moral imperative’s defining commitment to doing for others around me. Self-congruence resembles, instead, self-interest and the narcissism that threatens genuine ethical concern for others.</p>
                     <p>Modernity’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>FEARSOME AUTHENTICITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Levinas and the Rehabilitation of Sincerity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to Lionel Trilling, authenticity ”usurp[ed] [sincerity’s] place in our esteem” somewhere between sincerity’s heyday (the sixteenth or seventeenth century) and today.¹ While sincerity ”had dominion over men’s imagination of how they ought to be” in the early modern period,² late modernity has become, in Charles Taylor’s words, ”The Age of Authenticity.”³ Although both are forms of self-congruence, sincerity and authenticity often stand at odds with each another. Most late modern thinkers prefer authenticity over sincerity for one of two overlapping reasons. (1) For some (Jean-Paul Sartre), sincerity (self-representation for others) assumes a problematic, essentialist conception of the self. If</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>BEYOND SINCERITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Levinasian Substitution in the Theater of Transcendence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though the topic has received little scholarly attention, Levinas’s<italic>Otherwise Than Being</italic>contains the strongest recent defense of sincerity.¹ Despite this neglect, Levinas’s preference for sincerity over its typically better-esteemed alternative, authenticity, marks one of the most intriguing moments in the history of self-congruence. As the last chapter demonstrates, Levinas goes so far as to champion sincerity as a virtual synonym for both responsibility and subjectivity. In words taken from his<italic>Humanism of the Other</italic>(1972), ”Sincerity . . . is the very responsibility for others” (<italic>HO</italic>69); ”Is subjectivity not sincerity—putting oneself out in the open, which is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At this point, one might rightly wonder if the three problems with sincerity highlighted here (imperfection, inexpressibility, and individualism) give way to a more positive conception of the right role of congruence and incongruence in our lives. To repeat the earlier point, each problem with sincerity gave way already to one or more ethical theatricalities and also to a revised understanding of self-congruence. However, one might nevertheless wonder if these three distinct problems, not to mention their solutions, give way to a joint— dare I say<italic>unified</italic>—view of sincerity and theatricality. After all, Kant’s imitation of the moral exemplar,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wvwdtb.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
