<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn32dt</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Post-Foundational Political Thought</book-title>
         <subtitle>Political Difference in Nancy, Lefort, Badiou and Laclau</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Marchart</surname>
               <given-names>Oliver</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748624973</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748630684</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Oliver Marchart</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1r2bs1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A wide-ranging overview of the emergence of post-foundationalism and a survey of the work of its key contemporary exponents.This book presents the first systematic coverage of the conceptual difference between ‘politics’ (the practice of conventional politics: the political system or political forms of action) and ‘the political’ (a much more radical aspect which cannot be restricted to the realms of institutional politics). It is also the first introductory overview of post-foundationalism and the tradition of ‘left Heideggerianism’: the political thought of contemporary theorists who make frequent use of the idea of political difference: Jean-Luc Nancy, Claude Lefort, Alain Badiou and Ernesto Laclau.After an overview of current trends in social post-foundationalism and a genealogical chapter on the historical emergence of the difference between the concepts of ‘politics’ and ‘the political’, the work of individual theorists is presented and discussed at length. Individual chapters are presented on the political thought of Jean-Luc Nancy (including Philippe Lacoue-Labarthe), Claude Lefort, Alain Badiou, and Ernesto Laclau (including Chantal Mouffe).Overall the book offers an elaboration of the idea of a post-foundational conception of politics.Other titles in the Taking on the Political series: Valentine and Arditi/ Polemicisation 0 7486 1064 2Shapiro/ Cinematic Political Thought 0 7486 1289 0Chambers/ Language and the Politics of Untimeliness 0 7486 1766 3Bowman/ Post-Marxism Versus Cultural Studies 978 0 7486 1762 3Simons/ Critical Political Theory in the Media Age 0 7486 1583 0</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Expanded Contents List</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Absent Ground of the Social</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The following study on post-foundational political thought navigates around a curious difference, which has assumed some currency in recent continental and Anglo-American political thought: the difference between <italic>politics</italic> and <italic>the political</italic>, or, in French, between <italic>la politique</italic> and <italic>le politique</italic>, or again, in German, between <italic>Politik</italic> and <italic>das Politische</italic>. As is well known, a distinctive notion of the political was developed first in the German-speaking world, where it was Carl Schmitt who famously – infamously for some – sought to differentiate the political from other domains of the social, including the domain of politics in the narrow sense (see Chapter 2). In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>The Contours of ‘Left Heideggerianism’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Post-Foundationalism and Necessary Contingency</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the present chapter I seek to substantiate our main thesis – according to which the political difference must be understood as symptomatically pointing at the crumbling grounds of foundationalism – by analyzing its elements step by step, starting with an account of the notion of post-foundationalism itself and of the quasi-transcendental argument by which post-foundational thought proceeds. We will then examine the Heideggerian roots of post-foundationalism (around the four concepts of event, moment, freedom, and difference), which will put us in a better position to detect the commonalities between the Heideggerians of the Left discussed in Chapters 3–6. I will</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Politics and the Political:</title>
                     <subtitle>Genealogy of a Conceptual Difference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Politics, as Paul Ricœur once remarked, ‘only exists in great moments, in “crises”, in the climactic and turning points of history’ (1965: 255). In 1956, troops of the Warsaw pact states invaded Hungary and cracked down on the Hungarian revolution. This event had heavily dislocating effects on Western political thought – no matter whether Marxist or not. As a reaction, Paul Ricœur published one of his best-known essays, ‘The Political Paradox’, in which he seeks to come to terms philosophically with the exigency of the Hungarian events (1965). Counter to state-Marxism, his aim is to think what he perceives as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Retracing the Political Difference:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jean-Luc Nancy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Every inquiry into social post-foundationalism and the conceptual difference between politics and the political will have to take into account the work presented and elaborated at the Centre for Philosophical Research on the Political between 1980 and 1984. The Centre, founded by Philippe Lacoue-Labarthe and Jean-Luc Nancy, turned out to be the location for the most intense and influential re-elaboration so far of the notion of the political, or of the difference between politics and the political. The way Claude Lefort and Alain Badiou, for instance, frame their own versions of the political difference (oftentimes in contradistinction to Nancy and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>The Machiavellian Moment Re-Theorized:</title>
                     <subtitle>Claude Lefort</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>‘My purpose here is to encourage and to contribute to a revival of political philosophy.’ These words stand at the beginning of one of Claude Lefort’s most prominent articles (Lefort 1988: 9) – based on a talk he delivered at Nancy and Lacoue-Labarthe’s Centre for Philosophical Research on the Political. And indeed, there can be no doubt as to the significance of Lefort’s work for contemporary political philosophy and, in particular, for democracy theory. What Lefort has elaborated is one of the most powerful theorizations of the political, of democracy and totalitarianism, which can help us better to grasp the primacy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>The State and the Politics of Truth:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alain Badiou</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Badiou’s work constitutes one of the rare examples in current theorizing of a post-foundational philosophical <italic>system</italic> – and there is hardly a contradiction here between a post-foundational stance and systematic philosophy. For Badiou, true philosophy is always systematic, yet it is not systematic in the sense of being centered around a keystone: ‘if by “system” you mean, first, that philosophy is conceived as an argumentative discipline with a requirement of coherence, and second, that philosophy never takes the form of a singular body of knowledge but, to use my own vocabulary, exists conditionally with respect to a complex set of truths,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>The Political and the Impossibility of Society:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ernesto Laclau</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the above quotation, Ernesto Laclau indicates a large part of the aim of his theoretical enterprise, and, to some extent, of Chantal Mouffe’s theoretical enterprise. Their aim is to reverse the order of priority between the social and the political. The assumption that the political has been systematically ‘absorbed’ by the social places the Laclauian enterprise in the framework of theories that share Schmitt’s neutralization thesis and Arendt’s colonization thesis, as they were discussed in Chapter 2 respectively. However, contrary to Max Weber, who can be considered the actual source of the absorption thesis, no pessimistic or even fatalistic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Founding Post-Foundationalism:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Political Ontology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>One of our initial assumptions was that, if our aim is to delineate the contours of current post-foundational political thought, it is not sufficient to develop the conceptual history of the emerging concept of the political. In the present investigation I wanted to go one step further by concentrating on those theories that employ the term within the post-foundational framework of what was described as left Heideggerianism. So let us once more recapitulate the thesis: in most such theories, ‘the political’ in its difference vis-à-vis ‘the social’ and ‘politics’ serves as an indicator of precisely the impossibility or absence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2bs1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
