<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Church and Ethical Responsibility in the Midst of World Economy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Greed, Dominion, and Justice</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <string-name>
               <surname>CHUNG</surname>
               <given-names>PAUL S.</given-names>
            </string-name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>With a Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Duchrow</surname>
               <given-names>Ulrich</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227679999</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227901557</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Paul S. Chung</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgfbzc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Magisterial in scope and scrupulous in its investigation and attribution of sources, 'Church and Ethical Responsibility in the Midst of World Economy' will take its place as an important document that contributes much in terms of prophetic praxis - it challenges those who are comfortably complacent and unwilling to be disturbed.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="320"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Duchrow</surname>
                           <given-names>Ulrich</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who can write a book like this one? I guess only someone who has worked for a long time in interdisciplinary, intercultural, and interreligious ways. Paul Chung has already brought into dialogue Martin Luther with Buddhism, Karl Barth with religious pluralism, as well as Asian<italic>minjung</italic>theology with Buddhism, Daoism, and Confucianism—in order to construct an “Irregular Theology.” Now he masters the social, economic, historical, and cultural complexities of capitalism in the context of today’s crises. What is his special contribution to the broad debate on this subject spurred by the nearly complete collapse of the financial system in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Church and Economic Justice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A theological concept of the church’s mission and its ethical responsibility cannot be properly understood and practiced apart from God’s justice for those who suffer in the world. The God who forgives is the One who demands justice. The church is a community of witness to the universality of the gospel, especially in regard to the fragile, the voiceless, and the vulnerable. Economic justice is an indispensable part of the church’s responsibility for society. An integration of theology with the study of economics takes on a new and major significance given the reality of devastation that economic globalization has brought.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Colonialism and the Historical Development of Capitalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first stage of the journey toward capitalism was marked by the conquest and pillage of America (sixteenth century), while the second stage was marked by the rise and affirmation of the bourgeoisies (seventeenth and eighteenth century). These elements of capitalism fused into a powerful mix, propelling European states toward the territorial conquest of the world. Based on this unique fusion of state and capital, capitalism became identified with the state, thus triumphing.¹</p>
                     <p>What Western history calls “the great discoveries” initiated the first stage described above. In 1486, Bartholomew Diaz “discovered” and traveled around the Cape of Good Hope, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Max Weber (1864–1920) raised an important yet controversial thesis, arguing that there is a selective affinity between Protestantism and the spirit of capitalism. In his sociological analysis, a Western form of rationality finds its echo in Protestant innerworldly asceticism. Calvin’s theology of predestination is revealed as the ideological seedbed for creating a religious-ethical worldview conducive to the rise of capitalism. Calvin endorsed the charging of interest on loans and the relaxation on commerce. This chapter deals with Weber’s sociological evaluation of Martin Luther and John Calvin and includes Weber’s sociological study of Protestant religious ethics. It is certain that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Political Right and Economic Freedom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous two chapters we discussed the historical genesis and development of Capitalism within the framework of the world-economy, colonialism, and the rationalization process. Tracing the economic movement of Christian theology and mission, a critical study was undertaken in regard to Christian mission and colonialism in the New World and also Weber’s thesis of the Protestant ethic and capitalist spirit. Along with the capitalist development of world-economy and sociological analysis of religious ideas, it is necessary to examine how closely the philosophical ideas of individual rights, civil society, and freedom have been intertwined with the economic individualism of capitalism.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Industrial Capitalism and the Self-Regulating Market</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Max Weber’s sociological analysis of the affinity between Calvinism and capitalism finds its evidence in Holland and England. The political-economic development in the British context, including enclosure and mill, led to the industrial revolution. Industrial capitalism came into full swing with the self-regulating market. Along with the development of industrial capitalism, colonial trade played an indispensable role in connection with Christian mission. This chapter entails a critical study of the industrial revolution and British colonial economic policy in India and later China, including the opium wars to which Christian mission was linked. This chapter further includes a critical study of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Sociocritical Dialectics in the Shift from Alienation to Emancipation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is a study of the limitations and contributions of Karl Marx in the economic field. I shall deal with basic elements in Marx’s political economy and his method of historical materialism in reference to Hegel, because Marx’s thought cannot be properly understood without Hegel’s concept of labor and alienation in civil society. Marx’s critique of religion implies his negative evaluation of the role of church mission in the domestic-economic context, as well as in the colonial context. As we have previously seen, Marx’s critique of mission and colonialism and his analysis of the Christian character of capital accumulation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Dynamism and Limitations of the Capitalist System</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marx applied the sociohistorical method of the materialist dialectic to the study of economic problems. The use of the dialectical method is the<italic>differentia specifica of Capital</italic>, distinguishing Marx from all other economic theories. Economic phenomena are seen in their inner connection as an integrated totality which is structured by a basic mode of production. This totality is analyzed in all its aspects and manifestations in terms of the unfolding of the inner contradictions of that economic structure. The object of Marx’s investigation is the capitalist mode of production and the relations of production and forms of intercourse corresponding to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Reality of Late Capitalism and Its Challenge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the days of Marx, the shift to monopoly capitalism in the phase of imperialism has made Marx’s theory questionable and even obsolete. The unemployed army as capitalism’s gravediggers turned into labor aristocrats. Not competition in industrial capitalism, but monopoly played a decisive role in changed economic life. Bank capital has merged with industrial capital and this merger created finance capital. The export of capital became greatly important. Through international monopoly the territorial division of unoccupied parts of the world was established among the major capitalist powers and their satellites.¹</p>
                     <p>In our study of the relationship between monopoly capitalism and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Capitalism and World-Systems Analysis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have examined the development and expansion of capitalism in terms of a critical study of Marx’s idea and theory of monopoly capital and late capitalism. However, those committed to economic study from the standpoint of the world-system take issue with monopoly capitalism as a rational and progressive system which retains big business organized in giant corporations as its prime mover. Smaller business was treated as a part of the environment around the operation of big business.¹ A state under monopoly capitalism has a responsibility to insure that prices and profit margins in the deviant industries are brought within the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Economic Globalization, Neo-Liberalism, and Empire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the shift to economic globalization, we observe that the neo-liberalists begin to take initiative following the Bretton Woods conference in the United States (1944). The conference was intended to discuss a comprehensive set of new international regulations. It was designed to prevent a repeat of the mistakes that led to the collapse of the liberal international system in 1929. J. M. Keynes, the leader of the British delegation, submitted a plan to this effect. The core of the Keynes plan aims to further not only the short-term interests of creditors, but also the long-term economic balance. This plan attempts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Alternatives to Global Capitalism in Ecumenical Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The framing of the international landscape has shifted from a confrontation between East and West to the enormous disparity between North and South. Taking issue with the reality of economic globalization, there are several significant attempts to overcome the limitations and setbacks of global capitalism in ecumenical-global contexts. An alternative to global capitalism requires a new theological-ethical endeavor which should present the church’s ethical responsibility for the gospel and the world. A prophetic theology concerning the gospel and economic justice has been framed and undertaken in an ecumenical and global context to break through the limitation, setback, and crisis of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Excursus:</title>
                     <subtitle>East Asian Religions and Social Justice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We live in the midst of global complexity, confusion, and whirl. An ethics of peace, compassion, justice, and rectification of the integrity of life in a global-ecumenical context can be developed by learning from moral and ethical sources of great religious traditions which facilitate improving on the inadequacy and poverty of Westerncentric ethics.</p>
                     <p>As we have already examined, Duchrow has now started to enlarge the scope of alternatives by engaging in inter-religious solidarity building for justice. He does so by starting from a contextual re-reading of the theory of Axial Age (including Islam as a second wave of the Axial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Theology of God’s Life and Emancipation from Greed and Dominion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Church and ethical responsibility in the midst of world-economy</italic>is a study of capitalism and its world-wide global dominion. In this study we have observed the church’s failure in ethical responsibility in the context of colonialism. Furthermore, we have attempted to examine the church’s commitment to economic justice in the ecumenical context concerning the reality of economic globalization and global capitalism.</p>
                     <p>As we have examined the genesis and development of capitalism in its initial historical stage, the capital power of Genoa in the first phase linked up with the hegemonic territorial power of Spain in the sixteenth century. It was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbzc.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
