<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gx2w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Fredrik Barth</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Intellectual Biography</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Eriksen</surname>
               <given-names>Thomas Hylland</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Amit</surname>
               <given-names>Vered</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Garsten</surname>
               <given-names>Christina</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745335353</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781783713059</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Thomas Hylland Eriksen</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183p5d4"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Fredrik Barth is one of the towering figures of twentieth-century anthropology. This intellectual history traces the development of Barth’s ideas and explores the substance of his contributions. In an accessible style, Thomas Eriksen’s biographical study reveals the magic of ethnography to professional anthropologists and non-practitioners alike. Exploring his six decade career, it follows Barth from early ecological studies in Pakistan, to political studies in Iran, to groundbreaking fieldwork in Norway, New Guinea, Bali and Bhutan. Eriksen argues that Barth's voracious appetite for fieldwork holds the key to understanding his remarkable intellectual development and the insights it produced. The book raises many of the same questions that emerge from Barth's own work - of unity and diversity, of culture and relativism, of art and science. Thomas Eriksen is himself a major contributor to the study of anthropology, as well as a distinguished educator, and is therefore ideally placed to introduce the life and work of Fredrik Barth. This will surely be the definitive book on its subject for many years to come.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garsten</surname>
                           <given-names>Christina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Watching and Wandering</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first Barth on Norwegian soil was a mining engineer from Saxony, brought to the then Danish province by the king to assist in the excavation of silver from the mines in Kongsberg. As Fredrik Barth expresses it, he came to the country as a development expert. One of his descendants, Thomas (Tom) Fredrik Weybye Barth (1899–1971), also saw value in rocks. He became a geologist, took his doctoral degree at the age of 27, and travelled to Germany on a scholarship in 1927. During his academic sojourn in Leipzig, his first and only son was born on 22</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Power and the Glory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, formerly known as North-Western Province, in Pakistan occasionally makes international news in ways which indicate that this mountainous and remote region is even today only partly under the control of the state. The area is wedged between the borders to Afghanistan and Kashmir, and in cultural terms the Pashto speakers of Swat, Pathans or Pakthuns, have more in common with many Afghans than with most Pakistanis. The language belongs to a different branch of the Indo-European tree than Punjabi and Sindhi, the largest language communities in Pakistan; and most Taliban leaders are Pashto speakers..</p>
                     <p>Although Pakistan gained independence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Nomadic Freedom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Everything seemed to be in order before the departure. Barth had been to Paris and obtained his medical certificate at the eleventh hour, after having been interviewed by the renowned anthropologist Alfred Métraux about the assignment. The project, part of UNESCO’s Arid Zone initiative, had as its point of departure the problem with nomadic groups, seen from the perspective of the state. They are by definition difficult to govern. In most cases, nomads have no fixed address, no regular wage work and their children do not receive a formal education. They do not submit to the power monopoly of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Entrepreneurship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Barth arrived in Bergen, its fifteen-year-old university was located on a low hill near the city centre. Norwegian society, with its rural history and modern national identity associated with nature and rural life, has serious difficulties in handling urbanity – with Bergen a main exception. The main campus in Trondheim is located in an open field about 10 kilometres from the city, the University of Tromsø is closer to the airport than to the city, and in Oslo most of the departments are at Blindern, surrounded by apple trees and middle-class suburban bliss. New university colleges, from Vestfold to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Global Theorist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idea for the project on entrepreneurship came to Barth after a Wenner-Gren symposium on economic anthropology, to which Raymond Firth had invited him. The Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research was founded by the Swedish businessman Axel Wenner-Gren (who is, incidentally, often described as an entrepreneur) in 1941, then under the name of the Viking Foundation. Between 1958 and 1980, more than 80 conferences and workshops within all branches of anthropology, including biological anthropology, were organised at Burg Wartenstein castle in Austria. Barth was invited to several of these symposia, and he mentions that it had been suggested, tongue in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Ethnic Groups and Boundaries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was mainly from his colleagues and students that Barth sought – and received – inspiration on an everyday basis. The sociologist Stein Rokkan worked, like Barth, with comparative models, but he worked historically at the macro level, and their relationship was respectful, but restricted. Other ‘professor entrepreneurs’ in the burgeoning social science departments of the new university were useful allies in the effort to establish a faculty of social science at Bergen, but there was no intellectual affinity. The philosopher Knut Tranøy was a loyal ally and a personal friend, but there were no intellectual synergies to speak of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Baktaman Vibrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1968, more than ten years had passed since Barth had carried out long-term fieldwork. He had been aboard a fishing boat and studied economic spheres in Darfur, but had not carried out a larger ethnographic work of the kind that produces monographs, anecdotes for methodology seminars and cases for theoretical articles since the Basseri.</p>
                     <p>He needed to expose himself to something new. Barth has rarely mentioned wanderlust as a motivating factor in his professional life, but that must be because he takes it for granted. For it is difficult to imagine that he would have exposed himself to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>A New Kind of Complexity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During his twelve years in Bergen, Barth organised four major symposia: on the entrepreneur in Northern Norway, role theory, ethnicity and scale. By far the best known is the symposium on ethnicity, thanks to the subsequent book publication. However, the idea behind the scale conference was equally original, and deserved a better fate. The book<italic>Scale and Social Organization</italic>,¹ published only in 1978, is not very well known, even in Scandinavia. The anthropological concept of scale remains underused in a systematic way, even in studies where it would clearly have been useful.²</p>
                     <p>The concepts of large and small scale, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Turbulent Times</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fieldwork in Sohar had not been completed, but interrupted when the couple returned to Oslo in September 1974. Oslo was basking in a sunny, unusually warm Indian summer, while the returning anthropologists were shivering. By now, Barth had started his work at the Ethnographic Museum in earnest as well, and this job would – like his writing – turn out to be not entirely devoid of friction and difficulties in the coming ten years or so.</p>
                     <p>Before Barth went to Bergen in 1961, he envisioned the possibility of taking the professorship at the Ethnographic Museum when Gjessing retired, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Cultural Complexity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was during a visit to Swat in 1977 that Barth suggested that Wali Miangul Jahanzeb should write his autobiography. The<italic>wali</italic>was born in 1908 and was visibly ageing. He was the last<italic>wali</italic>of Swat, since the valley was by now, formally at least, an integral part of the Pakistani republic.</p>
                     <p>The<italic>wali</italic>was attracted to the idea, but he made it a condition that Barth should write the book. This was naturally a great honour and a genuine act of trust, and in practice it was impossible to refuse the offer, even if the material from Sohar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The Guru and the Conjurer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bali was not an obvious next stop in Barth’s life as an ethnographer. While he would have liked to go to Vanuatu, Bali had been Wikan’s preference. One reason for Barth’s initial doubt was the fact that Bali had been studied by good anthropologists previously. Margaret Mead and Gregory Bateson had been there in the 1940s, Clifford Geertz in the 1960s. The British anthropologist Mark Hobart was about to devote a lifetime of study to Bali. And there were others. Barth sensed that others had already been there and taken the prime cuts.</p>
                     <p>It is not difficult to understand why</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Between Art and Science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Trends and fashions come and go in the social sciences, but rarely without leaving something useful behind. From Foucault, we have kept concepts about discourse, power and regimes of knowledge; from Bourdieu, habitus, doxa and forms of capital; from Marxism, a sustained critical interest in power and economics; and from structuralism, the acknowledgement that the human mind functions in a particular way, frequently by way of contrasts. Nonetheless, structuralism, in its original form, is all but forgotten today. Few take up the cues left by 1960s and 1970s Marxism. Neither ethnoscience nor ethnomethodology are read as anything but intellectual history</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Works by Fredrik Barth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Other References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p5d4.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carlton</surname>
                           <given-names>Sue</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
