<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GF75 .V45 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Effect of human beings on</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Environmental protection</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Environmental degradation</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Global environmental change</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>General Science</subject>
         <subject>Ecology &amp; Evolutionary Biology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Veer Ecology</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Companion for Environmental Thinking</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cohen</surname>
               <given-names>Jeffrey Jerome</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Duckert</surname>
               <given-names>Lowell</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">Editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Glotfelty</surname>
               <given-names>Cheryll</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib4">
            <role>Afterword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Royle</surname>
               <given-names>Nicholas</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781517900779</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781452955742</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1452955743</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>MINNEAPOLIS; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Regents of the University of Minnesota</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt1pwt70r"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The words most commonly associated with the environmental movement-save, recycle, reuse, protect, regulate, restore-describe what we can do to help the environment, but few suggest how we might transform ourselves to better navigate the sudden turns of the late Anthropocene. Which words can help us to veer conceptually along with drastic environmental flux? Jeffrey Jerome Cohen and Lowell Duckert asked thirty brilliant thinkers to each propose one verb that stresses the forceful potential of inquiry, weather, biomes, apprehensions, and desires to swerve and sheer. Each term is accompanied by a concise essay contextualizing its meaning in times of resource depletion, environmental degradation, and global climate change.</p>
         <p>Some verbs are closely tied to natural processes: compost, saturate, seep, rain, shade, sediment, vegetate, environ. Many are vaguely unsettling: drown, unmoor, obsolesce, power down, haunt. Others are enigmatic or counterintuitive: curl, globalize, commodify, ape, whirl. And while several verbs pertain to human affect and action-love, represent, behold, wait, try, attune, play, remember, decorate, tend, hope-a primary goal of<italic>Veer Ecology</italic>is to decenter the human. Indeed, each of the essays speaks to a heightened sense of possibility, awakening our imaginations and inviting us to think the world anew from radically different perspectives. A groundbreaking guide for the twenty-first century,<italic>Veer Ecology</italic>foregrounds the risks and potentialities of living on-and with-an alarmingly dynamic planet.</p>
         <p>Contributors: Stacy Alaimo, U of Texas at Arlington; Joseph Campana, Rice U; Holly Dugan, George Washington U; Lara Farina, West Virginia U; Cheryll Glotfelty, U of Nevada, Reno; Anne F. Harris, DePauw U; Tim Ingold, U of Aberdeen; Serenella Iovino, U of Turin; Stephanie LeMenager, U of Oregon; Scott Maisano, U of Massachusetts, Boston; Tobias Menely, U of California, Davis; Steve Mentz, St. John's U; J. Allan Mitchell, U of Victoria; Timothy Morton, Rice U; Vin Nardizzi, U of British Columbia; Laura Ogden, Dartmouth College; Serpil Opperman, Hacettepe U, Ankara; Daniel C. Remein, U of Massachusetts, Boston; Margaret Ronda, U of California, Davis; Nicholas Royle, U of Sussex; Catriona Sandilands, York U; Christopher Schaberg, Loyola U; Rebecca R. Scott, U of Missouri; Theresa Shewry, U of California, Santa Barbara; Mick Smith, Queen's U; Jesse Oak Taylor, U of Washington; Brian Thill, Golden West College; Coll Thrush, U of British Columbia, Vancouver; Cord J. Whitaker, Wellesley College; Julian Yates, U of Delaware.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="536"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GLOTFELTY</surname>
                           <given-names>CHERYLL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If I ask you to brainstorm verbs that we commonly associate with the environmental movement, you might come up with<italic>reduce, recycle, reuse, conserve, preserve, protect, save, clean up, bike, garden, regulate, legislate</italic>, and<italic>restore</italic>. I would argue that these actions are still necessary but no longer sufficient. Most of these words describe work we can do to help the environment, but few of them tell us how to work on ourselves in a time of environmental upheaval. Taking a cue from Nicholas Royle’s recent book<italic>Veering: A Theory of Literature</italic>(2011), let us unpack the noun<italic>environment</italic>to discover</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Welcome to the Whirled</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COHEN</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY JEROME</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DUCKERT</surname>
                           <given-names>LOWELL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We call this book a<italic>companion</italic>in the hope of offering to its readers a ready partner and congenial fellow traveler, a vade mecum for fostering ecological attentiveness and encouraging further wandering. Through the transports of environmentally inclined verbs familiar and unexpected, this collaborative project aims not to provide encyclopedic overviews or definitive accounts of critical concepts (<italic>all</italic>concepts are critical) but to forge a welcoming and heterogeneous fellowship, a colloquy for pondering possibilities for environmental thinking, ecological theory, and engaged humanities practice during a time of widespread crisis. Imagining futures by rethinking possibilities present and past,<italic>Veer Ecology</italic>extends</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Vegetate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SANDILANDS</surname>
                           <given-names>CATRIONA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In popular parlance, when people vegetate, they spend the weekend on the couch in flannel pajamas in a monster binge of multiple seasons of<italic>Scott and Bailey</italic>(or, at least, I might). When people vegetate persistently, their brainstems keep basic functions going (circulation, respiration, digestion) but they do not display what we generally like to think of as consciousness: they are considered alive and cannot be killed/let die without a lot of legal wrangling, but they do not demonstrate critical kinds of awareness or independent capability. Even more: as Mark Twain wrote famously in<italic>The Innocents Abroad</italic>, vegetating is directly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Globalize</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TAYLOR</surname>
                           <given-names>JESSE OAK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We don’t live<italic>on</italic>Earth. We live<italic>in</italic>it. If there is a single perspectival shift demanded by the Anthropocene, it lies in acknowledging our own planetary internality. Earth’s atmosphere envelops all of history, a vaporous archive in which molecules exhaled by the dead remain suspended along with an ever-increasing quantity of industrial effluent. History bubbles up from the depths of an alien planet whose interior remains as mysterious as the heavens. Modernity runs on the fossilized remains of our prehistoric ancestors sucked and blasted from subterranean fissures. But the world we know has always been shaken, stirred, and, occasionally,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Commodify</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MENELY</surname>
                           <given-names>TOBIAS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We start with what is immediately at hand, what we see and touch, what supports and sustains us. In societies where capitalism “prevails,” Karl Marx writes, “wealth” (<italic>Reichtum</italic>) “appears” as a prodigious heap of commodities, “<italic>eine ‘ungeheure Warensammlung</italic>.’”¹ Marx begins<italic>Capital</italic>by reminding his readers of the historical distinctiveness of such a society, in which the existential richness of life comes to be measured in the profuse variety of goods available for purchase. Folklore describes the<italic>Ungeheure</italic>as an immense man-eating ogre. The joke, of course, is that human beings—what Marx calls living-labor, “the expenditure of human brain, nerves,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Power Down</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAMPANA</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSEPH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Power down—why not just power down? Everything seems to scream it: the rise of CO<sub>2</sub>levels, the rise of sea levels, superstorms, temperature swings, and polar vortices, not to mention the exponentially accelerating pace of extinctions, displacements, and deforestation, or the melting ice sheets, ice shelves, and glaciers, all of which make up a short list (you surely have your own) of only a few of the many symptoms of the already irrevocably altered ecosystems in which the lives of humans and other creatures will be increasingly trying and, perhaps eventually, impossible. If only we could surrender our addiction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Obsolesce</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RONDA</surname>
                           <given-names>MARGARET</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“There should be more nouns / For objects put to sleep / Against their will,” begins “Phone Booth,” a recent poem by Brenda Hillman that meditates on the lost pleasures of the phone booth.¹ These opening lines rue the impoverishment of our vocabulary for describing what happens to objects and materials that have been “put to sleep” before they are worn out and what remains of their obdurate, even “will[ful]” presence as they are rendered inactive by market forces or consumer whim. This not-yet-created language must account, Hillman suggests, not only for the complex material changes these objects undergo as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Decorate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>REMEIN</surname>
                           <given-names>DANIEL C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What decorates? And how? Why should the ecologically minded practitioner of the humanities concern herself with decorating—an activity of expenditure, of waste, an activity that resonates more with the theoretical invocations of<italic>oikos</italic>that mark an exclusively human household economy and the excesses of the<italic>domus</italic>(the household, yes, but also the unsustainable extravagance of the<italic>dominus</italic>, the lord, whose decorating displays his sovereignty and ownership) than the invocations of<italic>oikos</italic>in an ecological thinking that would mark the etymology of<italic>eco-</italic>in order to better think the earth as a much larger and complex household?¹</p>
                     <p>I come to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Remember</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WHITAKER</surname>
                           <given-names>CORD J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Love is like a cancer, three lyrics drawn from a representative collection of popular musical genres suggest. For hip-hop’s part, Lloyd Banks offers, “Love is like a cancer when you don’t let go.”¹ Post-hardcore punk band letlive offers, “And love is like a cancer.”² For the part of the blues, from which hip-hop and punk ultimately derive, Son Seals growls, “Your love is just like a cancer.”³ Cancerous love consumes its subject until nothing remains. But love also gives life: in the Middle Ages to the lusty squire of Chaucer’s<italic>Franklin’s Tale</italic>“yong, strong, right vertuous, and riche, and wys</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Represent</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>YATES</surname>
                           <given-names>JULIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the face of it, it seems hard to imagine a less likely candidate for inclusion in a lexicon of verbs vital to ecological thinking than the word<italic>represent</italic>, rubbished as it comes by a history of bad mediations, infidelities, ideological freighting, reduction, and redaction. The word sets in motion a string of approximating substitutions almost as if it concedes, from the beginning, that what matters, what it hopes to convey, shall simply slip through its fingers.</p>
                     <p>To<italic>represent</italic>means to remediate with words, images, bodies, with whatever technical resources you care to name, one encoding of information in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Compost</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OPPERMANN</surname>
                           <given-names>SERPIL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An essential process of biodegradation, composting occurs through the decomposition of nutrient-rich organic materials to enhance the soil properties. Since time immemorial nature’s invisible organic engineers have been composting to keep the soil alive, making it porous and aerated. If we zoom into this<italic>living canvas</italic>(to use Dorian Sagan’s definition of soil),¹ we encounter a throng of organisms composting in an eccentric landscape of diffractive relations.² An epic of life is being played out in this extraordinary terrain of microentities internalizing one another from their own residues without completely eliminating the traces of their origins. Fraught with its own</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Attune</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORTON</surname>
                           <given-names>TIMOTHY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since a thing cannot be known directly or totally, one can only attune to it, with greater or lesser degrees of intimacy. This is not a “merely” aesthetic approach to a basically blank extensional substance. Since appearance can’t be peeled decisively from the reality of a thing, attunement is a living, dynamic relation with another being.</p>
                     <p>The ecological space of attunement is a space of veering, because rigid differences between active and passive, straight and curved, become impossible to maintain. Consider, for example, the phenomenon of adaptation, a complex and curious event. An evolving species is adapting to another evolving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sediment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEMENAGER</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHANIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“All the sediments I have met with were amorphous,” writes Edmund Lloyd Birkett in<italic>Bird’s Urinary Deposits</italic>(1857).¹ The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>records this medical usage—poetic and oblique in its decontextualized solitude—for posterity. Birkett’s gloss on what urine yields as sediment also invokes a type scene for the nominal meaning of<italic>sediment</italic>as “matter composed of particles which fall by gravitation to the bottom of a liquid.” This scene of the urology lab spurs imagining perhaps too vivid to represent common usage. I envision the experimenter as white coated, precise in his rendering. Is he affronted by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Environ</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NARDIZZI</surname>
                           <given-names>VIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the end of the twentieth century, the consensus would seem to have been that the term and concept<italic>environment</italic>were no longer (and may never have been) critically productive. According to Wendell Berry in “Conservation Is Good Work,” “The idea that we live in something called ‘the environment’ … is utterly preposterous.” The prime position accorded to this noun in “the language we are using to talk about our connection to the world” signals, for Berry, both the anthropocentrism and the “inadequacy” of twentieth-century ecodiscourse. Berry aims to correct for this paucity in language by itemizing concrete nouns that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shade</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THILL</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rich tradition of linking ecological thought to spectacle—to the practices of bearing witness, on film and through documentary photography, to visible instances of environmental degradation and destruction—is no longer sufficient for confronting the existential threats posed by contemporary ecological crises. Carbon levels, species extinction, the collapsing ice shelf, rising seas, and other indicators of humankind’s impacts on the environment exceed our capacity to witness and document the true scope of the damage directly. Because it grants special weight to ecological spectacle and tableau that evoke strong feelings in us, the ecological image can only offer us an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Try</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DUCKERT</surname>
                           <given-names>LOWELL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I start with a twisting trial of strength. Off I go; with turns of the wrist, this essay attempts to encapsulate two years’ worth of teaching, tries to condense time’s course into instructive droplets. Distilled, one lesson is that something lingering always escapes a teacher’s endeavor, gets set free by the jugfuls across multiple-month journeys. A pedagogical paradox in Jordanian blue: rescuing is an effort to uncap, never to contain. To en-flash, to dream.<italic>Try it with me.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>I began teaching at West Virginia University in the autumn of 2012, and I have been grateful for the opportunities to engage</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rain</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SMITH</surname>
                           <given-names>MICK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The summer storm inundates the city, washing air clean of particulates, reviving and refreshing a world exhausted and choked by constant traffic. Breath comes more freely, colors appear more vibrant. Watered earth gently steams through turf and last year’s leaves. To stay without shelter under cloud-wracked sky, soaked through, is to receive a rare gift, albeit one often spurned. After all, we have so much to busy ourselves with and so ignore or demean such worldly providence, a generosity that would recall us, however momentarily, to our elemental, but never isolated, composure, our being-there-in-the-world together—our “we(a)ther-ing.” To feel our</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Drown</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COHEN</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY JEROME</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are experts at imagining end times.¹</p>
                     <p>After four millennia of practice, narratives of worldly obliteration come easily. The<italic>Epic of Gilgamesh</italic>is “a text haunted by rising waters and disaster.”² The Book of Revelation promises sudden global warming, floods of flame. Millenarianism springs eternal, from the medieval “Fifteen Signs before Doomsday” tradition to the endless Left Behind novels, internet sites, and films.³ Never out of print since its publication in 1960, Walter M. Miller Jr.’s<italic>A Canticle for Leibowitz</italic>imagines the long aftermath of nuclear winter by arcing time round into a radioactive Middle Ages. A genre dubbed “cli-fi”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Haunt</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THRUSH</surname>
                           <given-names>COLL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>About an hour south-southeast of Seattle, thirty miles as the heron flies. One of the outermost suburbs of the city, and one of its poorest, Auburn was founded in the mid-nineteenth century and was an important farming and railroad center by the turn of the twentieth century. Thirty years ago, when I was growing up there, it was a small town surrounded by dwindling farmland; now it is firmly held within the concreted fabric of suburbia, the nighttime darkness between towns that could once be seen from the hill where I lived now transformed into a seamless constellation of lights.¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Seep</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MENTZ</surname>
                           <given-names>STEVE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It seeps out from the edges of something, and when it’s done there are no clear edges. All the lines between the things have blurred. Liquid exchange replaces definition. The result is fuzzy, but not so indistinct that you can’t still make out separate shapes. When things seep together, they infiltrate each other but don’t merge. The process is a slow, inexorable, grinding-into. It’s hard to see it happening. By the time you notice any movement, it has seeped its way all through one thing to another, inch by inch, slowly. What was once a stain or the slightest tangent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Saturate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OGDEN</surname>
                           <given-names>LAURA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The islands of the Fuegian archipelago are like fragments of land, broken off from South America’s continental tip. They remind me of the way the jutting bits of family heirlooms are always vulnerable to neglectful care: teacup handles, the outstretched arm of a porcelain ballerina. But when you are on the islands, it is clear that there will be no putting things back together. Instead, the islands of Tierra del Fuego and Cape Horn seem to be barely holding their ground against the rough marriage of the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans. Generations of slow-moving glaciers created the archipelago’s topographic features,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Behold</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>IOVINO</surname>
                           <given-names>SERENELLA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>B<italic>ehold</italic>moves us out from where we stand. Closed in the solitude of self-contemplation, the I is thumped by a call—<italic>behold</italic>—that smashes its self-sufficient silence, a silence that concentrates all presence in the close proximity of the present or in the apparent distance of things.<italic>Behold</italic>forces us to look elsewhere—or just to swerve our mind beyond what seemed familiar, and conceals instead landscapes unseen. Because<italic>behold</italic>is a call that draws the eye/I to something that has always already been there—unheeded, undetected, or unrecognized—or to something that there will be, in a time that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Wait</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHABERG</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTOPHER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>10. When asked to choose a title verb for my chapter of this volume, I immediately thought of<italic>wait</italic>. Which is odd, in a way—I didn’t have to wait for it, at least not for long. This choice was partly due to my penchant for thinking about airports as environmentally rich sites. Places where, inevitably, one must<italic>wait</italic>. The surroundings press in on one, or float nebulously around, detached. Either way, the simple space of the airport is always also a tacky time, ready to latch on to the traveler at any moment. I like to contemplate airport temporalities: killing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Play</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MITCHELL</surname>
                           <given-names>J. ALLAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>P<italic>lay</italic>recreates itself moment-to-moment as a volatile field of interplay, veering among the elements. No reified concept quite captures the fugitive agencies and energies set loose. In the event, the meaning of<italic>play</italic>remains elusive even when sensed as a persistent stimulus, agitating and captivating those involved. Eliciting successive turns, moves, throws, rolls, feints, leaps, kicks, and blows, playing subsists in a dynamic negotiation. I hazard that the palpable, permutable, and relational aspects of playing open possibilities for future ecocritical endeavors, supplying motive and means for an immanent critique of possessive individualism and human triumphalism. Prompted by those who have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ape</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DUGAN</surname>
                           <given-names>HOLLY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAISANO</surname>
                           <given-names>SCOTT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Film adaptations of<italic>Romeo and Juliet</italic>frequently veer far from Shakespeare’s script. Both Franco Zeffirelli (1968) and Baz Luhrmann (1996), for example, eliminate the character of Paris from the final scene in the Capulet’s tomb.¹ But a more radical reimagining of the play’s end comes in Karina Holden’s<italic>Romeo &amp; Juliet A Monkey’s Tale</italic>, a television documentary produced by Animal Planet in 2006 about Macaque monkeys in Lopburi, Thailand.² From the opening iambs of its modified prologue (“In Thailand’s town …”), Holden’s urban wildlife film pulls two seemingly far-removed worlds—Shakespeare’s Globe and Animal Planet—into a potentially catastrophic orbit with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Love</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCOTT</surname>
                           <given-names>REBECCA R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>377</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There’s a public trail near my house that runs through a field of high grass and wild flowers, by some woods, and along a creek. I enjoy the trail but occasionally regard the creek as a poor substitute for the one I love and left behind in West Virginia. The creek by the trail where I live now is foamy when full, and on drier days is mostly notable for the dull opacity of its surface. The minnows and tadpoles observable in the flowing places are uneasy signs of health. It’s a creek that’s hard to love, flowing with runoff</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tend</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HARRIS</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNE F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>392</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>T<italic>end</italic>has a veering volatility. It bends around will and instinct, shaped by both, settling into neither:<italic>tend</italic>creates an oscillating ontological middle ground. That’s where I seek to be with you for this essay. Three animal tales and their images will keep us there; stories from medieval, early modern, and contemporary worlds that have been captured in miracle story, woodcut print, and documentary film because the animals involved behaved beyond instinct, which made the humans question their own wills. We will be in complex company across time and scale: the Cistercian recorder of miracles, Caesarius of Heisterbach, and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Unmoor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALAIMO</surname>
                           <given-names>STACY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Steve Mentz begins “Toward a Blue Cultural Studies” by declaring that “the new millennium is bringing humanities scholarship back to the sea.” He suggests that looking “closely at the sea, rather than the just the land, challenges established habits of thought.”¹ Indeed, he contends that “the scholarly benefits of the sea for many fields hinge on its unfamiliarity, and on the shock of novelty that comes from jolting one’s habits and practices into a new structure.”² In<italic>Shipwreck Modernity</italic>, Mentz discusses the marvelous 1627 woodcut of the Bookfish—a “codfish with a book in its belly”—a dramatic figuration of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Whirl</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>INGOLD</surname>
                           <given-names>TIM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Life begins in whirling. By “life” I do not mean an interior property that distinguishes some things we call “animate” from everything else we call “inanimate.” It is not to be found in the behavior of some magic molecule such as DNA that, in the right circumstances, can turn out replicas of itself. I mean, rather, the potential of a world given in movement to generate the forms of things, to hold them fast, and in turn to portend their dissolution. In a world of life, things are formed as eddies in the flow, that is as centers of stillness</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Curl</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FARINA</surname>
                           <given-names>LARA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>434</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lacking voices, faces, and quick motility, plants have seldom been considered candidates for the category of thinking beings in the West. Following Aristotle, early natural philosophers saw plants as the most minimal expression of “life,” possessing vitality but no feeling or awareness of their own matter.¹ As Tobias Baskin’s above response to Michael Pollan’s “The Intelligent Plant,” makes clear, resistance to extending sentience to<italic>species plantarum</italic>remains strong among bioscientists (Baskin is a cellular biologist studying botanic morphogenesis).² His use of the medieval figure of the mandrake root is meant to place plants’ possible “resemblance to our intelligence” firmly in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHEWRY</surname>
                           <given-names>TERESA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A poet calls for rain, hail, and floodwater to have a future, to “laugh again.”¹ The disturbing laughter of this work—Hone Tuwhare’s “Haiku (1),” first published in 1970—affirms the potential power and exuberance of marginalized water, but it also signals tensions that are bound up in hoping for a future involving floodwater.² The life jettisoned in floods—silt-choked grass; a drowned sheep, bent against a fence post—bears the marks of the extractive economy that settler farmers interwove with water in Aotearoa New Zealand, a landmass inundated by some 560 billion cubic meters of rain and snow every</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Veer</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROYLE</surname>
                           <given-names>NICHOLAS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>469</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An afterword, as Jacques Derrida once remarked, “ought never to be a last word. It comes<italic>after</italic>the discourse, that’s true, but detached enough from it or wandering away from it enough not to accomplish, finish off, close or conclude.”¹ An afterword should, in a word, veer. Heterogeneous to the text or texts that precede it, the afterword entails “an interruption,” Derrida suggests, something that “cannot be scarred over”: “There’s no suture once there’s the after-the-event, the<italic>Nachträglichkeit</italic>of an<italic>afterword</italic>.”² All of this may seem incontestable: the time of an afterword is different, out of joint with what it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>475</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Errata</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>477</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt70r.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>487</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
