<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS1235.3.E87 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. O.T. Genesis I-V</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Commentaries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible O.T. Genesis I-V</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. O.T. Genesis I-V</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc., Jewish</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. O.T. Genesis I-V</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Islamic interpretations</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. O.T. Genesis I-V</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminist criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Eve (Biblical figure)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Adam (Biblical figure)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Islam</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Eve and Adam</book-title>
         <subtitle>Jewish, Christian, and Muslim Readings on Genesis and Gender</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kvam</surname>
               <given-names>Kristen E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schearing</surname>
               <given-names>Linda S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ziegler</surname>
               <given-names>Valarie H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>1999</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253334909</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253109033</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253109035</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>BLOOMINGTON; INDIANAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2050vqm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The editors have performed a great service in making widely available a documentary history of the interpretation of the Eve and Adam story." -Publishers Weekly</p>
         <p>This fascinating volume examines Genesis 1-3 and the different ways that Jewish, Christian, and Muslim interpreters have used these passages to define and enforce gender roles.... a 'must'... " -Choice</p>
         <p>Wonderful! A marvelous introduction to the ways in which the three major Western religious traditions are both like, and unlike one another." -Ellen Umansky, Fairfield University</p>
         <p>No other text has affected women in the western world as much as the story of Eve and Adam. This remarkable anthology surveys more than 2,000 years of Jewish, Christian, and Muslim commentary and debate on the biblical story that continues to raise fundamental questions about what it means to be a man or to be a woman. The selections range widely from early postbiblical interpretations in the Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha to the Qur'an, from Thomas Aquinas to medieval Jewish commentaries, from Christian texts to 19th-century antebellum slavery writings, and on to pieces written especially for this volume.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="536"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS AND PERMISSIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XIII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Observers of American popular culture may recognize Genesis 1-3 as a text hotly defended by scientific creationists who want the “biblical account of creation” to be taught alongside evolutionary theories in the public schools. Long before Genesis 1-3 sparked debates about the teaching of science, however, interpreters were turning to—and arguing about—other foundational issues raised by the text. For centuries, the biblical account of creation has prompted readers to propose very different notions about what it means to be a man or to be a woman.</p>
                     <p>We discovered some of the historical uses of Genesis 1-3 independently from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Hebrew Bible Accounts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For two millennia now the Judeo-Christian tradition has placed man a little lower than the angels and woman a little higher than the demons.¹</p>
                     <p>No other text has affected women in the Western world as much as that found in the opening chapters of Genesis. The biblical story of the first man and woman became for many readers a blueprint for relationships between all men and women. Yet in spite of the wide-ranging influence of Genesis 1-3, there is surprisingly little agreement among readers concerning what these chapters actually say about such relationships. Do they present a message of subordination</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Jewish Postbiblical Interpretations (200s bce–200 ce)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jewish literature from 200 bce to 200 ce reflects an interest in Eve and Adam far beyond that found in the Hebrew Scriptures. Writings of the Apocrypha (Deuterocanon) and Pseudepigrapha (c. 200 bce-200 ce) and of such intellectuals as Philo (c. 20 bce-50 ce) and Josephus (c. 37-100 ce) retell, expand, and comment on Genesis 1-5. While many support hierarchical readings that subordinate Eve to Adam, others offer a more ambiguous, or at least less negative, interpretation of the first woman/Eve.</p>
                     <p>The most pejorative presentation of Eve in this period is found in the writings of Philo of Alexandria. Philo’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Rabbinic Interpretations (200–600s ce)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Talmudic and midrashic treatments of Genesis 1-3 combine an intense interest and curiosity about the text with a remarkable openness to interpretive options. No aspect of Genesis 1-3 escapes scrutiny and rabbinic comment; no gap in the story line goes unfilled. Modern readers of these compilations are likely to be overwhelmed by the plethora of opinions offered and the dissonance between authoritative rabbinic “voices.”</p>
                     <p>Looking at Eve through the lens of rabbinic discussions and arriving at an image of her likeness is like trying to connect dozens of puzzle pieces, each with its own shape and emphasis, in hopes of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Early Christian Interpretations (50–450 ce)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early Christian interpretations of Genesis 1-3 comprise a variety of texts. New Testament references of note range from the relatively early letters of Paul to the Pastoral Epistles (especially 1 Timothy) of the second century. In addition to the New Testament treatments, extracanonical sources such as the various gnostic scriptures and the Apocryphal Acts of the Apostles, as well as the writings of the Church “Fathers” (male writers who represented the view of Christianity eventually defined as orthodoxy), commented extensively on Genesis 1-3. Though the egalitarian model had its advocates, particularly in the earliest Christian communities, for the most part</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Medieval Readings:</title>
                     <subtitle>Muslim, Jewish, and Christian (600–1500 ce)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The medieval era¹ produced a variety of portrayals of Eve and Adam. While most accounts proposed hierarchical readings, a number of egalitarian readings emerged as well. This chapter continues our discussion of Jewish and Christian interpretations while adding a third significant partner: Islamic interpretations. In this time period, Islam enters the scene as a distinct religious tradition; thus we open this chapter with Muslim portrayals of Eve or—as she is known in Arabic—“Hawwa’.”</p>
                     <p>It is no accident that discussions of the character and activity of women play a significant role in Islam. Islam emphasizes the need for persons</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Interpretations from the Protestant Reformation (1517–1700 ce)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Protestant Reformation restructured the medieval church in ways that had the potential radically to transform Christian understandings of sexuality and gender roles. Since the days of the early church Fathers, theologians had argued that chastity was spiritually superior to marriage. Church vocations such as the priesthood or the various monastic callings were predicated upon celibacy. Moreover, the Fathers—and the medieval theologians who succeeded them—frequently argued that God created woman to enable humanity to procreate. Medieval theology valued celibacy above marriage and contrasted woman’s procreative power with man’s presumed lofty spiritual temperament. It is not hard to understand,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Social Applications in the United States (1800s ce)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines applications of Eve and Adam’s story to several social issues that were highly contested in the nineteenth century. While the chapter’s examination retains the preoccupation with Protestantism of the previous chapter (even as it adds voices from some new religious movements that arose out of Protestantism), it shifts the geographic locus from Europe to the United States. Since never in Western history had a culture produced more innovative readings of Genesis 1-3, or was a culture more determined to use the text in concrete social applications than nineteenth-century North America, this chapter will examine several of those</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Twentieth-Century Readings:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Debates Continue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Debates about the significance of Adam and Eve persist in our own day, as commentators continue to find in the story enduring models for social ordering. In response to modern reconsiderations of traditional roles for women, advocates of the hierarchical model have argued vigorously for the necessity of subordinating women to men, as prescribed by their readings of Genesis 1-3 and the Qur’an. In no previous century has concern for establishing men as the “head” of women been more pronounced.</p>
                     <p>And never before has the egalitarian reading of Eve and Adam’s story received such determined or sophisticated analysis. The emergence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                     <subtitle>The Preadamite Theory and the Christian Identity Movement: Race, Hierarchy, and Genesis 1–3 at the Turn of the Millennium</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>483</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>503</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2050vqm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>516</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
