<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">shou12328</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR3592.R4 S45 2001</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Milton, John, 1608–1674</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Knowledge</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity and other religions</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jewish learning and scholarship</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Relations</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                     <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
                  </subj-group>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jewish learning and scholarship in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hebrew literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Appreciation</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Milton, John, 1608–1674</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hellenism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Judaism in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Milton and the Rabbis</book-title>
         <subtitle>Hebraism, Hellenism, and Christianity</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Shoulson</surname>
               <given-names>Jeffrey S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>24</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2001</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231506397</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231506392</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2001</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/shou12328"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Taking as its starting point the long-standing characterization of Milton as a "Hebraic" writer,<italic>Milton and the Rabbis</italic>probes the limits of the relationship between the seventeenth-century English poet and polemicist and his Jewish antecedents. Shoulson's analysis moves back and forth between Milton's writings and Jewish writings of the first five centuries of the Common Era, collectively known as midrash. In exploring the historical and literary implications of these connections, Shoulson shows how Milton's text can inform a more nuanced reading of midrash just as midrash can offer new insights into<italic>Paradise Lost.</italic>
         </p>
         <p>Shoulson is unconvinced of a direct link between a specific collection of rabbinic writings and Milton's works. He argues that many of Milton's poetic ideas that parallel midrash are likely to have entered Christian discourse not only through early modern Christian Hebraicists but also through Protestant writers and preachers without special knowledge of Hebrew. At the heart of Shoulson's inquiry lies a fundamental question: When is an idea, a theme, or an emphasis distinctively Judaic or Hebraic and when is it Christian? The difficulty in answering such questions reveals and highlights the fluid interaction between ostensibly Jewish, Hellenistic, and Christian modes of thought not only during the early modern period but also early in time when rabbinic Judaism and Christianity began.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="384"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on the Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hebraism and Literary History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Credited by most recent discussions on the university as one of the central figures in the origins of the academic study of English, Matthew Arnold has helped to contribute and define many of the key terms still used in the analysis of literature. Arnold’s identification of the two distinctive forces behind Western culture’s continuing development in his seminal <italic>Culture and Anarchy</italic> has had the ongoing effect of rendering even contemporary discussions of literary history in terms of a tension between Hebraism, the first “energy” described above by Arnold, and Hellenism, the second “force.” Arnold famously asserts in the fourth part</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Diaspora and Restoration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>I begin with a few working definitions.¹ Midrash, from which most of my examples of rabbinic literature will be drawn, takes as its organizing principle the sequence of verses, portions, and books of the Hebrew Bible. Though its individual comments and observations can, and usually do, range widely within the biblical canon, its sequence of homilies, narratives, or legal pronouncements inevitably follows the main biblical text to which it has been appended.² In terms of the historical development of rabbinic interpretive genres, the midrashic mode seems to have predated the Mishnaic (Talmudic) mode. The midrashic approach, firmly anchored in biblical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“Taking Sanctuary Among the Jews”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Milton and the Form of Jewish Precedent</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>
                        <italic>Of Reformation in England and the Cawses that Hitherto have Hindered it</italic> (May 1641), the first of Milton’s five pamphlets written against the prelacy, the hierarchical clergy of the Church of England, begins with a protracted lament over the decline of the Church since the time of the apostles. Charged with key terms from the debates over religious doctrine, not only between the Roman church and Protestants, or among diverse Protestant groupings, but also from the age-old debates between Judaism and Christianity, Milton’s account of this decline describes</p>
                     <p>how that Doctrine of the <italic>Gospel</italic>, planted by teachers Divinely inspir’d, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Poetics of Accommodation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theodicy and the Language of Kingship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>When critics refer to Milton as a Hebraic writer, they frequently cite the God of <italic>Paradise Lost</italic> as a prime example of the poet’s ongoing fascination with the Jewish tradition. The depiction of the Father in relation to the Son dramatizes the poet’s interest in the connection between the Hebraic and the Christian, between the Old Covenant and its reformulation, especially by Paul, in the New Covenant. Milton, so the critical view goes, was more reluctant than some of his contemporaries to relinquish the legacy of Christianity’s Jewish heritage, a legacy to which he and many others lay claim in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Imagining Desire:</title>
                     <subtitle>Divine and Human Creativity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Genesis rabbah recounts a disputation between two of the most important schools of rabbinic thought, the house of Shammai and the house of Hillel. The midrash asks: What was created first, the heavens (the response given by the house of Shammai) or the earth (the house of Hillel’s response)? The debate continues:</p>
                     <p>According to the House of Shammai, it is like a king who built a throne for himself, and then made a footstool to go with it, as it is written, “The heaven is My throne and the earth is My footstool” (Isa. 66:1). According to the House of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“So Shall the World Go On”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Martyrdom, Interpretation, and History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>If midrash and <italic>Paradise Lost</italic> explore knowledge and being, they also interrogate the dynamics of experience and wrestle with the idea of history. The events of the past, both distant and more recent, posed a special challenge to the rabbis and Milton. With few exceptions, these events marked painful losses: the destruction of the Temple and the ensuing loss of political power within the Roman Empire on the one hand, the Restoration of the English monarchy and the disempowerment of more radical embodiments of Protestantism on the other. Yet if these texts purport to serve as theodicy—for the rabbis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward Interpreting the Hebraism of <italic>Samson Agonistes</italic>
                     </subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In chapter 5 I suggested a parallel between Milton’s imagined forecast of future times in the final books of <italic>Paradise Lost</italic> and the rabbinic fantasy of Moses’s visit to the bet midrash of R. Akiba. Both mountaintop scenes render complex perspectives on history, politics, belief, and human agency. These two scenes of instruction offer useful insights into one another, but Milton’s portrayal of Michael’s postlapsarian instructions to Adam has for its precursor a more explicit biblical account of divinely granted vistas, Moses’s Pisgah sight, just before his death, in Deuteronomy 34.¹ Anticipating Milton’s own reworking of this culminating biblical episode,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">shou12328.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
