<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS157 .D56 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Foreign influences</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Globalization in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Comparative</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">American and Ancient</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Comparative</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Ancient and American</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Influence (Literary, artistic, etc.)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Through Other Continents</book-title>
         <subtitle>American Literature across Deep Time</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dimock</surname>
               <given-names>Wai Chee</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691114507</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691114501</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400829521</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7skgc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What we call American literature is quite often a shorthand, a simplified name for an extended tangle of relations." This is the argument of<italic>Through Other Continents</italic>, Wai Chee Dimock's sustained effort to read American literature as a subset of world literature.</p>
         <p>Inspired by an unorthodox archive--ranging from epic traditions in Akkadian and Sanskrit to folk art, paintings by Veronese and Tiepolo, and the music of the Grateful Dead--Dimock constructs a long history of the world, a history she calls "deep time." The civilizations of Mesopotamia, India, Egypt, China, and West Africa, as well as Europe, leave their mark on American literature, which looks dramatically different when it is removed from a strictly national or English-language context. Key authors such as Thoreau, Margaret Fuller, Ezra Pound, Robert Lowell, Gary Snyder, Leslie Silko, Gloria Naylor, and Gerald Vizenor are transformed in this light. Emerson emerges as a translator of Islamic culture; Henry James's novels become long-distance kin to<italic>Gilgamesh</italic>; and Black English loses its ungrammaticalness when reclassified as a creole tongue, meshing the input from Africa, Europe, and the Americas.</p>
         <p>Throughout, Dimock contends that American literature is answerable not to the nation-state, but to the human species as a whole, and that it looks dramatically different when removed from a strictly national or English-language context.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Planet as Duration and Extension</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On April 14, 2003, the Iraqi National Library and the Islamic library in the Religious Ministry were burned to the ground. For months before this happened, archaeologists had been warning the United States government that an invasion of Iraq would pose the gravest threat to legacies from the Sumerian, Babylonian, and Assyrian civilizations, going back ten thousand years. After the invasion, the same archaeologists urged the U.S.-led coalition to observe the “international law of belligerent occupation” and protect the artifacts and archives left vulnerable by the conduct of war.¹ The coalition forces had in fact been protecting a number of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Global Civil Society:</title>
                     <subtitle>Thoreau on Three Continents</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How permanent is the nation as an associative form? Do human beings congregate naturally as sovereign states, defining themselves naturally by their membership in nations? Or are there other ties, other loyalties and commitments, based on non-national ideals and flourishing on nonnational platforms? Bruce Ackerman speaks of a “world constitutionalism,”¹ creating a rule of law across national boundaries. Jürgen Habermas argues for a “postnational constellation,” made up of a broad array of nongovernmental forms, an integrated network reflecting the planet as an integrated environment. Such a network casts doubt not only on the primacy but on the very rationality of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>World Religions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Emerson, Hafiz, Christianity, Islam</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Deep time, understood as temporal length added to the spatial width of the planet, gives us a set of coordinates at once extended and embedded, as fine-grained as it is long-lasting, operating both above and below the plane of the nation. The subnational and the transnational come together here in a loop, intertwined in a way that speaks as much to local circumstances as it does to global circuits.</p>
                     <p>In this chapter I take the subnational and the transnational into a different sphere of relations. As before, my starting point is a far-flung literary culture, spanning many centuries, threaded through</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Planetary Dead:</title>
                     <subtitle>Margaret Fuller, Ancient Egypt, Italian Revolution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Do the dead remain “human”? Does their membership in the species persist beyond their biological end? Or does that membership cease the moment their breath ceases? What is the principle that aggregates them, that makes us speak of them as one, a collective unit, “the dead”? And how does this oneness of the dead reflect on humans in general, currently not one but perhaps needing to be? What does it mean to belong to a species made up of two populations: those who are physically present and those who are not, no longer full-fledged members but also not quite nonmembers?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Genre as World System:</title>
                     <subtitle>Epic, Novel, Henry James</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What would literary history look like if the field were divided, not into discrete periods, and not into discrete bodies of national literatures? What other organizing principles might come into play? And how would they affect the mapping of “literature” as an analytic object: the length and width of the field; its lines of filiation, lines of differentiation; the database needed in order to show significant continuity or significant transformation; and the bounds of knowledge intimated, the arguments emerging as a result?</p>
                     <p>In this chapter—thinking about Henry James, and thinking about the novel and the epic—I propose one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Transnational Beauty:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aesthetics and Treason, Kant and Pound</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does beauty come under the jurisdiction of the nation-state? Is it a controlled phenomenon, the handiwork (and perhaps the handmaiden) of a territorial regime? Or is it more primitive, more unruly, having a deeper relation to humans as a species? If so, can it be invoked as a common ground of sorts, a platform for our shared humanness, over and against what would divide us?</p>
                     <p>The recent surge of interest in aesthetics¹ makes these questions all the more urgent. In this chapter I test the extent to which beauty can be aligned with a human commonality, rather than with one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Nonstandard Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Robert Lowell, Latin Translations, Vietnam War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Deep time is “un-American” in conforming neither to a national chronology nor to a national map. It nourishes a politics as well as an aesthetics: a devotion to ancient beauty that can lend itself to the charge of treason. Ezra Pound is an extreme case. Robert Lowell, in his attachment to Latin and his opposition to the Vietnam War, would seem to be rehearsing much the same dynamics. Rather than pitting him against the<italic>Saturday Review</italic>, I return now to a more theoretical argument of this book, having to do with the depth of literary culture and the sinuous threads</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>African, Caribbean, American:</title>
                     <subtitle>Black English as Creole Tongue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is african-american literature national or is it diasporic? Just how important is the first half of that hyphenated word? Does “African” reside solely in the pigment of the skin, or is it more active than that, more complexly present, working its way into ritual and music, into the very words one uses and the grammar that strings those words together? Is there a research program embedded in the word “African,” and if so, how does it square with the geography and chronology of the United States?</p>
                     <p>The “practice of diaspora” is emerging as a pivotal question in African-American literature.¹ In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Ecology across the Pacific:</title>
                     <subtitle>Coyote in Sanskrit, Monkey in Chinese</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What would ethics look like if its circumference were extended, its membership broadened to include not just a human population? And what would American literature look like if it were to follow suit, taking its cue from the diversity of the planet, a biosphere inhabited by more than one species, one kind of tenants?</p>
                     <p>This chapter pursues these questions through a kinship arc extending across the Pacific. The Buddhist-inflected ecology of Gary Snyder will open into a backward loop through a Sanskrit epic, the<italic>Ramayana</italic>, whose simian protagonist, Hanuman, would in turn take us to China, to the sixteenth-century novel</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7skgc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
