<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13kh4md</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ2605.A3734Z64</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Camus, Albert, 1913-1960</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Narcissistic Text</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Reading of Camus' Fiction</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Fitch</surname>
               <given-names>Brian T.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>1982</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781487598570</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781487595258</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1982</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/j.ctt1vgw8kv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This volume is the first book is the first to judge the whole of Camus' fiction by contemporary critical methods, and 'inter-textuality,' or the study of the interrelationship between Camus' own texts, using the critical tools elaborated in the writings of French formalists and the hermeneutic theory of literature.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="152"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>BTF</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author’s Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For some forty years now and since well before his premature death in an automobile accident in 1960, Albert Camus has been considered one of the most significant and influential writers of this century. Eloquent testimony to this fact is furnished by the several thousands of articles and books that have been devoted to the man and his work in countless countries on all five continents and in languages as diverse as Russian, Arabic, and Japanese.¹ That this status as one of the ‘classics’ of French literature would only be disputed precisely within the boundaries of his native land is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Writing on the Blackboard</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One finds in Camus’ fiction a curious and unremarked predilection for blackboards and analogous objects that fulfil the same function as circumscribed surfaces to be written upon. There is the blackboard on which the rebel Arabs leave Daru’s death sentence at the end of the short story ‘L’Hôte.’ The long process during which Joseph Grand labours painstakingly over the single sentence he seeks to perfect is also worked out on a blackboard, his room being described thus: ‘On remarquait seulement un rayon de bois blanc garni de deux ou trois dictionnaires, et un tableau noir sur lequel on pouvait lire</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Autoreferential Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>La Peste</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>La Peste</italic>is a text which often speaks of other texts. These other texts are, moreover, of all kinds, ranging from the very short to the very long and their status varies between the aesthetic and the practical. It could even be claimed that the real subject of<italic>La Peste</italic>is none other than the text in all its various forms.</p>
                     <p>This work starts out by explicitly designating itself as a text: ‘Les curieux événements qui font le sujet de cette chronique se sont produits en 194., à Oran.’ (i, 1217) Texts or parts or aspects of texts are mentioned</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Self-Generating Text:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘Jonas’</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I shall be looking at a different form of narcissism from that operative in<italic>La Peste</italic>. The<italic>textual</italic>narcissism of the latter novel will give way to the<italic>linguistic</italic>narcissism that can be seen at work within the very texture of the text as it spins itself out in a process of autogeneration, continually mirroring itself so that production and reproduction become synonymous.</p>
                     <p>The short story ‘Jonas ou l’artiste au travail’ concludes with an enigma which, in the context of the tale that precedes it, is tantamount to a pun, that is to say a play on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Hermeneutic Paradigm:</title>
                     <subtitle>L’Etranger</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us look again at the sentence that concludes ‘Jonas.’ All appearances to the contrary, we have still not exhausted its implications. In addition to its autoreferential rôle on the level of the generation of the text, it also points to the other end of the chain of literary communication: the subsequent reception of the literary text. The word on the artist’s canvas is, we are told, decipherable except for the doubt concerning one letter, a ‘<italic>d</italic>’ or a ‘<italic>t</italic>.’ However, either letter makes perfect sense: ‘solitaire’ or ‘solidaire’ (i, 1652) although there is a clear difference of meaning involved.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Interpreter Interpreted:</title>
                     <subtitle>La Chute</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although<italic>La Chute</italic>is narrated in the first person, the ‘I’ of the narrative voice is by no means the only ‘forme vide’ or empty slot that the text provides for the reader. Even the most cursory reading of this novel or ‘récit’ reveals the presence of a silent interlocutor, a paradoxical phenomenon made possible only because the words of Clamence’s companion are never reported directly by him. Clamence describes the person with whom he is conversing in terms that are general enough to have a general applicability and yet concrete enough to turn a shadow into a presence: he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Just between Texts:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intra-Intertextuality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapters, I have spoken of the way the Camusian text functions within itself, produces its own reflection, as well as the way it reproduces within itself its relationship to its reader. It remains to consider the manner in which the different texts relate to one another, for here too a mirroring effect can be seen to be at work. The intertextuality¹ in question is of a very special kind since no texts by other writers are concerned. In fact, if one were to consider the whole of Camus’ works as one single text, then one could more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography of Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vgw8kv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
