<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1551mgm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Resisting history</book-title>
         <subtitle>Religious transcendence and the invention of the unconscious</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hayward</surname>
               <given-names>Rhodri</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>19</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780719074141</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781847791467</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Rhodri Hayward</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt155j66d"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How can historians make sense of visions, hauntings and demonic possession? Do miraculous events have any place in a world governed by cause and effect? In Resisting history, Rhodri Hayward examines the cumulative attempts of theologians, historians and psychologists to create a consistent and rational narrative capable of containing the inexplicable. This lucid and provocative account argues that the psychological theories we routinely use to make sense of supernatural experience were born out of struggles between popular mystics and conservative authorities. Hayward’s lively analysis of the Victorian disciplines of Christology, psychology and psychical research reveals how our modern concept of the subconscious was developed as a tool for policing religious inspiration. He concludes his argument with a vivid study of the Welsh Revival of 1904-5, in which the attempt of thousands of converts to cast off their everyday identity was diffused and defeated using the language of the new psychology. By revealing the politics inherent in such language, Hayward raises questions about its deployment in the work of today’s historians. Written in a clear and accessible style, Resisting history provides a fresh and entertaining perspective for anyone interested in questioning the concepts that underlie historical writing and psychological thought today.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="168"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The invention of the self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are moments when the pursuit of history can seem truly unnerving. Sometimes that past which was meant to ground our ideas and conceptions gives way and reveals something stranger, alien and uncanny. Although such episodes are rare events in most historians’ lives, they form a recurring motif in fantastic literature, where they are widely associated with the breakdown of identity and personality. Stories of historians driven to madness and despair when their narratives are confounded recur repeatedly in novels, from Mary Ward’s<italic>Robert Elsmere</italic>and the ghost stories of M. R. James to the works of modern authors such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The invention of the unconscious</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The quest for the historical Jesus was not restricted to the universities or the established Churches. Across Britain and the United States, working-class radicals debated the historical basis of the Gospel records. Before George Eliot’s translation of the<italic>Leben Jesu</italic>appeared, plebeian secularists had issued cheap pirated editions of Strauss’s work. Their turn to historical enquiry was driven by a very different set of motives to those which animated Eliot and her ecclesiastical colleagues.¹ Some, including the Chartist ex-cobbler Thomas Cooper, believed that historical criticism would reveal the ‘legendary incrustations’ that had corrupted the true history of Christ.² Like Strauss</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The soul governed</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When William James sniffed nitrous oxide in the spring of 1882, he resurrected and transformed an experimental gesture which had been central to the practice of Christian mysticism. For centuries, Western ecstatics had attempted to transcend the boundaries of the human personality, and thus approach a knowledge of the divine life through the employment of ascetic and meditative techniques. The writings of Père Surin, Madame Guyon and Catherine of Genoa give minute and often horrifying descriptions of these methods: Surin crippled himself jumping from a window into the River Garonne; Catherine starved herself; while Mme Guyon (perhaps the most extreme</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The self triumphant</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Wales’ read the headlines of the<italic>Liverpool Echo</italic>in January 1905, ‘[is] in the grip of supernatural forces’.¹ The country was in a state of millennial fervour. Across the principality the familiar pattern of religious life was rent asunder as women and workers were being driven into public ecstasies and seized by religious raptures. Chapels and communities were transformed. The familiar procedures of the Sunday meeting were abandoned for the marathon sessions of praise and prayer. Other papers reported how natural law seemed to have lost its jurisdiction across the Principality. The nation was riven by portents and omens, from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j66d.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
