<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Christian Theology and Religious Pluralism</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Critical Evaluation of John Hick</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Nah</surname>
               <given-names>David S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227680155</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227901663</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>David S. Nah</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf1qd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The question of religious pluralism is the most significant yet thorniest of issues in theology today, and John Hick (1922–2012) has long been recognized as its most important scholar. However, while much has been written analyzing the philosophical basis of Hick’s pluralism, very little attention has been devoted to the theological foundations of his argument. Filling this gap, this book examines Hick’s theological attempts to systematically deconstruct the church’s traditional incarnational Christology. Special attention is given to evaluating Hick’s foundational theses “that Jesus himself did not teach what was to become the orthodox Christian understanding of him" and “that the dogma of Jesus’ two natures . . . has proved to be incapable of being explicated in any satisfactory way." By elucidating the ways in which Hick’s arguments fail, David Nah demonstrates that Hick was unwarranted in breaking away from the church’s incarnational Christology that has been at the core of Christianity for almost two thousand years.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="244"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In today’s postmodern age of religious diversity, John hick, the former Danforth Professor of Philosophy of Religion at the Claremont graduate university,¹ is widely recognized as one of the most important, if not the most influential and prolific, thinkers on religious pluralism. As possibly the most significant philosopher of religion in the second half of twentieth century, Hick’s contributions to the field of philosophy of religion in general, and in religious epistemology, theistic proofs, theodicy, death and eternal life, and mysticism, in particular, have widely been recognized. It is in the area of religious pluralism, however, that hick will long</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Religious Pluralism and John Hick</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More than any other time in the history of Western civilization, we are living today in a period of increasing religious plurality. it is becoming more common for persons living in many of the urban and suburban cities in the United States and around the world to have neighbors and acquaintances that are Jews, Muslims, Hindus, or Buddhists. In addition to familiar church buildings, it is now commonplace to find synagogues, mosques, and temples in many cities and even rural areas. The estimated Muslim population in the united States is now five million and growing.¹ Already by September of 2000,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Hick’s Philosophy of Religious Pluralism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before I begin examining and evaluating the specifics of Hick’s Christology in the next chapter, it is important for the purposes of this study to obtain a general understanding of Hick’s philosophy of religious pluralism. More so than the other pluralist theologians I mentioned in the last chapter, Hick’s theology of pluralism is fundamentally dependent on his philosophical insights. As has already been mentioned, hick began his academic career not as a theologian but, significantly, as a philosopher of religion. Throughout the course of his distinguished career, Hick has been widely recognized for his important contributions in the field of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Hick’s Theology of Religious Pluralism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having considered hick’s philosophy of pluralism in the last chapter, I am now ready to examine Hick’s theology of pluralism, concentrating especially on his Christology for a pluralistic age. as one of the leading philosophers of religion of our time, hick has not only been active in the contemporary theological scene, his contributions, particularly in the area of Christology, have been very significant. Specifically, hick has attempted to advance the limits of the traditional boundaries of Christology beyond the understanding of Christ and Christianity to the world of religions. Traditionally, Christianity has always confessed Jesus of Nazareth as god incarnate,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>An Evaluation of Hick’s Historical Arguments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, I have given a detailed survey of Hick’s negative descriptions of the traditional Christian understanding of Jesus of Nazareth as God incarnate, who became a man to die for sins, and who founded the church to proclaim this. I have also described hick’s own metaphorical Christology, proposed as an alternative model more appropriate for a pluralistic age. The purpose of this chapter and the next is to engage in a critical evaluation of these ideas. Specifically, in this present chapter, I shall evaluate what i have previously characterized as hick’s “historical argument” against the church’s incarnation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>An Evaluation of Hick’s Conceptual Arguments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having examined Hick’s thesis that Jesus never claimed to be divine but that this momentous doctrine was the creation of the church subsequent to his death, my next task is to assess his other important thesis, which I am here calling his “conceptual argument.”¹ This is the thesis that the belief in Jesus as God the Son incarnate, as articulated in the language of the two-natures Christology of Nicaea and Chalcedon, has proven to be incoherent and incapable of being explicated in any satisfactory way, and that, in fact, no adequate explanation has thus far been proposed. I shall examine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I stated at the beginning of the study, my purpose in writing this book was to examine John hick’s theology of religious pluralism with special regard to his rejection of the traditional Christian understanding that Jesus of Nazareth is “God incarnate, who came to die for the sins of the world and who formed the church to proclaim this.”¹ Hick’s negation of such a central tenet of orthodox Christianity is essential to his project of establishing religious equality among major religions, because, in hick’s own words, “if he [Jesus] was indeed god incarnate, Christianity is the only religion founded</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1qd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
