<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h08gn</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BJ1012.N43 1991</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Natural law</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Judgement (Ethics)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>God and the Grounding of Morality</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>NIELSEN</surname>
               <given-names>KAI</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>1997</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776616032</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">077661603X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa; Paris</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1991</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cn6sv1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>These essays make a single central claim: that human beings can still make sense of their lives and still have a humane morality, even if their worldview is utterly secular and even if they have lost the last vestige of belief in God. "Even in a self-consciously Godless world life can be fully meaningful," Nielsen contends.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="230"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essays included in this volume were written over a number of years and for a variety of occasions. They have, of course, a variety of themes and a battery of distinct arguments. They have, however, a unifying and a central claim. It is the claim, against an array of diverse beliefs and arguments, premodern, modern and post-modern, that human beings can still make sense of their lives and still have, without any failure of rationality, a humane morality, even if they are utterly secular in their beliefs and attitudes and, indeed, so secular that they have lost the last</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>God and the Good:</title>
                     <subtitle>Does Morality Need Religion?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is the claim of many influential christian and Jewish theologians (Brunner, Buber, Barth, Niebuhr, and Bultmann, to take outstanding examples) that the<italic>only</italic>genuine basis for morality is in religion. And any old religion is not good enough. The only truly adequate foundation for moral belief is a religion that acknowledges the absolute sovereignty of the Lord found in the prophetic religions.</p>
                     <p>These theologians will readily grant what is plainly true, namely, that as a matter of fact many non-religious people behave morally; but they contend that without a belief in God and his Law there is no<italic>ground</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Hobbesist and Humean Alternatives to a Religious Morality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his<italic>letter concerning toleration</italic>john Locke remarked, “. . . those are not at all to be tolerated who deny the being of a God. Promises, covenants, and oaths, which are the bonds of human society, can have no hold upon an atheist. The taking away of God, though but even in thought, dissolves all.”¹ When we read this now, we feel the cultural distance between ourselves and the seventeenth century. Even such a progressive and reasonable thinker as Locke, is, in this respect, at a very great distance from us. There are in North America Neanderthal undercurrents, indeed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>An Examination of the Thomistic Theory of Natural Moral Law</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theories of natural moral law have deep roots in our culture. They have emerged again and again in our western tradition, not, however, without important variations. They are less appealing in times of social and political stability than in times of social crisis. In times when man turns against man, voices are always raised to remind us that man by virtue of his very humanity has certain inalienable rights and certain absolute correlative obligations to his fellow man. Like Antigone, we appeal to moral laws that transcend an ethnocentric “closed morality” of social pressure. In our recent history, liberalism, both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>The Myth of Natural Law</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Natural moral law conceptions, grounded as they traditionally have been on metaphysical or theological principles, are myth-eaten and they ought to be discarded; aseptic, demythologized conceptions of “natural law,” like those set forth by Professor Hart in his<italic>The Concept of Law,</italic>are essentially sound and are fundamental in displaying the moral foundations of legal systems. Yet we must also come to understand that assent to the fundamental rules of human conduct that Hart notes is compatible with an acceptance of a thorough ethical relativism or conventionalism. I would like here to back up these controversial claims. In the first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>On Taking Human Nature as the Basis of Morality:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Exercise in Linguistic Analysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Generalizations about linguistic analysis and ethics are not likely to be very useful; nor, as a general rule, are general descriptions of linguistic methods in philosophy enlightening. Unless one has actually seen some live philosophical tangle unsnarled by such a technique, one will not be very convinced by even a very accurate general description of the methods used. On the other hand, sample analyses of moral concepts often do not make clear their relevance (direct or indirect) to actual moral perplexities. Nevertheless I shall brave the latter barrier, rather than launch into yet another general description of linguistic analysis in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Scepticism and Human Rights</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is usual nowadays when a philosophic defense of human rights or natural rights is undertaken to attempt to treat the right to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness, or the right to property, privacy, safety, education and the like as prima facie rights, or at least as rights that are in some way indefeasible.</p>
                     <p>To say these rights are prima facie is to say that such a right is a right that one can always exercise, if one chooses, if no stronger moral consideration supervenes. On such an account it can be maintained that there are certain prima</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>On Human Rights</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want to attempt in this chapter something that is no doubt over-ambitious. I want to ask, as bluntly as I can: are there human rights? That is, are there natural and inalienable rights which any human being anywhere, anytime, can appropriately lay claim to no matter what his situation in life and no matter in what society he finds himself? Bentham tells us that “Natural rights is simple nonsense: natural and imprescriptable rights rhetorical nonsense — nonsense upon stilts.” But in our time some able and analytically oriented moral philosophers have again defended, albeit not without modifications, this ancient notion.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Grounding Rights and a Method of Reflective Equilibrium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I try first, in sections I through IV, to show how there is a problem about the grounding of fundamental rights, and why skeptical challenges concerning a belief in natural rights or human rights cannot be so easily defeated or defused as some are wont to believe. I then turn, in Sections V through VIII, to a consideration of the extent to which the employment of the method of reflective equilibrium could be justifiably utilized to defend a belief in the soundness of a moral system which has, as an essential ingredient, principles which commit one to an acceptance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>On Sticking With Secular Morality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before I begin a response to Donald Evans’s thoughtful and generous elucidations and probing of my own views as well as his own transformations of them, I want, by way of a prolegomenon to the very idea of conceptualizing things in terms of “Religion and Irreligion,” to make some remarks, some of which may have something of an embarrassing autobiographical tone. I utter them both because I want to put my cards on the table and in the belief that they may be generally useful.</p>
                     <p>I find the very idea of religion versus irreligion somewhat distasteful. I ask myself, “Am</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Politics and Theology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Do We Need a Political Theology?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I shall begin by trying to give some reasonable construal of what political theology might come to. Traditionally, and somewhat ethnocentrically, theology is taken to be that discipline which more or less systematically examines the nature and attributes of God, his relation to creatures (human and otherwise), and to the rest of the universe. Political theology concerns itself with the political and broadly social aspects of this. Theology, as the editors of<italic>New Theology 6</italic>tell us, “exists — to help people interpret, to inspire them, and to judge their aspirations and methods.”¹ It of course unavoidably does this in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>God and the Basis of Morality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consider the fundamental religious beliefs common to the Judeo-Christian-Islamic traditions. If, as it seems likely, they cannot be proven to be true, can they be reasonably believed to be true because they can in some other way be justified? What I want to know is whether it is more reasonable to hold fundamental religious beliefs, such as there is a God and that we shall survive the death of our present bodies, than not to hold them. (I have discussed such general questions in Nielsen, 1971a, 1971b, 1973a and 1982a.) Part of that probing, the whole of which is surely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sv1.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
