<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Religion and Violence</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Dialectical Engagement through the Insights of Bernard Lonergan</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Arcamone</surname>
               <given-names>Dominic</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175712</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905296</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Dominic Arcamone</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgfbhn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The aim of Religion and Violence is to engage dialectically key symbols of religiously motivated violence through the insights of Bernard Lonergan. Sociologists and psychologists argue the link between religion and violence. Religion is viewed more as part of the problem and not part of the solution to violence. Bernard Lonergan’s insights have helped the author arrive at a number of conclusions regarding the link between religion and violence. He argues that there is a difference between distorted religion and genuine religion, between authenticity and inauthenticity of the subject. Distorted religion has the capacity to shape traditions in ways that justify violence, while genuine religion heals persons, helps them make different moral decisions when confronted with situations of conflict, and aims to explore new ways of understanding themselves as shaping history toward progress. Further, Religion and Violence, while arguing from within the Catholic Christian tradition, nevertheless seeks to provide a number of categories that will speak to people from other cultural traditions. Since many of the examples of religious violence cited by commentators come out of the Islamic tradition, the author has evidenced and explored more authentic aspects of the Islamic tradition that would help provide a solution to violence.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="294"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In social and cultural milieus across the globe, religion and violence are often linked dramatically by the actions of violent religious agents, and intellectually by academics, commentators, and authors who seek to understand these actions.¹ The link between violent struggle and the Koran has become commonplace in Western media since the events of September 11, 2001. More broadly, diverse groups and individuals across the religious spectrum have been involved in violent actions: so-called Christian groups blow up abortion clinics for the purpose of killing health professionals involved with acts of abortion; Jewish fundamentalist groups defend militarily their perceived religious right</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Why Draw on the Insights of Bernard Lonergan?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At this point, I want to present a justification for turning to the insights of the Catholic Canadian theologian and philosopher, Bernard Lonergan. While Lonergan’s works do not specifically concern themselves with religiously motivated violence, his insights nevertheless address the problem of violence by examining the performance of the subject as subject and by providing a philosophical analysis of the self-transcending subject. Lonergan postulates a set of foundational categories for discerning how we come to have religious knowledge, an explanatory account of historical progress and breakdown in human history, and a way forward for recovery in history that is achieved</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A Selective Literature Review</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I review selective literature dealing with religiously motivated violence. My choice of authors is based on a desire to listen to a diverse range of representative voices who have written academically in the field from various perspectives: cultural anthropological, philosophical and theological, psychological, and sociological. These authors include René Girard, Charles Taylor, James W. Jones, and Mark Juergensmeyer.</p>
                     <p>In terms of a cultural anthropology, René Girard has extensively explored the roots of violence and its relationship to religion, though it is difficult to pinpoint his writings as belonging to any one body of literature since he covers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Lonergan, Religion, and Violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The insights presented by Girard, Taylor, Jones, and Juergensmeyer have provided us with enough evidence to support the proposition that some forms of religious expression both motivate and justify the violent actions of religious agents. However, the survey of these authors’ works also leads me to assert that it is not enough simply to demonstrate empirically that people are motivated to commit violent acts by religious images, symbols, and doctrines. It is also important to dialectically engage religious images, symbols, and doctrines so as to judge whether they are conducive to authentic living, whether they are authentic understandings of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Dialectical Engagement with Cosmic War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmos</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, I outlined a theoretical framework for authentic and historical meaning-making based on Lonergan’s creative and healing vectors within the scale of values. The creative vector constitutes the movement from below upward, from vital, to social, cultural, and personal values. The need to realize vital values on a recurrent basis gives rise to questions at the social level to address the needs of sustainable living. Sustainable living invites questions at the cultural level so that a direction conducive to human living might be found. Questions at the cultural level draw forth our capacity for personal self-transcendence.</p>
                     <p>This</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>A Dialectical Engagement with Cosmic War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Warfare</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, I argued the importance of a dialectical engagement with the idea of<italic>cosmos</italic>within the symbol of cosmic war. We saw that the designation of<italic>cosmic</italic>war that linked violence, divine will, and warfare within a cosmologically oriented mindset was imprecise, especially when dealing with religious groups who demonstrate that their cultures have achieved, if only partially, an anthropological breakthrough. A better, more nuanced understanding of the religious agent’s horizon would be to categorize it in terms of a grace–sin dialectic but that carries the danger of cosmic dualism, and consequently a lack of appreciation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>A Constructive Engagement with Warfare</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Authors such as Juergensmeyer and Jones do not sufficiently attend to the distinction between genuine and false religion, nor do they explore the different moral horizons that inform religious agents’ reasons for warfare. There can be no doubt that the sacred texts of religious traditions also in-fluence the moral horizons of believers, whether or not those texts have been communicated and received after critical and responsible interpretation. Judeo-Christian and Islamic religious texts, uncritically examined, can lead one to conclude that religious traditions present a preoccupation with warfare and an image of a warrior God. The Old Testament Scriptures give many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>A Dialectical Engagement with Martyrdom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I engage dialectically with the idea of martyrdom, the second of Juergensmeyer’s symbols for understanding the link between violence and religion. I critique his claim that religious martyrdom and self-sacrifice are simply ritualized rites of destruction that in the eyes of religious agents leave the impression of a religious heroism that transforms history. Since martyrs are also called heroes, I hypothesize that true heroism is marked by a particular kind of courage, hope, and an ethic of risk. I assume that true heroism is a necessary, though not a sufficient, condition for true religious martyrdom, and I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>A Dialectical Engagement with Demonization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The third symbol presented by Juergensmeyer and others for understanding the link between violence and religion is the phenomenon of demonization. In this chapter, I will argue that without a heuristic account of evil, people will be unable to discern why demonization continues the cycle of violence. We will see that social exclusion and humiliation provide for the emergence and survival of demonizing processes, while acts of dehumanization escalate those processes to the point where those demonized are robbed of their subjectivity. Emerging out of situations where there is an imbalance of power, I will demonstrate the role of<italic>ressentiment</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>A Dialectical Engagement with Warrior Empowerment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Juergensmeyer’s fourth symbol for understanding the link between violence and religion is warrior empowerment, which joins two interrelated aspects: the practice and code of the warrior, and the empowering of the warrior. Although Juergensmeyer’s title chapter uses the term “warrior” to structure his analysis, he does not use the term in the body of his writings, preferring to refer to “fighters” and “soldiers.”¹ However, there is evidence that the term “warrior” has been used in communities, for example, the<italic>mujahid</italic>or holy warrior is a key figure in Islamic warfare. Holy warriors are called to<italic>inghimas</italic>or to throwing themselves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Conclusions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My aim in this book has been to explore the link between religion and violence, which I have done through four key symbols employed by commentators and academics convinced that religion often promotes violence. These symbols were: cosmic war, martyrdom, demonization, and warrior empowerment. I engaged dialectically with each of these symbols, using the insights of Bernard Lonergan, and through that engagement, I addressed a number of questions: What are the truthful and mistaken assertions made by authors through the lenses of these symbols around the link between religion and violence? Are there better categories to understand religiously motivated violence?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgfbhn.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>262</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
