<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Hermeneutical Self and an Ethical Difference</book-title>
         <subtitle>Intercivilizational Engagement</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <string-name>
               <surname>Chung</surname>
               <given-names>Paul S.</given-names>
            </string-name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173817</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227901014</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Paul S. Chung</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf16n"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In response to the religious and spiritual transition experienced in our modern world, Chung creates a postcolonial framework for inter-religious exchange, focussing on issues of interpretation, moral deliberation and ethical praxis. He investigates the relationship between hermeneutical theory and ethics and produces a new theory for intercivilizational dialogue, studying theological-philosophical theory of interpretation, ethics, the experience of cultural hybridity and inter-civilisational alliance, set within multiple horizons and diverse contexts</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="290"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                     <subtitle>Of Caves and Butterflies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Berthrong</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Paul S. Chung’s fascinating study of inter civilizational hermeneutics, we get caves and butterflies, Plato and Zhuangzi, Mencius/Mengzi and Aquinas, Zhu Xi and Wang Yangming, Gadamer, Ricouer, David Tracy, Edward Said, and a host of other classical and modern scholars in search of a new and refreshing global hermeneutical theory and project. It is a truly international and encompassing tour of the history of hermeneutics both in the West and East Asia. What is particularly refreshing is that this is a comparison of diverse hermeneutical traditions or as the Neo-Confucians would say, the art of reading through the multi-colored</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An engagement with the themes of the hermeneutical self and the ethical difference is undertaken in a comparative religious framework. In the aftermath of colonialism it implies an attempt to overcome the Western tradition of individual consciousness from Descartes to Husserl. In this tradition the thinking subject (knowledge of the self) takes on an ever-increasing importance in the theory of knowledge. In this philosophical development, the thinking subject has been prioritized, while sidestepping human life embedded within socio-historical locations and ethical practices. To improve on this shortcoming, I undertake a comparative religious-ethical study concerning interpretation and ethical self in dialogue</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Interpretation and Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Friedrich D. Schleiermacher (1768–1834) is the founder of modern Protestant theology, as well as the father of modern hermeneutics. When he lived in Berlin, Schleiermacher was in close personal contact with Friedrich Schlegel and the other Romantics, kindling his interest in hermeneutics. Schleiermacher argues that the universe is active and reveals itself to us at every moment. An impact of the universe on us is to accept everything individual as a part of the whole. Individual ability depends upon the prior activity of the universe. Our place in the universe (or “being-in-the-world” in Heideggarian fashion) transcends both our cognitive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Interpretation and Life Connection</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Schleiermacher’s influence continued in Dilthey’s (1833–1911) hermeneutical philosophy. As a student of Schleiermacher, he published in 1871 his monumental<italic>Life of Schleiermacher</italic>. Dilthey began to see in hermeneutics the foundation for the<italic>Geisteswissenschaften</italic>(human studies, or human sciences, or the social and human sciences), which means the humanities and social sciences aiming at interpreting expressions of human inner life. Human understanding penetrates into alien expressions of life through a transposition of the fullness of one’s own experience. The cultural sciences seek transposition, transferring mental objectifications back into reproductive experience.¹</p>
                     <p>In 1883, Dilthey published his<italic>Introduction to the Human Sciences</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Phemenology and Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dilthey in his later years came to appreciate Husserl’s (1859–1938) teachings, which avoid psychological reasoning and articulate the importance of the idea of evidence and a methodological procedure in cognitive analyses. Husserl’s<italic>Logical Investigations</italic>, published in two volumes in 1900 /1901, created phenomenology, including a new insight into hermeneutical theory. Husserl takes issue with Dilthey’s notion of worldview associated with historicism, because he believes that Dilthey depends on knowledge of historical relativity, causing the absolute validity of any particular life-interpretation, religion, or philosophy to disappear. The formation of a historical consciousness destroys “the belief in the universal validity” undertaken</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Understanding and Linguistic Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Heidegger (1884–1976) studied Husserl’s early writings and worked as his assistant in 1916, and succeeded Husserl in the chair at the University of Freiburg in 1928. Unlike Husserl, Heidegger’s basic conviction is that we do not study our activities by bracketing the world, because we are always “in-the-world.” Heidegger in his early career declared that the fundamental question of metaphysics is the question of Being: “why is there anything at all rather than nothing?” He sought to discover Being or reality (later called a new ground of meaning) by beginning with authentic human existence. This project introduces us to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Mediation:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Hermeneutical Self and Moral Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Immanuel Kant (1724–1804) saw morality in light of human reason. Practical reason itself becomes the criteria for right and wrong, stimulating moral action. Practical reason enables the human being to grasp innate moral law. The moral law is deontological in the sense that moral action has little to do with the consequences. For Kant, the categorical imperative is grounded solely in the notion of duty. There is one domain of value, the domain of moral value which is immune to human fragility and vulnerability. The very notion of a moral precept, for instance “Don’t kill”, can never conflict with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Interpretation and Ethics of Virtue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aristotle Revisited</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Driven by Gadamer’s appropriation of Aristotle into hermeneutical self, I take interest in examining Aristotle’s implication for interpretation and ethical theory. A notion of the mean and prudence is central to Aristotle’s notion of interpretation. This chapter is a study of Aristotle concerning interpretation and virtue ethics. This provides us with a framework for upholding a comparative study between Confucian ethics and Greek ethics in the next chapter.</p>
                     <p>Aristotle (born in 384 BCE) spent half his life in Athens, and became a pupil of Plato at the age of seventeen. The Aristotelian Corpus contains three complete treatises on moral science,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Intercivilizational Encounters:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Mean in Confucian Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The doctrine of the mean occupies an important academic position in theories on ethics and the conduct of life in both Western and Eastern civilization. In the previous chapter we discussed the place of the mean within Aristotelian theory of interpretation and virtue ethics. This chapter addresses the nature and moral orientation of Confucianism in regard to Aristotle’s ethics and Greek ethos. The Confucian notion of appropriateness can be compared with Greek notion of prudence. A Confucian hermeneutics of sincerity is to be reconstructed in examining the universal dimension of the mean within the context of<italic>Great Learning</italic>. Here care</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Thomas Aquinas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theological Virtue Ethics and Analogy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we examined Confucian ethics of the mean, appropriateness, and its hermeneutical implications for sincerity and selfcare, in view of Aristotle’s notion of the mean, the Greek notion of ethos, and care of self. A study of Thomas’s theological virtue ethics in this chapter is to be undertaken in view of Aristotle. The concluding reflection is a critical appreciation of Thomas’s perspective on the relationship between God and human being in a hierarchical and analogical manner. Analogy as theological language is imbued with Thomist virtue ethics in a spiritualistic and hierarchical manner. Thomas’s theology and virtue ethics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>A Comparative Religious Study of Aquinas and Mengzi</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With a comparative study of Aquinas and Mengzi (371–289 BCE), Yearley makes a contribution the religious study of virtue-ethics. To undertake a comparative, religious study of Aquinas and Mengzi, I also study Matteo Ricci (1552–1610), the first Western missionary scholar in China, who undertook studies of and developed intercivilizational encounters with Confucianism. Reviewing Yearely’s and Ricci’s works, I introduce Weber’s comparative study of Confucianism and Puritanism. Weber acknowledges the charismatic dimension of Mengzi’s political ethics better than Ricci and Yearley, but it remains insufficient. I will bring up Mengzi’s political ethics as one of the major contributions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART III. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of the present part is to examine the philosophical development of the hermeneutical subject and ethics of the Other in the Western context, viewing the struggle with the enlightenment project and also in the aftermath of modernity. A philosophical debate concerning the legacy of the Enlightenment finds its voice in a postcolonial argument in the aftermath of colonialism. In order to understand and develop a global-critical and postcolonial study of Confucian philosophy of interpretation and ethical integrity in the dialogue of civilizations (in Part IV), it is important to review the modernist and postmodernist debate concerning the hermeneutical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Interpretation in Long Route and Social Location</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hermeneutics of the symbol paves the way for hermeneutical relevance to social science and practical philosophy. According to Ricoeur, we must think not behind the symbols, but start from symbols. In short, the symbol gives rise to thought (thought in the sense of philosophical reflection).¹ In<italic>Existence and Hermeneutics</italic>, Ricoeur defines a symbol</p>
                     <p>as any structure of signification in which a direct, primary, literal meaning designates in addition, another meaning which is indirect, secondary, and figurative and which can be apprehended only through the first.²</p>
                     <p>The first, literal, patent meaning analogically intends a second meaning which is not given otherwise</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Discourse Ethics and Communicative Rationality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The end of ideologies” has changed into the end of history,¹ according to Fukuyama: liberal democracy constitutes the end point of humankind’s ideological evolution and the final form of human government; and, finally, liberal democracy forms the end of history.² In the phase of late capitalism embedded within the empire and the end of ideologies, a lifeworld is violated, reified, and colonized by political power, capital dominion, and mass media. In taking issue with this process of colonizing the lifeworld, Habermas’s notion of communicative moral practice becomes a counter proposal to “the end of ideologies” and can be endorsed as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Neo-Aristotelian Ethics and Neo-Kantian Framework</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the work of Aristotle, the central question is: “How should I live? or “How should one live?” Practical questions are invested with teleological significance. The question “what ought I to do?” or “what is right for me?” is subordinate to the question “what is the good life?” Aristotle speaks of the good and happy life in this regard. He views the ethos of the individual as embedded in the<italic>polis</italic>comprising the citizen body. Practical reason assumes the role of judgment illuminating the historical life-horizon of an ethos.¹ In the turn toward an ethics of the good, practical reason</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>Aesthetics of Existence and Ethics of Alterity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen the gamut of interaction between Aristotelian virtue ethics and Kant’s deontological rigor. In this interaction Habermas’s discourse ethics occupies a significant place, while Neo-Aristotelian ethics plays a counterpart to Neo-Kantian deontological orientation. However, in postmodernity’s ethical emphasis on the Other, an ethical-hermeneutical model assumes an aesthetic dimension and prophetic witness. Foucault’s concept of care of self and Levinas’s unprecedented concern for the Other are to be understood as a new mode of interpretation in prioritizing care for others.</p>
                     <p>Foucault’s care of the self, in contrast to Heidegger’s, constitutes a non-totalizing response towards alterity, closer to Levinas’s ethical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART IV. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An encounter with the Other is further to be conceptualized in a broader intercivilizational and global-critical spectrum. I am interested in conceptualizing such a reconstruction of hermeneutical self and ethical difference in a Confucian context. Chapter 14 deals with the necessity and purpose of dialogue between civilizations in the aftermath of colonialism. The basic argument of this chapter is to examine the contribution of non-Western culture and civilization as an irregular or subside to Western modernity. Critically scrutinizing Western civilization and modernity, my concern is to emphasize the Confucian contribution together with Latin American, African, and Islamic history.</p>
                     <p>Chapter 15</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Intercivilizational Reconstruction and Global-Critical Inquiry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cultural reality is socially, religiously, and linguistically constructed. Through the words of many cultures and religions, human thought and consciousness is embedded within diversity, plurality, and entanglement with the Other. Human religious experience and discourse cannot escape social situational, determination and life connection, which refers to the socio-historical location of human experience and social discourse. Given this, religion is an eminently social and cultural thing, implementing its spiritual meaning connected with the depth of human spiritual life: the ultimate concern. The purpose of this chapter is to delineate a global-critical and postcolonial enquiry for dealing with a comparative-religious study and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Engaging the Cave and the Butterfly:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dialectics of Enlightenment and Neo-Confucian Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a comparative religious study of interpretation and morality in an intercivilizational framework, I begin my long route in chapter 15 and 16 by comparing Plato’s analogy of the cave and Zhuangzi’s story about the butterfly dream. Plato, a pupil of Socrates, uses the analogy of a cave to illustrate his well-known and powerful image of the human condition in his book<italic>Republic</italic>(514a–519a).¹ He likens the ordinary human to a prisoner in a cave, forced to gaze at shadows. The human being strives to see the light that brings illumination to the truth. This story venerates the journey</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16.</label>
                     <title>Interpretation as Conflict and Creativity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Retrieval of Wang Yangming</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we dealt with Ricci’s interpretation of Confucianism and critique of Zhu Xi, while considering Zhu Xi’s creative development regarding self-cultivation and the art of interpretation. Developing an intercivilizational encounter in this regard, we reviewed Aristotle’s notion of analogy and moral being in regard to the Confucian notion of language and moral self.</p>
                     <p>Zhu Xi’s hermeneutics of investigation (“pilgrimatics of self-cultivation”)¹ demonstrates a hermeneutical theory in a dialectical revealing of the Heavenly Principle,<italic>Dao</italic>, in connection with human methodological, empirical investigation of things in the world. Zhu Xi’s greatness can be seen in his remarkable ability to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17.</label>
                     <title>Concluding Reflection:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Hermeneutical Self and an Ethical Difference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is a narrative on dialectics of Enlightenment and ethical self in a comparative, religious and intercivilizational quest, driven by an interest in addressing the hermeneutical self and the ethical difference. A narrative on dialectics of enlightenment and ethical self includes a reflection of what I have pursued in construal of postcolonial theory and its ethical strategy through global-critical and comparative study.</p>
                     <p>This project of postcolonial hermeneutics and ethics of difference is founded upon an irregular perspective on analogy and discourse, in light of God’s Saying as the infinite horizon in shaping and influencing global-critical epistemology. It is shown</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Interpretive Reason and Postcolonial Irregularity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this Epilogue, I shall present a postcolonial hermeneutics in terms of proposing archeology and social biography as a postcolonial epistemology. This new perspective articulates the important task of archeological endeavor in rewriting and re-reading the history of the innocent victim as excluded and silenced. History is not deconstructed in the name of binary oppositions, but to remember, in our current socio-biographical solidarity, those who are fragile and vulnerable, existing in the interstitial zone. To begin with archeological hermeneutics, it is important to consider a hermeneutics of analogical imagination and its dimension of suspicion and living discourse in an intercivilizational</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>274</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf16n.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
