<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h08gn</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B3181.B68 1994</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kant, Immanuel, 1724-1804</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Contributions in theory of knowledge</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Transcendentalism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Knowledge, Theory of</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Apperception, Knowledge, and Experience</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BOSSART</surname>
               <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>1994</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776615370</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776615378</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1994</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cn6r4p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Postmodernism is sometimes characterized as a loss of faith in reason, a loss of self, and an exaggerated relativism. W.H. Bossart discusses these alleged losses in the light of the "triumph" and subsequent decline of the transcendental turn in philosophy initiated by Kant.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="258"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In “Averroes’ Search” Borges imaginatively reconstructs the effort of the greatest of the Western Muslim philosophers to deal with the<italic>Poetics</italic>of Aristotle.¹ Averroes’ commentaries on Aristotle were a powerful influence on Scholasticism, which means, of course, on the history of Western philosophy in general. But Averroes was dealing with an Aristotle in translation, an Aristotle, in fact, twice removed from Arabic, for Aristotle was first translated into Syriac by Christian Syrians and then into Arabic from the Syriac.² Knowing neither Greek nor Syriac, this monumental scholar, whom the Schoolmen honoured simply as the “the Commentator,” was twice removed from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Kant’s Transcendental Problematic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A traditional way of introducing Kant to an audience somewhat familiar with the history of philosophy is to view him as attempting to synthesize the primary insights of Continental rationalism and British empiricism. Although this approach tends to downplay Kant’s genuine originality as a thinker, its virtue lies in the ready access it provides to many of the more technically difficult themes of Kant’s epistemology. And that is why I shall employ it in these brief introductory remarks.</p>
                     <p>Kant’s central thesis is that the mind structures experience according to certain universal and necessary laws. To know these laws is, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Closure of Kant’s Problematic:</title>
                     <subtitle>Idealism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kant’s central thesis is that the mind structures the sensible manifold, which is given to us under the a priori forms of space and time, into a public world of objects by synthesizing that manifold according to certain a priori rules. This thesis is supposed to defeat scepticism by providing a body of a priori laws that govern the structure of experience. These laws provide the conceptual framework within which all empirical cognition takes place. But they hold only of the phenomenal world and not of things as they may be in themselves and apart from the manner in which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Closure of Kant’s Problematic:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phenomenology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kant undertook the transcendental turn in philosophy to counter the scepticism of Hume; that is, he sought to provide an explanation of how it is possible to have knowledge that is both necessary and objective. Since knowledge derived from experience can never claim necessity, Kant concludes that such knowledge must be transcendental in origin. His account of how such knowledge is possible focusses on transcendental apperception and the order that it imposes upon the experience. We have seen, however, that his account fails to show that the categories can be derived entirely a priori, and that his final account of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Discontinuity and Coherence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have been reading certain developments in German philosophy as an attempt to close the gap between Kant’s transcendental apparatus and the world to which that apparatus gives order and coherence. We have seen, however, that none of the developments under consideration has been able to provide a completely transcendental or a priori account of the Kantian schema. Rather schemata appear to result from the interaction of the mind and the empirical data of experience. Hence we might conclude with Heidegger that it is through schemata that what we call a “world” is first opened up. In confronting these diverse</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The Library of Babel” opens as follows:</p>
                     <p>The universe (which others call the Library) is composed of an indefinite and perhaps infinite number of hexagonal galleries, with vast air shafts between, surrounded by very low railings. From any of the hexagons one can see, interminably, the upper and lower floors. The distribution of the galleries is invariable. Twenty shelves, five long shelves per side, cover all the sides except two; their height, which is the distance from floor to ceiling, scarcely exceeds that of a normal bookcase. One of the free sides leads to a narrow hallway which opens onto</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6r4p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
