<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>"Without Ceasing to be a Christian"</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Catholic and Protestant Assess the Christological Contribution of Raimon Panikkar</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RANSTROM</surname>
               <given-names>ERIK</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROBINSON</surname>
               <given-names>BOB</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506418544</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506418551</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>MINNEAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tm7h06"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Since his death in 2010, there has been continuing and growing interest in the life, vision, and thought of the late Spanish-Indian mystical theologian Raimon Panikkar. As well as offering both a personal affirmation and critique of Panikkar‘s thought from a Catholic and Protestant perspective, the work compares and contrasts him with a range of Western and Indian theologians, both Catholic and Protestant, and outlines the possibilities of learning from Panikkar in an ecumenical context.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="260"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RANSTROM</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Raimundo Alemany Panikkar (1918–2010)—or as he is more widely known today, Raimon Panikkar—lived, wrote, and taught on three continents over an astoundingly long period, stretching from roughly the close of World War I until the first decade of the twenty-first century. During that span, he published over three hundred articles and sixty books on a wide range of scientific, philosophical, cultural, and theological topics as seismic shifts in global cultural life were occurring—a point of which he was keenly aware. This very considerable output dealt with the interface between various aspects of Christianity, Hinduism, Buddhism, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Unknown Jesus or Unknown Christ?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Diversity in Panikkar’s Early Christology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RANSTROM</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter exposits and evaluates Panikkar’s Christology of religions from the beginning of his publishing career until the first edition of the<italic>Unknown Christ of Hinduism</italic>in 1964.¹ Unlike his later thought, which is more consistent on a host of philosophical and theological issues, a close look at his early christological writings reveals tension in terms of how to properly formulate the relationship between Christ and the religions.² More specifically, the broad outlines of two distinct approaches to Christ and the religions are evident during this early period, one of which has immense implications for a retrieval of Panikkar’s work.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The “Orthodox” Creativity of Panikkar’s Early Dialogue with Hinduism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RANSTROM</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter will explore Panikkar’s little-known comparative theological study of Hindu and Christian worship,<italic>Le mystère du culte dans l’hindouisme et le christianisme</italic>. The basis of the work was first given as a presentation at the thirty-seventh World Eucharistic Congress in Munich, Germany, in 1960.¹ The theme of the international theological conference which took place concurrently with the Congress was “Worship and Man Today.”² Panikkar’s paper was “conceived as a contribution in the Indian sphere”³ and then re-written and expanded for a book. The first edition was written by Panikkar in German⁴ and later translated into French in 1970. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>A Critical Reading of Panikkar’s Cosmotheandric Christology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RANSTROM</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter features a systematization of Panikkar’s later Christology, which is characterized by an escalation of the incipient pluralist trends found in the first edition of the<italic>Unknown Christ of Hinduism</italic>. It is also marked by an utter departure from the conviction that Jesus’s person and work is constitutively key to the relationship between God and the world. The chapter will also evaluate Panikkar’s later christological development based upon priorities and principles earlier drawn from “Meditaciόn sobre Melquisedec” and<italic>Le mystère du culte</italic>, as well as various systematic theologians. I will also set Panikkar’s later theology within a wider personal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>A Constructive Protestant Appreciation and Interaction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBINSON</surname>
                           <given-names>BOB</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Raimon Panikkar presents many non-Catholic readers with a set of challenging theological and inter-religious options. What follows in this chapter intends to affirm, to interact with and, in places, to complement and even expand aspects of Panikkar’s thought.¹ Apart from occasional hints, critical comment is reserved for the next chapter. There are, of course, Protestants who are wholly sympathetic with, for example, the radical pluralism advocated by Panikkar. But, on the whole, even academic Protestants who are concerned about interreligious issues are likely either to be unacquainted with his writings or unappreciative of his thought—despite his very considerable reputation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>The Great Tradition Ruptured?</title>
                     <subtitle>A Constructive Interaction and Critique</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBINSON</surname>
                           <given-names>BOB</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before further engagement with Panikkar’s thought, it is important to note one problem presented by the reality that Panikkar’s large body of writing spans a period in excess of fifty years: any attempted summary or survey is difficult, given the evolving nature of his thought. The difficulty is compounded by one of the logically prior challenges of making sense of Panikkar: the idiosyncratic relationship between the publishing dates of Panikkar’s books and other writings and the actual genesis of their content. At times, this makes it difficult to understand the development of Panikkar’s thought, even about a single issue. Nonetheless,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>A Concluding Dialogue about Panikkar between the Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RANSTROM</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBINSON</surname>
                           <given-names>BOB</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There were more than several instances in the preceding chapters of recognizing in the style and sensibility of a colleague from the Protestant tradition an echo of my own perspective, although I will save ecumenical insights for the next sections. Bob’s well-formulated summary of the objections against christocentrism as a theological method neatly encapsulates what I, and others, see as a widespread cultural aversion to the<italic>living heart</italic>of the Great Tradition. It is incumbent upon theologians whose task comes forth from the corporate identity of the church to theologize in such a way as to draw others towards the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Permissions List</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7h06.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
