<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h09qg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC571.P52 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human rights</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United Nations. General Assembly. Universal Declaration of Human Rights.</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Philosophical Theory and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sweet</surname>
               <given-names>William</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2003</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776616728</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776616722</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2003</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ckpdx6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Philosophical Theory and the Universal Declaration of Human Rights</italic>examines the relations and interrelations among theoretical and practical analyses of human rights. Edited by William Sweet, this volume draws on the works of philosophers, political theorists and those involved in the implementation of human rights. The essays, although diverse in method and approach, collectively argue that the language of rights and corresponding legal and political instruments have an important place in contemporary social political philosophy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sweet</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>THEORIES OF RIGHTS AND POLITICAL AND LEGAL INSTRUMENTS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sweet</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his famous lecture “The Rights of Man,”¹ the French philosopher Jacques Maritain draws attention to a remarkable event which occurred shortly after the end of the Second World War. Despite the diversity of interests, histories, cultures, politics, and ideologies, nations from every part of the planet were able to agree on a list of universal human rights. And for the more than fifty years since, the United Nations Universal Declaration of Human Rights (UDHR) of 1948 and the rights it enumerates have played a central role in calls for justice, equality, and the respect of human dignity throughout the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>One</label>
                     <title>NATURAL LAW AND NATURAL RIGHTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kainz</surname>
                           <given-names>Howard P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First, I want to discuss some terms. “Natural rights” and “human rights” are closely related but not synonyms. Natural rights are connected with natural law theory and encompass human rights. If something is considered a natural right, it is also a human right. Not every proponent of human rights subscribes to natural law theory, however. From this perspective, it is false to say that if something is a human right, it is also a natural right. Although we expect a broad convergence of rights agreed on from both perspectives, divergences may occur.</p>
                     <p>Also, “natural rights” should be distinguished from “natural</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Two</label>
                     <title>THE ETHICAL BACKGROUND OF THE RIGHTS OF WOMEN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hutton</surname>
                           <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dictionary definitions are often historically revealing. The term “right” as used in the expression “human rights” is usually understood as some kind of entitlement or “privilege.” The term has both legal and ethical connotations. According to the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>, a right is a “justifiable claim, on legal or moral grounds, to have or obtain something, or to act in a certain way” or “a legal, equitable or moral title or claim to the possession of property or authority.”¹ What is right is also just. The legality and moral value of rights is implied in the definition of “right” as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Three</label>
                     <title>ECONOMIC RIGHTS AND PHILOSOPHICAL ANTHROPOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Armour</surname>
                           <given-names>Leslie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the Universal Declaration of Human Rights was put forth a little over fifty years ago, there was a rough division of the world in two – and a rough division of the proclaimed rights into two groups. Traditional personal rights and liberties fell into one group and what came to be known as economic rights fell into the other. But in between were what might be called “social rights,” and blurring these perhaps permitted both sides to feel that they had done rough justice to the ideas of the other.</p>
                     <p>Though both groups were able to agree on the Declaration,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Four</label>
                     <title>T. H. GREEN ON RIGHTS AND THE COMMON GOOD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>Rex</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>T.H. Green’s posthumously published<italic>Lectures on the Principles of Political Obligation</italic>(1886) is one of the finest books in the philosophy of rights to date. In it, Green emphasized two distincf elements of rights: the requirement of social recognition and the idea of a common good. But this leads to a tension in his theory. Either of the two principal elements could plausibly be said to exist in the absence of the other. Where this happens, or could happen, does the element that stands alone lose all claim to the status of a right? An attempted resolution of this potential</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Five</label>
                     <title>A POSTSECULAR EXCHANGE:</title>
                     <subtitle>JACQUES MARITAIN, JOHN DEWEY, AND KARL MARX</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jeannot</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Suppose a conversation among three humanists from the recent modern past could be staged: namely, Jacques Maritain (1882–1973), a principal figure in the twentieth-century revival of Thomism and a leading Catholic philosopher; John Dewey (1859–1952), the American pragmatist and ambivalent apologist for liberalism; and Karl Marx (1818–83), founder of modern communism and the most trenchant critic of the capitalist mode of production. What might it contribute to the way we understand our contemporary situation? A successful conversation does not require complete agreement as its outcome, but it can lead to what Hans-Georg Gadamer called a “fusion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Six</label>
                     <title>HUMAN RIGHTS:</title>
                     <subtitle>FIFTY YEARS LATER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Faghfoury</surname>
                           <given-names>Mostafa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are, at least, two general ways of viewing humanity. On one account, humanity is a single entity which encompasses the whole human species: past, present, and future. On this account, whether humanity is created by God or has evolved, each person has a single origin, lives with others, forms communities, thinks and reasons, and aims for a common good.</p>
                     <p>The Persian poet Sa’di (1212–92) summarized this view of the humanity in the following verses.</p>
                     <p>All members of each other are mankind</p>
                     <p>Since all of one sole ore have been refined</p>
                     <p>One member’s pain of body, heart or mind</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Seven</label>
                     <title>THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS, MARITAIN, AND THE UNIVERSALITY OF HUMAN RIGHTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Munro</surname>
                           <given-names>Bradley R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Universal Declaration of Human Rights (UDHR) was proclaimed by the General Assembly of the United Nations on 10 December 1948. That the Universal Declaration could be proclaimed by a body representative of most of the world’s states is a remarkable achievement and worthy of celebration in this so-called postmodern world. Indeed, most of the states that since joined the General Assembly have also endorsed the UDHR. Truly remarkable about this tremendous achievement is the UDHR embracing a whole series of principles and value statements that define what constitutes human dignity. The world has an exceedingly rich array of cultures,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Eight</label>
                     <title>THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS IN THE SUPREME COURT OF CANADA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Iwanicki</surname>
                           <given-names>Jack</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Universal Declaration of Human Rights (UDHR), passed by the General Assembly fifty years ago, is an international document of immense importance. That importance could be developed and examined along a number of dimensions to gain an over all appreciation of its significance. I suggest considering it along the political, moral, educational, and legal dimensions. My plan for this chapter is to discuss briefly the first three dimensions, but then concentrate on the legal. More specifically, I plan to examine in detail cases that have come before the Supreme Court of Canada since the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Nine</label>
                     <title>HUMAN RIGHTS AND THE SURVIVAL IMPERATIVE:</title>
                     <subtitle>RWANDA’S TROUBLED LEGACY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lancaster</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We can understand the enthusiasm of the drafters of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights (United Nations General Assembly resolution 217A of 10 December 1948) by considering the historical context of their deliberations. After two cataclysmic global wars, the psychological urge to peace may have overwhelmed philosophical reservations that might have prolonged debate indefinitely.¹ Some may even have been blind to the weakness of the Kantian logic that I believe is clearly evident in the preamble or may have found their own reasons to support it.² The diplomatic bargaining involved in composing a declaration to which all could agree is,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Ten</label>
                     <title>RECONCILING INDIVIDUAL RIGHTS AND THE COMMON GOOD:</title>
                     <subtitle>AQUINAS AND CONTEMPORARY LAW</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Groarke</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>West</surname>
                           <given-names>J.L.A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following paper is divided into three sections. The first section briefly reviews the history of the concept of rights and its significance in the ongoing debate between liberals and communitarians. The contemporary literature has overlooked the possibility of constructing a theory of rights on Thomistic principles, which would reconcile individual rights with the common good. The second section reviews Aquinas’s position with respect to unjust laws in the<italic>Summa Theologiae</italic>and draws attention to the prominence of the principle of equality in his discussion. This principle is sufficient to provide the basis for a viable theory of individual rights</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Eleven</label>
                     <title>MODERATING THE PHILOSOPHY OF RIGHTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nelson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ralph</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Surely one of the most remarkable occurrences in the last half of the twentieth century was the revival of human–formerly natural–rights theory. The Universal Declaration of Human Rights of 1948; the emergence of notions of human rights in political philosophy, especially liberal political philosophy; the use of the rhetoric of rights in international relations; the entrenchment of rights in the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms; and last, but not least, the adoption by Pope John Paul II of the language of human rights bear testimony to this renewed interest.</p>
                     <p>We know that declarations may not be followed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Twelve</label>
                     <title>MACINTYRE OR GEWIRTH?</title>
                     <subtitle>VIRTUE, RIGHTS, AND THE PROBLEM OF MORAL INDETERMINACY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walters</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the history of Western ethics, we find both the teleological approach, exemplified by Aristotle’s ethics of virtues, and the deontological approach, heralded by Kant’s ethics of duty, rule-utilitarianism, and divine will/command conceptions of morality. Usually, we assume that these two approaches are incompatible and we must follow either the “good” or the “right.”¹ In this essay, I am concerned with what I believe is the most significant contemporary manifestation of the virtue-rights debate. Alasdair Maclntyre’s work in virtue ethics is now well known, but rarely discussed is Maclntyre’s critique of Alan Gewirth’s theory of morality as a theory of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Thirteen</label>
                     <title>UNIVERSAL HUMAN RIGHTS, CONCEPTS OF OWNERSHIP, AND ABORIGINAL LAND CLAIMS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lea</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Article 17 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights states, “Everyone has a right to own property alone as well as in association with others.” Though the UN has thrown its weight behind a universal right to property, the bare assertion of a right to property needs further clarification. This assertion certainly means that these rights should be recognized by all states, regardless of their conventions and local legislation. We can also say that this means such rights are independent of the established legislation (“positive law”) of a particular country, in that these rights possess a legitimacy that is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Fourteen</label>
                     <title>SOLIDARITY AND HUMAN RIGHTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sweet</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word “solidarity” and the call to solidarity are familiar to us all. “Solidarity” reminds many of us of the trade union movement that arose in 1980 in opposition to the Polish government, whose leader Lech Walesa was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1983 and whose actions were instrumental in the collapse of totalitarian regimes in Central and Eastern Europe. And for some four decades, the term “solidarity” and the call to be “in solidarity” have been uttered wherever we find those in need–the poor, the oppressed, and the marginalized.</p>
                     <p>Now, we might ask, how is it that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckpdx6.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
