<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Travellers' Tales of Wonder</book-title>
         <subtitle>Chatwin, Naipaul, Sebald</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cooke</surname>
               <given-names>Simon</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748675463</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748675470</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748675477</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Simon Cooke</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt3fgtg6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Exploring travellers’ tales of wonder in contemporary literature, this study challenges a sensibility of disenchantment with travel. It reassesses travel writing as an aesthetically and ethically innovative form in contemporary international literature, and demonstrates the crucial role of wonder in the travel narratives of writers such as Bruce Chatwin, V.S. Naipaul, and W.G. Sebald. Their ‘travellers’ tales of wonder’ are read as a challenge to the hubris of thinking the world too well known, and an invitation to encounter the world – including its most troubling histories – with a sense of wonder.Key FeaturesReassesses the place of travel writing in literary history to argue that the genre is important as a site of aesthetic innovation and ethical engagement in contemporary literatureDemonstrates the central role of wonder in travel accounts often regarded as narratives of disenchantmentExplores the way travellers’ tales of wonder recover and renew ancient and early modern forms in approaching modern and contemporary issuesOffers new, in-depth readings of the work of three major writers, in each case drawing on as yet unpublished results of archival research</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="216"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Wonder that Came Later</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To speak of travellers’ tales of wonder in late twentieth-century literature may well strike some as oxymoronic, anachronistic, quaint: more tall tale than area of inquiry. Already at the end of the thirteenth century, the ‘wise and learned citizen of Venese’ (Polo 1938: 73) was beginning to tire of accounts of the Provinces. What promise for wonder voyaging, then, when the idiom of the ‘global village’ (McLuhan 1988: 28-31) itself rings overly familiar? Travellers’ tales of wonder belong, according to most accounts, in bygone ages: to Messer Polo; to the medieval Wonder Book; to Columbus and Ralegh and the first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>A Question of Form:</title>
                     <subtitle>Genre and the Journey</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Voyages and travels are among the oldest and most culturally widespread forms in literary history. Among the earliest extant texts is a traveller’s tale of an island of marvels, ‘The Shipwrecked Sailor’ (Tappan 1914: 41–6), written in Egypt’s Twelfth Dynasty (that is, around 2200 bce). The journey is the common denominator for accounts as varied as<italic>The Histories</italic>of the ancient Greek Herodotus, Egeria’s pilgrimage to the Holy Land in the fourth century ce, the writings of household-name scientists such as Charles Darwin with<italic>Voyage of the Beagle</italic>and works by canonical literary authors such as Henry James, with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>‘An End to Journeying’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Travel and its Discontents in Late Modernity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘An End to Journeying’: thus the often-cited, era-defining title – part injunction, part lament – of the first part of Claude Lévi-Strauss’<italic>Tristes tropiques</italic>, his seminal anthropological memoir (and, indeed, travel account) of his years in South America. First published in 1955, it was translated from French into English by John Russell in 1961 with the substantially inaccurate, and thus all the more telling, title of<italic>A World on the Wane</italic>. The combative, exasperated, self-chastising opening sentences – ‘I hate travelling and explorers. Yet here I am proposing to tell the story of my expeditions’ (Lévi-Strauss 1976: 15) – launches</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Forms of Recovery and Renewal:</title>
                     <subtitle>Travels in Contemporary Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It might at first appear an irony: the peak in anxieties about the end of travel coincides, almost exactly, with what has been described as the ‘renaissance of the travel book’ (see for example, Graves 2003). But this convergence in the late 1970s and 1980s is more likely an expression of a broad literary and cultural engagement with questions of travel in a world increasingly on the move, increasingly interconnected. The publication of Bruce Chatwin’s<italic>In Patagonia</italic>in 1977, alongside that of Patrick Leigh Fermor’s<italic>A Time of Gifts</italic>, is often given as the literary historical moment in which travel</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Bruce Chatwin and the ‘modern WONDER VOYAGE’:</title>
                     <subtitle>In Patagonia (1977)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Bruce Chatwin published an account of a journey to a part of the world which had come to symbolise, in the Western cultural imagination, the distance to which ‘one travels no more’, it appeared as both novelty and relic, at once literary newfoundland and lost world regained. As its premise was the mythically resonant, marvellously unlikely quest for a replacement for a scrap of Giant Sloth skin which the traveller had gazed upon in wonder as a child in his grandmother’s cabinet of curiosities, believing it to be a ‘piece of brontosaurus’, and which had been discarded after her</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>V. S. Naipaul and the ‘gift of wonder’:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Enigma of Arrival (1987)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If Chatwin’s<italic>In Patagonia</italic>had dazzled into literary consciousness an idea that ‘Patagonia’ as place and figurative possibility may still inspire, or require, wonder in the contemporary world, then V. S. Naipaul’s<italic>The Enigma of Arrival</italic>is the late twentieth century’s most exemplary and subtle monument to the idea that ‘after Patagonia’ there do indeed remain strange, distant and mysterious places in the world: ‘unknown Wiltshire’ (Naipaul 2002: 111), for example, deep in the archipelago of the British Isles. Before we even begin to explore<italic>The Enigma of Arrival</italic>as a text which both unflinchingly portrays and profoundly questions a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>W. G. Sebald’s Travels through ‘das unentdeckte Land’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Die Ringe des Saturn (1995)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It seems fitting for a study in contemporary literary history to culminate in a reading of W. G. Sebald. The body of work he brought into expression from the late 1980s through to his death in a car accident in 2001, not far from his adopted home of some twenty years near Norwich, England, was itself a culmination, the harvest of a long personal apprenticeship: a German émigré, Sebald had been active as an academic in England since the 1960s, and was a professor of European literature at the University of East Anglia when his first major ‘non-academic’ work, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>The ‘unlimited vicissitudes of travelling’</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study began with a consideration of dimensions of the literary and cultural horizon of expectations that are often brought to bear when encountering travels in contemporary literature; that is, what we may bring with us upon ‘arrival’. Before closing, it may be appropriate to offer a consideration of what we take with us when we ‘leave’. The question is not so much, as is often the case in studies in travel writing, ‘where next?’ This study has attempted to question a model of reading travels as exclusively or primarily documents of geographical discovery, rendered precarious by the increasingly full</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgtg6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
