<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7p3tx</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Verse and Voice in Byrd's Song Collections of 1588 and 1589</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Smith</surname>
               <given-names>Jeremy L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781783270828</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782047407</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Woodbridge, Suffolk, UK; Rochester, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jeremy L. Smith</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt1bh49c3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>As he grappled with the challenges of composing for various instrumental and vocal ensembles, William Byrd (c. 1540-1623), England's premier Renaissance composer, devoted considerable attention to the poetry and prose of his native language, producing such treasured masterpieces as the hauntingly beautiful "Lulla lullaby"; the infectiously comedic "Though Amarillis dance in green"; and two extraordinarily dramatic Easter anthems. This book, the first full-length study specifically devoted to Byrd's English-texted music, provides a close reading of all of the works he published in the late 1580s, constituting nearly half of his total song output. It delves into the musical, political, literary, and, specifically, the sequential qualities of Byrd's 1588 and 1589 published collections as a whole, revealing, explaining, and interpreting an overall grand narrative, while remaining fully attentive to the particularities of each individual piece. Often deemed "unliterary" and generally considered political only in his approach to Latin texts, which were often of special interest to his fellow Catholics, Byrd was not only an inspired composer who had mastered the challenges of his nation's burgeoning verse, but also one who used his voice in song to foster a more inclusive polity in a time of religious strife. Jeremy L. Smith is Associate Professor of Musicology at the University of Colorado Boulder.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="337"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Music Examples</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Editorial Conventions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1588, the year of England’s triumph over the formidable Spanish Armada, a Catholic composer, William Byrd (c. 1540–1623) – the leading figure in the Queen’s Protestant chapel – brought out a collection of thirty-five songs he entitled<italic>Psalmes, Sonets, &amp; songs</italic>(BE 12).¹ Within the next three years he would also publish, along with two impressive sets of Latin-texted motets, an additional forty-seven numbered English-texted<italic>Songs of sundrie natures</italic>(BE 13) (see Figs. 1 and 2). Byrd was not the first Elizabethan composer to venture into print with a set of songs. Thomas Whythorne published his<italic>Songes for Three</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Psalmes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the ten songs of his opening section of the<italic>Psalmes, Sonets</italic>, &amp;<italic>songs</italic>of 1588, with which we begin, Byrd offered the strongest evidence that the overall message of this sequence was at least in part a personal one – or that he wished to make that impression. As Rivkah Zim explains, “sixteenth-century commentators encouraged individuals to recognize representations of their own experiences and emotions in psalms, and to use them as models for personal prayer and meditation.”¹ Byrd may have originally set these psalms to music for other people and other purposes – although at least one appears to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Sonets &amp; Pastoralls, I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The middle section of Byrd’s<italic>Psalmes, Sonets</italic>, &amp;<italic>songs of sadnes and pietie</italic>, with sixteen songs (BE 12: 11–26), is the longest of the set. On the title page Byrd labeled the works “sonets” (BE 12, p. xli) but at the opening and ending of the section he added the word “pastoralls” (BE 12: 11) in describing them again. Neither term was used very precisely at the time, but the latter proves to be slightly more helpful, as only two songs in the section are sonnets (BE 12: 18 and BE 12: 20) whereas more, although by no means all,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Sonets &amp; Pastoralls, II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The four works of the “sonets” section on temperance, discussed in the previous chapter, form a clearly defined set that comes to a satisfying close, at least in terms of structure and narrative. Yet there are some issues evoked within them that would resonate into the next series. In the key poem of that earlier group, “Who likes to love” (BE 12: 13), Cupid was ousted from his throne because of his “love for golde” (l. 24). The gods then granted some women whom Cupid had abused a “longer day” (l. 21) to “devise” (i.e., decide, l. 22) who should</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Sonets &amp; Pastoralls, III</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is not uniquely postmodernist to contend that women can be magnificent and men can be chaste. Elizabethans believed this as well. The character Marinell of the<italic>Faerie Queene</italic>, who avoids love out of fear, represents, for example, a virginal chaste man in Edmund Spenser’s epic poem.¹ Elizabeth Talbot, aka Bess of Hardwick, commissioned a full set of tapestries depicting women who exemplified a number of virtues.² In his epitaph for Mary Queen of Scots, which was mounted on her tomb, the Byrd patron Henry Howard, first Earl of Northampton, championed his subject above all for her magnanimity and chastised</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Songs of sadnes and pietie</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the title page of his<italic>Psalmes, sonets and songs</italic>Byrd described the third section of the book as “songs of sadnes and pietie” (BE 12., p. xli). Here, as elsewhere, Byrd’s title does not serve as a completely reliable guide to the nature of the set’s contents. It might easily be assumed that the phrase “sadness and piety” applies to all nine songs in this final section, but a cursory study of the poems suggests that five songs are devoted to “piety” (BE 12: 27–31) and four to “sadness” (BE 12: 32–35) – reversing the topic order</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Songs of Three Parts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preface to his<italic>Songs of sundrie natures</italic>of 1589 Byrd celebrates the success of his<italic>Psalmes, Sonets</italic>,<italic>&amp; songs</italic>of 1588 – its “good passage and utterance” (BE 13, p. xxxvii) – and offers this happy outcome as his rationale for publishing another set of music of a similar vein. In 1588 he could describe all the works therein as originally composed for a single voice and (four) instruments, although he makes sure to note that he has added texts to all the parts in the edition. As they were so consistent in their scoring and, to some extent,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Songs of Four Parts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the songs à 4 of the 1589<italic>Songs of sundrie natures</italic>Byrd’s auditor approaches the middle portions of an intricate sequential narrative. Already in the á 3 section Byrd had moved his audience from the great “gravitie” of penitential psalms through images of Mary Queen of Scots and Christ, only to settle in the mischievously “myrth[ful],” but ultimately innocent, world of Anacreontic Love (to quote from Byrd’s title page, BE 13, p. xxxv). This was a complex enough path, but in the section of songs in four parts, to abide by Peter Brooks’s claims about a good narrative, before</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Songs of Five Parts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we begin our discussion of Byrd’s songs of five parts, the penultimate segment of his<italic>Songs of sundrie natures</italic>, it is worth noting that one of the composer’s proclivities, as a sequence maker, was to provide effective transitions as he moved from section to section. The songs of three parts, for example, ended with “The greedy hawk” (BE 13: 14) seemingly posing the question: Will Cupid strike? In the first four-voiced song, “Is love a boy?” (BE 13: 15), Byrd confirmed that this was indeed the question, and that it would later be answered affirmatively.</p>
                     <p>Byrd uses similar tactics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Songs of Six Parts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we move into the final section of Byrd’s<italic>Songs of sundrie natures</italic>it is worth stepping back from the topical stories discussed thus far, involving Mary Queen of Scots and Sir Philip Sidney, to note that this is a collection that begins with biblical material in the songs in three parts and ends with a six-voiced depiction of the Resurrection, in “Christ rising again” | “Christ is risen again” (BE 13: 46–47). It is, in many ways, a satisfying way to draw things to a close, the gradual shift from few to many voices representing a long but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With his setting of Amen at the end of “Christ is risen again” (BE 13: 47) Byrd brought a long story told through song to a stirring conclusion, evoking finally Christ’s much-anticipated triumph over the devil and death with a resonant moment of intense counterpoint. To achieve this effect Byrd revised the last phrase of his original version as he prepared this particular section of music for publication. But, for all the special effort here, it is fair to claim that Byrd, as he brought each and every one of his songs to a close, was aware that in certain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Byrd’s Songs from the 1588 and 1589 Collections</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh49c3.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
