<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B3279.H49B75 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Heidegger, Martin, 1889–1976</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Languages</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Heidegger's Estrangements</book-title>
         <subtitle>Language, Truth, and Poetry in the Later Writings</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bruns</surname>
               <given-names>Gerald L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>1989</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300044201</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300237535</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1989</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xp3sjh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book concerns the relationship between language and poetry in Heidegger's later writings, the texts collected in his<italic>Unterwegs zur Sprache</italic>(On the Way to Language). Gerald L. Bruns illuminates these difficult and strange writings by analyzing Heidegger's style and form and by reflecting on the philosopher's central insights into the non-humanness of language.</p>
         <p>According to Bruns, the strangeness of Heidegger's later writings is a deliberate attempt to expose philosophy to what it cannot contain within its powers of description and explanation. Heidegger takes poetry more seriously than any philosopher since Plato, says Bruns. In his texts on language and poetry he reappropriates the ancient notion of poetry as enigma, the impermeable text that resists our efforts to lay bare its meaning or structure. What matters to Heidegger in these writings, Bruns explains, is the rift between poetry and thinking., where each is said to repose in its own darkness. Poetry moves thinking away from philosophy by turning the thinker into a wanderer, closer to listening than to reasoning, more at home with puns than with concepts. Bruns shows this to be no less true of Heidegger's later writings as he examines them for the way they resist conventional methods of reading.</p>
         <p>This book will be helpful not only to students of Heidegger's philosophy but also to literary critics who are interested in the uses of language and poetry.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="233"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                     <subtitle>From the Orphic to the Hermetic with Heidegger</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>Understanding Heidegger</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My purpose in what follows will simply be to work through Martin Heidegger’s later writings on language and poetry in order to give as clear an account as I can of what he has to say, as well as of the way in which his “saying” has to be enclosed in quotation marks. As Habermas says, “Communication does not belong to the basic vocabulary of this philosophy.”¹ By “work through” I mean roughly, or loosely, what my discipline calls a close reading that lends special attention to the language of the dark or recalcitrant text. So what follows is also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>The Aesthetics of Estrangement:</title>
                     <subtitle>Heidegger on the Work of Art</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the first temptation in taking up Heidegger’s notion of language is to read<italic>Being and Time</italic>as a foundational text, the second is to leap immediately from<italic>Being and Time</italic>to the essays in<italic>Unterwegs zur Sprache</italic>in which Heidegger at last brings the question of language up for reflection. But if we want to understand the relation of language and poetry in Heidegger’s thinking, we need to start differently.¹</p>
                     <p>For me the crucial text for the study of the later Heidegger is “The Origin of the Work of Art,” in which language is hardly mentioned. This is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>The Step Back:</title>
                     <subtitle>Heidegger’s Uncanny Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Plato’s<italic>Euthyphro</italic>(11b-e) Socrates compares words to the statues of Daedalus, which were said to be so lifelike that they had to be restrained like slaves, because they kept trying to escape. Untethered words wander around aimlessly, whence we get our concept of ambiguity or the waywardness of discourse. However, the tying down of one’s words is not easy. In fact, sometimes Socrates makes it sound like the question is all that can be justifiably put into words. For the rest one should keep silent, or speak only in the most guarded fashion, darkly, and then perhaps only of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>The Abandonment of Philosophical Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question remains, or continues to draw us out: What is it to speak? That is, what is it for speaking to occur when no one speaks but only language? “Language speaks [<italic>Die Sprache spricht</italic>].” We are very far from understanding what this can mean. All we can say is that Heidegger encourages us, allows us, to think of speaking in terms of calling rather than as signifying. But where does this leave us?</p>
                     <p>In the last chapter I tried to show that what matters is what comes to stand in front of the call, not what lies behind it,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>The Poetic Experience with Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One therapeutic effect of Heidegger’s first essay on language is that it disconnects us—estranges or alienates us—from the very idea of language, especially as this comes down to us in idealist and analytic philosophies of language, linguistics, semiotics, various criticisms, and so on; and this also means alienation from what we might call the social theory of language, where the idea is not to retrieve the deep grammatical, semantic, or propositional structure of human expression, but just to study how people talk, what they say when, their language games, their discursive practices and institutions, their forms of life.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Words and Sounds in Heidegger</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I said at the end of the last chapter that “thinking needs to link itself up with poetry,” but obviously this is a careless way of talking — and misleading in the bargain, especially if we go on to imagine that if language cannot avail itself to us logically, then it must do so preconceptually, intuitively, practically, or by some primordial process of knowing that logic might subsequently come along to verify; but this isn’t what Heidegger is talking about at all. It is not that there are, for example, two categories of mental operation, one primitive and one enlightened, one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>Otherwise than Language</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What goes on in the writings of the later Heidegger cannot truthfully be called a reasoning of any sort. From the standpoint of progressive, systematic, calculative thinking, it is certain to appear repetitious, opaque, pointless or unproductive. It is not (like this book) an attempt to get straight about anything. It may not even be the sort of thinking that Heidegger talks about in What is Called Thinking? And no one who had ever given a thought to poetry would call it poetry. One could call it, loosely, reflection, but Heidegger would probably say that it doesn’t need to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                     <subtitle>The Dark Comic World of Martin Heidegger</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The folly of trying to follow closely Heidegger’s thinking, I mean his later writings, comes out very forcefully when you try to stop, because there is no natural stopping place, no place of arrival where everything falls into place and you can say, “Well now that’s done: and I’m glad it’s over.” Instead, the movement you get into is that of going back over what has been said in order to pick up on what is missing or what has been left out of account. So you are always starting over with something familiar, and then going astray as you</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sjh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
