<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">FC2945.S2274A23 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion and sociology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Québec (Province)</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Saint-Joseph-de-Beauce</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Saint-Joseph-de-Beauce (Québec)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Church history</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Saint-Joseph-de-Beauce (Québec)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Saint-Joseph-de-Beauce (Québec)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Church and state</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Québec (Province)</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Body or the Soul?</book-title>
         <subtitle>Religion and Culture in a Quebec Parish, 1736-1901</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ABBOTT</surname>
               <given-names>FRANK A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773599161</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773599169</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Chicago</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d9892h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>There are many analyses of Tractarianism – a nineteenth-century form of Anglicanism that emphasized its Catholic origins – but how did people in the colonies react to the High Church movement? Beating against the Wind, a study in nineteenth-century vernacular spirituality, emphasizes the power of faith on a shifting frontier in a transatlantic world. Focusing on people living along the Newfoundland and Labrador coast, Calvin Hollett presents a nuanced perspective on popular resistance to the colonial emissary Bishop Edward Feild and his spiritual regimen of order, silence, and solemnity. Whether by outright opposing Bishop Feild, or by simply ignoring his wishes and views, or by brokering a hybrid style of Gothic architecture, the people of Newfoundland and Labrador demonstrated their independence in the face of an attempt at hierarchical ascendency upon the arrival of Tractarianism in British North America. Instead, they continued to practise evangelical Anglicanism and participate in Methodist revivals, and thereby negotiated a popular Protestantism, one often infused with the spirituality of other seafarers from Nova Scotia and New England. Exploring the interaction between popular spirituality and religious authority, Beating against the Wind challenges the traditional claim of Feild’s success in bringing Tractarianism to the colony while exploring the resistance to Feild’s initiatives and the reasons for his disappointments.There are many analyses of Tractarianism – a nineteenth-century form of Anglicanism that emphasized its Catholic origins – but how did people in the colonies react to the High Church movement? Beating against the Wind, a study in nineteenth-century vernacular spirituality, emphasizes the power of faith on a shifting frontier in a transatlantic world. Focusing on people living along the Newfoundland and Labrador coast, Calvin Hollett presents a nuanced perspective on popular resistance to the colonial emissary Bishop Edward Feild and his spiritual regimen of order, silence, and solemnity. Whether by outright opposing Bishop Feild, or by simply ignoring his wishes and views, or by brokering a hybrid style of Gothic architecture, the people of Newfoundland and Labrador demonstrated their independence in the face of an attempt at hierarchical ascendency upon the arrival of Tractarianism in British North America. Instead, they continued to practise evangelical Anglicanism and participate in Methodist revivals, and thereby negotiated a popular Protestantism, one often infused with the spirituality of other seafarers from Nova Scotia and New England. Exploring the interaction between popular spirituality and religious authority, Beating against the Wind challenges the traditional claim of Feild’s success in bringing Tractarianism to the colony while exploring the resistance to Feild’s initiatives and the reasons for his disappointments.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Figures and Tables</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Habitants and Religion in Nineteenth-Century Québec</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his well-known mid-nineteenth-century painting,<italic>Breaking Lent</italic>, the Dutch-born artist Cornelius Krieghoff (1815–1872) depicted half a dozen members of a nineteenth-century habitant family at table in their rudely furnished cabin. They are consuming a forbidden Lenten meal of meat during the Catholic Church’s forty-day period of obligatory fasting and abstinence before Easter. Into the room strides the formidable Father Brassard, the parish priest in Longueuil, on the south shore of the St Lawrence River across from Montréal, where Krieghoff himself was living between 1845 and 1848. The curé has just arrived unannounced to discover the family guiltily hiding the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Development and Transformation:</title>
                     <subtitle>St-Joseph-de-Beauce, 1736–1901</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the end of a long journey from Québec City, the lawyer and legislative councillor Henri-Elzéar Juchereau-Duchesnay (1809–71), related by marriage to the powerful Taschereau family of nearby Ste-Marie, confessed to being most unimpressed with the small rural parish of St-Joseph-de-Beauce.¹ It was near the end of the 1850s when he saw the collection of whitewashed houses and commercial establishments in the centre of the parish. He remarked somewhat scathingly that the village, “if one could give that name to a dozen scattered houses,” offered few advantages and had many disadvantages compared to Ste-Marie.² The most notable feature of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Render unto God:</title>
                     <subtitle>Buildings and Belief</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One should really only approach the striking architectural panorama of St-Joseph-de-Beauce from the west. The more direct highway 73 running south from Québec City passes behind the village so that a traveller arrives by the back door and misses the full effect of the buildings. The more indirect route from the west takes longer. It begins east from Montreal on the TransCanada / Autoroute Jean Lesage (Highway 20) and, once past the exit to Trois-Rivières, the traveller looks for Highway 165, which branches off through the Appalachians in the direction of Thetford Mines. From there Highway 112 passes through communities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Ministering to a Rural Parish:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Curés of St-Joseph, 1761–1901</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No study of the role of religion in a small rural parish such as St-Joseph can proceed very far without looking at the place of the parish priest in the community. Surveyor General Joseph Bouchette observed in 1831 that the parish priests in Lower Canada were honoured members of their communities. They were, he said, “labourious in their duties, frugal in their living, decorous in their manners; possessed of much intelligence, and some learning, they are gentle, modest, and benevolent.”¹ Likewise, Lucien Lemieux found, in the period 1760–1840, that out of 700 priests who served in Québec only 60</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“Holy Water and Candles”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Catholicism in St-Joseph</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Almost in the same breath as he described the independent nature of the habitants in 1830, the surgeon and author Pierre de Sales Laterrière (1789–1834) argued that the influence of Catholicism over the habitants was largely positive or at least harmless. Laterrière argued that the Church did not exercise untrammelled power or that “a complete subjection of the people has not taken place, and a grovelling superstition and furious bigotry” had not been introduced, even if many were mildly “superstitious”:</p>
                     <p>It may be said, and perhaps with truth, that the Canadian population are, for the most part, superstitious; but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Beliefs, Superstitions, and Popular Spirituality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Important as it was in the life of the parish, institutional Catholicism did not hold uncontested sway over the spiritual terrain of St-Joseph. A popular metaphysical world that constituted a significant sector of the mental universe of the habitants existed beside it, presenting both an alternative to and a reinforcement of the Church’s own teachings. Peter Moogk has observed that there is a fundamental difficulty for anyone today who tries to comprehend the mental and moral landscape of New France, one that was very much alive in nineteenth-century rural Québec. Our world is secular and materialistic and based on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Holy Water versus Fire Water:</title>
                     <subtitle>Habitant Sociability and the Curés</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Québec’s customary period of winter sociability, the<italic>temps des fêtes</italic>, lasting from Christmas to the start of Lent, is the ideal period for examining the link that many parish priests drew between the traditional celebrations of their parishioners and the difficulties that the Church encountered in attempting to transform them into more submissive Catholics. Studying the forms and meanings of this sociability enables us to understand how the habitants implicitly asserted some of the important secular values of their traditional way of life in the face of explicit and repeated clerical disapproval. As Ollivier Hubert has observed, French Canadian popular</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Sociability and Sexuality:</title>
                     <subtitle>“On danse pour le plaisir de danser”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In their annual reports to their superiors in Québec City during the last half of the nineteenth century, the curés in St-Joseph continuously lamented their inability to reduce, let alone prohibit, what they felt were the large number of evening parties, drinking, and dancing in the parish. The Reverend David Martineau noted in his 1854 report that dances and<italic>veillées</italic>were “still too frequent.”¹ His successor for the period 1856–68, James Nelligan, left no parish reports, and it is not possible to say whether such celebrations diminished, though it is unlikely. A week before Christmas in 1868, Nelligan’s successor,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Body and the Soul</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few if any of the clergymen who served the parish of St-Joseph-de-Beauce from the mid-eighteenth century to the start of the twentieth, and particularly after 1852, would have disputed the implication in Cornelius Krieghoff’s painting<italic>Breaking Lent</italic>that the temptations of their bodies were more important to the habitants than the salvation of their souls. On the surface, their sociable behaviour does indeed indicate that the parishioners of St-Joseph had much in common with their fellow French Canadians’ oft-noted propensity for celebration. Having looked beneath that surface, it is clear that their sociability had multilayered meanings that were not always</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                     <subtitle>“Questions, Rapports des Paroisses”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d9892h.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
