<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccm4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS2655.S23.P38 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sacrifice</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Biblical teaching</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Metaphor in the Bible</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible.Corinthians, 1st</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. Philippians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Keeping the Feast</book-title>
         <subtitle>Metaphors of Sacrifice in 1 Corinthians and Philippians</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Patterson</surname>
               <given-names>Jane Lancaster</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884140672</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884140665</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt17kk6wx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Develop a keener ear for Paul's rhetorical strategy</p>
         <p>Patterson uses cognitive metaphor theory to trace the apostle Paul's use of metaphors from the Jewish sacrificial system in his moral counsels to the Philippians and the Corinthians. In these letters, Paul moves from the known (the practice of sacrifice) to the unknown (how to live in accord with the life, death, and resurrection of Jesus Christ). Patterson illustrates that the significant sacrificial metaphors in 1 Corinthians and Philippians are not derived from Jewish sacrifices of atonement, but rather from the Passover and sacrifices of thanksgiving. Attention to these metaphors demonstrates that imagery drawn from these sacrifices shapes the overall moral counsel of the letters, reveals more varied and nuanced interpretations of sacrificial references in Paul's letters, and sheds light on Paul's continuity with Jewish cultic practice.</p>
         <p>Features</p>
         <p>Clarification of the strategic function of metaphors as a means of establishing an imaginative framework for ethical deliberationEvidence of Paul's active processes of theological reflectionExploration of the intertwining of Jewish cultic practice with the rhetoric of moral commitment within early Christian churches</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="218"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Metaphors and sacrifices have in common that they both turn one thing into something else. But what does it mean when all this alchemical power is combined in<italic>metaphors</italic>of<italic>sacrifice</italic>? Paul’s metaphors have the power to turn bodies into temples, communities into fields. Sacrifices turn farm animals into smoke that reaches God in heaven, a pleasing odor for the divine. Metaphors drawn from the sacrificial system turn crucifixion into glory, shame into honor, death into life. This study of sacrificial metaphors in Philippians and 1 Corinthians is a revised version of my dissertation, presented at Southern Methodist University in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Sacrifice as Metaphor in Pauline Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Clearly, before any early Christian began to use metaphors of sacrifice in teaching or argumentation, there was the actual practice of sacrifice in Jewish and Greco-Roman worship. That statement may seem so obvious that it hardly bears mentioning, but the fact often becomes lost in Christian theologizing, in which the move from sacrificial practice to sacrificial metaphor has become obscured by what appears to be the givenness of the metaphor of sacrifice. While in the first century CE sacrifice was a<italic>familiar</italic>category that could be employed to explain the<italic>not-yet-understood</italic>implications of Jesus’s life and death for the Christian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Sacrifice as a Greco-Roman and Jewish Practice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While it makes sense logically that Paul might develop a language of temple and sacrifice that would be as valid for the Greco-Roman cults as for the Jewish cult, in fact part of what will become clear in chapter 6 is how Paul’s metaphors of temple and sacrifice in 1 Corinthians seem to have as their principal referent the Jewish cult in particular, and not a more generalized reference to ancient cults of all kinds.¹ It is the Jewish system of texts and practices in which Paul is a learned specialist. His expertise and authority are based in his experience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Sacrifice as an Object of Study</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sacrifice has been a widely practiced human act, various in its details, variously understood by those who have sought to explain it, and now almost unknown as an actual practice in developed countries. Most of those who have written on the subject would agree that sacrifice “means something” or “accomplishes something” beyond what is strictly observed, though most primary texts on sacrifice focus on what is<italic>done</italic>, not on what it<italic>means.</italic>J. H. M. Beattie wrote in 1980, “sacrificial ritual, like other rites, is a form of art, a drama, which is believed by its performers … to work.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Philippians:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sacrificial Giving</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relatively brief letter to the Philippians, consisting of only four chapters, offers a chance to try out the theory that attention to metaphors of sacrifice makes sense of the letter as a whole, especially as regards the ethics of life in Christ. The<italic>shelamim</italic>(or sacrifices of well-being) is the name given, in the Jewish tradition, to the basic form of sacrifice in the Hellenistic world, the commensal sacrifice. This sacrifice was often motivated by a spirit of thanksgiving or a desire to celebrate a feast with family and friends. Regarding the letter to the Philippians as a document</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>1 Corinthians:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Community That Keeps the Feast</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1 Cor 16:8, Paul says that he plans to stay in Ephesus until Pentecost (ἕως τῆς πεντεϰοστῆς). It is unclear how long before Pentecost he was writing,¹ but the number of metaphorical references to the Passover in 1 Corinthians suggests that that festival was near, and provided a background to his thinking about the situation in Corinth. In any case, just as metaphors of the sacrifices of thanksgiving (<italic>shelamim</italic>) appear to underlie much of Philippians, metaphors relating to the Passover appear to bring together a number of Paul’s counsels in 1 Corinthians, and to offer a set of associations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Conclusions, Romans, and a Look Ahead</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much of this work has concerned the<italic>resonance</italic>of metaphors and the importance of developing an<italic>ear</italic>for how it is that metaphors of sacrifice function in particular Pauline letters. So it is perhaps not out of line to make a comparison between Paul’s complex use of metaphors and something else that creates a very complicated, multi-layered sound.</p>
                     <p>In the late 1920s the American philanthropist Charles R. Crane made a trip to Russia on which he was exposed for the first time to the sound of the ringing of Russian church bells. Russian bells are neither made nor rung like</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Modern Authors Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk6wx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
