<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt147dpm1</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">wu--17160</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BQ1217.S77 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Buddhism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Sacred books</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Buddhism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Buddhist literature, Chinese</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Spreading Buddha's Word in East Asia</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Formation and Transformation of the Chinese Buddhist Canon</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wu</surname>
               <given-names>Jiang</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Chia</surname>
               <given-names>Lucille</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Yü</surname>
               <given-names>Chün-fang</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>series editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231540193</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231540191</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/wu--17160"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A monumental work in the history of religion, the history of the book, the study of politics, and bibliographical research, this volume follows the making of the Chinese Buddhist canon from the fourth century to the digital era. Approaching the subject from a historical perspective, the book ties the religious, social, and textual practices of canon formation to the development of East Asian Buddhist culture and opens up the study of Chinese Buddhist texts to readers interested in the evolution of Chinese writing in general and the Confucian and Daoist traditions in particular.</p>
         <p>The collection undertakes extensive readings of major scriptural catalogs from the early manuscript era as well as major printed editions, including the Kaibao Canon, Qisha Canon, Goryeo Canon, and Taisho Canon. Contributors add fascinating depth to such understudied issues as the historical process of compilation, textual manipulation, physical production and management, sponsorship, the dissemination of various editions, cultic activities surrounding the canon, and the canon's reception in different East Asian societies. The Chinese Buddhist canon is one of the most enduring textual traditions in East Asian religion and culture, and through this exhaustive, multifaceted effort, an essential body of work becomes part of a new, versatile narrative of East Asian Buddhism that has far-reaching implications for world history.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="432"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lancaster</surname>
                           <given-names>Lewis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>XI</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XVII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONVENTIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XIX</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wu</surname>
                           <given-names>Jiang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chia</surname>
                           <given-names>Lucille</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The importance of studying the historical development of a religious canon seems obvious. Equally obvious is the daunting challenge of trying to study the many aspects of an immense canon incorporating thousands of works. In the case of the Buddhist canon in Chinese, compiled and recompiled many times and transmitted throughout East Asia,¹ much research remains to be done, especially as the canon continues to evolve in the modern digital age of information. In this volume, we present nine articles of original research on the tradition of the Chinese Buddhist canon that exemplify new directions in studying and understanding the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>The Chinese Buddhist Canon Through the Ages:</title>
                     <subtitle>ESSENTIAL CATEGORIES AND CRITICAL ISSUES IN THE STUDY OF A TEXTUAL TRADITION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wu</surname>
                           <given-names>Jiang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Chinese Buddhist canon is an organized collection of Buddhist texts translated into or written in Chinese. Its main content centers on translated Buddhist works from Indian and Central Asian regions and is supplemented with Buddhist and related texts written in Chinese. In Buddhist communities, a complete set of the canon has also been treated as the object of worship and devotion, acquiring significant textual and spiritual authority. Because of the complexity of its structure and historical evolution, the formation and transformation of the Chinese Buddhist canon can be considered a phenomenon with religious, social, and textual significance in Buddhist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>From the “Cult of the Book” to the “Cult of the Canon”:</title>
                     <subtitle>A NEGLECTED TRADITION IN CHINESE BUDDHISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wu</surname>
                           <given-names>Jiang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the importance of the canon in Chinese Buddhism, it is still unclear how the making and remaking of a canon initiated new social, cultural, and religious transformations in Buddhist communities. Previous studies have overwhelmingly concentrated on the canon as a collection of sacred texts, without adequate attention to its actual use. It is often neglected that the canon as a whole has become a sacred object, allowing believers to form an intimate relationship through participating in a series of cultic practices.</p>
                     <p>In the history of Chinese Buddhism, the canon, which primarily contains translated texts and Chinese Buddhist writings, has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Notions and Visions of the Canon in Early Chinese Buddhism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zacchetti</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>All the various bodies of scriptures evoked by the name “Buddhist canon”—such as the Pali canon, the Tibetan canon, the Mongolian canon, and the Chinese canon, just to mention those surviving in a more or less complete form—are in fact very different things from the viewpoint of their internal structure and formative principles. They were shaped by different historical forces, in response to different cultural and political conditions. All these differences are partly masked by the use of unifying terms such as “canon,” “Tripitaka,” etc., to refer to these collections. If taken uncritically, all these designations are potentially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Fei Changfang’s Records of the Three Treasures Throughout the Successive Dynasties (Lidai sanbao ji 歷代三寶紀) and Its Role in the Formation of the Chinese Buddhist Canon</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Storch</surname>
                           <given-names>Tanya</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It can be argued that the proper history of the Chinese Buddhist canon begins with its printed editions because the printed format allows for easier access, wider dissemination, standardization of the contents, and preservation of textual stability. But before the earliest printed editions appeared, for a period of more than five hundred years, Chinese scholars zealously labored over the creation of the principles of textual criticism and taxonomic organization, which they applied to the handwritten canon and which eventually affected the contents and structure of the printed version. In the canon catalogs, various manuscripts of translated Buddhist texts, as well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>The Birth of the First Printed Canon:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE KAIBAO EDITION AND ITS IMPACT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wu</surname>
                           <given-names>Jiang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chia</surname>
                           <given-names>Lucille</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zhichao</surname>
                           <given-names>Chen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fourth year of the Kaibao 開寶 reign (971), Emperor Taizu (r. 960–975) of the Song Dynasty 宋太祖 ordered the first carving of a set of woodblocks for the Chinese Buddhist canon. Thus this edition is referred to as<italic>Kaibao Canon</italic>, or the Shu (i.e., Sichuan) edition (<italic>Shuban</italic>蜀版)—since it was collated and the blocks were carved in Sichuan. In 1127, Kaifeng, the Northern Song capital, was sacked by the invading Jurchens, who abducted the two emperors and carted off many treasures. The imperial libraries were looted and many of their books and woodblocks taken north. One</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>The Life and Afterlife of Qisha Canon (Qishazang 磧砂藏)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chia</surname>
                           <given-names>Lucille</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given the great size of the Chinese Buddhist canon—the printed editions of which usually comprise five to six thousand volumes (<italic>ce</italic>冊) in the traditional sutra binding—it is somewhat astounding to consider the low survival rate for both the woodblocks and the printed copies of these works. Between the tenth and fourteenth centuries, the Chinese Buddhist canon was printed in China in at least seven different woodblock editions, yet not one of them is extant in its entirety.¹ We are therefore fortunate to have, among the editions of the Chinese Buddhist canon printed in the Song and Yuan,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Managing the Dharma Treasure:</title>
                     <subtitle>COLLATION, CARVING, PRINTING, AND DISTRIBUTION OF THE CANON IN LATE IMPERIAL CHINA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Long</surname>
                           <given-names>Darui</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Chinese produced the first woodblock edition of the Buddhist canon during the early Song Dynasty (972–83), and over the next thousand years, more than thirteen other editions were carved. These are considered invaluable treasures in both the Chinese cultural heritage and Buddhist literature. Although many scholars today use<italic>Taishō Canon</italic>printed in modern movable type,¹ further research on the earlier woodblock editions will help us understand how the Chinese imperial court, Buddhist monks, and laypeople managed such a huge printing project.</p>
                     <p>The production of any edition of the Chinese Buddhist canon was a massive undertaking, requiring decades to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Better Than the Original:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CREATION OF GORYEO CANON AND THE FORMATION OF GIYANG BULGYO 祈禳佛教</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wu</surname>
                           <given-names>Jiang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dziwenka</surname>
                           <given-names>Ron</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1884, U.S. Navy officer George Clayton Foulk (1856–93), one of the first Westerners who toured the Korean peninsula, visited Haeinsa 海印寺 after hearing about its great reputation. Although the monastery seems to have been a disappointment for him, he was impressed by its collection of a huge number of woodblocks.</p>
                     <p>Behind the main building was a high hall, on top of which were two long buildings, each 250 feet, parallel, and apart say 100 feet. The eaves are lined with brass bells which ring quite loudly in the wind. In these buildings, well arranged in suitable racks by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Taishō Canon:</title>
                     <subtitle>DEVOTION, SCHOLARSHIP, AND NATIONALISM IN THE CREATION OF THE MODERN BUDDHIST CANON IN JAPAN</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilkinson</surname>
                           <given-names>Greg</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Taishō Canon</italic>(<italic>Taishō Shinshū Daizōkyō</italic>大正新修大蔵經), published between 1924 and 1932, was one of several projects in modern Japan aimed at creating a revised edition of the Chinese Tripitaka. This new edition has become a standard for academic research and devotional study, simply known as<italic>“T”</italic>in academic notation. Less known is how the production of the modern Japanese edition was influenced by a combination of religious devotion, Western-style academic scholarship, and Japan’s rising nationalism. In religious terms, Buddhist priests and intellectuals in Japan believed that these new printings of the Chinese Tripitaka would not only elevate Buddhism and Japan</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 1.</title>
                     <subtitle>A BRIEF SURVEY OF THE PRINTED EDITIONS OF THE CHINESE BUDDHIST CANON</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fuhua</surname>
                           <given-names>Li</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mei</surname>
                           <given-names>He</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Compiled by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wu</surname>
                           <given-names>Jiang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix 2.</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CREATION OF THE CBETA CHINESE ELECTRONIC TRIPITAKA COLLECTION IN TAIWAN</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tu</surname>
                           <given-names>Aming</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zi</surname>
                           <given-names>Xin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">wu--17160.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
