<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Memory, Narrative and the Great War</book-title>
         <subtitle>Rifleman Patrick MacGill and the Construction of Wartime Experience</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Taylor</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781846318719</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781387122</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>David Taylor</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18mbc8p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Memory, Narrative and the Great War provides a detailed examination of the varied and complex war writings of a relatively marginal figure, Patrick MacGill, within a general framework of our current pre-occupation with blood, mud and suffering. In particular, it seeks to explain how his interpretation of war shifted from the heroic wartime autobiographical trilogy, with its emphasis on 'the romance of the rifleman' to the pessimistic and guilt-ridden interpretations in his post-war novel, Fear!, and play, Suspense. Through an exploration of the way in which war-time experiences were remembered (and re-remembered) and retold in strikingly different narratives, and using insights from cognitive psychology, it is argued that there is no contradiction between these two seemingly opposing views. Instead it is argued that, given the present orientation and problem-solving nature of both memory and narrative, the different interpretations are both 'true' in the sense that they throw light on the ongoing way in which MacGill came to terms with his experiences of war. This in turn has implications for broader interpretations of the Great War, which has increasingly be seen in terms of futile suffering, not least because of the eloquent testimony of ex-Great War soldiers, reflecting on their experiences many years after the event. Without suggesting that such testimony is invalid, it is argued that this is one view but not the only view of the war. Rather wartime memory and narrative is more akin to an ever-changing kaleidoscope, in which pieces of memory take on different (but equally valid) shapes as they are shaken with the passing of time.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="236"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Problem with Pat</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 21 November 1914 an impetuous, self-confident (some would say cocky) 17-year-old Anglo-Irish redhead, Sydney Cadman, left his home in Tottenham and, much to the surprise of his parents, enlisted in the London Irish Rifles. Suffering just one wound worthy of the name, he came through the war in France unscathed. Almost five years afterwards to the day he was demobilized, though the Great War did not end for him then. Having lost his Catholic faith while in France, highly conscious of the transience of life and with no obvious career ahead of him, he returned to civilian life an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Some Changing Perspectives on the Great War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The status of the Great War as a justified and honourable undertaking has suffered considerably in recent years. Niall Ferguson, as-ever pithy and to the point, summed up the dominant view in the final sentence of his widely read book,<italic>The Pity of War</italic>, in which he dismissed it as ‘the greatest error of modern history’.¹ More importantly, the popular perception of the war has been simplified to the point of trivialization. Depending on one’s age and/or taste, it is summed up in either<italic>Oh What A Lovely War!</italic>or<italic>Blackadder Goes Forth</italic>: it is a view of a war</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Memories and Narratives of War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his<italic>Carnet d’un combattent</italic>, the French First World War veteran Louis Mairet was unequivocal: ‘I told the truth. Let them contradict me if they dare!’¹ Mairet was not the only former soldier to claim that his direct experience of war ensured that his account was authentic. What is more, many historians have similarly privileged the accounts of those men and women who had been at the Front. Lindert, writing about the German experience of the First World War, talks of the ‘air of unimpeachable authority’ that surrounds such writings.² Similarly, the writings of certain British ex–soldiers – notably Graves,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Sources:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Problems and Findings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The volume of material relating to the soldiers’ experience of the Great War is truly astounding. It has grown dramatically in the last few decades and shows little sign of diminishing. Indeed, with the centenary of the outbreak of the war only two years away (at the time of writing), there is every likelihood that there will be a further upsurge, not least from those interested in family history for whom ‘grandfather’s war’ (and increasingly ‘great-grandfather’s war’) remains a matter of central interest. It would be hypocritical to bemoan such a wealth of material but, putting aside the practical problems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>At the Front:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fighting and Writing the War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following the outbreak of war Patrick MacGill enlisted in the London Irish Rifles, the 18th battalion of the London Regiment. A young adult in his mid-20s, he brought with him experiences and values that would influence his recollection of wartime experiences. He already had a life narrative that would shape his responses but that in turn would be challenged and changed by the new experiences of being a soldier on active service in France. But what sort of man was he as he entered army life? What values did he espouse? How did he define himself as a man? How</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Writing the War from the Home Front</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MacGill returned to England in September 1915 and spent time ‘all dressed in blighty blue’ in the first Birmingham War Hospital at Ruberry Hill.¹ In the following month he contributed to<italic>The Times</italic>fund-raising publication<italic>Red Cross Story Book</italic>and by February 1916 he was fit enough to appear in London Irish Rifles uniform at fund-raising evenings in London during which his wife read from his ‘Story of Loos’, which was to become a central part of<italic>The Great Push.</italic>His commitment to the war was reflected in<italic>The Red Horizon</italic>which opened simply:</p>
                     <p>MacGill remained in the London Irish</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>The War in Retrospect</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ending of hostilities in November 1918, while welcome in obvious ways, created a problem for MacGill and highlighted other difficulties in his life. Like others who had served during the war, he had to make the complex and problematic adjustment to civilian life, which included a further reassessment of the war and his role therein. The war had undoubtedly provided him with a focus and sense of purpose, notwithstanding his changing relationship with and responses to the conflict, and his wartime writings had added to the reputation as a realist writer that he had gained following the publication of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Changing Perspectives and Coming to Terms with the War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the time of writing the centenary of the outbreak of the Great War is rapidly approaching. Notwithstanding the often tumultuous events of the twentieth century, the war still enjoys a unique status as a watershed in modern British history, and interest in it shows no sign of abating. On the contrary, not least as a result of the continuing growth in family history, interest in grandfather’s war and great-grandfather’s war ensures that it lives on in contemporary society. And yet the Great War has become a part of history in the sense that the passing of the last men</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbc8p.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
