<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781442687660</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BJ1533.C9D39 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Courtesy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Courtesy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Courtesy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">England</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Courtesy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Courtesy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Civility</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Cultural History</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DAVETIAN</surname>
               <given-names>BENET</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780802097224</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442687660</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press Incorporated</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/9781442687660"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Davetian's rich, multi-dimensional review of civility from 1200 to the present day provides an in-depth analysis of the social and personal psychology of human interaction and charts a new course for the study and understanding of civility and civil society.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="608"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The origins of this book are rooted in my childhood. My father worked for the United Nations, so we moved from one country to another every three or four years. I came to be fascinated by the manner in which people differed from one place to another. In the British school, we were sent to the principal if we were caught using a ballpoint instead of a fountain pen. In the American school, we were forbidden from using fountain pens. In the French school, we could use anything we wanted to just as long as we didn’t forget to stand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>From Barbarism to Courtly Manners</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our contemporary Western understanding of<italic>courtesy</italic>and<italic>civility</italic>is founded on our experience of a democratic society in which all citizens are supposed to enjoy fair treatment before the law. The massive amount of literature that has recently appeared on the supposed waning of courtesy shows how much we have come to value democratic civility as a sign of civilized pro-social behaviour. Yet nostalgia for a supposedly more civil era distracts us from realizing that in a different time and place the outright disrespect, hatred, and exclusion of the ‘other’ was considered normal and vital for survival. Ironically, when Western</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Secular Civility in the Renaissance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Renaissance was an important era in Western history because of its immense infl uence on the manner in which individuals conceived of their place in the universe and the way in which this conception facilitated the development of a civility tradition that was not as dependent on theological dogma. The subsequent Protestant Reformation and Enlightenment movements were facilitated by Renaissance interaction values because the Renaissance thinkers set the stage for a reversal in the ideologies that had kept absolutist monarchies in power. Although princes remained all-powerful in the Renaissance city-states, a new appreciation of individualism provided the rationale for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Shifts in Identity and Awareness:</title>
                     <subtitle>Protestantism and the Enlightenment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thinkers of the Renaissance placed a certain amount of responsibility on the individual for his actions and moral behaviour. Many of the writings of Renaissance thinkers favoured a personal morality that was not dependent on religious edict. This was an important transformation in worldview and it facilitated the massive cultural changes that occurred as a result of the Protestant Reformation and then the Enlightenment. Both historical developments had the effect of weakening the religious foundations of courtesy and transforming it into a practice of responsible secular citizenship. Our understanding of these changes is important if we are to appreciate how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>French Court Society, the French Revolution, and the Paradoxes of French Civility</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the Italians played a seminal role in the development of the Western civility tradition, it was during the reign of the French absolutist monarchs that civil etiquette became substantially associated with the preservation of privilege. The fact that egalitarian Protestantism was a minority movement in France allowed the French monarchs to adhere to an etiquette philosophy based on a social philosophy of distinction and superiority. In this chapter we would like to review the transition from etiquette to civility in France and discuss important aspects of French civil society prior to the twentieth century. This knowledge is crucial to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>England and the Victorian Ethic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The English political system had a considerable influence on the formation of a distinct English civility ethos. Although the French and the Americans chose to reject rule by monarchy, the English decided to remain with a constitutional monarchy tempered by an active parliament.</p>
                     <p>Despite the fact that England’s history is a dizzying narrative of violence, riots, political plots, religious and international wars, and considerable exploitation of the poor (Tilly [1995] 2005), an outright English revolution was avoided due to steadily improving economic and judicial systems (Gilmour 1993). Although there were no less than 8,088 ‘contentious gatherings’ in southeast England alone</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The American Experience:</title>
                     <subtitle>Democracy and Informal Civility</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In previous chapters we have described how the development of centralized monarchies gave rise to a civility ethos that served to legitimize the privileges accorded to aristocrats. As we will argue in our comparison of contemporary civility practices in France and England (chapter 10), this background has had a salient influence on the manner in which individuals interact with one another. In this present chapter we will describe the formation of a civility tradition that was not the outcome of aristocratic society, but a reaction to it. The American experience not only shows us the roots of American civility, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Conformity, Opposition, and Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Part I we tried to show how France, America, and England developed different civility preferences due to the manner in which each nation was affected by a variety of factors, including political philosophy and system of government, religion, intellectual history, geography, economy, familial norms, and the manner in which emotions were restrained and expressed. By the close of the nineteenth century each nation possessed its own civility and interaction ethos. The industrialization of the West did not have a substantial levelling effect over national identity or national ideology.</p>
                     <p>A similar partiality towards cultural ideology seems to have held during</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Towards a Cultural Sociology of Civility</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>343</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of the historical background of a culture is vital to one’s understanding of its civility practices as well as its ongoing present. Yet, there are other equally important factors that must be considered. Although they may in some measure be the outcomes of historical and moral forces, these factors need to be studied on their own merit because the manner in which they intersect makes for an ‘anatomy of civility’ that is sociological as well as psychological. In this part of the book we will discuss these various factors and show how a ‘cultural sociology of civility’ needs</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>A Comparative Field Study of France, America, and England</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preceding sections we have repeatedly spoken of civility ‘habituations’ in broad and ideal terms. Of course, this does not mean that an entire population is going to behave in a standard fashion. For example, when we speak of an American civility ethic that favours informality we remain aware that there are many Americans who do remain impeccably reserved in their dealings with others. Equally, when we speak of the French being emotionally expressive, we remain aware that there are emotionally restrained individuals in France who would find even the amiable reserve of the English rather maudlin. Thus, we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Civilizing and Recivilizing Processes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>497</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of civility is the study not only of the social history of a culture but of the human need for satisfactory social bonds and the problems that emerge when these bonds become too loose or too tight. When they are too tight, we are left with a collectivism that engulfs the individual, drowning out personal needs and aspirations. When they are too loose, the individual is deprived of the safety of communal norms and abandoned to a wasteland of freedom in which interactions between self and others lack meaning and depth. How a culture reacts to either extreme</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>531</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781442687660.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>573</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
