<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gx2w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Community, Cosmopolitanism and the Problem of Human Commonality</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Amit</surname>
               <given-names>Vered</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rapport</surname>
               <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">Series Editors:</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Amit</surname>
               <given-names>Vered</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mitchell</surname>
               <given-names>Jon P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745329031</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781849647090</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Vered Amit</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Nigel Rapport</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183pd2b"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this follow up to their widely read earlier volume, The Trouble with Community, Vered Amit and Nigel Rapport ask: 'Do notions of community remain central to our sense of who we are, in the dislocating context of globalization, or can we see beyond community closures to a human whole?' This volume explores the variable nature of contemporary sociality. It focuses on the ethical, organizational and emotional claims and opportunities sought or fashioned for mobilizing and evading social collectivities in a world of mobile subjects. Here is an examination of the tensions and interactions between everyday forms of fluid fellowship, culturally normative claims to identity, and opportunities for realizing a universal humanity. The book offers a new perspective on human commonality through a dialogue between two eminent anthropologists who come from distinct, but complementary positions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Book’s Structure</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Trouble with Community: Anthropological Reflections on Collectivity, Movement and Identity</italic>(2002), Vered Amit and Nigel Rapport entered into a dialogue that concerned the ideology, the practice and the conceptualization of community at the millennial turn. ‘The trouble with community’ concerned the tension between attempts to fix social and political relations in communal frames and the drives toward individuation and fragmentation that regularly undid these efforts but that also could be constrained by them. This volume assumes the same dialogic form and revisits the themes of the first volume.<italic>Community, Cosmopolitanism and the Problem of Human Commonality</italic>continues Amit’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Community as ‘Good to Think With’:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Productiveness of Strategic Ambiguities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>You might not be surprised to learn that when I picked up my daily newspaper the other day (<italic>The Globe and Mail</italic>, 25 April 2009) and tried to locate references to ‘community’, I was quickly able to identify dozens of them. These references ranged over a wide variety of contexts and applications: ‘local community leader’, ‘arts community’, ‘farming community’, ‘small community’, ‘utopian communities’, ‘outlying community’, ‘technology community’, ‘building communities’, ‘mining community’, ‘religious community’, along with ‘excluded and marginalized community’ were but some of the citations that appeared, including many that were not specified. ‘The community will not stand for this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Consociation and Communitas:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ambiguous Charms of the Quotidian</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter (‘Community as good to think with’), I noted that some of the most influential theorists of community – Anthony Cohen, Benedict Anderson, Victor Turner – have located this sense of connection in oppositional or extraordinary circumstances rather than within more mundane, quotidian relations. In other words, the theorization of community has often tended to disembed this concept from day-to-day sociality. In earlier work (Amit, 2002a), I argued that one version of this tendency towards disembedding has involved an increasing analytical focus on community as an<italic>idea</italic>, that is, a symbol or categorical referent rather than a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Disjuncture as ‘Good to Think With’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Considerations of community always implicitly or explicitly invoke its alter, that is, situations that do not involve community. How this is defined or set out is usually bound up with the conceptualization of community itself. For example, if community is defined in terms of boundaries – social, symbolic, political – then we would be likely to view the question in terms of who is or is not included in a particular, identifiable or claimed grouping. In this volume, however, I have suggested that it is conceptually more productive to view community in terms of mobilization and attendant issues of coordination</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Mobility and Cosmopolitanism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Frustrated Aspirations towards Disjuncture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The recent resurgence of interest in cosmopolitanism has been characterized by a proliferation of overlapping definitions of this concept. Thus, while concluding that cosmopolitanism is still an imprecise concept that refers to a great variety of ‘often unfinished projects’, Ulf Hannerz nonetheless notes that it ‘has to do with a sense of the world as one’ (2007: 83–84). Pnina Werbner similarly invokes the Greek roots of the term as a ‘citizen of the world’ to argue that ‘at its most basic, cosmopolitanism is about reaching out across cultural differences through dialogue, aesthetic enjoyment, and respect; of living together with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes to Part I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References to Part I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is cosmopolitanism? It is a kind of space for human expression and for individual emancipation. Cosmopolitanism promises a freedom for the individual from imprisonment in culture and community, in country and church, in class and category. I introduce cosmopolitanism, below, by elaborating upon this space and also the universal individual human subject who might be expected to take advantage of it.</p>
                     <p>What kind of human life does cosmopolitanism envisage? Three key words are movement, voluntarism and fulfilment. Cosmopolitanism envisages the evolution of individual identity, voluntary membership in any number of social and cultural clubs at any one time and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Space of Cosmopolitanism and the Cosmopolitan Subject</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The human condition, according to Georg Simmel (1971), could be truly apprehended only by taking account of a certain ‘dialectical circuitry’ which underlay experience and gave human life a sense of passage and progress. The characteristic human experience concerned ‘co-present dualisms’: public and private, rule and practice, antagonism and solidarity, freedom and constraint, rebelliousness and compliance, creativeness and structure. Here were paired phenomena one element of which presupposed the second element which yet, in turn, presupposed the first; one element influenced the second element which yet, in turn, influenced the first. Human experience oscillated and flowed between one and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Cosmopolitan Living:</title>
                     <subtitle>People of the Air and Global Guests</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Luftmenschen</italic>– ‘People of the Air’, ‘People of Smoke’ – was a slur favoured by the Nazis.<italic>Luftmenschen</italic>were those who were without roots, and who would not or could not take root, rootless (see Berg, 2006).<italic>Luftmenschen</italic>renounced the blood and honour (<italic>Blut und Ehre</italic>) of a genealogical attachment to the earth. The ideal types of<italic>Luftmenschen</italic>were the Gypsies and the Jews. In this the Nazis could be said to have followed Hegel, who deemed these people’s situation to be pathological. In leaving the Land of Israel – the ‘Garden of Eden’, the ‘pastures of Abraham’ – the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Cosmopolitan Learning:</title>
                     <subtitle>Diffusion, Openness and Irony</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does socialization via a society’s institutional procedures necessarily produce members who are formed in the society’s image? Does a moral and just society need to be a community of fellow-believers, a churchly congregation writ large, faithful to the iteration of a particular tradition? What do social efficiency and vitality mean in the context of cosmopolitanism? These are the questions I wish to treat in this chapter. I do so by way of ‘diffusion’, as a concept and a value. I introduce diffusion into the context of institutions of socialization.</p>
                     <p>There is something potentially cosmopolitan about diffusion: the diffusion of ideas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Cosmopolitan Planning:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anyone, Society and Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his obituary of Ernest Gellner (1925–1996), Tom Nairn (1996) suggests that Gellner’s first academic appointment, a Demonstratorship in Moral Philosophy at Edinburgh University between 1947 and 1949, may have had a formative influence upon him. Not only did Gellner become aware of how a geographical periphery could be a centre of civilization (<italic>polis</italic>vis-à-vis<italic>cosmos</italic>) but also how the Scottish Enlightenment idea of a civil society – of ‘society’ as distinct from ‘culture’ – could be rehabilitated so as to illuminate contemporary conditions of political liberty. This then gave onto a lifetime’s deliberations on the rise of nationalism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmopolitanism and Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have wanted to identify a cosmopolitan space which<italic>Anyone</italic>might occupy. To do so, the three chapters above have traversed a spectrum suggested by Kluckhohn and Murray (1953: 54–56) at the outset:<italic>Anyone</italic>is ‘in certain respects, (a) like all other men, (b) like some other men, (c) like no other man’. In ‘Cosmopolitan Living’,<italic>Anyone</italic>appeared as a<italic>Luftmensch</italic>or global guest who might lodge an individual quest for personal truth or authenticity in the time and the dimensions of his or own unique life. In ‘Cosmopolitan Learning’,<italic>Anyone</italic>passed through the pedagogic company of certain significant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes to Part II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References to Part II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Vered Amit Responds to Nigel Rapport</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I live across the street from an urban park. Spanning one long block on all sides, this is not a very large park but it is an intensively used one. Throughout even the rainiest day, dog owners bring their pets to cavort in the fenced and gated dog run. Some of the owners play with their dogs; others relax on the park benches or take the opportunity to chat with each other. Schools, daycares, sports associations, families and individuals make use of the sports field that supports a baseball diamond in the summer and a skating rink in the winter.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Nigel Rapport Responds to Vered Amit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>Nigel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her section of the book, Vered Amit challenges us to think more precisely about ‘community’, to use the word with more analytical vigour, even if this leads us to an appreciation of the inherent ambiguities and diversities of the way that the concept is deployed in everyday life. She makes five key points.</p>
                     <p>1. Relations of ‘community’ can be understood to involve a variety of kinds of sociation. ‘Community’ in use indicates no single kind of relationship. Indeed, there is no one thing in common between all the different usages of and claims for ‘community’.</p>
                     <p>2. There is work involved and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References to Part III</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pd2b.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
