<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">E184.A1C75 1997</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Race relations</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Whites</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Race identity</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Whites</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Attitudes</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Critical White Studies</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Delgado</surname>
               <given-names>Richard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Stefancic</surname>
               <given-names>Jean</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781566395311</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781439901519</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PHILADELPHIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1997</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Temple University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1bw1kc5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>No longer content with accepting whiteness as the norm, critical scholars have turned their attention to whiteness itself. In<italic>Critical White Studies: Looking Behind the Mirror</italic>, numerous thinkers, including Toni Morrison, Eric Foner, Peggy McIntosh, Andrew Hacker, Ruth Frankenberg, John Howard Griffin, David Roediger, Kathleen Heal Cleaver, Noel Ignatiev, Cherrie Moraga, and Reginald Horsman, attack such questions as:*How was whiteness invented, and why?*How has the category whiteness changed over time?*Why did some immigrant groups, such as the Irish and Jews, start out as nonwhite and later became white?*Can some individual people be both white and nonwhite at different times, and what does it mean to "pass for white"?*At what point does pride in being white cross the line into white power or white supremacy?*What can whites concerned over racial inequity or white privilege do about it?Science and pseudoscience are presented side by side to demonstrate how our views on whiteness often reflect preconception, not fact. For example, most scientists hold that race is not a valid scientific category -- genetic differences between races are insignificant compared to those within them. Yet, the "one drop" rule, whereby those with any nonwhite heritage are classified as nonwhite, persists even today. As the bell curve controversy shows, race concepts die hard, especially when power and prestige lie behind them.A sweeping portrait of the emerging field of whiteness studies,<italic>Critical White Studies</italic>presents, for the first time, the best work from sociology, law, history, cultural studies, and literature. Delgado and Stefancic expressly offer critical white studies as the next step in critical race theory. In focusing on whiteness, not only do they ask nonwhites to investigate more closely for what it means for others to be white, but also they invite whites to examine themselves more searchingly and to "look behind the mirror."</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="330"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Are you white? (Or, do you have a friend who is?) If so, how do you know? Is race real—or is it constructed, an “as-if” concept, something we all agree to bestow on each other? Is it a relational concept, existing only in binary fashion (e.g., black/white), so that if all the people on a tropical island, say, looked pretty much the same, there would be no race or races? Modern-day scientists tell us that whites and blacks have more genes in common than the ones that distinguish them—the variability between the average white and the average black,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The End of the Great White Male</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRAHAM</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Five centuries ago, the foundations of the world were shaken. So-called immutable truths toppled forever as man was replaced by the sun as the center of our universe. Equally wrenching is the current shattering of white males’ world view, in which they long have seen themselves as the central characters on society’s stage. All around are the effects of a revolution that is both painfully distressing and totally confusing to what well may become known as the last of the great white males.</p>
                     <p>As the turmoil continues, white males are the inevitable scapegoats—and their difficulties only are beginning. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>White Racial Formation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Into the Twenty-First Century</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GALLAGHER</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLES A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whiteness is in a state of change. One only need browse book stands or news racks for examples of how the idea of whiteness is being interpreted, defined, reinterpreted, and contested by popular writers and journalists. Whites perceive themselves, according to one account, as being part of a distinctly different, colorblind, sympathetic generation that has learned to look beyond “the color of the skin” to “the beauty within.”¹</p>
                     <p>Whereas some whites see a common humanity with their nonwhite counterparts, others see whiteness as a liability. A white sergeant with the Los Angeles County Sheriff’s office announced creation of the Association</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Skin We’re In</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILLS</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTOPHER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Melanin is in the news these days. There’s a pseudoscientific idea floating around that says that if you have lots of melanin—the pigment that colors your skin and hair and the irises of your eyes—you will be smart and exquisitely attuned to life’s rhythms and have a warm, outgoing personality. In short, you will be nicer and more talented than people with less melanin—that is, white people.</p>
                     <p>Proponents of this idea, such as Leonard Jeffries, chairman of the Department of Black Studies at the City College of New York, have based their conclusions on the single scientific</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Way of the WASP</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BROOKHISER</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Benjamin Franklin decided to improve his own character, he drew up the list of virtues which so annoyed D. H. Lawrence [<italic>Studies in Classic American Literature</italic>, chapter 2. Ed.]. Originally there were twelve. “But a Quaker friend having kindly informed me that I was generally thought proud … of which he convinced me by mentioning several instances; I determined endeavoring to cure myself, if I could, of this vice or folly among the rest, and I added<italic>Humility to</italic>my list”—along with an explanatory note: “Imitate Jesus and Socrates.”¹</p>
                     <p>Virtues, which we hope to acquire, may be listed.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Hiring Quotas for White Males Only</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FONER</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thirty-two years ago, I graduated from Columbia College. My class of 700 was all-male and virtually all-white. Most of us were young men of ability, yet had we been forced to compete for admission with women and racial minorities, fewer than half of us would have been at Columbia. None of us, to my knowledge, suffered debilitating self-doubt because we were the beneficiaries of affirmative action—that is, favored treatment on the basis of our race and gender.</p>
                     <p>Affirmative action has emerged as the latest “wedge issue” of American politics. The recent abrogation of California affirmative action programs by Governor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Innocence and Affirmative Action</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSS</surname>
                           <given-names>THOMAS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we create arguments, when we act as rhetoricians, we reveal ourselves by the words and ideas we choose to employ. Verbal structures that are used widely and persistently are especially worth examination. Arguments made with repeated, almost formulaic, sets of words suggest a second argument flowing beneath the apparent argument. Beneath the apparently abstract language and the syllogistic form of these arguments, we may discover the deeper currents that explain, at least in part, why we seem so attached to these verbal structures.</p>
                     <p>In particular, the rhetoric of<italic>innocence</italic>persists as an important tool in discussions of race. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Doing the White Male Kvetch (A Pale Imitation of a Rag)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TRILLIN</surname>
                           <given-names>CALVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Growing Up White in America?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GROVER</surname>
                           <given-names>BONNIE KAE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Growing up<italic>white</italic>in America. How do you do that? I mean, lots of folks grow up Italian in America, lots more grow up capitalist in America, and legions of us have grown up middle class, working class, poor, or even rich in America. But<italic>white</italic>?</p>
                     <p>White is transparent. That’s the point of being the dominant race. Sure, the whiteness is there, but you never think of it. If you’re white, you never<italic>have</italic>to think of it. Sometimes when folks make a point of thinking of it, some (not all) of them run the risk of being either sappy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Growing Up (What) in America?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARRS</surname>
                           <given-names>JERALD N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Do you recognize these lyrics? Can you hum them to yourself and include the next verse about Mr. Cold Miser? Are these words part of your culture?</p>
                     <p>These are the words that first triggered a realization in my life. A realization that no matter how hard I try, I can’t stop being white. I can’t undo my<italic>culture</italic>. And I have tried hard to do just that. But what does this mean? What does this make me?</p>
                     <p>I grew up white. Born in Utah, raised in New Mexico and Colorado. Graduated from a white/middle-class high school near Denver, and then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>White Images of Black Slaves (Is What We See in Others Sometimes a Reflection of What We Find in Ourselves?)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FREDRICKSON</surname>
                           <given-names>GEORGE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his provocative study of American slavery, Stanley Elkins provides a vivid description of the black slave as he was usually represented in antebellum southern lore:</p>
                     <p>Sambo, the typical plantation slave, was docile but irresponsible, loyal but lazy, humble but chronically given to lying and stealing; his behavior was full of infantile silliness and his talk inflated with childish exaggeration. His relationship with his master was one of utter dependence and childlike attachment: it was indeed this childlike quality that was the very key to his being. Although the merest hint of Sambo’s “manhood” might fill the Southern breast with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The White Race Is Shrinking:</title>
                     <subtitle>Perceptions of Race in Canada and Some Speculations on the Political Economy of Race Classification</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DANIELS</surname>
                           <given-names>DOUG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For many years I have been teaching a sociology class on ‘Minorities and Ethnic Group Relations’ at the University of Regina, Canada, where the ethnic make-up of the student body is quite unremarkable. As on so many campuses in North America, our student body is almost exclusively ‘white’ in the sense that most come from British and East European families. We have a smattering of students from abroad (mainly Hong Kong) and a very few Canadian Indian and Metis students. In addition, our population is inundated with the usual US television programs, magazines, and university texts, so our perceptions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Ignoble Savages</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>D’SOUZA</surname>
                           <given-names>DINESH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the Europeans who first voyaged abroad, much of the rest of the world came as a shock for which they were poorly prepared. Early modern accounts, such as Richard Hakluyt’s sixteenth century<italic>Principal Navigations</italic>or Samuel Purchas’s seventeenth century<italic>Purchas His Pilgrimage</italic>and<italic>Hakluytus Posthumus</italic>, convey the stupefaction of the Europeans who encountered distant and unfamiliar peoples. Europeans who were even then making a transition into the modern era found themselves genuinely amazed and horrified at other cultures which appeared virtually static, confined from time immemorial in the nomadic or the agrarian stage. The consequence was that many Europeans</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Darkness Made Visible:</title>
                     <subtitle>Law, Metaphor, and the Racial Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JONES</surname>
                           <given-names>D. MARVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In August 1862, Abraham Lincoln called a number of “Negro” leaders to the White House. Laboring under harsh racial assumptions, which conflicted with the moral eloquence to come at Gettysburg, Lincoln told his assembled audience, “You and we are different races…. This physical difference is a great disadvantage to us both, as I think your race suffer very greatly, many of them by living among us, while ours suffer from your presence.”² With these prefatory remarks, Lincoln proceeded to try to persuade his audience of the merits of his plan: To emancipate slaves and expatriate them to a colony in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Playing in the Dark:</title>
                     <subtitle>Whiteness and the Literary Imagination</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORRISON</surname>
                           <given-names>TONI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the end of<italic>The Narrative of Arthur Gordon Pym</italic>, Edgar Allan Poe describes the last two days of an extraordinary journey:</p>
                     <p>“<italic>March 21st</italic>—A sullen darkness now hovered above us—but from out the milky depths of the ocean a luminous glare arose, and stole up along the bulwarks of the boat. We were nearly overwhelmed by the white ashy shower which settled upon us and upon the canoe, but melted into the water as it fell….</p>
                     <p>“<italic>March 22d</italic>—The darkness had materially increased, relieved only by the glare of the water thrown back from the white curtain before</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Transparently White Subjective Decisionmaking:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fashioning a Legal Remedy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLAGG</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Goodson, Badwin &amp; Indiff is a major accounting firm employing more than five hundred persons nationwide. Among its twenty black accountants is Yvonne Taylor, who at the time this story begins was thirty-one years old and poised to become the first black regional supervisor in the firm’s history. Yvonne attended Princeton University and received an M.B.A. from the Kellogg Graduate School of Management at Northwestern University. While employed at Goodson, she was highly successful in attracting new clients, especially from the black business community. In all other respects her performance at the firm was regarded as exemplary.</p>
                     <p>Yvonne always was comfortable</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>The Rhetorical Tapestry of Race</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSS</surname>
                           <given-names>THOMAS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For many, the rhetoric supporting the institution of slavery was constructed simply. Once one got past establishing the nonhuman nature of blacks, the rest was easy. If whites had any moral obligation in the matter, it was to use blacks to further the interests of society, a society from which the black was excluded. The horrific conditions of slave existence became the tokens of charity and benevolence to the black brute. This particular rhetoric took various forms but always avoided any real conflict in values and principles by placing blacks outside the community of humans.</p>
                     <p>The rhetoric of the nineteenth-century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Imposition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DELGADO</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STEFANCIC</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Society generally deploys terms of<italic>imposition</italic>at key moments in the history of a reform effort, such as blacks’ struggle for equal opportunity, or women’s campaign for reproductive rights. Before reaching that point, society tolerates or even supports the new movement. We march, link arms, and sing with the newcomers, identifying with their struggle. At some point, however, reaction sets in. We decide the group has gone far enough. At first, justice seemed to be on their side. But now we see them as imposing, taking the offensive, asking for concessions they do not deserve. Now they are the aggressors,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Racial Reflections:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dialogues in the Direction of liberation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BELL</surname>
                           <given-names>DERRICK A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HIGGINS</surname>
                           <given-names>TRACY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SUH</surname>
                           <given-names>SUNG-HEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <role content-type="editor">EDITORS</role>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can we explain the willingness of so many white Americans to sacrifice their interests in social reform to insure that blacks they deem “undeserving” do not gain? What precisely are they trying to protect in this land where equality is a concept while ownership of property is a basic measure of worth?</p>
                     <p>Over time, beliefs in white dominance, reinforced by policies subordinating black interests to those of whites, have led to an unrecognized, but no less viable, property right in whiteness. In challenging the legality of racial segregation in the late nineteenth century, the plaintiff in<italic>Plessy v. Ferguson</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>The Tower of Babel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BROWN</surname>
                           <given-names>ELEANOR MARIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Social scientists have identified a number of features that characterize contemporary white attitudes toward blacks. First, traditional stereotypes and blatant discrimination are no longer common. Most whites, regardless of their political orientation, reject these traditional forms of discrimination. This is particularly true of white liberals who condition their behavior toward blacks on beliefs that strongly condemn traditional discrimination. Second, whites use ostensibly nonracial factors to justify any behavior that may have a disproportionate impact on blacks or could be perceived as being racist. Third, whites harbor attitudes of ambivalence toward blacks resulting in extreme positive or negative reactions. These attitudes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>The Quest for Freedom in the Post-Brown South:</title>
                     <subtitle>Desegregation and White Self-Interest</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOUGLAS</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVISON M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In their response to the civil rights movement of the 1960s, moderate southern communities differed from their recalcitrant counterparts in at least one significant aspect. These communities understood that white self-interest demanded a certain degree of accommodation to integration demands. Thus, in many moderate southern cities, white elites, especially business leaders, played critical roles in facilitating limited racial integration as a means of preserving a strong business environment. At the same time, this need to appear racially moderate provided the black community with an important opportunity to challenge racial segregation that activists successfully exploited in many southern communities.</p>
                     <p>The desegregation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>“Soulmaning”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Using Race for Political and Economic Gain</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WRIGHT</surname>
                           <given-names>LUTHER</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philip and Paul Malone, twin brothers from Boston, applied to be firefighters in 1975, but were not hired because of low civil service test scores. The brothers reapplied in 1977, changing their racial classifications from “white” to “black”¹ Due to a court mandate requiring Boston to hire more minority firefighters and police,² the Malones were hired in 1978, even though their test scores remained the same. Had the Malones listed their race as white in 1977, they most likely would have been denied employment a second time. In 1988, ten years after being hired, the Malone brothers’ racial classifications were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>Dysconscious Racism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ideology, Identity, and Miseducation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KING</surname>
                           <given-names>JOYCE E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Dysconscious racism” is a form of racism that tacitly accepts dominant white norms and privileges. It is not the<italic>absence</italic>of consciousness but an<italic>impaired</italic>consciousness or distorted way of thinking about race as compared to, for example, critical consciousness. Uncritical ways of thinking about racial inequity accept certain culturally sanctioned assumptions, myths, and beliefs that justify the social and economic advantages white people have as a result of subordinating others. Anything that calls this ideology of racial privilege into question inevitably challenges the self-identity of white people who have internalized these ideological justifications. The reactions of my students to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>Race and Manifest Destiny:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Origins of American Racial Anglo-Saxonism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HORSMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>REGINALD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By 1850 American expansion was viewed in the United States less as a victory for the principles of free democratic republicanism than as evidence of the innate superiority of the American Anglo-Saxon branch of the Caucasian race. In the middle of the nineteenth century a sense of racial destiny permeated discussions of American progress and of future American world destiny. Many think of rampant doctrines of Caucasian, Aryan, or Anglo-Saxon destiny as typical of the late years of the nineteenth century, but they flourished in the United States in the era of the Mexican War.</p>
                     <p>The contrast in expansionist rhetoric</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>The Invention of Race:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rereading White Over Black</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAMPBELL</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OAKES</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Winthrop Jordan’s<italic>White Over Black</italic>was published in 1968, big reviews came out right away, followed by big prizes. Everyone noticed; everyone raved. Yet for all its monumental proportions, the book cast a curiously slender historiographical shadow. Jordan’s work did not become the centerpiece of a long and fruitful scholarly debate. It sits on our shelves, the proverbial book we read in graduate school. It was Jordan’s singular misfortune to produce a history of racial attitudes at the same time that Americans were beginning to look beyond racism to the political and economic sources of social inequality. The “real”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>“Only the Law Would Rule between Us”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Antimiscegenation, the Moral Economy of Dependency, and the Debate over Rights after the Civil War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VAN TASSEL</surname>
                           <given-names>EMILY FIELD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gender and race were closely connected in the ideology of the white South; they were mutually defining. Consider legal prohibitions on interracial marriage, for example. At the core of the early debate were several closely linked questions about what kind of contract marriage was, its social and legal meaning in the shambles of the slave system, and, finally, what the limits of the right to marry, or to choose one’s associates, might be in a world where the meaning and content of “rights” remained to be decided.</p>
                     <p>Another question, from the perspective of whites, was how manhood would be defined</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26</label>
                     <title>The Antidemocratic Power of Whiteness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CLEAVER</surname>
                           <given-names>KATHLEEN NEAL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like the formally neutral concept of “civil rights,” “race” usually makes one think of blacks. To link the idea of race with the social construct of whiteness is uncommon. As a rule, white Americans no longer see race in relation to their own identity, and genuinely believe that racism poses a problem for “others.” A widespread failure to acknowledge that whiteness conveys internal meanings at the same time it fulfills anti-black functions helps frustrate programs that seek to eliminate racism’s pernicious legacy.¹ Thus,<italic>The Wages of Whiteness</italic>, a sophisticated analysis of the significance of racism in the formation of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>27</label>
                     <title>Who’s Black, Who’s White, and Who Cares</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WRIGHT</surname>
                           <given-names>LUTHER</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Strict racial classification rules were at the very core of maintaining the institution of slavery and the system of white dominance. One problem with the existence of indentured servants and slaves in a free society was the ease with which slaves or servants could escape if they were not distinguishable from free citizens. By linking slavery to race, slave escape became much more difficult, particularly once all blacks were presumed to be slaves. Suddenly, racial classification became of critical importance in American society—it could be the difference between freedom and slavery and later, the difference between privilege and disenfranchisement.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>28</label>
                     <title>Images of the Outsider in American Law and Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DELGADO</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STEFANCIC</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Several museums have featured displays of racial memorabilia from the past.¹ Each of these collections depicts a shocking parade of Sambos, mammies, coons, uncles—bestial or happy-go-lucky, watermelon-eating African-Americans. They show advertising logos and household commodities in the shape of blacks with grotesquely exaggerated facial features. They include minstrel shows and film clips depicting blacks as so incompetent, shuffling, and dim-witted that it is hard to see how they survived to adulthood. Other images depict primitive, terrifying, larger-than-life black men in threatening garb and postures, often with apparent designs on white women.</p>
                     <p>Seeing these haunting images today, one is tempted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>29</label>
                     <title>Back to the Future with The Bell Curve:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jim Crow, Slavery, and G</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JONES</surname>
                           <given-names>JACQUELINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to Richard Herrnstein and Charles Murray, we live in an age and a country untainted by history, an age that springs full blown from g, or the “general intelligence” of the citizens who live here, now. In presenting their rigidly deterministic view that IQ is the major force shaping social structure in the United States today, the authors of<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>exude a smug complacency about late-twentieth-century American society: they argue that, judging from current housing and job patterns, people are pretty much where they should be—members of the so-called cognitive elite are ensconced in the wealthiest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>30</label>
                     <title>The Genetic Tie</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBERTS</surname>
                           <given-names>DOROTHY E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The genetic tie’s prominence in defining personal identity arose in a racial caste system that preserved white supremacy through a rule of racial purity. In America, perhaps the most socially significant product of the genetic link between parents and children is still race. The inheritability of one’s race—which determines one’s social status—radically distorts the lens through which we view the biological relationship between generations. It is crucial to examine the historical interplay between concepts of race, social status, and genetic connection.</p>
                     <p>Scientific racism places great value on the genetic tie, as it understands racial variation as a biological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>31</label>
                     <title>White Law and Lawyers:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Surrogate Motherhood</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HALEWOOD</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much has been written on surrogate motherhood as an application of biotechnology which challenges conventional understandings of equality and the family. Surrogacy also challenges conventional notions of embodiment. Indeed, the law has responded to surrogacy by bracketing off the surrogate mother’s embodiment—her factual experience of pregnancy—from the legal facts relevant to deciding disputes over custody arising from surrogacy arrangements. For example, even where the so-called surrogate is pregnant with her own fertilized ovum, she is defined not as the “biological” mother but as the “surrogate” mother, thus denying the biological and experiential fact that she is the mother.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>32</label>
                     <title>Social Science and Segregation before Brown</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOVENKAMP</surname>
                           <given-names>HERBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No historical legal policy can be evaluated without an understanding of the framework in which the policymakers viewed the world. If members of a society believe a particular scientific theory—for example, that interracial sex produces degenerate children—then they may be willing to sacrifice a great deal to avoid the consequences of interracial marriages. If they later discover that interracial marriages have no such consequences, then their views will probably change accordingly. In short, people’s scientific view of the world determines in large part the social situation that they regard as optimal. The genetic determinism that dominated social science</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>33</label>
                     <title>Mexican-Americans and Whiteness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARTINEZ</surname>
                           <given-names>GEORGE A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During slavery, the racial divide between black and white became a line of protection from the threat of commodification: whiteness protected one against being an object of property. Even after slavery ended, the status of being white continued to be a valuable asset, carrying with it a set of assumptions, privileges and benefits. Given this, it is hardly surprising that minorities have often sought to “pass” as white—i.e., present themselves as white persons. They did so because they thought that becoming white insured greater economic, political and social security. Becoming white, they thought, meant gaining access to a panoply</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>34</label>
                     <title>Race and the Core Curriculum in Legal Education</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ANSLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCES LEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It hardly needs saying that the Constitution represents contested and bloody ground. The celebration of the Constitution’s bicentennial brought on a great debate about race and the Constitution. No doubt scholars of differing persuasions would have raised the race question during the bicentennial in any event, but a highly publicized speech by Justice Thurgood Marshall underscored the question in a dramatic fashion and provoked additional responses. Justice Marshall wrote:</p>
                     <p>The focus of this celebration invites a complacent belief that the vision of those who debated and compromised in Philadelphia yielded the “more perfect Union” it is said we now enjoy.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>35</label>
                     <title>The Transparency Phenomenon, Race-Neutral Decisionmaking, and Discriminatory Intent</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLAGG</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this society, the white person has an everyday option not to think of herself in racial terms at all. In fact, whites appear to pursue that option so habitually that it may be a defining characteristic of whiteness: to be white is not to think about it.¹ I label the tendency for whiteness to vanish from whites’ self-perception the transparency phenomenon.² Because transparency is such a pervasive fact of whites’ conceptualization of ourselves, we have reason to be skeptical of ostensibly race-neutral decisionmaking by white decisionmakers. I propose that white decisionmakers adopt that deliberate skepticism as well regarding their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>36</label>
                     <title>Toward a Black Legal Scholarship:</title>
                     <subtitle>Race and Original Understandings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CULP</surname>
                           <given-names>JEROME MCCRISTAL</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Initially, the law largely treated black slaves as non-beings.¹ Eventually, the law evolved into a paternalistic system that viewed blacks as lesser beings whom white masters and overseers needed to protect from their own ignorant, sloven, and evil nature. Finally, slave law provided for legal limitations on the activities of slaves and their masters; in other words, the state stepped between slaves and masters and imposed external rules.² Thus, slavery bequeathed three powerful constructions of law to legal interpretation—ignoring blacks altogether, treating blacks paternalistically, and creating limited legal rules to regulate white behavior toward blacks. The post-slavery period added</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>37</label>
                     <title>Identity Notes, Part One:</title>
                     <subtitle>Playing in the Light</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAVIS</surname>
                           <given-names>ADRIENNE D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“What parts do the invention and development of whiteness play in the construction of what is loosely described as ‘American’”?¹ And how does<italic>binarism</italic>affect law and legal study? [“Binarism” refers to the socially constructed, dualistic black/white paradigm of race, which is dominant in Western culture today. Ed.] The paradigm<italic>appears</italic>internally neutral, as though blacks and whites were equally situated within it. Yet the cases discussed below suggest that a primary motivation in the crafting of the American racial architecture may not have been a pure desire to have a taxonomy for classifying races, but to define and protect</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.51</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>38</label>
                     <title>The Constitutional Ghetto</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAYMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT L.</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEVIT</surname>
                           <given-names>NANCY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three themes characterize latter-day desegregation law.</p>
                     <p>First,<italic>Plessy</italic>originated, and recent decisions embrace, a concept of natural racism. This view holds that racism inheres in the human condition. Racism is innate and inevitable and, as a consequence, it must be tolerated—by the federal courts among others—as an unfortunate fact of human existence. The Constitution and the construing Court are powerless to alter the course of racial instincts; separation may not be equal, but it is entirely natural.</p>
                     <p>Second, recent decisions complete another cycle begun in<italic>Plessy:</italic>the discrediting of racism as a barrier to constitutional equality. In several</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.52</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.53</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.54</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.55</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>39</label>
                     <title>Do You Know This Man?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ZALEWSKI</surname>
                           <given-names>DANIEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What did Jesus look like? Think for a second: Most likely, your mind will conjure up airbrushed golden locks, a silky beard, and baby blue eyes. Yet another reproduction of Warner Sallman’s 1940 painting<italic>Head of Christ</italic>will have permeated your brain. Sallman’s portrait may be bad art (one critic has called it a “pretty picture of a woman with a curling beard”), but, for better or worse, the image has cornered our consciousness. How did Sallman’s Savior become so popular? A new essay collection,<italic>Icons of American Protestantism: The Art of Warner Sallman</italic>(Yale), edited by Valparaiso art historian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.56</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>40</label>
                     <title>The Curse of Ham</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JONES</surname>
                           <given-names>D. MARVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Society has created a connection between color and meaning. But what of black and white?</p>
                     <p>Black is … the<italic>total absence of color</italic>, due to the absence or total<italic>absorption</italic>of light…. “White” is “fully luminous and devoid of any distinctive hues.” That void is the point where white and black meet and reverse; for if white is an empty fullness (fully luminous but<italic>void</italic>), then black is a full emptiness (<italic>total</italic>absence).¹</p>
                     <p>The fact that black and white represent a falling out of color represents the idea that ultimately black and white signify a falling out of meaning² and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.57</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>41</label>
                     <title>Los Olvidados:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Making of Invisible People</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PEREA</surname>
                           <given-names>JUAN F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to its English conquerors, America was always meant to belong to white Englishmen. In 1788, John Jay, writing in the Federalist Number 2, declared: “Providence has been pleased to give this one connected country to one united people—a people descended from the same ancestors, speaking the same language, professing the same religion, attached to the same principles of government, very similar in their manners and customs….”¹ Although Jay’s statement was wrong—early American society was remarkably diverse—his wish that America be a homogeneous, white, English-speaking Anglo society was widely shared by the Framers of the Constitution and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.58</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>42</label>
                     <title>White Innocence, Black Abstraction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSS</surname>
                           <given-names>THOMAS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To understand the power of the theme of white innocence, one must begin with the cultural conception of innocence. To be innocent is important everywhere in our culture. The argument for the white person’s innocence in matters of race connects with the cultural ideas of innocence and defilement. The very contrast between the colors, white and black, is often a symbol for the contrast between innocence and defilement. Thus, the theme of white innocence in the legal rhetoric of race draws its power from more than the obvious advantage of pushing away responsibility. It takes power from the cultural, religious,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.59</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>43</label>
                     <title>Race and the Dominant Gaze:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narratives of Law and Inequality in Popular Film</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RUSSELL</surname>
                           <given-names>MARGARET M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Birth of a Nation</italic>(Epoch Pictures, 1915), frequently cited as a milestone in the history of American motion pictures, D. W. Griffith offered his vision of race relations in the United States. Originally entitled<italic>The Clansman</italic>, the film portrays a South ravaged by the Civil War, corrupted by Reconstruction, and eventually redeemed by the birth of the Ku Klux Klan.<italic>The Birth of a Nation</italic>conveys its blunt white supremacist message through a narrative chronicling the effect of the Civil War on the South Carolina plantation of the Cameron family. As the silent film begins, subtitles extol the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.60</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>44</label>
                     <title>Residential Segregation and White Privilege</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHONEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Residential segregation and white dominance are integrally related. White choices are not only the aggregation of individual preferences regarding proximity to blacks. Rather, governmental and private forces—in interaction with each other—in the past created a racialized process of urban/suburban development in which “good” neighborhoods were defined as white and whiteness was defined as good, stable, employed, and employable.</p>
                     <p>Racial segregation was systematically promoted during the 1930s, 1940s, and 1950s by federal programs like the Home Owners Loan Corporation (HOLC), which made loans to homeowners, and the Federal Housing Authority (FHA), which insured private-sector loans.¹ These programs refused to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.61</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>45</label>
                     <title>Mules, Madonnas, Babies, Bathwater:</title>
                     <subtitle>Racial Imagery and Stereotypes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AMMONS</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDA L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Facts from a recent case help to illustrate how the conduct of a battered black woman is contrasted with the perception of how a battered white woman responds. A twenty-nine-year-old black woman, Pamela Hill, lived with her abusive boyfriend, Roy Chaney. At trial, the evidence revealed that police had been called to Hill’s residence on five separate occasions to protect her. According to the police report, on the night in question, Chaney had been drinking and began slapping Hill. Hill got a knife and the two began struggling over it. Hill got control of the knife and suffered several cuts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.62</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>46</label>
                     <title>The Other Pleasures:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Narrative Function of Race in the Cinema</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EVERETT</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even with the phenomenal influence of cultural studies and of cognitive and feminist theories, there remains a conspicuous absence of theorizing about the narrative function of race<italic>qua</italic>race in contemporary films. I contend that<italic>Scenes from the Class Struggle in Beverly Hills</italic>(1988),<italic>The Player</italic>(1992),<italic>Cool Runnings</italic>(1993),<italic>Blue Chips</italic>(1994),<italic>The Nightmare before Christmas</italic>(1993), and<italic>The Perfect Woman</italic>(1993) all, in varying degrees, devise narrative situations that rely on race to authorize their speaking the unspeakable, performing the prohibited, defiling the sacred, and generally transgressing most sanctioned codes of social conduct. These films deploy racialized archetypal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.63</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.64</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.65</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.66</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>47</label>
                     <title>White Privilege and Male Privilege:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Personal Account of Coming to See Correspondences through Work in Women’s Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McINTOSH</surname>
                           <given-names>PEGGY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Through work to bring materials and perspectives from Women’s Studies into the rest of the curriculum, I have often noticed men’s unwillingness to grant that they are over-privileged in the curriculum, even though they may grant that women are disadvantaged. Denials which amount to taboos surround the subject of advantages which men gain from women’s disadvantages. These denials protect male privilege from being fully recognized, acknowledged, lessened, or ended.</p>
                     <p>Thinking through unacknowledged male privilege as a phenomenon with a life of its own, I realized that since hierarchies in our society are interlocking, there was most likely a phenomenon of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.67</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>48</label>
                     <title>From Practice to Theory, or What Is a White Woman Anyway?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MacKINNON</surname>
                           <given-names>CATHARINE A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>300</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent critiques of feminist work for failing to take account of race or class, race and class are regarded as unproblematically real and not in need of justification or theoretical construction.³ Only gender is not real and needs to be justified.⁴ Although many women have demanded that discussions of race or class take gender into account, typically these demands do not take the form that, outside explicit recognition of gender, race or class do not exist. That there is a diversity to the experience of men and women of color, and of working-class women and men regardless of race,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.68</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>49</label>
                     <title>Racial Construction and Women as Differentiated Actors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHONEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is race? A social construct, a concept having no natural truth, no truth separate from historical development, and possibly no truth comprehensible apart from domination. The term has meant different things in this country over time; and its social and cultural meanings continue to change within our own time. In law as well as elsewhere in society the term “race” has been used to stand for several different concepts. Even the Supreme Court, when faced with the question, had to recognize that “race” was a contingent category that shifted over time.¹</p>
                     <p>Race is a social construct. However, that does</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.69</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>50</label>
                     <title>The GI Bill:</title>
                     <subtitle>Whites Only Need Apply</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SACKS</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREN BRODKIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>310</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The GI Bill of Rights, as the 1944 Serviceman’s Readjustment Act was known, was arguably the most massive affirmative action program in U.S. history. It was created to develop needed labor-force skills, and to provide those who had them with a life-style that reflected their value to the economy. The GI benefits ultimately extended to sixteen million GIs (veterans of the Korean War as well) included priority in jobs—that is, preferential hiring, but no one objected to it then—financial support during the job search; small loans for starting up businesses; and, most important, low-interest home loans and educational</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.70</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>51</label>
                     <title>Making Systems of Privilege Visible</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILDMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHANIE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>WITH</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAVIS</surname>
                           <given-names>ADRIENNE D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>314</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Race and gender are, after all, just words. Yet when we learn that someone has had a child, our first question is usually “Is it a girl or a boy?” Why do we ask that, instead of something like” Are the mother and child healthy?” We ask, “Is it a girl or a boy?” according to philosopher Marilyn Frye, because we do not know how to relate to this new being without knowing its gender.¹ Imagine how long you could have a discussion with or about someone without knowing her or his gender. We place people into these categories because</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.71</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>52</label>
                     <title>Race and Racial Classifications</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WRIGHT</surname>
                           <given-names>LUTHER</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>320</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1983, Susie Phipps’ five-year, $49,000 legal battle to have her birth certificate’s “erroneous” racial classification changed ended with the court denying her petition.¹ Six years later, Mary Walker’s fight to have her racial classification changed on her birth certificate ended with the court granting the change she sought.² Why did these two cases, seemingly very similar, have totally opposite outcomes? First, Susie Phipps sought to have her racial classification changed from “black” to “white,” while Mary Walker sought a change from “white” to “black.”³ Second, Susie Phipps’ home state, Louisiana, was the only one with a statute legally defining</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.72</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>53</label>
                     <title>Reflections on Whiteness:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Latinos(as)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILDMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHANIE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Imagine that a plane crashes, and in the wreckage we discover a book. Nothing on its cover gives any indication of its contents. But when we open it up, it reveals all the secrets of how to behave as if you rule the world. Suddenly we have an explanation for why so many of them seem to behave the same way and also why they just don’t get it: This handbook teaches them all how to be who they are and makes them so they can’t hear us or see us, so much of the time. These are the rules</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.73</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>54</label>
                     <title>Stirring the Ashes:</title>
                     <subtitle>Race, Class, and the Future of Civil Rights Scholarship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ANSLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCES LEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “class model” of white supremacy portrays it as a means to justify and enhance class dominance and thus to strengthen existing relations of economic power. This function gives racism its central status in American political life and assures its survival. This is the source of racism’s strength and resilience. The class model addresses how, in a white supremacist system, the poor people of all races come out on the short end while the people of the dominant classes appear to extract extraordinary benefits.</p>
                     <p>The “class domination model” sees racism as an economic tool of the dominant classes, assuring the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.74</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>55</label>
                     <title>The Social Construction of Whiteness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHONEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>330</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Race is a phenomenon always in formation. Therefore whiteness, like other racial constructions, is subject to contest and change. Whiteness is historically located, malleable, and contingent. Arguments about the contingency of white privilege, and its dysfunctionality for white working people, may seem counterintuitive. Most writers emphasize what whites gain—the existence and benefits of privilege—or what whites lose—the costs of change for whites—rather than looking at transformative interests for whites. Yet some struggles that brought antiracist consciousness to the defense of shared class interest succeeded, historically, even under the formidable difficulties of formal segregation, and fomentation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.75</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>334</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.76</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>334</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.77</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.78</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>56</label>
                     <title>The Mind of the South</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CASH</surname>
                           <given-names>W. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There remain the people who, under the classical interpretation, were lumped together as poor whites—the non-slaveholding masses of the South. Who were they? Obviously and simply, in the large and outside the oldest regions, the residue of the generally homogeneous population of the old backwoods of the eighteenth century, from which the main body of the ruling class had been selected out. The relatively and absolutely unsuccessful, the less industrious and thrifty, the less ambitious and pushing, the less cunning and lucky—the majority here as everywhere. The weaker elements which, having failed in the competition of the cotton</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.79</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>57</label>
                     <title>Old Poison in New Bottles:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Deep Roots of Modern Nativism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FEAGIN</surname>
                           <given-names>JOE R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>348</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dating back at least two centuries, anti-immigrant nativism has profoundly shaped the history and present demography of this nation. For instance, the 1990 census revealed that<italic>only twelve</italic>of the world’s nearly two hundred countries were checked off by as much as one percent of Americans as countries of national origin: Britain, Ireland, Canada, Italy, Russia, Poland, France, Netherlands, Sweden, Germany, Norway, and Mexico. From 1607 to 1990 the major waves of immigrants to this country came from Great Britain and certain other European countries (all but one in northern Europe), and from Africa and Mexico. Conspicuously absent from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.80</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>58</label>
                     <title>The First Word in Whiteness:</title>
                     <subtitle>Early Twentieth-Century European Experiences</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROEDIGER</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>354</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A character in Chester Himes’ 1945 novel,<italic>If He Hollers Let Him Go</italic>, has a “funny thought.” He begins to “wonder when white people started to get white—or rather, when they started losing it.” The narrower question of when new immigrants “started to get white” and of what they lost in doing it has received passionate and varied treatment within African-American thought. That treatment provides the best points of entry to the question of white identity among new immigrants to date.</p>
                     <p>The simplest and perhaps most celebrated answer to how the whiteness of new European immigrants came about appears</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.81</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>59</label>
                     <title>Life on the Color Line</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILLIAMS</surname>
                           <given-names>GREGORY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Billy!” Dad said sharply as he leaned across the aisle. I looked into his face. The Greyhound’s air brakes hissed as it slowed for the junction with State Highway 201. In a somber voice he continued. “Boys, I’ve got some bad news for you.” He paused. We leaned forward, anxiously. The wool of the seat made me itch. “We’re not going to stay with Grandpa and Grandma Cook when we get to Muncie.”</p>
                     <p>The gears clunked and the bus shuddered to a stop at an intersection.</p>
                     <p>“Why not?” I demanded.</p>
                     <p>“Your mother and I are getting a divorce. We can’t</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.82</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>60</label>
                     <title>Others, and the WASP World They Aspired To</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BROOKHISER</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>360</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In its brief history, America has experienced the greatest population transfer the Western world has known since the fall of Rome, with happier results.</p>
                     <p>This human tsunami has been seen as a simple transfer, not an amalgamation: a shift of bodies, not souls. Michael Novak called ethnics unmeltable. Father Andrew Greeley, the novelist and pollster, pops up every few years with a study showing how different Catholic and Protestant Americans continue to be (and justifying, incidentally, the existence of priestly pollsters).</p>
                     <p>Many WASPs have made similar assumptions about the tenacity of immigrant behavior and have brooded about the effects it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.83</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>61</label>
                     <title>Beyond the Melting Pot</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GLAZER</surname>
                           <given-names>NATHAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOYNIHAN</surname>
                           <given-names>DANIEL PATRICK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>368</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was reasonable to believe that a new American type would emerge, a new nationality in which it would be a matter of indifference whether a man was of Anglo-Saxon or German or Italian or Jewish origin, and in which indeed, because of the diffusion of populations through all parts of the country and all levels of the social order, and because of the consequent close contact and intermarriage, it would be impossible to make such distinctions. After all, in 1960 almost half of New York City’s population was still foreign-born or the children of foreign-born. Yet it is also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.84</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>62</label>
                     <title>The Economic Payoff of Attending an Ivy-League Institution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COOK</surname>
                           <given-names>PHILIP J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRANK</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>378</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many of our best and brightest high-school seniors know what most of our higher-education leaders have been reluctant to admit: An increasingly small number of colleges and universities have become the gatekeepers for society’s top-paying jobs.</p>
                     <p>Look at the legal profession. Lawyers who deal with mergers and business acquisitions, for example, receive just a small percentage of the money that changes hands in the transactions that they negotiate, but their fees can amount to millions of dollars in multibillion-dollar deals. Not surprisingly many bright and ambitious young people ask themselves, “How can I get a job as a Wall Street</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.85</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>63</label>
                     <title>Useful Knowledge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAPPELLO</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the process of becoming official, of gaining the authority to reproduce knowledges about the history of private and public utterances in the United States, in entering the academy as an assistant professor of English, I have experienced in many ways the not-so-subtle necessity of having to move as far away as possible from who I am. When I think “working class,” pictures come to me more readily than words, thus signaling this aspect as perhaps the most unspeakable feature of my identity in academe. I am, after all, much more aware of how even my lesbianism, an obvious site</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.86</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>64</label>
                     <title>Stupid Rich Bastards</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BLACK</surname>
                           <given-names>LAUREL JOHNSON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sunday morning, six o’ clock. Dad knocks on my door and in a stage whisper tells me to get up and get going. Trying not to wake up my sister, I crawl out of bed into the chilly Massachusetts air and pull on jeans, a T-shirt, a sweatshirt, and sneakers. Nothing that can’t get dirty. This isn’t church, but it might as well be, an education full of rituals, its own language, its mystery and rewards, its punishments for falling away.</p>
                     <p>Every Sunday, each child in turn went with Dad to the flea markets, the yard sales, the junk yards,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.87</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>65</label>
                     <title>How Did Jews Become White Folks?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SACKS</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREN BRODKIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The late nineteenth and early decades of the twentieth centuries saw a steady stream of warnings by scientists, policymakers, and the popular press that “mongrelization” of the Nordic, or Anglo-Saxon, race—the real Americans—by inferior European races (as well as inferior non-European ones) was destroying the fabric of the nation. I continue to be surprised to read that America did not always regard its immigrant European workers as white, that it thought people from different nations were biologically different. My parents, first-generation U.S.-born eastern European Jews, are not surprised. They expect anti-Semitism to be part of the fabric of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.88</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>66</label>
                     <title>How White People Became White</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARRETT</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROEDIGER</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>402</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1980, Joseph Loguidice, an elderly Italian-American from Chicago, sat down to give his life story to an interviewer. His first and most vivid childhood recollection was of a race riot that had occurred on the city’s near north side. Wagons full of policemen with “peculiar hats” streamed into his neighborhood. But the “one thing that stood out in my mind,” Loguidice remembered after six decades, was “a man running down the middle of the street hollering …’I’m White, I’m White!’” After first taking him for an African-American, Loguidice soon realized that the man was a white coal handler covered</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.89</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>67</label>
                     <title>Paths to Belonging:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Constitution and Cultural Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KARST</surname>
                           <given-names>KENNETH L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Virtually every cultural minority in America has had to face exclusion, forced conformity, and subordination. All these patterns are variations on the same theme: those who are different cannot belong as full members of the community. The victims of cultural domination, therefore, face a serious problem: they must necessarily live their lives within the larger society, and in order to define themselves they must satisfy their basic needs for connection. They may choose to turn inward to the solidarity of the excluded group, banding together to confront the larger society. Alternatively, individual members of the cultural minority may, as to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.90</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>68</label>
                     <title>Is the Radical Critique of Merit Anti-Semitic?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FARBER</surname>
                           <given-names>DANIEL A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHERRY</surname>
                           <given-names>SUZANNA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>414</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>[According to critical race theory,] a group’s success cannot be justified on the basis of any presumed excellence in the performance of its members. [Critical race theory holds that notions of merit are manipulable and based on culture. Ed.] As applied to so-called “model minorities” like Jews or some groups of Asian Americans, however, this creates a paradox, for these groups seem to have succeeded in important social arenas beyond the average achievements of the dominant majority of white Gentiles. In 1970, Jewish family income was 172% of the average American income, Japanese-American family income was 132% of the average,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.91</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>420</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.92</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.93</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.94</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>69</label>
                     <title>Passing for White, Passing for Black</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PIPER</surname>
                           <given-names>ADRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>[T]racing the history of my family is detective work as well as historical research. To date, what I<italic>think</italic>I know is that our first European-American ancestor landed in Ipswich, Massachusetts, in 1620 from Sussex; another in Jamestown, Virginia, in 1675 from London; and another in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, in 1751 from Hamburg. Yet another was the first in our family to graduate from my own graduate institution in 1778. My great-great-grandmother from Madagascar, by way of Louisiana, is the known African ancestor on my father’s side, as my great-great-grandfather from the Ibo of Nigeria is the known African ancestor on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.95</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>70</label>
                     <title>Black Like Me</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRIFFIN</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN HOWARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>432</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the past four days, I had spent my time at the doctor’s or closed up in my room with cotton pads over my eyes and the sun lamp turned on me. They had made blood tests twice and found no indication of damage to the liver. But the medication produced lassitude and I felt constantly on the verge of nausea.</p>
                     <p>The doctor, well-disposed, gave me many warnings about the dangers of this project in so far as my contact with Negroes was concerned. Now that he had had time to think, he was beginning to doubt the wisdom of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.96</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>71</label>
                     <title>The Michael Jackson Pill:</title>
                     <subtitle>Equality, Race, and Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CULP</surname>
                           <given-names>JEROME McCRISTAL</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>438</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>I was leaving Langdell Hall, after having feasted too fervently at my fifteenth law school reunion, when I noticed what looked like a very ancient document pushed down in the trash can. The ancient scroll seemed out of place so carelessly thrown away outside the world’s largest law school library. I picked it up and was surprised to discover that there, very near Derrick Bell’s former office, I had found another of the scrolls that Professor Bell’s friend Geneva had revealed to him before she joined the celestial curia. What was this wondrous document doing in Langdell Hall? Maybe it</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.97</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>72</label>
                     <title>Did the First Justice Harlan Have a Black Brother?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GORDON</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>444</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On September 18, 1848, James Harlan, father of future Supreme Court Justice John Marshall Harlan, appeared in the Franklin County Court for the purpose of freeing his mulatto slave, Robert Harlan. This appearance formalized Robert’s free status and exposed a remarkable link between this talented mulatto and his prominent lawyer-politician sponsor.</p>
                     <p>This event would have little historical significance but for Robert Harlan’s being no ordinary slave. Born in 1816, and raised in James Harlan’s household, blue-eyed, light-skinned Robert Harlan had been treated by James Harlan more like a member of the family than like a slave. Robert was given an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.98</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>73</label>
                     <title>Learning How to Be Niggers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILLIAMS</surname>
                           <given-names>GREGORY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>458</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Come on boys. Let’s go to Aunt Bess’s.”</p>
                     <p>We followed the alley to Monroe Street. As we trudged south, I realized I’d never seen so many black people in Muncie before. What bothered me most, however, was the tattered, down-at-the-heels feel of the neighborhood. The contrast with Grandpa and Grandma Cook’s sparkling white two-story home in the new Mayfield Addition was striking. Here, gloomy weather-beaten houses tottered on crumbling foundations. Exposed two-by-fours propped sagging porches. Jagged glass shards were all that remained in many windows. Graffiti-covered plywood sheets partially covered doorways. The yards were small, littered, and unkempt. Across First</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.99</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>74</label>
                     <title>What Does a White Woman Look Like?</title>
                     <subtitle>Racing and Erasing in Law</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRANKE</surname>
                           <given-names>KATHERINE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>467</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In significant ways, legal texts produce a narrative of national identity. They weave stories about who we are, what we are committed to, and what we expect of one another, individually and collectively. Certain foundational fictions, like “We the People,” provide the glue that over time binds a people to its past and to one another as a nation. But should law play the same role with respect to other aspects of human identity? I think not. Current debates surrounding affirmative action, congressional redistricting, the Million Man March, and the appointment of Clarence Thomas to the Supreme Court all represent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.100</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>75</label>
                     <title>La Guera</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORAGA</surname>
                           <given-names>CHERRIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>471</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am the very well-educated daughter of a woman who, by the standards in this country, would be considered largely illiterate. My mother was born in Santa Paula, Southern California, at a time when much of the central valley there was still farm land. Nearly thirty-five years later, in 1948, she was the only daughter of six to marry an anglo, my father.</p>
                     <p>My mother is a fine story-teller, recalling every event of her life with the vividness of the present, noting each detail right down to the cut and color of her dress. I remember stories of her being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.101</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>76</label>
                     <title>Notes of a White Black Woman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCALES-TRENT</surname>
                           <given-names>JUDY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>475</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We Americans have been talking about race for a long time. It is a constant theme in our lives and in our common language. Although the specific topic changes over the years—varying all the way from fugitive slave laws to affirmative action—the theme remains. Ideas about race lie at the core of the American character and the American dream.</p>
                     <p>In general, discussions about race center on the state of relations between black Americans and white Americans. They focus on who will control the resources: freedom, jobs, schools, housing, medical care. In some of this debate, black people call</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.102</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>77</label>
                     <title>Our Next Race Question:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Uneasiness between Blacks and Latinos</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DE ALVA</surname>
                           <given-names>JORGE KLOR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHORRIS</surname>
                           <given-names>EARL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEST</surname>
                           <given-names>CORNEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>482</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The angry and confused discourse about American race relations that followed the O. J. Simpson trial may have been passionate, but it blindly assumed (as if the year were 1963 or 1861) that the only major axis of racial division in America was black-white. Strangely ignored in the media backwash was the incipient tension between the country’s largest historical minority, blacks, and its largest future one, Latinos.</p>
                     <p>In fifteen years, Latinos (known to the U.S. Census as Hispanics) will outnumber blacks, as they already do in twenty-one states. Each group constitutes an ever greater percentage of the total population; each</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.103</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>78</label>
                     <title>A Review of Life on the Color Line</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LIAS</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA CHAMA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHANE</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>493</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1954, at the age of ten, Greg Williams took an unforgettable journey to Muncie, Indiana. Until that time, Greg and his younger brother Mike had lived in Virginia as white children. Their mother was white, and their father (then called Tony, later Buster) told everyone that he was Italian. But when the marriage broke up and Tony’s financial ventures failed, he pushed Greg’s life over the color line. He moved the boys to the black section of Muncie, where he had been raised. “In Virginia you were white boys,” he told Greg and Mike. “In Indiana you’re going to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.104</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>79</label>
                     <title>What Is Race, Anyway?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLSON</surname>
                           <given-names>TOD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>499</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the winter of 1993, the small town of Wedowee, Alabama, became a flashpoint of racial tension. The white principal of Randolph County High School had gathered the student body together to find out how many students planned to attend the prom with dates “outside their race.” When several students raised their hands, he canceled the event. “How would that look at a prom, a bunch of mixed couples?” he scolded. From the stunned audience, a single voice responded. Junior-class president Revonda Bowen, daughter of a white father and an African-American mother, asked, “Who am I supposed to take to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.105</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.106</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>502</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.107</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>503</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.108</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>80</label>
                     <title>The Misleading Abstractions of Social Scientists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAGAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JEROME</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>507</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Five-month-old infants who stare at surprising events for a long time, 5-year-old children with large vocabularies, and 50-year-old adults who invent new computer programs are all described as intelligent. The use of the same adjective implies that the same process is operating in all three situations. But we have no good evidence to support the idea that the psychological processes that produce an attentive infant are the same as those that produce a creative computer programmer. Moreover, a small number of psychologists—including J. P. Guilford, Howard Gardner, and Robert Sternberg—have argued persuasively against the usefulness of the notion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.109</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>81</label>
                     <title>Caste, Crime, and Precocity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HACKER</surname>
                           <given-names>ANDREW</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>510</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have no problem accepting<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>’s finding that Americans with European forebearers average better on IQ tests than citizens with African ancestries. And for present purposes, I will concede the authors’ claim that the capacity for scoring well via the multiple-choice method is “substantially heritable.”</p>
                     <p>Yet Herrnstein and Murray also warn that while individuals get their genes through their parents, this inheritance does not entitle us to make race-based generalizations. “That a trait is genetically transmitted in individuals,” they write, “does not mean that group differences in that trait are also genetic in origin.”</p>
                     <p>Really? Surely what we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.110</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>82</label>
                     <title>Embodiment and Perspective:</title>
                     <subtitle>Can White Men Jump?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HALEWOOD</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>512</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where we are positioned in society, and how we think of and live in our bodies, are questions we do not usually connect to the (both everyday and scholarly) claims we make about social and legal problems. “The body” and “knowledge” have traditionally been understood as unrelated categories. However, recent interdisciplinary work in philosophy and law emphasizes “positionality,” and calls into question the abstract, disembodied quality of conventional Western theories of knowledge (epistemologies) which ground the Western conception of law. Western epistemology, its critics say, has artificially bracketed off the material particulars of experience and identity, including the spatial particularity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.111</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>83</label>
                     <title>Bell Curve Liberals:</title>
                     <subtitle>How the Left Betrayed IQ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WOOLDRIDGE</surname>
                           <given-names>ADRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>515</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Opposition to the use of IQ testing goes back as far as testing itself. Its practitioners have been accused of misusing science to justify capitalist exploitation; allowing their obsession with classification to blind them to the huge variety of human abilities; encouraging soulless teaching; and, worst of all, inflaming racial prejudices and justifying racial inequalities. To this school of thinking,<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>was a godsend. Charles Murray and Richard J. Herrnstein succeeded in effectively linking IQ testing firmly in people’s minds with spectacularly unpopular arguments: that different racial groups have different IQ averages; that America is calcifying into rigid</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.112</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>84</label>
                     <title>Brave New Right</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LIND</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>519</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The controversy about<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>is not about<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>only. It is about the sudden and astonishing legitimation, by the leading intellectuals and journalists of the mainstream right, of a body of racialist pseudoscience created by a small group of researchers, most of them subsidized by the hereditarian Pioneer Fund.<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>is a layman’s introduction to this material, which had been repudiated by the responsible right for a generation.</p>
                     <p>Whatever the leaders of mainstream conservatism may claim now, in the seventies and eighties they themselves, and not merely the “politically correct” left, repudiated the kind</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.113</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>85</label>
                     <title>Race and Parentage</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBERTS</surname>
                           <given-names>DOROTHY E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>523</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most striking features of technological efforts to provide parents with genetically related offspring is that they are used almost exclusively by affluent white people. The use of fertility clinics does not correspond to rates of infertility. Indeed, the profile of people most likely to attempt IVF [in vitro fertilization. Ed.] is precisely the opposite of those most likely to be infertile. The people in the United States most likely to be infertile are older, poorer, black, and poorly educated. Most couples who use IVF services are white, highly educated, and affluent. New reproductive technologies are popular not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.114</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>86</label>
                     <title>The Sources of The Bell Curve</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LANE</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>528</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By scrutinizing the footnotes and bibliography in<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>, readers can more easily recognize the project for what it is: a chilly synthesis of the work of disreputable race theorists and eccentric eugenicists. It would be unfair, of course, to ascribe to Murray and Hermstein all the noxious views of their sources. Mere association with dubious thinkers does not discredit the book by itself. But even a superficial examination of the primary sources suggests that some of Murray and Hermstein’s substantive arguments rely on questionable data and hotly contested scholarship, produced by academics whose ideological biases are pronounced. To</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.115</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>87</label>
                     <title>Hearts of Darkness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JUDIS</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>530</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the problems with<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>is that the authors continually muddy their own water with equivocation, qualification, and even contradiction. Which of these statements do Murray and Herrnstein really believe?</p>
                     <p>“We cannot think of any legitimate argument why any encounter between individual whites and blacks need be affected by the knowledge that an aggregate ethnic difference in measured intelligence is genetic rather than environmental.”</p>
                     <p>“The assumption of genetic cognitive equality among the races has practical consequences.”</p>
                     <p>“Race is such a difficult concept to employ in the American context. What does it mean to be ‘black’ in America,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.116</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>88</label>
                     <title>Thank You, Doctors Murray and Herrnstein (Or, Who’s Afraid of Critical Race Theory?)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BELL</surname>
                           <given-names>DERRICK A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>534</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Radical assessment can encompass illustration, anecdote, allegory, and imagination, as well as analysis of doctrine and cases. I want to utilize all of these techniques to comment on a contemporary phenomenon:<italic>The Bell Curve</italic>. A great deal of attention and energy has been devoted to commending and condemning Charles Murray and the late Richard Herrnstein, authors of this best-selling book on racial intelligence. This book suggests great social policy significance in the fact that black people score, on average, fifteen points below whites on I.Q. tests.</p>
                     <p>This thesis has been criticized as the rehashing of views long-ago rejected by virtually</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.117</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>89</label>
                     <title>Dangerous Undertones of the New Nativism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KANSTROOM</surname>
                           <given-names>DANIEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>538</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the late summer of 1918, with the final defeat of the German empire only a few months away, the first volume of<italic>The Decline of the West</italic>appeared in Germany and Austria. Written by a then unknown German historian named Oswald Spengler, the book soon became a sensation with a profound impact on intellectual debate and German politics for the following two decades. Though originally conceived as a political critique of the folly and criminal and suicidal optimism of pre–First World War German foreign policy, the work grew substantially beyond that modest goal. According to Spengler, the book</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.118</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>542</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.119</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>542</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.120</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>543</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.121</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>90</label>
                     <title>The Rise of Private Militia:</title>
                     <subtitle>A First and Second Amendment Analysis of the Right to Organize and the Right to Train</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>POLESKY</surname>
                           <given-names>JOELLE E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>547</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Copious news coverage of Ruby Ridge,¹ Waco,² and the Oklahoma City bombing³ has prompted a growing concern with the proliferation of paramilitary organizations and paramilitary activity.⁴ The public’s anxiety is fueled by the belief that private militia pose a threat to society. Private militia are commonly misunderstood and mischaracterized as organizations comprised solely of right-wing militants adhering to Aryan, racist ideology. Although many militia members subscribe to these views, allegiance to the far right is not a prerequisite to membership in a private militia.⁵ Instead, ardent belief in the need to protect individual rights from encroachment by the federal government</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.122</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>91</label>
                     <title>The Changing Faces of White Supremacy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSS</surname>
                           <given-names>LORETTA J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAUNEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY ANN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>552</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>White supremacy holds that the interests of people of European descent are superior to those of people who believe, act, or look differently than” normal.” It perpetuates the stratification of class, race, religion, sexual orientation, and gender. It embraces Nazism, fascism, and violence. Its open manifestations are extremist hate groups; its results are political and social systems based not on the democratic ideals of majority rule, tolerance, diversity, equality, and justice, but on “white is right.” White supremacists are America’s deepest nightmare because they attack not only individuals and groups, but the legitimacy of our democratic process itself.</p>
                     <p>Because the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.123</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>92</label>
                     <title>Hatelines:</title>
                     <subtitle>Week of Sunday, April 7, 1996</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>COMPILED BY</role>
                        <collab>THE CENTER FOR DEMOCRATIC RENEWAL</collab>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>558</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>White pride, white pride, white pride. It’s great to be white! White man, fight back! First, the good news. Nigger Ron Brown and a gaggle of chief executive officers from American big business died in a beautiful plane crash. The greedy big business CEO’s were in Bosnia to help<italic>their</italic>economy, not ours. There will be no tears shed at Klan headquarters over the well-deserved death of a bunch of greedy, scumbag internationalists and businessmen.</p>
                     <p>In other good news, that old crone, Mother Teresa. fell and broke her collarbone. Mother Teresa wastes her time in India fishing mud babies out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.124</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>93</label>
                     <title>Blue by Day and White by [K]night</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARNES</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>561</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Embittered by the South’s defeat during the Civil War, early Klansmen set out to keep the “niggers” in their place and to eliminate all scalawags, carpetbaggers, and other northerners who preached political and social equality for blacks. Under the banner “White Supremacy Forever,” the group’s activities included beatings, lynchings, torture, and mutilation, often inflicted with impunity because judges, politicians, and law-enforcement officers were fellow Klansmen or loyal sympathizers.</p>
                     <p>In 1871, during its deliberations on what has become widely known as the Ku Klux Klan Act, Congress compiled nearly six hundred pages of testimony dealing with the activities of Klansmen and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.125</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>94</label>
                     <title>The Race Question and Its Solution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ARMSTRONG</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>566</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The political doctrine of the equality of men is a beautiful, but self evident lie. There is no equality among people of even the same blood.</p>
                     <p>Nature delights in nothing so much as in the inequality of her products. She revels in unlikenesses, in differences, in disparities. She endows the brain of one man, or one race, with the noblest genius, while to another she gives scarcely anything at all, except a brutal instinct to satisfy the simplest of animal needs and passions. We see it in the contemplation of savage and civilized man—in the difference between the tools,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.126</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>95</label>
                     <title>The American Neo-Nazi Movement Today</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LANGER</surname>
                           <given-names>ELINOR</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>573</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In writing about a subject that carries with it the automatic weight of its association with Nazi Germany, I find myself … suspended between caution and alarm. Especially about a movement as underreported as this one, you do not write, in the first place, merely to observe “This too will pass away”; you write to sound an alert. At the same time, you know that the tests of time are different and that historians of another generation will consider the evidence and say either that it was all simply part of another “Brown Scare” in which people, as usual, lost</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.127</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>96</label>
                     <title>Talking about Race with America’s Klansmen</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EZEKIEL</surname>
                           <given-names>RAPHAEL S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>586</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the Reconstruction era to 1945, between 3,000 and 5,000 black Americans were killed in mob violence, much of it instigated by the Ku Klux Klan. Some victims were hanged or burned to death; often men’s genitals were mutilated. Later, during the civil-rights struggles of the 1960s, reincarnations of the Klan spread terror and death, burning buses, clubbing demonstrators, and bombing homes and churches. Today we see another white racist movement, with Klansmen joined by neo-Nazis, racist skinheads, and members of intensely racist churches. Most of today’s violence is perpetrated by individuals who are not formally affiliated with these organized</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.128</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>97</label>
                     <title>Antidiscrimination Law and Transparency:</title>
                     <subtitle>Barriers to Equality?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLAGG</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>589</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Racial identity is not a central life experience for most white people, because it does not have to be.¹ Like members of any socially dominant group, white people have the option to set aside consciousness of the characteristic that defines the dominant class—in this case, race. Thus whiteness is experienced as racelessness, and personal identity is conceived in a race-neutral manner. However, race plays quite a different role in the lives of people of color in this society. It is, again as a consequence of existing social structures that define and give meaning to racial identity, a central facet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.129</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>98</label>
                     <title>White Supremacy (And What We Should Do about It)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ANSLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCES LEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>592</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Civil rights scholars have offered various analyses to explain the development of the civil rights movement, civil rights litigation, and civil rights legal doctrine. Implicit in these analyses are different ideas about the nature of racism. In asking how and why the existing system of racial dominance and subordination has survived the powerful waves of opposition and resistance that have broken upon it, scholars have necessarily confronted, directly or indirectly, the question of white supremacy’s origin and why it has such staying power. According to an approach that I will call here the “race model” (and in contrast with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.130</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>99</label>
                     <title>White Superiority in America:</title>
                     <subtitle>Its Legal Legacy, Its Economic Costs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BELL</surname>
                           <given-names>DERRICK A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>596</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A major function of racial discrimination is to facilitate the exploitation of black labor, to deny blacks access to benefits and opportunities, and to blame all the manifestations of exclusion-bred despair on the asserted inferiority of the victims. Two other inter-connected political phenomena emanate from the widely shared belief that whites are superior to blacks. First, whites of widely varying socio-economic status employ white supremacy as a catalyst to negotiate policy differences, often through compromises that sacrifice the rights of blacks. Second, even those whites who lack wealth and power are sustained in their sense of racial superiority and more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.131</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Synopses of Other Important Works</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>601</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.132</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>604</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.133</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>604</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.134</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>100</label>
                     <title>Treason to Whiteness Is Loyalty to Humanity</title>
                     <subtitle>AN INTERVIEW WITH NOEL IGNATIEV OF RACE TRAITOR MAGAZINE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>IGNATIEV</surname>
                           <given-names>NOEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>607</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A traitor to the white race is someone who is nominally classified as white, but who defies the rules of whiteness so flagrantly as to jeopardize his or her ability to draw upon the privileges of the white skin.</p>
                     <p>“Race” has meant various things in history. We use the term to mean a group that includes all social classes, in a situation where the most degraded member of a dominant group is exalted over any member of a subordinate group. That formation was first successfully established in the 17th century. By then there already existed a trade across the Atlantic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.135</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>101</label>
                     <title>How to Be a Race Traitor:</title>
                     <subtitle>Six Ways to Fight Being White</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>IGNATIEV</surname>
                           <given-names>NOEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>613</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Identify with the racially oppressed; violate the rules of whiteness in ways that can have a social impact.</p>
                     <p>Answer an anti-black slur with, “Oh, you probably said that because you think I’m white. That’s a mistake people often make because I look white.” Reply “Me, too” to charges that “people on welfare don’t want to work, they just want to stay home and have babies.”</p>
                     <p>Oppose tracking in the schools, oppose all mechanisms that favor whites in the job market, and oppose the police and courts, which define black people as a criminal class.</p>
                     <p>Do not merely oppose these things</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.136</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>102</label>
                     <title>Rodrigo’s Eleventh Chronicle:</title>
                     <subtitle>Empathy and False Empathy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DELGADO</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>614</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We picked out our desserts, which the waiter quickly brought, Rodrigo’s a creamy French-Vietnamese pastry of some sort, mine a tangy lemon sorbet. After eating for a few minutes in tacitly agreed-to silence, I looked up at Rodrigo.</p>
                     <p>“I hope that my real dessert will be that you tell me what your solution is to the predicament in which we find ourselves. Reformers and minorities get little if any genuine empathy in courts, or indeed anywhere, and can count on no one but themselves to climb out of poverty and despair. Life’s road is hard going. Can’t we find confederates?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.137</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>103</label>
                     <title>Obscuring the Importance of Race:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Implications of Making Comparisons between Racism and Sexism (or Other Isms)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRILLO</surname>
                           <given-names>TRINA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILDMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHANIE M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>619</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While this chapter was being written, Trina Grillo, who is of Afro-Cuban and Italian descent, was diagnosed as having Hodgkin’s disease [a form of cancer]. In talking about this experience she said that” cancer has become the first filter through which I see the world. It used to be race, but now it is cancer. My neighbor just became pregnant, and all I could think was ‘How could she get pregnant? What if she gets cancer?’”</p>
                     <p>Stephanie Wildman, who is Jewish and white, heard this remark and thought, “I understand how she feels; I worry about getting cancer too. I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.138</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>104</label>
                     <title>White Men Can Jump:</title>
                     <subtitle>But Must Try a Little Harder</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HALEWOOD</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>627</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I hope to demonstrate that progressive, committed, white male law teachers should engage in scholarship investigating the relation of law to social and political subordination, provided that they do so in ways that respond to feminist and minority critiques, and provided that in doing so they do not preempt or displace scholars who are white women or people of color. I think that while specific forms of subordinated experience are not at hand to white male scholars on which to base their scholarship, nonetheless one usually has some fragment of such experience from which to build bridges to other groups’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.139</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>105</label>
                     <title>“Was Blind, but Now I See”:</title>
                     <subtitle>White Race Consciousness and the Requirement of Discriminatory Intent</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLAGG</surname>
                           <given-names>BARBARA J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>629</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most striking characteristic of whites’ consciousness of whiteness is that most of the time we don’t have any. I call this the<italic>transparency</italic>phenomenon: the tendency of whites not to think about whiteness, or about norms, behaviors, experiences, or perspectives that are white-specific. Transparency often is the mechanism through which white decisionmakers who disavow white supremacy impose white norms on blacks. [See also Chapters 15, 35, and 97. Ed.] Transparency operates to require black assimilation even when pluralism is the articulated goal; it affords substantial advantages to whites over blacks even when decisionmakers intend to effect substantive racial justice.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.140</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>106</label>
                     <title>White Women, Race Matters:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Social Construction of Whiteness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRANKENBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>RUTH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>632</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fundamentally a relational category, whiteness<italic>does</italic>have content inasmuch as it generates norms, ways of understanding history, ways of thinking about self and other, and even ways of thinking about the notion of culture itself. We need to look more closely at the content of the normative and attempt to analyze both its history and its consequences. One step in this direction is antiracist writers’ increasing use of the terms Euro-American or European American alongside African American, Asian American, Native American, Latino, and Chicano. Using “European American” to describe white Americans has the advantage that it parallels and in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.141</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>107</label>
                     <title>Resisting Racisms, Eliminating Exclusions:</title>
                     <subtitle>South Africa and the United States</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOLDBERG</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID THEO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>635</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Resistance to racisms consists in vigorously contending and disputing exclusionary values, norms, institutions, and practices, as well as assertively articulating open-ended specifications and means for an incorporative politics. Where racisms are openly and volubly expressed, it is likely a matter of time before a more or less organized resistance by its objects, often in alliance with other antiracists, will arise in response; witness the emergence of resistance to slavery in the United States, to the destruction of indigenous people on all continents, to the [Nazis and their allies in Europe and to]<italic>apartheid</italic>in South Africa, to David Duke in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.142</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>108</label>
                     <title>Dysconscious Racism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Cultural Politics of Critiquing Ideology and Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KING</surname>
                           <given-names>JOYCE E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>640</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One goal of my course, when I was Associate Professor of Teacher Education at Santa Clara University, was to sharpen the ability of students to think critically about educational purposes and practice in relation to social justice and to their own identities as teachers. The course thus illuminates a range of ideological interests which become the focus of students’ critical analysis, evaluation, and choice. For instance, a recurring theme is that of the social purposes of schooling. This is a key concept about which many students report they have never thought seriously. Course readings, lectures, discussions, and other activities are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.143</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>109</label>
                     <title>What Should White Women Do?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHONEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>642</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Focusing solely on the sexual exploitation of women hides both racist oppression and the strength, struggles, and multiple interests of women of color. The experience of being a woman of color cannot be understood in any way that sees only what is done to women generally. White people will think racially as whites without thinking “about race,” because we tend to equate “race” with “non-white.” We will not understand that we are thinking racially when we are not thinking about people of color. This aspect of our experience as white women will shape what we do, but it will be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.144</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>110</label>
                     <title>Confronting Racelessness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BROWN</surname>
                           <given-names>ELEANOR MARIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>644</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kendall Thomas coined the phrase “we are raced”¹ as a race-conscious challenge to the abstract notions of citizen and state as they are conceptualized in liberal legalism. Thomas insists that our received notions of rights and duties in law are rife with racial implications. This is particularly the case given the highly charged racial context within which notions of rights and duties were developed, who they were meant to exclude, and our societal struggle to make the law “color-blind.” In this context, abstract notions of citizen, government, rights, and duties do not begin to account for the relationship between people</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.145</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>111</label>
                     <title>A Civil Rights Agenda for the Year 2000:</title>
                     <subtitle>Confessions of an Identity Politician</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ANSLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCES LEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>646</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am not an African-American, and I will not be speaking from the perspective of the African-American community, although I am firmly convinced that my own well-being is intimately bound up with the well-being of that community. I am a European-American, a female, someone who has counted myself a part of legal and social struggles for justice—for people of color, for women of all races, and for individuals from all races and both genders whose economic resources consist only of their increasingly uncertain ability to sell their labor to others. I have less to say to and about the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.146</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>112</label>
                     <title>What We Believe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <collab>THE EDITORS OF RACE TRAITOR MAGAZINE</collab>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>653</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The white race is a historically constructed social formation. It consists of all those who partake of the privileges of the white skin in this society. Its most wretched members share a status higher, in certain respects, than that of the most exalted persons excluded from it, in return for which they give their support to a system that degrades them.</p>
                     <p>The key to solving the social problems of our age is to abolish the white race, which means no more and no less than abolishing the privileges of the white skin. Until that task is accomplished, even partial reform</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.147</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>113</label>
                     <title>Segregation, Whiteness, and Transformation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MAHONEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTHA R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>654</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Transformative work against segregation and racial oppression must directly confront racism and the social construction of race. Whiteness and blackness are not merely mirror images of each other. “White” does not only mean “opposite of Other” but also stands for the dominant, transparent norm that defines what attributes of race should be counted, how to count them, and who (as in white employers or mortgage bankers) gets to do the counting. Therefore, destabilizing “Other” -ness doesn’t entirely destabilize the dominance of whiteness. Even though race has no natural reality or truth, it has great social force. More work is required,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.148</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>114</label>
                     <title>White Out</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILKINS</surname>
                           <given-names>ROGER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>658</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I live on a street in Washington, D.C., where the Speaker of the House, senators, congressmen, and a couple of Supreme Court justices also live. A few blocks away are two large public-housing projects. The Safeway where we all shop may be the most racially and economically integrated supermarket in America. Public servants with big titles shop alongside people who buy their staples with food stamps. And a couple of times a year there are street murders a half-mile away.</p>
                     <p>Since the late fifties, when I was a welfare caseworker in poor black precincts in Cleveland, my heart has never</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.149</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From the Editors:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues and Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>664</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.150</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>664</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.151</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>665</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.152</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>671</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bw1kc5.153</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>681</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
