<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125vtw</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">berm14950</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN56.M54B47 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Modernism (Literature)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Modernist Commitments</book-title>
         <subtitle>Ethics, Politics, and Transnational Modernism</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Berman</surname>
               <given-names>Jessica</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231520393</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231520395</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/berm14950"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Jessica Berman demonstrates how modernist narrative connects ethical attitudes and responsibilities to the active creation of political relationships and the way we imagine justice. She challenges divisions between "modernist" and "committed" writing, arguing that a continuum of political engagement undergirds modernisms worldwide and that it is strengthened rather than hindered by formal experimentation. In addition to making the case for a transnational model of modernism, Berman shows how modernism's play with formal matters, its challenge to the boundaries between fact and fiction, its incorporation of vernacular and folkways, and its engagement with embodied experience and intimacy offer not only an expanded account of modernist texts and commitments but a new way of thinking about what modernism is and can do.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="384"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>Imagining Justice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In his first novel,<italic>Untouchable</italic> (1928), the celebrated Indian writer Mulk Raj Anand follows a day in the life of an untouchable boy named Bakha, whose travails in a small village raise complex questions about the ethical and political dimensions of modernity in latecolonial India. One of the first novels to feature the outcaste as hero,<italic>Untouchable</italic> documents the conflicts between Bakha’s obligations as a sweeper and his rising ethical awareness, which grows over the course of the novel and infuses its subjective, highly focalized narration. The novel is stunning in its depiction of the corporeality of Bakha’s existence, incorporating the sounds</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Intimate and Global:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethical Domains from Woolf to Rhys</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In her posthumously published satiric essay, “Middlebrow,” Virginia Woolf writes, “In whatever company I am I always try to know what it is like—being a conductor, being a woman with ten children and thirty-five shillings a week, being a stockbroker, being an admiral, being a bank clerk, being a dressmaker, being a duchess, being a miner, being a cook, being a prostitute.”¹ Imagining herself into these many identities, with their various habits, conditions of existence, and distinct ways of riding “at a gallop across life,”² provides Woolf with food for thought and material for fiction. But it also presents</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Comparative Colonialisms:</title>
                     <subtitle>Joyce, Anand, and the Question of Engagement</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In his collection of essays,<italic>Conversations in Bloomsbury</italic>, the celebrated Indian writer Mulk Raj Anand, whose <italic>Untouchable</italic> I discussed in the introduction, described the beginnings of his novelistic craft. When he was a university student in England, Joyce’s<italic>Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man</italic>spoke to him across the divide of culture and nurtured his desire to write: I “recognized myself in the hero of the <italic>Portrait</italic>.”¹ In<italic>Portrait</italic>Joyce presented not only Stephen Dedalus’s inner world, compelling to Anand in its own right, but also, importantly, a version of what was taking place within Anand himself. Comparing Joyce to his mentor, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Modernism in the Zenana:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Domestic Spaces of Sorabji, Hussain, and Ishvani</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Near the end of the celebrated Indian novel<italic>Kamala</italic>, written between 1889 and 1894 by Krupabai Satthianadhan, the eponymous protagonist, a young Hindu woman who has suffered the death of her beloved father, the disdain of her husband, and the loss of the man she loves, leaves home with her infant daughter. In pity, her husband offers her money, which she declines while telling him he will never see her again. She wanders, distraught and nearly suicidal, until a glimpse of the heavens filled with stars calls her back to a life of community service and charitable work. The narrator</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Commitment and the Scene of War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Max Aub and Spanish Civil War Writing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>“It is not easy to convey the nightmare atmosphere of that time,”¹ George Orwell wrote of the period in 1937 when the course of the Spanish Civil War became more grim and political repression from the left in Barcelona complicated the differentiation of right and wrong for both sides. But despite the nightmarish conditions and the difficulty in getting the story correct, writers were drawn to the Spanish Civil War in great numbers, churning out narratives, poems, and newspaper dispatches with astonishing regularity from the outbreak of war in 1936 until well into the postwar period.² For Englishlanguage readers, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Arising from the Cornlands:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Working-Class Voices of Conroy and Le Sueur</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Agnes Smedley begins<italic>Daughter of Earth</italic>, her compelling and distinguished 1929 novel of working-class life, with a disclaimer: “What I have written is not a work of beauty, created that someone may spend an hour pleasantly; not a symphony to lift up the spirit, to release it from the dreariness of reality.” She dwells on the details of the life she will depict and its connection to the despair and ugliness of poverty in the United States. “I belong to those who do not die for the sake of beauty. I belong to those who die from other causes—exhausted by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>On December 10, 2009, Barack Obama delivered his much-anticipated speech accepting the Nobel Peace Prize. In it he created a complex argument, based on the theology of Reinhold Neibuhr, about the moral necessity of political action in a flawed and dangerous world. His remarks describe the fine line between just and unjust war, evoking the principle that warfare is justified “if it is waged as a last resort or in self-defense; if the force used is proportional; and if, whenever possible, civilians are spared from violence.” But the speech also asked its audience “to think in new ways about the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">berm14950.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
