<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN56.S5765G55 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Slavery in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Slavery</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Slavery and the Culture of Taste</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gikandi</surname>
               <given-names>Simon</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691140667</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">069116097X</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400840113</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7svr8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>It would be easy to assume that, in the eighteenth century, slavery and the culture of taste--the world of politeness, manners, and aesthetics--existed as separate and unequal domains, unrelated in the spheres of social life. But to the contrary,<italic>Slavery and the Culture of Taste</italic>demonstrates that these two areas of modernity were surprisingly entwined. Ranging across Britain, the antebellum South, and the West Indies, and examining vast archives, including portraits, period paintings, personal narratives, and diaries, Simon Gikandi illustrates how the violence and ugliness of enslavement actually shaped theories of taste, notions of beauty, and practices of high culture, and how slavery's impurity informed and haunted the rarified customs of the time.</p>
         <p>Gikandi focuses on the ways that the enslavement of Africans and the profits derived from this exploitation enabled the moment of taste in European--mainly British--life, leading to a transformation of bourgeois ideas regarding freedom and selfhood. He explores how these connections played out in the immense fortunes made in the West Indies sugar colonies, supporting the lavish lives of English barons and altering the ideals that defined middle-class subjects. Discussing how the ownership of slaves turned the American planter class into a new aristocracy, Gikandi engages with the slaves' own response to the strange interplay of modern notions of freedom and the realities of bondage, and he emphasizes the aesthetic and cultural processes developed by slaves to create spaces of freedom outside the regimen of enforced labor and truncated leisure.</p>
         <p>Through a close look at the eighteenth century's many remarkable documents and artworks,<italic>Slavery and the Culture of Taste</italic>sets forth the tensions and contradictions entangling a brutal practice and the distinctions of civility.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="386"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Overture:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sensibility in the Age of Slavery</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sometime around 1659, the Dutch painter Harmenszoon van Rijn Rembrandt sat in his studio in Amsterdam and commenced work on<italic>Two Negroes</italic>(fig. 1.1), considered one of the most compelling paintings of the last phase of his illustrious career. Working with African models and operating within a Dutch culture whose domestic economy was driven by the slave trade, Rembrandt sought to turn his black figures, people who most probably had arrived in the European Low Countries as slaves or servants, into elevated subjects through art. This gesture—the transformation of the most marginal figures in society into elevated works of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Intersections:</title>
                     <subtitle>Taste, Slavery, and the Modern Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Judging from the entry she made in her diary, Monday, April 24, 1797, was a very good day for Anna Margaretta Larpent (fig. 2.1), a theater critic and woman of taste. On that particular day, Larpent rose up early and, after prayer, attended to some family business, including hemming and mending a handkerchief for her son George; she then read Claude Carloman de Rulhièr’s<italic>Histoire ou Anecdotes sur La Révolution de Russie; en l’Année 1762</italic>. She would spend the rest of the day visiting or corresponding with friends, attending to other domestic matters, and doing some reading. We know that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Unspeakable Events:</title>
                     <subtitle>Slavery and White Self-Fashioning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The year 1763 was a traumatic one for Olaudah Equiano (fig. 3.1), future abolitionist and Anglo-African man of letters. After spending four ostensibly blissful years in England and the high seas living out a meaningful life as a sailor, a profession that often masked his condition of enslavement, Equiano suddenly found himself back in the belly of the beast that was slavery. Without warning or explanation, his master, Michael Henry Pascal, decided to sell Equiano to a Captain James Doran, who planned to take the African back to the West Indies and the accursed life of plantation slavery. This was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Close Encounters:</title>
                     <subtitle>Taste and the Taint of Slavery</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In January 24, 1790, Gouverneur Morris, a New York citizen of the new American republic, wrote a letter to George Washington, then the president of the United States, urging him to “fix the taste” of the new country and to become a model of what we may now call the aesthetic self: “It is . . . my wish that everything about you should be substantially good and majestically plain, made to endure.”¹</p>
                     <p>This was an earnest but unusual request for three reasons. First, it was puzzling because on the surface there was no apparent reason why Morris should have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“Popping Sorrow”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Loss and the Transformation of Servitude</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If one were looking for an intimate connection between slavery and the culture of taste, there would be no better place to go than the series of paintings and engravings done by the Italian artist Agostino Brunias under the commission of Sir William Young, the governor of Dominica and commissioner of St. Vincent in the Windward Islands (figs. 5.1 and 5.2). On the surface, Brunias’s images were colorful evocations of tropical landscapes, now familiar touristic pictures of a West Indian paradise where happy blacks and enchanting mulattoes encountered one another in markets, streets, and dance arenas against the picturesque background</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Ontology of Play:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mimicry and the Counterculture of Taste</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sometime between 1730 and 1745, an African drum was collected in Virginia by a certain Reverend Clarke on behalf of Sir Hans Sloane, distinguished English naturalist and founder of the British Museum (fig. 6.1). The drum, now at the British Museum, is a remarkable piece of work, one whose meaning is suspended somewhere between the aura of art and ritual. Constructed in the Akan style, and made of wood (Cordia and Baphia) native to Africa, deerskin, and vegetable fiber, it is considered to be one of the earliest known surviving examples of African objects in North America.¹ If the drum</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three Fragments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On February 13, 1819, James Tallmadge Jr., the Republican representative from New York, rose in the U.S. Congress to introduce an amendment to the bill seeking to grant statehood to Missouri. He proposed that “the further introduction of slavery or involuntary servitude be prohibited” in Missouri as a condition for its entry into the union and that “all children of slaves, born within the said state, after admission thereof into the union, shall be free at the age of twenty-five years.”¹ Since Alabama, a slave-owning state, had recently been admitted into the union, the overt goal of the amendment was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7svr8.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
