<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The God of All Flesh</book-title>
         <subtitle>and Other Essays</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brueggemann</surname>
               <given-names>Walter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hanson</surname>
               <given-names>K.C.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227176177</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905845</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Walter Brueggemann</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1p5f1q3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Biblical faith is passionately and relentlessly material in its emphasis. This claim is rooted in the conviction that the creator God loves the creation and summons creation to be in sync with the will of the creator God. This collection of essays is focussed on the bodily life of the world as it ordered in all of its problematic political and economic forms. The phrase of the title “all flesh" in the flood narrative of Genesis 9 refers to all living creatures who are in covenant with God – human beings, animals, birds, and fish – as recipients of God’s grace, as dependent upon God’s generosity, and as destined for praise and obedience to God. The insistence on the materiality of life as the subject of the Bible means that the difficult issues of economics and the demanding questions of politics are front and centre in the text. So the Pentateuch pivots around the Exodus narrative and the emancipation from an unbearable context of abusive labour practices. In a similar manner, the prophets endlessly address such questions of social policy and the wisdom teachers reflect on how to manage the material things of life and social relationships for the well-being of the community. This emphasis, pervasive in these essays, is a powerful alternative and a strong resistance against all of the contemporary efforts to transcend (escape!) the material into some form of the “spiritual". All around us are efforts to find an easier, more harmonious faith. This may be evoked simply because of a desire to shield economic, political advantage from the inescapable critique of biblical faith. Such a temptation is a serious misreading of the Bible and a critical misjudgment about the nature of human existence. Thus the Bible addressed the most urgent issues of our day, and refuses the “religious temptation" that avoids lived reality where the power of God is a work.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="186"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanson</surname>
                           <given-names>K. C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is the second volume of collected essays from Walter Brueggemann originally written for Festschriften; the first was<italic>The Role of Old Testament Theology in Old Testament Interpretation: And Other Essays</italic>(Cascade Books, 2015). These essays demonstrate his discerning analyses of biblical texts. But more than that, they articulate the depth his theological insight, as well as his social analysis.</p>
                     <p>In his Preface, Brueggemann notes that these essays highlight his enduring interest in the books of Jeremiah and Psalms. I would also point out that a recurring theme here is God’s created order. This focus has long been a major</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brueggemann</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>one</label>
                     <title>THE GOD OF ALL FLESH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all of Terry Fretheim’s remarkable published corpus, I regard his 1991 article, “The Plagues as Ecological Signs of Historical Disaster,” as his most remarkable piece and arguably his most important.¹ In that article, Fretheim argues that Exodus 1–15 is grounded in creation theology. He makes his case by careful attention to the rhetorical usage of the inclusive adjective “all” (לכ) and by translating לכא as “earth,” not merely “land.”</p>
                     <p>This essay builds upon that article by exploring four Jeremiah passages that reflect the horizon of creation through the recurring phrase “all flesh” (דשכ לכ). That phrase refers not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>two</label>
                     <title>THE CREATURES KNOW</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is by now a truism that “wisdom thinks resolutely within the framework of a theology of creation.”¹ That now common assumption among interpreters, however, has not always been obvious. It is, rather, a hard-won consensus that emerged in a season of scholarship preoccupied with “history,” in which theological interpretation of the Old Testament was dominated by the programmatic slogan “God acts in history.” The connection between wisdom and creation has permitted interpretation to move outside “history” and to challenge the fear of “natural theology” that pertained in Barthian circles of interpretation. Once that consensus judgment was reached about creation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>three</label>
                     <title>JEREMIAH:</title>
                     <subtitle>CREATIO IN EXTREMIS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The book of Jeremiah offers a clear test case and model for the shift in scholarly paradigms in Old Testament study. In the “history of traditions” perspective dominated by Gerhard von Rad, the tradition of Jeremiah is firmly situated in the exodus and Sinai-covenant traditions of Moses, but with some engagement with the Davidic-messianic traditions as well.¹ This entire phase of scholarship has resulted in a lopsided emphasis upon the traditio-historical background of the book.</p>
                     <p>We may notice, however, an addendum to von Rad’s perspective that has controlled Jeremiah studies. Because of the three-source theory of Bernhard Duhm and Sigmund</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>four</label>
                     <title>ISRAEL’S SENSE OF PLACE IN JEREMIAH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a delight to offer this essay to James Muilenburg, the only one of his kind in our discipline. His delicate balance of rigorous objectivity and passionate subjectivity is a rare model for us. This paper, which seeks to pursue themes and methods important in his own work, is presented with the gratitude only his students can understand.</p>
                     <p>Recent Old Testament study, in addressing the issue of Israel’s view of time and space, has tended to celebrate time and minimize space as an important faith motif.¹ This emphasis was shared not only by Bultmannian scholars² but also by some</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>five</label>
                     <title>IMAGINATION AS A MODE OF FIDELITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bernhard Anderson has recently published an important book on biblical interpretation,<italic>The Living Word of the Bible</italic>.¹ It is an important book, as is usual for him, carefully and precisely articulated. But predictably, because it is a popular book, it is largely a neglected book.</p>
                     <p>The following paper seeks to explore one theme from that book. The first chapter of Anderson’s hermeneutical statement is entitled “Word of Imagination.”² In that chapter Anderson identifies three fronts on which the question of biblical authority and interpretation is important:</p>
                     <p>1. In relation to literalists, some of whom practice “papal ecclesiasticism”;</p>
                     <p>2. In relation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>six</label>
                     <title>PSYCHOLOGICAL CRITICISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>EXPLORING THE SELF IN THE TEXT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the beginning, the human self has been a compelling enigma for the community that produced the Bible.¹ Ancient Israel regularly asked, in narrative and liturgical texts, “What are human beings?” (Ps 8: 4). Of equal importance, they asked the question with the accompanying phrase, “that you are mindful of them?”² The question—as well as the answer—is a theological one: the community addresses the question of the self by means of the defining reality of God. While they gave many answers to that question, Psalm 139 seems the most appropriate response to the question “What is a human?”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>seven</label>
                     <title>PSALM 37:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONFLICT OF INTERPRETATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In two decades of energetic activity, wisdom studies have reached something of a plateau.¹ As a result of the work of Professor Whybray, along with Gerhard von Rad, James L. Crenshaw, and Roland E. Murphy (to name the most prominent), we are now able to take as a consensus a great deal concerning Israelite wisdom literature, e. g. its modes of disclosure, its assumptions about authority, its probable social contexts, its general theological intentionality, its tensions with more dominant modes of faith, and its paradoxical relation to broader wisdom traditions in the Near East.² The dominant wisdom literature, which functions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>eight</label>
                     <title>THE “US” OF PSALM 67</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Old Testament traditions are, of course, dominated by the self-conscious, intentional self-presentation of Israel as a peculiar people in the midst of many other peoples, the existence of which is also acknowledged. That self-presentation as a peculiar people is said to have a theological grounding as the chosen people of Yahweh (as in Deut 7:6–7; 9:4–5; 14:2), an affirmation variously articulated but assumed and traded upon widely in the tradition. That theological claim, moreover, is at the same time to be understood as an instrument of social construction, no doubt fostered and enhanced through intentional social practice.¹</p>
                     <p>While</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>nine</label>
                     <title>AUTHORITY IN THE CHURCH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theme of authority is a vexed one in our contemporary social setting. And our church participates fully in that vexation. Indeed, one can guess that it is the key question, both for a frightened world and for a weary church. We discover that as believers we are not immune to the problematic.</p>
                     <p>All around us, we are experiencing the collapse of conventional authority. We do not understand all of the reasons for this, but we need not doubt that it is happening. For good reason it makes us nervous. In my own setting, two simple examples suffice. On the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1q3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
