<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1pwt3qp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Constructing Constructive Theology</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Introductory Sketch</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wyman</surname>
               <given-names>Jason A.</given-names>
               <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506418605</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506418600</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506418612</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506418619</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pwt3qp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>To date, constructive theology hasn’t been viewed or conceptualized as a movement or trend in theology on its own as a whole. Questions arise as to what constructive theology is, where it came from, why it considers itself “constructive," and why constructive is something different from the ways in which theology has been done in the past. This book traces the overall historical arc of constructive theology, from proto-movement through the present. Inklings of constructive theology emerged well before it began to take any formalized shape. At the same time, an important shift occurred when a group of theologians decided to create the Workgroup on Constructive Theology. Further, even as the workgroup continues to work collectively, producing textbooks, statements, and methodologies concerning theology, many theologians who are not part of the workgroup or may not even know it exists have adopted the moniker of “constructive theologian." The book also considers the term “constructive" itself, offering possible reasons and historical contexts that led to this distinction being made in contrast to “systematic" theology and its subcategories. Constructive theology speaks to a very specific, historically situated emergence in the academy generally and in theology’s attempts to engage those shifts specifically.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="260"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theology, as an academic discipline, has found a comfortable place as a “systematic” endeavor. Responding to the rigors of the academy, historical philosophies, and the Enlightenment and modernity, theology has for the most part produced works systematically, using classic theological doctrinal loci one by one in order to arrive at a coherent, rigorous whole, either through dogmatic theology or systematic theology. Yet in recent years, such a preoccupation hasn’t sustained talk about God as it has in the past. Within theological work, there has always been a constructive element or phase of doing theology; recently, however, a methodological trend has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Emergence of Constructive Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The very earliest mentions of “constructive theology” appear in unlikely places and earlier than one might expect. In 1902 a book titled<italic>Contentio Veritatis: Essays in Constructive Theology</italic>was published, written by “six Oxford tutors,” H. Rashdall, W.R. Inge, H.L. Wild, C.F. Burney, W.C. Allen, and A.J. Carlyle. This is the only early mention of “constructive theology” outside the United States, but it’s important because it’s the first apparently anywhere.<italic>Contentio Veritatis</italic>, so early on, sets the tone for what constructive theology in some ways still tends to be, and introduces a key question, the relationship between liberal theology¹ and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Workgroup on Constructive Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Workgroup on Constructive Theology, founded in 1975 at Vanderbilt University, has served as an organizational center for the development of constructive theology and a place where its key methodological and thematic proposals have been nurtured and propagated. Most basically, the Workgroup is a collection of prominent theologians that, in various configurations, have gathered periodically over the last forty years and collaboratively published four textbooks and one historical theology reader. Throughout its history, the Workgroup on Constructive Theology has variously defined itself, though never in very stark terms. This is partly intentional as one defining feature of constructive theology is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Constructive Theology as Interdisciplinary Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Workgroup on Constructive Theology gave constructive theology a sense of legitimacy within the theological academy. Yet the conversation for constructive theology doesn’t end within the sphere of theology. Starting with its emphasis on philosophy, social sciences, and culture, constructive theology has been in conversation with other academic disciplines throughout its history. That is to say constructive theology is inherently interdisciplinary. In its effort to be an actionable, relevant form of theology, it has always, from the proto-constructive theologies of Ten Broeke and Meland, through the Workgroup’s textbooks and today, maintained the importance of incorporating insights from other disciplines into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Constructive Theology as Activist Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Constructive theology took a decided turn with the publication of<italic>Reconstructing Christian Theology</italic>in 1994. Intent on taking account of liberation theologies, the Workgroup on Constructive Theology decided once again to try to reimagine theology for the contemporary world. Once again, the traditional formulation of doctrinal loci was favored despite its seeming obsolescence.¹ The method of constructive theology didn’t change. Instead, the apparent need amidst world crises for a theology that acts for the mission of justice was incorporated into a project that had already distinguished itself.</p>
                     <p>Of course, constructive theologians had been working in a progressive, justice-oriented mode before</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Constructive Theology as a Method and a Tradition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a genre, constructive theologies come in staggering variety. To this point in its history no attempts have been made to define constructive theology as one movement or method in theology. Some encyclopedia entries and cursory descriptions of constructive theology have appeared in various places, but never in a comprehensive way. In one of the most extensive descriptions of constructive theology, found in the<italic>Encyclopedia of Sciences and Religion</italic>, Joerg Rieger writes:</p>
                     <p>[Systematic theology] seeks to develop a system, based on philosophical approaches or particular themes or insights, which provides a comprehensive framework for theological topics. Constructive theology, on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Questions of theological method are always complicated ones. Theology doesn’t invite method in the same way as the sciences, or even the social sciences do. As Kaufman argues, the object of theology, according to Kant and most epistemology after him, is off limits to direct human observation. There is no way to directly prove the veracity of theological claims through observation in the same way as scientific ones, and for that matter, neither can one prove the very existence of the object of study itself. The recognition in the contemporary United States of the magnitude of religious diversity in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt3qp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
