<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Lacanian Left</book-title>
         <subtitle>Psychoanalysis, Theory, Politics</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Stavrakakis</surname>
               <given-names>Yannis</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748619801</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748629077</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yannis Stavrakakis</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1r288w"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In recent years psychoanalysis – especially Lacanian theory – has been gradually acknowledged as a vital resource in the ongoing re-orientation of contemporary political theory and analysis. Of particular note is that the work of Jacques Lacan is increasingly being used by major political philosophers associated with the Left. This indicates the dynamic emergence of a new theoretico-political horizon: that of the ‘Lacanian Left’. However, this has yet to be properly conceived and structured as a field. The Lacanian Left is the first book to bring it into academic consciousness and to draw its implications for concrete political analysis in a systematic way. It offers:• An accessible mapping of its main contours. • A detailed examination of the points of convergence and divergence between the major figures active or at the periphery of this terrain, including Slavoj h the central Lacanian notion of ‘enjoyment’, The Lacanian Left puts forward innovative analyses of political power and authority, nationalism, European identity, consumerism and advertising culture, de-democratisation and post-democracy. It will be of value to everyone interested in exploring the potential of psychoanalysis to reinvigorate political theory, critical political analysis and democratic politics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="328"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliographical Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Locating the Lacanian Left</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Over the last ten to fifteen years, psychoanalysis, and especially Lacanian theory, has emerged as one of the most important resources in the ongoing re-orientation of contemporary political theory and critical analysis. So much so is now acknowledged even in mainstream political science fora. For example, in a critical review essay recently published in the <italic>British Journal of Politics and International Relations</italic> – one of the journals of the UK Political Studies Association – and characteristically entitled ‘The Politics of Lack’, one reads that ‘an approach to politics drawn from Lacanian psychoanalysis is becoming increasingly popular of late among theorists . .</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Antinomies of Creativity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lacan and Castoriadis on Social Construction and the Political</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Of all the theorists examined in this book, Cornelius Castoriadis is neither the most well-known nor the closest one to Lacan’s legacy. However, the decision to put this chapter first is not entirely arbitrary.¹ From a historical point of view, Castoriadis was one of the first major political and social theorists of the Left – a founding member of the famous <italic>Socialisme ou barbarie</italic> group – to engage so closely with Lacanianism, and already in the 1960s.² More importantly, exactly because he was gradually led to a violent rejection of Lacanian theory, his work can function as an external frontier, helping us</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Laclau with Lacan on<italic>Jouissance</italic>:</title>
                     <subtitle>Negotiating the Affective Limits of Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>If Castoriadis constitutes the (extimate) frontier of the emerging Lacanian Left, two of its pivotal figures are certainly Ernesto Laclau and Chantal Mouffe. For a start, they have both exhibited, again and again, their increasing readiness to take on board many crucial Lacanian insights in their innovative analysis of political discourse and in reorienting the political theory of the Left in the direction of a ‘radical and plural democracy’. In their joint work, theoretical affinities with Lacanian thought are evident from at least the time of <italic>Hegemony and Socialist Strategy</italic> (Laclau and Mouffe 1985), if not earlier. This is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Ž¡žekian ‘Perversions’:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Lure of Antigone and the Fetishism of the Act</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>My engagement with the work of Laclau has focused on the importance of combining a Lacan-inspired awareness of lack and of the limits of discourse (the Lacanian conceptualisation of negativity qua encounter with the real) with a more substantive dimension, crucial for understanding political life and especially the affective aspect of identification processes: the axis of enjoyment in its different modalities and in its continuous interaction with the discursive constitution of our social and political reality, with the materiality of the signifier. As we have seen, such an articulation requires a delicate balancing act between negativity and positivity. If the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Excursus on Badiou</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>As seen in the preceding chapter, Žiž¡ek’s act is conceptualised in a close dialogue with Alain Badiou’s theorisation of the event. Before bringing the first part of <italic>The Lacanian Left</italic> to a close, it is thus important to deal more thoroughly with the relation between Žiž¡ek and Badiou, more precisely between Žiž¡ek’s act and Badiou’s event, and with the place Badiou’s ethics occupy within the Lacanian Left.¹ The exact parameters of this relation are greatly obscured not only by the complexity of the two theoretico-political projects and their various reorientations over time, but also by the often contradictory comments of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>What Sticks?</title>
                     <subtitle>From Symbolic Power to<italic>Jouissance</italic>
                     </subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Throughout the first part of this book I have discussed central aspects of the work of major figures associated with the Lacanian Left. Engaging in a dialogue with the theoretico-political projects of Castoriadis, Laclau, Ž¡ž¡ek and Badiou, I have tried to highlight the major contributions Lacanian theory has to offer to a critical understanding of political phenomena and to a much-needed ethicopolitical re-orientation. In the second part of <italic>The Lacanian Left</italic> I will be shifting my attention to a variety of concrete issues which can be fruitfully analysed and illuminated from the Lacanian viewpoint sketched in the preceding chapters. My</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Enjoying the Nation:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Success Story?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Although our contemporary world is marked throughout by the importance of questions of identity, something increasingly reflected in the directions of contemporary social–scientific research, in the general field of nationalism studies the issue of the attraction and salience of national identities has not been sufficiently examined. This is partly due to the hegemonic position of modernist and constructionist approaches in the relevant literature.² In opposition to the common doxa reproduced by nationalist myths, contemporary research on the nation tends to stress the constructed character of national identity: the nation is primarily understood as a modern social and political construction.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Lack of Passion:</title>
                     <subtitle>European Identity Revisited</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>I started the previous chapter with an observation regarding the importance that questions of identity have gradually acquired. It would be bizarre if the broad field of international relations were to stay untouched by this trend. In fact, no one is surprised any more by the fact that ‘the discipline of international relations (IR) is witnessing a surge of interest in identity and identity formation’ (Neumann 1999:1). The same applies to the sub-discipline of European Studies – affecting both marginal and mainstream approaches. As Anthony Smith has pointed out, one of the fundamental reasons for the current interest in ‘European unification’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Consumerist ‘Politics of<italic>Jouissance</italic>’ and the Fantasy of Advertising</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The preceding explorations of nationalism and European identity reveal how much the fate and prospects of particular identifications and hegemonic projects rely on the affective dimension, on <italic>jouissance</italic> in its different modalities and interactions with the world of signification and social practice. Obviously the emergence of the ‘new’ cannot succeed if it ignores this important parameter, but this is not to say that sedimented, libidinally invested identifications are in any way privileged to retain their hegemonic position indefinitely. Processes of dis-identification and affective re-investment are, on the contrary, part and parcel of social and political life. In capitalist – especially late</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Democracy in Post-Democratic Times</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Throughout this book, side by side with my critical explorations of the various theoretical projects associated with the Lacanian Left, side by side with the analyses of central socio-political phenomena undertaken from a Lacanian perspective, I have also been sketching – in an admittedly indirect way – some of the preconditions for a democratic ethics of the political, an orientation drawing on both Lacanian theory and theories of radical democracy. In fact, forging a link between the Lacanian ethics of psychoanalysis and radical democratic theory has already been one of the main aims of <italic>Lacan and the Political</italic>.¹ Today, in the emerging</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r288w.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
