<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h0b18</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT695.5.D35 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human ecology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Berry, Thomas Mary, 1914-</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Contributions in ecological theology</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lonergan, Bernard J. F. (Bernard Joseph Francis), 1904-1984</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Contributions in ecological theology</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Theology for the Earth</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Contributions of Thomas Berry and Bernard Lonergan</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DALTON</surname>
               <given-names>ANNE MARIE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>23</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>1999</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776615318</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776615319</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cn6smd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While many feel that something must be done, few perceive the state of the ecological crisis as a "profound religious problem." While Thomas Berry sought to fire the imagination and motivate his listener to action, Bernard Lonergan was absorbed by the growing gulf between traditional Christian theology and its relevance to modern problems. This book brings together the work of these dynamic thinkers and examines their mutual contribution to theology for our time and for our planet.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="223"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Berry</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have seldom reflected on the epistemological or critical implications of my writings. Thus it is a special delight to read these pages of Anne Marie Dalton. They give me insights into my own thinking that I have seldom thought about in any conscious manner. It is particularly helpful to have her reflections done in the context of the epistemological and theological work of Bernard Lonergan. She is quite correct in understanding my work in terms of Lonergan’s notion of Descriptive Discourse, for my intent has been simply to present and to leave the reader to respond out of whatever</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scholars of religion are no strangers to challenges from the modern and post-modern world. In this latter half of the twentieth century, the ecological crisis is perhaps among the more difficult of these challenges. When the very foundations of life itself are threatened, how does one engage in reflection on one’s religious faith? Thomas Berry was one of the first and most creative North American religionists to seriously consider the issue of the role of religion in restructuring human-earth relations.</p>
                     <p>Thomas Berry was born in Greensboro, North Carolina, November 9, 1914. From his own reports, he had an early interest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>THE METHOD AND TRADITION OF BERRY’S CULTURAL HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Berry’s first interest was cultural history, a designation he gave his own work and which remained significant. While on occasion he showed his awareness of political and social influences on the topic under discussion, it is clear throughout his work that his predominant focus was the influence of ideas and intellectual/spiritual movements in history. His penchant for tracing ideas across cultures and making syntheses of large amounts of data remained characteristic of his work.</p>
                     <p>Berry wrote his dissertation on Giambattista Vico. Even a cursory look at the work on Vico is enlightening in clarifying the significance of Berry’s self-designation as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>THE INFLUENCE OF WORLD RELIGIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Berry’s professional career, his teaching and much of his scholarly research and writing, was in world religions, especially the religions of India and Asia. (His writings about North American native religions came later and within the context of the ecological crisis.) Within the field of world religions he remained primarily a cultural historian, interested in the ideas and events that shaped human culture. Later, as his concern turned toward the ecological crisis, his focus became a history of nature and of ideas relevant to the humanearth relationship. Berry commonly referred to himself as a “geologian,” conveying his notion that his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>INTERACTION WITH THE THOUGHT OF TEILHARD DE CHARDIN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Introduction Two early essays of Thomas Berry, “Creative Evolution” and “The Christian Process” suggest a reason for his initial interest in Teilhard. Berry, like Teilhard, raised questions about the increasing split he perceived between religion (Christianity, in particular) and the world of the twentieth century. They both attributed the increase in secularization and the growing sense of human alienation from religion to a ghettoized Christianity, whose efforts to meet the needs of the modern world had, to date, been minimal.¹</p>
                     <p>In these two essays, Berry dealt primarily with the radical change that he saw occurring in culture and society, change</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>THE INFLUENCE OF MODERN SCIENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given the nature of the genetic development of Berry’s thought, it is no surprise that Berry’s interest in science was primarily in scientific critiques of mainstream post-Enlightenment scientific methodology. While he always maintained a respect for many of the contributions of Western science, he relied especially in his own work on scientists who tested new waters and were often only tentatively accepted by the established scientific community. He considered these scientists to give credibility to the counter-Enlightenment traditions that he upheld. His overriding interest remained cultural; therefore, his questions for science were concerned with the cultural assumptions and effects of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>BERRY’S PROPOSAL FOR THE ECOLOGICAL CRISIS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While most of the relevant categories of Bernard Lonergan’s thought will be employed in more detail below, some comments about his distinction between two language categories (description and explanation) shed initial light on the nature of Berry’s proposal. Succinctly stated, description deals with things as they relate to us; explanation with things as they relate to each other.¹ So, for instance, to speak of a wheel as round is to<italic>describe</italic>the wheel as we see or feel it; that is how the wheel relates to us. On the other hand, to speak of wheels in terms of the relationship</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>BERNARD LONERGAN AND EMERGENT PROBABILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapters have been an attempt to understand Berry’s response to the ecological crisis in the context of the genetic development of his thought and under the horizon that attracted him in the later years of his work. In moving the horizon to Christian theology, we move beyond the question of what Berry himself meant or intended to the further question, What aspects of his work are going forward with respect to a reform of Christian theology in the light of the ecological crisis? Bernard Lonergan’s compelling and inclusive account of emergent probability is especially suited as a framework</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>A THEOLOGICAL ANALYSIS OF BERRY’S PROPOSAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Introduction If theology is, as Lonergan described it, a mediation “between a cultural matrix and the significance and role of a religion in that matrix”¹ then there are two major questions that arise in considering Berry’s contribution to Christian theology: (1) The methodological question: How is Berry’s “new story” situated in terms of mediating between Christianity and culture? In Lonergan’s terms, this is to ask whether methodologically the “new story” belongs to<italic>cosmopolis</italic>, since<italic>cosmopolis</italic>is the symbolic name for the mediation of authentic meanings and values to aid progress or to meet decline. (2) The content question: If the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This work originated in a desire to discover the relationship between two urgencies of our times. The first was the ecological crisis and the second, the reform of Christian theology. The preliminary, largely untested insights that moved the project into actuality were that (1) as Thomas Berry had loudly and clearly proclaimed, the ecological crisis was also religious; it had religious roots and it required a religious solution, and (2) a theology that did not serve to increase hope in the possibility of authentically negotiating the major crises of our time had already died. Bernard Lonergan seemed to corroborate this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY—WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6smd.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
