<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ms88</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">FC2926.9.N3B68313 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nationalism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nationalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Québec (Province)</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnicity</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Colonies</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">National state</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Making of the Nations and Cultures of the New World</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Essay in Comparative History</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BOUCHARD</surname>
               <given-names>GÉRARD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="translator">TRANSLATED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WEINROTH</surname>
               <given-names>MICHELLE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BROWNE</surname>
               <given-names>PAUL LEDUC</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773532137</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773574526</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0773574522</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zszcb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Making of the Nations and Cultures of the New World explores the question of how a culture - a collective consciousness - is born. Gérard Bouchard compares the histories of New World collectivities, which were driven by a dream of freedom and sovereignty, and finds both major differences and striking commonalities in their formation and evolution. He also considers the myths and discursive strategies devised by elites in their efforts to unite and mobilize diversified populations.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="448"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the English Translation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bouchard</surname>
                           <given-names>Gérard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Translators’ Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Comparative History of New Collectivities and Founding Cultures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idea of this research on the comparative history of new collectivities arose in the course of a previous extensive study on the Saguenay, an area of settlement situated in northern Quebec and opened to colonization in the 1830s. This study in social history aimed to reconstitute the (demographic, economic, cultural, etc.) features of rural French-Canadian society as it developed in those remote places, recently carved out of the bush (Bouchard 1996b). Given their typical isolation, it was reasonable to assume that these settlement communities exhibited such features in a rather magnified form. The results of my work were thus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Why Compare (Oneself)?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By drawing primarily on historiographical scholarship in Quebec, I intend to present some views on the role of comparison as a process of objectification in building historical knowledge. In very general terms, comparison refers here to any scientific approach which consists in: (1) relating two or several objects of analysis belonging to as many collective settings and (2) foregrounding differences and similarities so as to increase knowledge either of one or of each of these objects. I return to this later. My ideas are intended as a vindication of comparative history; there are, however, several ways to broach the argument.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A New Old Country?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Formation and Transformations of Culture and Nation in Quebec</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the following pages, I probe Quebec’s cultural and national history on the central questions outlined in chapter 1. Like all new collectivities, Quebec had to ensure its survival and development on a continent yet to be discovered and tamed, alongside long established inhabitants, Aboriginal peoples with whom it invariably had to reckon. As elsewhere, the formation and transformations of the new collectivity occurred in a context of colonial dependency. In fact, in Quebec’s case, at least four types of dependency appeared simultaneously or successively between the seventeenth and the mid-twentieth centuries: political (France, Great Britain), religious (France, the Vatican),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Growth of National Consciousness in Mexico and Latin America</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After Quebec, our attention turns to Mexico and Latin America (Map 1). Considering the continent’s diversity, it might appear surprising that this inquiry starts with Mexico and then spills into the whole of Latin America.¹ Yet, beyond their important distinguishing features, I believe that the collectivities of this continent shared dreams, problems, and historical experiences that legitimize my approach. Moreover, the act of recognizing elements of a common narrative can, in turn, shed light on particular trajectories. In describing the process whereby European immigrants appropriated these new spaces between the sixteenth and twentieth centuries, I use the concept of “Americanization”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Political Emancipation and National Identity in Australia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First a word to signpost our journey. The concept of oceanity refers at once to the direction and to the outcome of the symbolic appropriation of the Australian continent; in this sense, oceanity constitutes a reference point diametrically opposed to the European pole, since it is constructed at the latter’s expense. The concept ends up embracing all the attempts to create an authentic national identity, sometimes known as<italic>Australianity</italic>. In discussing the European pole, I will frequently refer to the British mother country. Strictly speaking, one should distinguish between England and the other parts of the United Kingdom; however, since</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Other Pathways:</title>
                     <subtitle>Canada, New Zealand, and the United States</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter offers only a glimpse of three other new collectivities. It gives a bird’s-eye view of these three pathways so as to situate them in relation to the ones previously discussed. Needless to say, I sketch them with fairly broad strokes; my purpose is primarily to establish a few landmarks that suggest a course of action for future analyses. Once again, the inquiry presented in chapter 1 serves as a guide. However, I limit myself to some key questions.</p>
                     <p>Canada, as we shall see, resembles Australia and New Zealand in multiple ways. This should not come as a surprise,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Collective Paths, Discursive Strategies:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Model</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The forays made throughout the preceding chapters, though very incomplete, have brought to light numerous particularities and convergences in the historical paths under discussion; they have allowed us to uncover surprising recurrences in the discursive strategies that new collectivities deployed to construct and order imaginaries at different times. I now proceed to make sense of each of these recurring tendencies and, in conclusion, ask what we have learned about these routes and representations.</p>
                     <p>A first conclusion to draw concerning the ideal types (or, better still, the continuum) of continuity and rupture is that self-differentiation in the sphere of custom appears</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>332</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay in comparative history has led me to consider the collective imaginary as a social fact, the transformations of which are directly or indirectly linked to other social facts. In turn, the study of these changes themselves not only discloses the logic of discourse but also the social dynamic to which it belongs and of which it is an important driving force. In this sense, the cultural and social are two sides of a common history. I have chosen to give priority to the first because of the question that served as my point of departure: self-representations are constituted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zszcb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
