<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Our Only Hope</book-title>
         <subtitle>More than We can Ask or Imagine</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Adam</surname>
               <given-names>Margaret B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174685</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902783</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Margaret B. Adam</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf36m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Our Only Hope' encourages theologians to continue critical and creative examinations of the hope they teach, promote, and presuppose. Margaret B. Adam advocates that those examinations include a reconsideration of dismissed traditional doctrine and a readiness to consider current discourses not traditionally consulted for input on theological hope.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Years ago, I heard a sermon about hope as I sat with my baby girl near the back of our Episcopal church. The preacher urged the congregation to face life’s challenges with hope. He gently criticized the parishioners for their tendency to sit back and let life go by, and he championed instead more active, responsible, and upbeat engagements with the world. He proclaimed the virtue of making a difference in one’s own life and in the world by adopting an attitude of hopefulness. I listened to this sermon from within the depths of an overwhelming bout of depression. I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Moltmann’s Hope and Moltmannian Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Patron Of Theological hope in the United States for the past fifty years has been Jürgen Moltmann. His celebrated book of 1964,<italic>Theology of Hope: On the Ground and the Implications of a Christian Eschatology,</italic>reinvigorated theological scholarship about hope and still inspires academic and congregational engagements with hope. His account of hope emphasizes God’s experience of crucified godforsakenness, Jesus Christ’s promise of resurrection, the future coming of God’s new creation, and the work of hope in this life, now. Moltmann’s theology inspires a body of writing and belief—Moltmannian hope—that approximately reflects his work and functions as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Costs of a Moltmannian Theological Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Legacy Of Moltmann’s theological hope abides as a contemporary doctrine, loosely articulated and broadly accepted. The broad outlines of his eschatological hope shape the presuppositions and imaginations of many theologians, clergy, and lay Christians, including some who have never engaged with his work directly. I have identified the legacy of Moltmann’s theology of hope as<italic>Moltmannian</italic>, because it reflects his work, at least indirectly, even though it does not attend to all of the particulars of his theological scholarship. When this Moltmannian hope constitutes the exclusive resource for eschatological hope, the costs are great.</p>
                     <p>Moltmann offers Christians fresh access</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A Thomistic Grammar of Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chapter 1 Described The distinctive characteristics of Moltmann’s theology of hope and the subsequent construction of Moltmannian hope. Chapter 2 examined some of the costs of an exclusive reliance on a Moltmannian theology of hope. This chapter considers the theology of hope presented by Aquinas that Moltmannian hope misunderstands and dismisses,¹ in order to recover some resources for contemporary theological hope. Chapter 4 will investigate resources from discourses not often considered in conversations about theological hope.</p>
                     <p>Moltmann’s prioritization of colloquialized theology in a modern and secularized time reflects his conviction that Christian theology can suit contemporary concerns and terms, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Provocative Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Resources For A contemporary Christian theology of hope extend far beyond the narratives discussed in the previous three chapters. This chapter considers five discourses that are not conventionally consulted for input on theological hope: nihilism, lament, disability, feminist theory, and feminist theology. The philosophical and critical theory conversation of nihilism and its relative, indeterminism or undecidability, suggests a kind of hope without over-confident claims of knowable hopes for the future. Scriptural and extra-scriptural lament demonstrates a persistent and apparently futile hope that continues into and through death with no sign of God’s response or rescue. Disability theology challenges hopes about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Our Only Hope</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chapter 1 described Jürgen Moltmann’s future-determined, creationfocused, ideologically-modern, hope in the passible God who has been brought to suffer with humanity by Jesus Christ’s suffering and death. I followed the sketch of Moltmann’s theological hope with examples of Moltmannian hope and its humanist, this-worldly hope in the changes that responsible, hopeful actions can make. In chapter 2, I noted what an exclusive reliance on Moltmannian hope loses: non-modern imagination, divine impassibility, Christ’s two natures, heaven, transcendent human flourishing, and apparently irresponsible discipleship. Chapter 3 considered patristic and Thomistic presentations of theological hope and twenty-first-century treatments of hope from theologians appreciative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf36m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Backmatter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>236</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
