<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">coll17686</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P99 .C5698 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Semiotics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Visual pathways</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Language and languages</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Origin</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">To 1500</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Evolutionary psychology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Brain</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Evolution</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Neurolinguistics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Linguistics</subject>
         <subject>Ecology &amp; Evolutionary Biology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Neopoetics</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Evolution of the Literate Imagination</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Collins</surname>
               <given-names>Christopher</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231542883</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231542887</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Christopher Collins</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/coll17686"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The quest to understand the evolution of the literary mind has become a fertile field of inquiry and speculation for scholars across literary studies and cognitive science. In<italic>Paleopoetics</italic>, Christopher Collins's acclaimed earlier title, he described how language emerged both as a communicative tool and as a means of fashioning other communicative tools-stories, songs, and rituals. In<italic>Neopoetics</italic>, Collins turns his attention to the cognitive evolution of the writing-ready brain. Further integrating neuroscience into the popular field of cognitive poetics, he adds empirical depth to our study of literary texts and verbal imagination and offers a whole new way to look at reading, writing, and creative expression. Collins begins<italic>Neopoetics</italic>with the early use of visual signs, first as reminders of narrative episodes and then as conventional symbols representing actual speech sounds. Next he examines the implications of written texts for the play of the auditory and visual imagination. To exemplify this long transition from oral to literate artistry, Collins examines a wide array of classical texts-from Homer and Hesiod to Plato and Aristotle and from the lyric innovations of Augustan Rome to the inner dialogues of St. Augustine. In this work of "big history," Collins demonstrates how biological and cultural evolution collaborated to shape both literature and the brain we use to read it.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>One</label>
                     <title>Innovating Ourselves</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the evolution of speech, writing has arguably been our species’ most consequential innovation. By “innovation” I mean any successful, alternative way of doing something. Some of these changes were the result of gene mutation, the prime factor in natural selection, as over time alternative procedures aided their users to survive and reproduce and were thereby passed along to their descendants. Other innovations, learned by imitation, were transmitted through cultural evolution. Nonhuman animals show little or no capacity for innovation. Our nearest evolutionary cousins, the chimpanzees, for example, have the innate ability to hurl things, yet they cannot learn how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Two</label>
                     <title>Narrative Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ability to transmit symbolic signs through gestures and, later, vocal sounds eventually evolved into fully grammatical language. But as the language-ready brain was millions of years in the making, so it took perhaps as long as 200,000 years for oral cultures in separate locations, e.g., Mesopotamia, the Nile and Indus valleys, northern China, and Mesoamerica, to have the institutions in place to support the production and storage of written records. It then took millennia more before writing expanded from administrative recordkeeping to historiography, philosophy, natural science, and what we now generally mean by “literature.” All the while, writing remained</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Three</label>
                     <title>The Dancing, Singing Daughters of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Storytelling also circles—it comes back and starts over. This is as true in literate cultures that cherish traditional religious or secular narratives as it is in preliterate cultures. Stories, unless they are wholly improvised, are not merely performed: they are<italic>re</italic>performed and for that reason must be<italic>re</italic>collected. In an oral culture, storytelling may not require verbatim recall, but the skillful reperformance of a well-known narrative does require a very good memory for times, places, and persons. This is especially the case when that performance includes rhythm, melody, and movement. One can appreciate why, in some cultures, performers, before</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Four</label>
                     <title>Visual Instruments of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous two chapters, I have explored four mnemonic methods:<italic>time, place, person</italic>, and<italic>performance</italic>, each as a means by which oral cultures preserve narrative information. Time, place, and person are the named elements that anchor the action of the narrative; performance is the narration itself. As proposed in the last chapter, skillfully performed narration, enhanced by musical elements, induces pleasurable emotions, which in turn increase the likelihood that the piece will be reperformed and its narrative content preserved.</p>
                     <p>The final two mnemonics exist neither in narrative nor in the act of narration. Instead they are displacements of narrative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Five</label>
                     <title>Poets’ Play and Plato’s Poetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Singing is a universal human behavior combining words that awaken the memory, melodies that arouse the emotions, and rhythms that move the body. The singer, who might also play a drum or stringed instrument, therefore always occupied a prominent place in social and religious gatherings, which often would be held during times of leisure and feasting after other group activities, such as hunting, planting, harvesting, and herding.</p>
                     <p>In ancient Greece, these performers, the<italic>aoidoi</italic>(singers), were the essential agents of the Muses’ art, or<italic>mousikê</italic>. Singers in an oral culture, though prized as archives of communal information, were also adept</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Six</label>
                     <title>Writing for the Voice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the silence of the written surface, the literate imagination has from its very beginnings been deeply engaged in restoring the immediacy of the human voice. In this chapter I will first revisit the question of why the Greeks and Romans preferred to write their words in continuous script without inserting spaces between words and suggest how speech simulation may have influenced this choice. Then I consider that other literary uncertainty, the evolution of the lyric, the genre Plato and Aristotle ignored, that nevertheless over the centuries has become recognized as the prototypical poetic genre. This is a long story,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Seven</label>
                     <title>Writing and the Reading Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter, I discussed writing as a means of reenacting speech events such as dialogues and monologues, either for others or for oneself. If for oneself, this performance could be a silent simulation of speech using the reader’s articulatory and auditory imagination. In this concluding chapter I will sketch out some of the unique ways in which writing also began to represent aspects of the mind that only writing could reveal. We have no reason to assume that the new model of the mind that literate culture introduced was the inevitable outcome of evolutionary forces. For Europe, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                     <subtitle>Poetics and the Making of the Modern Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is more than mere passage of time that separates the poets of Rome’s Golden Age from those that John Stuart Mill had in mind when, in 1833, he contrasted poetry with eloquence. Both these discourses, he said, are “alike the expression or uttering forth of feeling. But … eloquence is<italic>heard</italic>; poetry is<italic>over</italic>heard. Eloquence supposes an audience; the peculiarity of poetry appears to us to lie in the poet’s utter unconsciousness of a listener. Poetry is feeling confessing itself to itself, in moments of solitude.… All poetry is of the nature of soliloquy” (Mill 1965, 109–110). Classical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three Horatian Texts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">coll17686.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
