<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7hbh6s</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC599.U5T68 1994</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civil society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civil society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social justice</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Public welfare</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Socialism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Post-communism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Toward a Global Civil Society</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Walzer</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781571810540</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782381600</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782381600</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michael Walzer</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Berghahn Books, Inc.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1x76fjn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The demise of Communism has not only affected Eastern Europe but also the countries of the West where a far-reaching examination of political and economic systems has begun. This collection of essays by internationally renowned scholars of political theory from Europe and the United States explores both the concept and the reality of civil society and its institutions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dettke</surname>
                           <given-names>Dieter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Toward a Global Civil Society</italic>is the first volume of a new series entitled<italic>International Political Currents</italic>, published by the Washington Office of the Friedrich Ebert Foundation. The series will address major international economic, political, and cultural issues. Publications in this series will try to contribute to a discourse on public policy issues with international dimensions. Based in Germany, the Friedrich Ebert Foundation, Germany’s oldest political foundation, is involved in programs in 89 countries in Asia, Africa, Latin America, Central America and the Caribbean, the U.S., and Europe. Our activities are increasingly global and international in character.</p>
                     <p>The essays in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walzer</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are many definitions of “civil society,” and there is considerable disagreement at the margins about what the concept includes and excludes. I won’t add to that disagreement here (I offer my own, fairly imprecise definition in the first of the papers in this collection). It is enough to say that civil society incorporates many of the associations and identities that we value outside of, prior to, or in the shadow of state and citizenship. The subject is of great interest just now because of the argument that democracy requires a strong and lively civil society—if not for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>The Concept of Civil Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walzer</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My aim in this essay is to defend a complex, imprecise, and, at crucial points, uncertain account of society and politics. I have no hope of theoretical simplicity, not at this historical moment when so many stable oppositions of political and intellectual life have collapsed; but I also have no desire for simplicity, since a world that theory could fully grasp and neatly explain would not, I suspect, be a pleasant place. In the nature of things, then, my argument won’t be elegant, and though I believe that arguments should march, the sentences following one another like soldiers on parade,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Private and Public Roles in Civil Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nardin</surname>
                           <given-names>Terry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is an ambiguity in the idea of “civil society” as the arena of private economic and social relations, rather than of government. First, there is the idea that these relations are freely chosen. Civil society, as Michael Walzer puts it, is “the space of uncoerced human association.” But second, there is the idea that these relations depend upon shared values. Civil society is therefore also “the set of relational networks—formed for the sake of family, faith, interest, and ideology—that fill this space.” … The idea of civil society, then, can receive both liberal and communitarian interpretation, depending</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Interpreting the Notion of Civil Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I will address three questions disturbing to those who make use of the concept of civil society.</p>
                     <p>1. Is the term “civil society” really a code word for the market, private property, capitalism?</p>
                     <p>2. If not, is the discourse of civil society necessarily traditionalistic—does it ignore hierarchies and forms of domination on the terrain of the social?</p>
                     <p>3. Is the politics of civil society necessarily a- or anti-political? What is the relation between a politics of civil society and the state or the economy?</p>
                     <p>The concept of civil society has recently become fashionable thanks to struggles against communist and military dictatorships, first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Reconceptualizing Civil Society for Now:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Somewhat Gramscian Turnings</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nielsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Kai</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Civil society,” much more than “state,” “government,” “power,” or even “democracy,” is a term of art in political theory. There is no discovering what the concept means, let alone what it “really means.” What instead is to be done is to see if we can forge some conceptualization or reconceptualization of civil society which would be useful, given, on the one hand, some important political or ethical purposes or, on the other, some theoretical purposes.</p>
                     <p>In ancient usage,<italic>civilis societas</italic>(in Cicero, for example) referred to the condition of living in a civilized political community: a community with a legal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Civil Society, Hard Cases and the End of the Cold War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Strong</surname>
                           <given-names>Tracy B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The passage that Michael Walzer quoted from<italic>The German Ideology</italic>continues on from “doing just as one wishes to, hunting in the morning, fishing in the afternoon, and criticizing after dinner” by indicating that one will be able to undertake these activities “without ever thereby becoming a hunter, a fisherman, or a critical critic.” I mention this not to critique Walzer but to extend what I take to be one possible thrust of his comments. I take Marx’s continuation in this passage to be an expression of anxiety on Marx’s part. The danger with what one might call civil society,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>In Common Together:</title>
                     <subtitle>Unity, Diversity, and Civic Virtue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Elshtain</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean Bethke</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the one and the many, of unity and diversity, has been posed since the beginning of political thought in the West. The American Founders were well aware of the vexations attendant upon the creation of a new political body. They worked with, and against, a stock of metaphors that had previously served as the symbolic vehicles of political incorporation. As men of the Enlightenment, they rejected the images of the body politic that had dominated medieval and early modern political thinking. For a Jefferson or a Madison such tropes as “the King’s two bodies” or John of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Too Many Rights, Too Few Responsibilities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Etzioni</surname>
                           <given-names>Amitai</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A sociological prize of sorts ought to be given to the member of the TV audience who, during a show about the savings and loan mess exclaimed, “The tax payers shouldn’t pay for this, the government should!” He reflected quite well a major theme in American civic culture: a strong sense of entitlement, demanding the community to give more services, strongly upholding rights—coupled with a relatively weak sense of obligation, of serving the commons, and without a feeling of responsibility for the country. Hence: Americans recently called for more government services but showed greater opposition to new taxes; they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Progressive Politics and Communitarian Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Galston</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the hallmarks of communitarianism is its sensitivity to cultural and historical differences that may differentiate one community or subcommunity from another. And in precisely that spirit, I must introduce a question: how much can Europe learn from America, and how much can America learn from Europe, if what differentiates us is arguably as important as what unites us?</p>
                     <p>From a communitarian perspective, a fascinating problematic has been established, which is an empirical question that cannot be resolved philosophically or ideologically. But it is nevertheless a question I have reflected on through the exemplary person of Alexis de Tocqueville,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Neo-Hegelian Reflections on the Communitarian Debate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pinkard</surname>
                           <given-names>Terry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I will offer some very general reflections on why certain communitarian ideas have been raised in the national debate and why the communitarian agenda on its own cannot be the full story of what we should be doing and thinking. It strikes me that we ought to begin with the very general question: why is it that communitarianism has suddenly been appearing on the political and philosophical landscape in the way that it recently has? In trying to answer this question, I am going to do three things. I am going to begin with an anecdote, end with a slogan,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>From Socialism to Communitarianism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Selznick</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My own departure from socialism occurred almost fifty years ago. In 1940 I broke with a small Trotskyist, Marxist-Leninist group and for a while belonged to the Norman Thomas socialists. However, by the time I returned from service in the army in 1946, I was convinced that the idea of socialism, at least for the United States, was no longer something I could really support. I retained very warm feelings for Norman Thomas, and felt a strong moral continuity with his concept of democratic socialism.</p>
                     <p>Nevertheless, I could no longer accept socialist economic doctrines, and since 1948 I have been</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>On Labels and Reasons:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Communitarian Approach–Some European Comments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kallscheuer</surname>
                           <given-names>Otto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is there a common idea of the “left” in Europe and the United States? And should this idea be a “communitarian” one? Or is this “just another label”—as many people (especially in Eastern Europe) have also come to think about the common label “left” (used by both social democrats and communists)? Is there in the United States a coherent “communitarian” school of political thought, moral philosophy and even of economic analysis? Does this “communitarianism” have well-defined rules of methodology (in research) and membership (who is to be regarded as a “communitarian” and who not)? One might doubt it—even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Economic Policy and the Role of the State—The Invisible, the Visible and the Third Hand</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Altvater</surname>
                           <given-names>Elmar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is evident that, among other factors, the functioning of the welfare state as well as the institutional richness and democratic reach of the civil society depends heavily on the economic efficiency of a given society. Now, the question is: what does economic efficiency depend on? There are several different answers, each of them depending on their theoretical background. Neoliberals or neo-classical economists stress the meaning of the “invisible hand” of a free-market system as the crucial prerequisite for achieving the best distribution of productive factors, of finding the best path of innovation and evolution, and for realizing the highest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>Industrial Policy—Will Clinton Find the High Wage Path?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Faux</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bill Clinton’s charge that “we are working harder for less” was repeated at campaign bus stops all the way to the White House. Echoing a decade of policy debate among Democrats, he talked of the need for America to seek a “high-wage” path through the new competitive global marketplace. With his election, “industrial policy” has crept back on to the national agenda: the question now is not whether the government should guide the private sector to become more competitive, but how.</p>
                     <p>It’s still too early to judge Clinton’s answers. But, although he is pointed in the right direction, political and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Redefining the Role of the State to Facilitate Reform in East and West</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hahn</surname>
                           <given-names>Ottokar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a statement of principle, the Marxism and Leninism as applied by Lenin and Stalin have nothing to do with socialism. They are complete perversions of the great vision of socialism. And instead of creating a free society of equal chances and international solidarity, they established an especially crude form of capitalism and of national supremacy.</p>
                     <p>The former Soviet Union had become one of the few countries in the world where the partition between the classes, the ruling class of the Communist Party and the underprivileged class of the proletariat was extensively elaborated and shown openly to the outside world.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Between Social Darwinism and the Overprotective State — Some Reflections on a Modern Concept of Social Welfare Policy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Strasser</surname>
                           <given-names>Johano</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Until very recently, there had been a violent discussion going on in all highly developed industrial societies on the limits of the welfare state, and even today the topic plays an important role in the scientific and political debate in Western Europe — and North America. Ironically, this debate was started in the early 1960s (M. Friedman, F.A. Hayek) and resumed with special vehemence in the 1970s (Wilbur J. Cohen/M. Friedman, J.M. Buchanan, etc.) in a country which, compared with the standard of social welfare in, e.g., Sweden or Germany, might perhaps be counted among the “underdeveloped” welfare states: the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16.</label>
                     <title>Civil Society and Social Justice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frankenberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Günter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Solidarity as a voluntary act of recognizing others as deserving one’s esteem, care and support is possible in a secular society where the responsibility to help is not always already commanded by religion, tradition, or status (noblesse oblige). Yet, solidarity seems to be almost impossible in a society based on contractual relations governed (a) by the principle<italic>pacta sunt servanda</italic>and (b) by the idea of liberty that establishes a system of limited irresponsibility (the limits being contracts and some obligations for “dependents”). That is why societies that we have come to regard as modern do not rely on social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17.</label>
                     <title>American Social Reform and a New Kind of Modernity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sullivan</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The United States, as has been said for at least 100 years, is different from Europe. And it has been different, it has been said over and over again, because of the importance of the doctrine of laissez faire in the United States. This has been a society in which mobility and expansion (perhaps we could call it the frontier thesis in many ways) have played the role that politics and political negotiation and conflict have played in European societies. So, as it has often been noted, even labor in the United States never had an estate consciousness; rarely, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18.</label>
                     <title>East European Reform and West European Integration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Glotz</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The political world has been changing radically since the Central European revolution of 1989. Instead of traditional bi-polar conflict, we now have the potential for multi-polar political conflict. Small wars have once again become a real possibility. Ethnic and social conflicts in Central and Eastern Europe are brewing into equally revolutionary and explosive mixtures. Despite these changes, however, Western Europe’s political classes are still sitting impassively at yesterday’s gambling tables, placing their bets as though oblivious of the fact that “Rouge” and “Noir” have become almost indistinguishable after the historic downpour. They mutter strange codes under their breath (CSCE, CFE,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19.</label>
                     <title>Rooted Cosmopolitanism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Mitchell</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The resurgence of nationalism after the collapse of communism startled many observers in the West. What could have been more stark than the contrast between Western and Eastern Europe? As the European Community pursued new modes of integration, nationalist virulence asserted itself in more than one of the previously communist lands. The bloody unravelling of Yugoslavia has been the most potent example, and the fear remains that the former Soviet Union could become Yugoslavia writ large. Evidently, Leninist and Stalinist dominion led neither to a withering away nor to the successful repression of national sentiments. At the same time, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20.</label>
                     <title>Ethnicity, Migration, and the Validity of the Nation-State</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hobsbawm</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bush’s new world order is a new world disorder, and for the time being, no restoration of stability is visible or even conceivable. It is against this background that we see the present rise of ethnic or nationalist or separatist phenomena in various, but by no means in all parts of the world. But on the other side of the coin is supranationalism or transnationalism, that is, the development of an increasingly integrated world economy or, more generally, a world whose problems cannot effectively be tackled let alone solved within the borders of nation states.</p>
                     <p>The paradox of the situation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21.</label>
                     <title>Neither Politics Nor Economics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wolfe</surname>
                           <given-names>Alan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Americans are increasingly oblivious to politics but exceptionally sensitive to culture. What constitutes for other countries the meat and potatoes of political conflict—the distribution of income among classes, regulation of industry, protectionism versus free trade, sectional antagonism—here captures only the attention of the interests immediately affected. Politics in the classic sense of who gets what, when, and how is carried out by a tiny elite watched over by a somewhat larger, but still infinitesimally small, audience of news followers. The attitude of the great majority of Americans to such traditional political subjects is an unstable combination of boredom,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22.</label>
                     <title>The Left in the Process of Democratization in Central and Eastern European Countries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hajek</surname>
                           <given-names>Milos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Other than the time between the two World Wars, democracy has been a remarkable success after World War II. From 1918 through 1939, after the progression of democratic tendencies in the beginning of the 1920s, most countries in Europe gradually returned to autocratic, even fascist regimes. Today it is a fact that democracy is deeply rooted in Western European countries and all communist regimes in the eastern half of Europe have failed. Some countries, in that region, though, are on their way to democracy, and in other countries democratic governments are trying their first steps, which turn out to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23.</label>
                     <title>After the Disappointment of the Epoch:</title>
                     <subtitle>American Social Tradition between Past and Future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
                           <given-names>Norman</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are indeed liberal and productive forms of capitalism. Invariably, these bear the indelible imprint of Western socialism or of solidaristic social Christianity. The collapse of the Communist regimes by no means entails the imminent triumph of an enlightened capitalism across large areas of the earth’s surface. An appreciably more savage version of capitalism is dominant in many societies (in Latin America, for instance). As they consider the economic and social costs of their integration into the world market, the peoples of the former Soviet Union and Eastern Europe have good reason to be apprehensive. In our own nation, meanwhile,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24.</label>
                     <title>Pluralism and the Left Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mouffe</surname>
                           <given-names>Chantal</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the project of the Left is to survive the discredit that the collapse of “actually existing socialism” has thrown over the very idea of socialism, it requires a new formulation. Even social democracy is presently suffering from the impact of the events in the East and the proclaimed triumph of liberal capitalism. Claims for social justice, economic democracy and struggles against inequalities are increasingly dismissed as relics of a foregone age dominated by the rhetoric of class struggle.</p>
                     <p>The recognition of the virtues of pluralist democracy is indeed an important achievement, but it would be a serious setback for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25.</label>
                     <title>What’s Left After Socialism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Motchane</surname>
                           <given-names>Didier</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the Berlin wall and the Gulf War underscored, the European Left is out of step with history. As long as Europe remains little more than an alibi for surrendering or converting to liberalism, it will continue to be a non entity.</p>
                     <p>The basic foundation for a European renaissance is to understand that the reemergence of Europe and the left are one and the same.</p>
                     <p>The collapse of communism is not a victory for capitalism, but the sign of the failings of Social Democracy. Democracy cannot be restricted to political institutions, but must spread throughout society, internationalism, as well as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26.</label>
                     <title>Some Reflections on the New World Order and Disorder</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ossorio</surname>
                           <given-names>Julian Santamaria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The breakdown of the Berlin wall and more generally, the failure of communism in the (now former) Soviet Union and eastern Europe has suddenly put an end to half a century of cold war. The division of the world in two opposing blocs is over. The nuclear danger looks much less imposing and real. The existential enemy has vanished and the political, ideological, and military threats that the enemy was supposed to embody have faded within a short period of time. Democracy has become the only legitimate principle of political organization accepted almost worldwide, while the market economy and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1x76fjn.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>342</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
