<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h097q</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN75.F7N673 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Frye, Northrop, 1912-1991</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Northrop Frye</book-title>
         <subtitle>New Directions from Old</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rampton</surname>
               <given-names>David</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776618005</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776618008</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ckph8t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>More than fifty years after the publication of<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>, Northrop Frye remains one of Canada's most influential intellectuals. This reappraisal reasserts the relevance of his work to the study of literature and illuminates its fruitful intersection with a variety of other fields, including film, cultural studies, linguistics, and feminism. Many of the contributors draw upon the early essays, correspondence, and diaries recently published as part of the<italic>Collected Works of Northrop Frye</italic>series, in order to explore the development of his extraordinary intellectual range and the implications of his imaginative syntheses. They refute postmodernist arguments that Frye's literary criticism is obsolete and propose his wide-ranging and non-linear ways of thinking as a model for twenty-first century readers searching for innovative ways of understanding literature and its relevance to contiguous disciplines. The volume provides an in-depth examination of Frye's work on a range of literary questions, periods, and genres, as well as a consideration of his contributions to literary theory, philosophy, and theology. The portrait that emerges is that of a writer who still has much to offer those interested in literature and the ways it represents and transforms our world. The book's overall argument is that Frye's case for the centrality of the imagination has never been more important where understanding history, reconciling science and culture, or reconceptualizing social change is concerned.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="430"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>II</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Volumes of the Collected Works of Northrop Frye and of Frye Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rampton</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>VIII</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Ascent may be to the new: when it is, descent is the recovery of the old that was excluded by repression, forgetting, or lack of awareness. It’s a harrowing of hell or rather limbo: a redemption of the dead, a recalling of past to present. Similarly new formulations of myth recapture lost and neglected implications. The Grail stories are profounder than cauldrons-of-plenty myths, and my reading of them is profounder than they are.”¹</p>
                     <p>Northrop Frye, the curious universal scholar who wrote this confident and prophetic account, liked to use the short paragraph as a mode for his extemporized formulations. This</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Collected Works of Northrop Frye:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Project and the Edition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lee</surname>
                           <given-names>Alvin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The initial idea of a collected edition of Frye’s writings and speeches first surfaced on 2 May 1991, a little more than three months after Frye’s death. James Carscallen, a colleague and former student of Frye, made the suggestion in a conversation with Eva Kushner, President of Victoria University, who then asked him to put the case for such an undertaking in the form of a letter to her. Later that day Carscallen did so, in a two-page single-spaced letter in which he recognized something of the complexity of what he was proposing and the large body of Frye’s productions,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Pity the Northrop Frye Scholar”?</title>
                     <subtitle>Anatomy of Criticism Fifty Years After</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Denham</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have a relatively clear memory of my first encounter with<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>. Browsing the shelves of the University of Chicago bookstore in the early 1960s, I picked up a copy of the book, not because anyone had recommended it but because it looked interesting. I had decided by then that I would be doing my degree in the history and theory of criticism, and leafing through this book made me think it worth looking into, though I did not actually read it until a couple of years later. That was after I was jerked out of my graduate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Genius of Northrop Frye</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Willard</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The coda to<italic>Northrop Frye’s Late Notebooks</italic>is a brief but memorable statement:</p>
                     <p>Statement for the day of my death: The twentieth century saw an amazing development of scholarship and criticism in the humanities, carried out by people who were more intelligent, better trained, had more languages, had a better sense of proportion, and were infinitely more accurate scholars and competent professional men than I. I had genius. No one else in the field known to me had quite that.¹</p>
                     <p>Robert Denham, who edited the late notebooks, reports that the typewritten statement turned up among papers from the mid-1970s, when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jumping to Conclusions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Northrop Frye on Canadian Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bentley</surname>
                           <given-names>D. M. R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Do you get<italic>The Forum</italic>?” Duncan Campbell Scott asked E.K. Brown in December 1943. “If so you will have read the article in the Dec[ember] N[umber] on Canadian Poetry…. I suppose Northrop Frye is a nom de plume; if so who is he?” (McDougall 86). The article to which Scott refers is “Canada and Its Poetry,” the lengthy review of A.J.M. Smith’s<italic>Book of Canadian Poetry: A Critical and Historical Anthology</italic>(1943) in which Frye made his major public debut as a critic of Canadian literature and first enunciated his view that “the outstanding achievement of Canadian poetry is in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>History, Tradition, and the Work of Pastoral:</title>
                     <subtitle>Frye’s “Conclusion to a Literary History of Canada”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stacey</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It would be difficult to exaggerate the impact Frye’s 1965 “Conclusion to a<italic>Literary History of Canada</italic>” has had on the theory and practice of Canadian literary criticism. Republished in 1971 as the conclusion to yet another landmark text, Frye’s own<italic>The Bush Garden: Essays on the Canadian Imagination</italic>, which collected the author’s Canadian criticism written over the previous twenty-five years, the essay has exerted a tremendous influence—registered with varying degrees of anxiety—on successive generations of Canadian critics. For Robert Lecker writing in 1993, the ideas expressed in the “Conclusion” “form the primary basis of how most Canadian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Reverend H. Northrop Frye</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sloan</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Northrop Frye’s original theological concept, the concept of the kerygmatic mode of language, emerged late in his thinking and writing. Before then, Frye is probably best seen as a profoundly able teacher of the liberal arts who, along with many others, transformed the liberal humanism arts curriculum of the late 19<sup>th</sup>century into a curriculum for his time. His debts as a teacher of literature to a liberal Christian religious tradition were always there to be seen (perhaps nowhere more explicitly than in<italic>The Critical Path</italic>[1972]). However, his exposition of the excluded initiative of the kerygmatic in his second</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Recovery of the Spiritual Other:</title>
                     <subtitle>Martin Buber’s “Thou” in Northrop Frye’s Late Work</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tóth</surname>
                           <given-names>Sára</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the posthumously published<italic>Double Vision</italic>, the only book in which Northrop Frye explicitly discussed the question of religion and the church as distinguished from literature, he described God as “a spiritual Other” (<italic>dv</italic>20). Although Frye’s engagement with religious and spiritual questions was certainly evident to careful readers of his work from the beginning, with the ongoing posthumous publication of his diaries and notebooks from 1996 onward, the religious aspect of his work has become that much more obvious. The notebooks contain uninhibited speculations on the nature of God, and they reveal how Frye’s theological vision grounded and guided</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Frye’s “Pure Speech”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Literature and the Sacred without the Sacred</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sherbert</surname>
                           <given-names>Garry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given the desire to write about “pure speech” (<italic>dv</italic>83) in literature and the work of Northrop Frye, one might suspect that I would be precipitously thrown into a discourse on religion for, as Jacques Derrida observes, “the desire for purification in general” is “the desire for the safe and sound, for the intact or immune (<italic>heilige</italic>)” (<italic>Echographies</italic>134). In his essay “Faith and Knowledge: The Two Sources of ‘Religion’ at the Limits of Reason Alone,” Derrida asks, “Can a discourse on religion be dissociated from a discourse on salvation: which is to say, on the holy, the sacred, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Northrop Frye and the Chart of Symbolism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ayre</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As they prepared the<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>for publication in the fall of 1955, Princeton University Press’s senior editor Benjamin Houston and Northrop Frye knew they might be in for a rough ride. Douglas Bush, the press’s major reader for the book, had given his blessing for its publication but groused about its excessive schematism. Schematism with its tables and geometric diagrams, either implied or manifest, never seems to have found a happy place in English studies. The only geometric model that has ever fully established itself is Freytag’s Pyramid, which illustrates narrative resolution. Avoidance of such constructions in English</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Earth’s Imagined Corners:</title>
                     <subtitle>Frye and Utopia</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dolzani</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A utopian tale traditionally begins by recounting how a traveller discovered utopia, usually by stumbling across it accidentally. I stumbled across “utopia” as a subject by editing two Frye texts, first the “Third Book” notebooks, and later the Collected Works edition of<italic>Words With Power</italic>. Somewhere around 1964, Northrop Frye began recording notes toward what he called the “Third Book”—that is, his third major work after<italic>Fearful Symmetry</italic>and<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>. Since<italic>Anatomy</italic>was a “centripetal” approach, concerned with the formal relations of literature, the Third Book was to be about criticism and society. Its first subject was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Transcending Realism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Northrop Frye, the Victorians, and the Anatomy of Criticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perkin</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Russell</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Northrop Frye’s scholarly career spanned many decades, and he responded to many of the different concerns of each of them. The author of the<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>and<italic>The Modern Century</italic>seems to encapsulate the mid-20<sup>th</sup>century, the era of optimism about technology and unprecedented expansion of higher education.<italic>The Critical Path</italic>and some of Frye’s essays on education are shaped by the social protest and campus radicalism of the late 1960s. Recognizably a figure of the 1980s, the author of<italic>The Great Code</italic>and<italic>Words With Power</italic>is engaged with theoretical questions about language and culture; he also anticipates</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Re-Valuing Value</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Grady</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sir Edward Elgar, that sublime and melancholy composer, found it a lasting source of wormwood and gall to be identified in the British public mind with his minor, patriotic<italic>Pomp and Circumstance</italic>marches. I suspect that, after the publication of his<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>in 1957, Frye found it similarly irksome to have a reputation not as the cartographer of the literary universe but as that man who argued that critics should avoid value judgments. He certainly became tired of being asked what he meant by such an assertion. “I have nothing new to say on this question,” he began</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Interruption of Myth in Northrop Frye:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Revision of the “Silent Beatrice”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Grande</surname>
                           <given-names>Troni Y.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A growing number of feminist critics are finding their own new directions from the critical path forged by Northrop Frye.¹ While his outline of literature as a “systematic structure of knowledge” (<italic>ac</italic>19) has certainly been useful to feminists, Frye’s myth-making, aimed at creating an integrated community, has been judged a failure insofar as it ignores the problem of gender difference—specifically, the subjugation and exclusion of the embodied woman. Yet if Frye himself showed no focused interest in the way gender inflects the reading of literature and the practice of criticism, the woman (both as a figure and an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Frye and Film Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anatomy of Irony</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jarraway</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On first view, Northrop Frye might have been somewhat discomfited with the “new direction” that my paper proposes to rethink his critical oeuvre. After all, in a passage somewhat dismissive of Marshall McLuhan in<italic>The Critical Path</italic>(1971), Frye claims that it is the written document that is “the model of all teaching … repeating the same words however often one consults it … [hence,] a repetition of the kind that underlines all genuine education,” and indeed, that “makes democracy technically possible” (150–151).¹ Yet in<italic>Anatomy of Criticism</italic>(1957), there are enough references to moviemaking throughout that tour de</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reframing Frye:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bridging Culture and Cognition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sinding</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Opinion is divided on Northrop Frye’s relation to ruling schools of thought in literary and cultural scholarship—that is, cultural studies and new historicism. Some in these schools have drawn deeply on Frye’s literary thought while condemning a perceived anti-historical, formalist, and religious bias (e.g., Jameson—see White, “Frye’s” and “Ideology” for other critics). Others (Hamilton, Salusinszky, Adamson, Wang) have strongly argued Frye’s importance as both contributor and challenger to these schools. Hayden White calls him the “greatest natural cultural historian of our time” (“Frye’s” 28). However, such contextualizations, even when favourable, risk leaving Frye obscured in the shadow of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>An Access of Power:</title>
                     <subtitle>Job, Evolution, and the Spirit of Consciousness in Northrop Frye and Daniel C. Dennett</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Donaldson</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffery</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My subject here, simply put, is the relationship between spirit and the neurological brain. I hope to translate what would normally (and dismissively) be called an “analogous” relationship between a brain’s synapses and an individual’s spirit—in Frye, so closely linked to if not synonymous with powers of the imagination—into a contiguous narrative that shows how one may be related to the other (that is, spirit to brain cell) as a blossom is to its seed, and not as a painting of a flower is to the real flower. In<italic>Words With Power</italic>, Frye himself comes near to reflecting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Biographies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>346</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ckph8t.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>368</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
