<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gwwt</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Religion Without Redemption</book-title>
         <subtitle>Social Contradictions and Awakened Dreams in Latin America</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Andrade</surname>
               <given-names>Luis Martínez</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Báez</surname>
               <given-names>Antonio Carmona</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Löwy</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745335728</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781783712939</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Luis Martínez Andrade</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183gzrq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The world’s eyes are on Latin America as a place of radical political inspiration and as an alternative to the neoliberal model. Each country in the region deals differently in its method of government, yet there are common cultural themes that tie the continent’s trajectory together. Religion without Redemption looks at the sociology of religion, political philosophy and the history of ideas of the continent, in an attempt to show how Western understanding fails to come close to a correct analysis of how and why political and economic characteristics work as they do. Luis Martínez Andrade focuses on how the centrality of religion for the people of Latin America has influenced how they interact with the changes in the modern economic system. Capitalism, for example, has taken on religious characteristics: it has sacred places of worship (the shopping mall) as well as its own prophets. Martínez Andrade discusses how this form of ‘cultural religion’ accompanies many aspects of life in a contradictory manner: not only does it fulfil the role of legitimating oppression, it also can be a powerful source of rebellion, unveiling thus a subversive side to the status quo. Religion Without Redemption advances the ideas of liberation theory into the 21st century, and challenges the provincialism to which many Latin American thinkers are usually consigned.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="176"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Löwy</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luis Martínez Andrade is a brilliant young Mexican scholar, whose writings, published in Spanish, Portuguese, Polish, English and French, are beginning to attract world-wide attention. His essay on shopping malls, included in this book, received first prize for the 2009 international competition Thinking Against the Current, organised by the Cuban Book Institute. This volume is a collection of essays, on very different topics; however, in spite of the diversity, it holds remarkable unity and coherence, given by his theoretical/political approach: a critical Marxist viewpoint, from an emancipatory – that is, anti-capitalist – Latin American perspective. The multiplicity of his intellectual sources in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essays that the reader now holds in her/his hands have been written at different latitudes but all hold the same origin. On the one hand, they were born out of rage and, on the other, out of hope. Rage due to the dire situation with which most of humanity is confronted and the terrible level of exploitation that brings both human life and the entire planet to the edge of destruction. This should not be interpreted as some naïve irritation, commonly found among those ‘warm souls’ who, when watching children die of hunger, cry for the suffering of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Civilising Paradigms and Colonial Atavisms:</title>
                     <subtitle>Power and Social Sciences</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sixteenth century shaped not only the identity of what would later become Latin America but also laid the basis for the emergence of the capitalist world-system (Wallerstein, 1999), the emergence of the coloniality of power (Quijano, 2000) and the advent of modernity (Dussel, 1994). These events profoundly influenced the endogenous and exogenous dynamics of different societies and human groups. In the late fifteenth century, and at the dawn of the sixteenth century, such transcendental phenomena were generated in everyday life around the world (<italic>Lebenswelt</italic>). The year 1492 represents a foundational moment in the collective imaginary of modern Western subjectivity,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Shopping Mall as the Paradigmatic Figure of Neocolonial Discourse:</title>
                     <subtitle>Racism and Power in Latin America</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In social reality, the processes of fetishisation and de-fetishisation (resistance and struggle) are composed of multiple discourses that legitimise, strengthen and configure them with the break from domination. The constitution of social reality is constantly being transformed, due to conflict, tensions and shifts between power(s) and counter-power(s). However, after more than five centuries of imperial, colonial and capitalist domination and exploitation, we observe that the political asymmetry, economic inequality and ethno-racial injustice have become more acute in peripheral societies. Is it possible that the ‘structural sin’ – to borrow a term from the theologists of liberation – continues to take its toll</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Portentous Eclosion of the Principle of Hope:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ernst Bloch and Liberation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 56-page report on the United Nations (UN) Millennium Development Goals (United Nations, 2009) we can find the most despicable features of the economic system. The officials and bureaucrats of the main international financial institutions (the World Trade Organization, International Monetary Fund and World Bank, among others) boast of the ‘humanitarian aid’ dispensed over recent years. However, the good intentions of eradicating poverty in 2015 have vanished in the face of a reality where 1.02 billion people suffer from hunger daily.² According to the report, 51 per cent of the Sub-Saharan population appeared to be living on US$ 1.25</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Gun Powder of the Dwarf:</title>
                     <subtitle>Unearthly Reflections on Contemporary Political Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The twenty-first century heralded serious environmental damage, a significant increase in poverty and the highest levels of social exclusion that radically put into question the very paradigm of civilisation. In the light of current events that have arisen over recent years (‘preventative’ wars, treacherous massacres against civilian populations and the institutionalisation of the ‘State of Exception’ among others), it is important to ask ourselves about the role and contribution of philosophy and theology in the development of alternative projects and in counterposing the hegemonic narrative. Our purpose is to analyse, from political philosophy, the principal tenets of Slavoj Žižek, Enrique</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Tendencies and Latencies of Liberation Theology in the Twenty-First Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The French-Brazilian sociologist Michael Löwy distinguishes between<italic>liberation theology</italic>and<italic>liberation Christianity</italic>to explain the socio-historical movement of the late 1960s in Latin America. For Löwy (1998: 53), Liberation Christianity is a deeper phenomenon, which also includes Protestants and lay people, and allowed the emergence of liberation theology in the early 1970s. In this sense, Liberation Christianity (as a conceptual term) achieves an articulation of the elements that subsequently composed liberation theology, that is, it refers to a fixed worldview.</p>
                     <p>For Löwy, the emergence of the Catholic left in Brazil in the 1960s was the first manifestation of what would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gzrq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Compiled by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carlton</surname>
                           <given-names>Sue</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
