<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">E40.L38 1995</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Amérique latine</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilisation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Antilles, Région de la mer des</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canada</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilisation</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Influence étrangère</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reordering of Culture</book-title>
         <subtitle>Latin America, the Caribbean and Canada in the Hood</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Editor</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ruprecht</surname>
               <given-names>Alvina</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>Associate Editor</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Taiana</surname>
               <given-names>Cecilia</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>1995</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780886292690</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773584273</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1995</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Carleton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.cttq93rp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Political, economic and social barriers among Latin America, the Caribbean and Canada are giving way to global forces and the "global dreams" they inspire. This collection of original articles and essays examines popular culture, literature, theatre, belief systems, indigenous practices and questions of identity, exile and alienation. The interconnectedness and distinction of cultural production throughout the Americas, "transplanted" interests, the mediation of African and European influences, and the expression of shifting identities, all reflect the development of a new American neighbourhood.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="601"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>LATIN AMERICA, THE CARIBBEAN AND CANADA: THE NEW CULTURAL NEIGHBOURHOOD</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ruprecht</surname>
                           <given-names>Alvina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE RECENT SIGNING of the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) between Mexico, the United States and Canada, the creation of the<italic>MERCOSUR</italic>with Argentina, Brazil, Paraguay and Uruguay as well as the regrouping of the greater Caribbean in the loosely formed Association of Caribbean States,¹ in preparation for eventual trade relations with the other countries of the Americas, are evidence that geographical, political and economic barriers are crumbling on this side of the Atlantic. The global “tectonic shift” currently transforming the world is leaving its mark on relations between Latin America, the Caribbean and Canada. However, analyses of these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE POPE MUST HAVE BEEN DRUNK THE KING OF CASTLE A MADMAN:</title>
                     <subtitle>CULTURE AS ACTUALITY, AND THE CARIBBEAN RETHINKING MODERNITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wynter</surname>
                           <given-names>Sylvia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the basis of the Cenù Indians’ perception of the Requisition, by means of which the Spaniards legitimated their claim to the indigenous lands, what seemed to the Spaniards to be a universally applicable order of truth, was “mad and drunken speech.” The crisis of today’s Haiti and the paradox of the United State’s response to this crisis are to be understood in the terms of a parallel contradiction.</p>
                     <p>The crisis of the Caribbean as exemplified in the Haitian situation, is the crisis, too, of our present order of knowledge where the contemporary Western industrialized order, which represents its own</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A CONFLICT OF THEOLOGICAL INTERPRETATIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>BAROQUE SCHOLASTICISM VERSUS LIBERATION THEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lannoy</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Louis de</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In its concern for achieving a greater adaptation of Christian doctrines to the contemporary social conditions of Latin America, liberation theology offers divergent views on many social conceptions inherited from the Baroque scholastic tradition. It also takes its inspiration from some Marxist theories concerning social structures and institutional violence, in order to respond to the new manifestations of poverty and oppression which are appearing in Latin American societies. Although Baroque scholasticism, Marxism and liberation theology agree on notions such as the “the finality of history,” the conflicts of interpretation between Christianism and Marxism have compelled the liberation theologians to reformulate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TELL OUT KING RASTA DOCTRINE AROUND THE WHOLE WORLD:</title>
                     <subtitle>RASTAFARI IN GLOBAL PERSPECTIVE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>D.Yawney</surname>
                           <given-names>Carole</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper discusses the implications for the Rastafari movement, of its spread worldwide in the last two decades. It suggests that further opportunities for Rastafari mobilization, which began in Jamaica in the early 1930s, exist outside the Caribbean, especially in North America and United Kingdom. On the other hand, Rastafari communities abroad have to deal with pressures such as racism, criminalization, and commodification in more intense ways than in the Caribbean. The author argues that all these factors influence the shape that Rastafari takes outside the Caribbean, as well as at its point of origin. It suggests that the impact</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>DE LA MARGINALISATION À LA DÉTERRITORIALISATION DU RASTAFARI</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Curtius</surname>
                           <given-names>Anny Dominique</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mouvement révolutionnaire mais surtout religion antillaise née de diverses conjonctures socio-historiques, le Rastafari a subi, dés son émergence en Jamaïque en 1930, une grande marginalisation avant d’acquerir une certaine popularité. Celle-ci se caractérise, toutefois, par une déterritorialisation-recontextualisation aussi bien dans les autres îles des Antilles qu’en Amérique du Nord, en Europe et ailleurs. Il s’agit de réexaminer le Rastafari dans deux contextes : d’une part il s’agit de revoir ses caractéristiques fondamentales y compris sa marginalité en Jamaïque; d’autre part il s’agit détudier sa réappropriation en Grande Bretagne et en Martinique ou le Rastafari, ayant subi une forte érosion idéologique,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CARIBBEAN CANADIAN WRITERS:</title>
                     <subtitle>A LITERARY FORUM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These texts by Austin Clarke, Cyril Dabydeen, Cecil Foster and Dany Laferrière have been adapted from the transcript of a round table hosted by John Harewood at Carleton University during an evening of discussion and poetry reading with Caribbean and Canadian/Caribbean writers in the context of the annual meeting of the Canadian Association for Latin American and Caribbean Studies (1993). The writers were invited to discuss the particularities of writing in Canada.</p>
                     <p>Austin Clarke describes the genesis of his fiction and speaks of recreating the black immigrant experiences of the 1950s and 1960s by putting English-speaking West Indians face-to-face with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON LATIN AMERICAN-CANADIAN LITERATURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Etcheverry</surname>
                           <given-names>Jorge</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>LATIN AMERICAN-CANADIAN LITERATURE is currently undergoing rapid development. Practically nonexistent, until the second half of the 1970s except for the presence of certain writers, it is now laying claim to a well-defined space within the “Canadian mosaic.” Symptomatic of this trend is the fact that publishing houses such as Coach House, Wallace, Québec Amérique, and others,¹ are publishing Canadian-Latin American authors in English and French translation. Apart from this activity, there are also publishing efforts in the Latin American ethno-cultural sphere itself, characterized by editorial criteria that vary from publisher to publisher; however, all these publishers give priority to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LATIN AMERICAN WRITERS IN CANADA:</title>
                     <subtitle>INTEGRATION AND DISTANCE, WRITING AT THE CROSSROADS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nomez</surname>
                           <given-names>Naïn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE PHENOMENON of the massive transplantation of Latin American intellectuals to other areas of the world, particularly to more economically developed countries, that began in the 1970s has generated a varied literature dealing with the problems of transculturation, exile, and the symbolic relationships of the individual with these diverse societies. Due to its specific original matrix of an English domaine belatedly converted into an independent nation state, Canada has a porous way of absorbing ethnic groups of diverse genesis without completely destroying them. At the beginning, some of the typical cultural traits of these groups were retained, but with time,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WRITING IN EXILE:</title>
                     <subtitle>WRITING NOWHERE FOR NOBODY?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Urbina</surname>
                           <given-names>José Leandro</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>COMPELLED TO THINK about my particular state of life as a Chilean-Canadian writer who came to this country as an exile, I have been literally overwhelmed by the number of different angles and levels from which it is possible to review such an experience. One could in fact write several books just on the most obvious problems encountered when writing in exile.</p>
                     <p>If I had to define simply, for the purpose of analysis, what I thought a writer was, I would say that he or she is an individual who produces texts by working with a specific language and within</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>MESSAGE FROM THE CROSSROADS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Urías</surname>
                           <given-names>Alfonso Quijada</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE NOTION OF “CROSSROADS,” which in Spanish also has the figurative meaning of “dilemma” is associated with another closely related word, “labyrinth,” which in present times implies a pathway through a literary universe where Kafka, Borges, Hawthorne and Octavio Paz, author of<italic>The Labyrinth of Solitude,</italic>all serve as guides. I believe that as writers and poets become aware of their vocation, they discover a different world—of words, of the imagination—and that this discovery makes them appear strange to other people. They are perceived as having failed to adjust to a reality that is too harsh or alien</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE WRITER IN EXILE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Urbanyi</surname>
                           <given-names>Pablo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FOR ANYONE, ARTIST OR NOT, the experience of exile is bound to be upsetting to their happiness and well-being (if such things really exist). It matters little whether such an uprooting is the result of voluntary emigration in search of a better world or forcible banishment from one’s homeland. The loss of points of reference, of the feeling of belonging, combined with an abrupt break in the continuity and evolution of a person’s life, are overwhelming and can lead to an acute sense of disorientation and chaos, especially if the person is a writer.</p>
                     <p>In order to clarify certain issues</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AQUÍ ESTAMOS:</title>
                     <subtitle>AN OVERVIEW OF LATIN AMERICAN WRITING IN QUEBEC TODAY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hazelton</surname>
                           <given-names>Hugh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A NEW LITERATURE,<italic>la latino-québécoise,</italic>has put down roots in Quebec during the last two decades and is now bearing abundant fruit. Born from seeds transplanted from almost every part of Latin America, it is both an autonomous field of literary endeavour and a part of the worlds of Quebec and Canadian literatures. Over the last few years, it has increasingly appropriated its own space to grow and become part of the northern literary scene.</p>
                     <p>Much time has gone by since the first Latin American authors began to arrive in Canada among the refugees and immigrants who left their native</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LE THÉÂTRE DE L’ATÉRITÉ DANS LA COMPAGNIE DES ARTS EXILO</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kurapel</surname>
                           <given-names>Alberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gaucho</surname>
                           <given-names>Le guanaco</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Company of Arts Exilio, the first Latin American company of theatre-performance was founded in 1981 as a scenic expression of exile, integrating the place of its birth, North America, into the multiple Latin American roots of its practitioners.</p>
                     <p>The result is an interdisciplinary form of theatre-performance which integrates different media: film, video, texts, dance, slides, electro-acoustic music, as it experiments with postmodern strategies of staging Otherness, always understood within the special circumstances of these exiled creators.</p>
                     <p>La Compagnie des Arts Exilio, la premiere compagnie de théâtre-performance latino-américaine, a été fondée en 1981 en tant qu’expression scénique de I’exil; par</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REDEFINING THE CENTRE:</title>
                     <subtitle>AUSTIN CLARKE AND OTHER WEST INDIAN CANADIAN WRITERS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Algoo-Baksh</surname>
                           <given-names>Stella</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper argues that West Indian Canadian Writers have contributed significantly to a redefinition of the<italic>centre.</italic>Such writers have moved black characters from the periphery to centre stage, exploring the black experience from the inside rather than from a Eurocentric vantage point. Questioning the “hegemony of the centre,” they often examine the problems of their societies from a fresh perspective. In the process, they expose the insidious effects of colonialism on the colonized, who ultimately lose sight of their own history, heritage and at times even their identity. The author emphasizes the work of Austin Clarke, the pioneer among</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NARRATIVE QUILTING IN BANANA BOTTOM AND VOYAGE IN THE DARK</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Allen</surname>
                           <given-names>Carolyn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>EVER SINCE THE FIRST NATIONALIST stirrings in the Caribbean back in the 19th century, our intellectuals have been engaged in efforts to elaborate a model of identity. The deterministic European model proved problematic. It would demand a degree of intellectual sleight of hand to construct a persuasive argument of origins in a region where the indigenous population was all but eradicated. The solution? Creole. A cross-cultural definition which distinguished persons of Old World lineage, but New World birth and breeding. The term was used for first generation descendants in several colonial zones, but it is in the Americas, and particularly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NATURE AND IMAGINATION:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE BESTIARY OF DULCE MARÍA LOYNAZ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arauúo</surname>
                           <given-names>Nara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN 1992, THREE CARIBBEAN WRITERS were honoured with important literary prizes: Dereck Walcott with the Nobel, Dulce María Loynaz with the Cervantes, and Patrick Chamoiseau with the Goncourt. This seems a delightful coincidence in a year in which, between debates and festivities, the encounter between Europe and the so-called Americas was remembered.</p>
                     <p>The simultaneous recognition of artists from three linguistic areas of the Caribbean seems more than a fateful coincidence and might be explained by other causes. The Nobel and the Cervantes are awarded to a whole body of work, and the Goncourt, in accordance with the statutes of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>POETIC DISCOURSE IN BABYLON:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE POETRY OF DIONNE BRAND</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Case</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederick Ivor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THOUGH DIONNE BRAND is not a member of the Rastafari, her published collections of poetry¹ display characteristics of one who has lived the alienation of Babylon and has had to confront it with the arms at her disposal. While her poetry is essentially about the right to define and to determine one’s own being, it would be misleading to speak of the universal appeal of her work, since there are many who would react sharply to her unambiguous ideological perspectives.²</p>
                     <p>It is essential to emphasize the thematic aspects of Brand’s ontological enterprise, and it is equally important to bear in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>MAÎTRE OU MENTOR:</title>
                     <subtitle>L’OMBRE DE GLISSANT DANS TEXACO DE PATRICK CHAMOISEAU</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>N’Zengou-Tayo</surname>
                           <given-names>Marie-José</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DANS LES INTERVIEWS accordés á la presse, lors de l’obtention du Prix Goncourt 1992 pour son roman<italic>Texaco,</italic>Patrick Chamoiseau reconnaissait le rôle déterminant joué par Edouard Glissant dans sa vie d’écrivain et d’homme antillais. Le romancier donnait ainsi acte de l’influence de Glissant sur<italic>Texaco</italic>comme sur ses oeuvres précédentes. Cependant, cette reconnaissance, déjà présente dans divers textes ayant précédé<italic>Texaco</italic>
                        <italic>(Eloge de la Créolité,</italic>articles publiés dans<italic>Antilla</italic>et enfin la dédicace et les exergues de<italic>Texaco</italic>même), nous invite à nous interroger sur la véritable nature de la relation Glissant-Chamoiseau et à essayer de repérer/identifier les traces</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BANISHED BETWEEN TWO WORLDS:</title>
                     <subtitle>EXILES IN CHILEAN CANADIAN LITERATURE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perron</surname>
                           <given-names>Sylvie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE STUDY OF LATIN AMERICAN literature written outside the country of origin leads inevitably to the theme of exile. First treated during the Middle Ages, the problem of exile lends itself in various ways to literary study. One such way is provided by the exiled character him or herself, a source of insight into a wide sphere of social issues. Appearing periodically in Latin American literature to illustrate the various sociopolitical upheavals history, the exile in our own time figures prominently in Chilean writing in Canada, where writers are currently reworking this theme, each in their own style. Of particular</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WOMEN’S WORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>FROM RESISTANCE TO CHALLENGING THE PATRIARCHAL CULTURE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rojas-Trempe</surname>
                           <given-names>Lady</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CONTEMPORARY LATIN AMERICAN literature in the past two decades—the 1970s and 1980’s—reliably proves that the written word of women has contributed to the outlining and definition of a culture which challenges male hegemony as well as androcentric power relations and knowledge.² The breach that certain feminist and nonfeminist writers opened in the patriarchal culture allowed them, as a point of departure, to underline the fact that they were different from men. At the same time, they emphasized the historical cost of marginalization and took up the struggle for fair treatment.³ Soon after, they established certain epistemological bases for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“L’AMÉRIQUE C’EST MOI”:</title>
                     <subtitle>DANY LAFERRÉRE AND THE BORDERLESS TEXT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ruprecht</surname>
                           <given-names>Alvina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE WRITINGS OF DANY LAFERRlÈRE, and more specifically his three North American novels¹ centered on the adventures of a sexually insatiable black man, are examples of textual hybridity, characteristic of “Border Writing,” as defined, among others, by Emily Hicks (1991). This notion, inscribed in a geographical metaphor, is the nucleus of a multidisciplinary network of categories useful to the understanding of a writer like Laferriére, whose work paradoxically defies and encompasses borders of all kinds.</p>
                     <p>The border as metaphor, evokes, among other things, a space securely partitioned by physical limits but where the different areas defined by those limits must</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CULTURE AND EDUCATION IN POST-COLONIAL DEVELOPMENT:</title>
                     <subtitle>A SOUTHERN ANDEAN STUDY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arratia</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria-Inés</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS PAPER DEALS PRIMARILY with the need to integrate local cultural dynamics into all activities related to community development, including education. It also deals with a particular positioning for social scientists committed to the defence of native cultures and to the promotion of a pluralistic and democratic attitude towards local development through the use of participatory methodologies (Fals Borda, 1979, 1980, 1987). Based on my field experience and understanding of development as cultural action, I am questioning previous categories of analysis and constructed theoretical positions affecting the various processes involved in community development.</p>
                     <p>In this paper I focus on development</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>YEKMASEUALKOPAN:</title>
                     <subtitle>Y-A-T-IL UNE MANIÉRE MODERNE D’ÊTRE NAHUA?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beaucage</surname>
                           <given-names>Pierre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>COMME LE SOULIGNE BAUDRILLART, on ne peut donner à la notion de modernité un contenu précis, valable pour tous les lieux et toutes les époques : couvrant un champ aussi vaste que flou, elle recoupe les domaines de l’histoire et de l’idéologie, de l’économique et de l’éthique, de l’esthétique et de la politique. Elle est à la fois «catégorie générale et impératif culturel [...] Mouvante dans ses formes, dans ses contenus, dans le temps et dans l’espace, elle n’est stable que comme systéme de valeurs» (1985 : 424). Selon le même auteur, ses principaux traits sont : la sécularisation de</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ART AS A FORMATIVE FORCE IN LATIN AMERICA:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE RECLAMATION OF THE INDIGENOUS AND POPULAR PAST IN THE ART OF NICARAGUA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Craven</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN HIS BOOK OF 1983 entitled<italic>Nicaragua tan violentamente dulce,</italic>the writer Julio Cortazar observed the following: “The fact is this, hardly had I arrived in Nicaragua, on the 19th of July of course, when the word ‘culture’ began to echo in my ears and to form part of an extremely varied thematic and sweeping program ... [Nicaraguan] culture did not appear to me to be an isolated component of social sustenance nor did it seem to be the salt or sugar that were added as mere flavor or seasoning to a plate of food” (Cortázar, 1983).</p>
                     <p>With this observation,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BEYOND DEVELOPMENT AND MODERNITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>REGENERATING THE ART OF LIVING</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Esteva</surname>
                           <given-names>Gustavo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IF THE HOUR HAS COME for rethinking modernity, it is time to make very explicit the irrenconcilable opposition between culture and development. An analogous opposition would seem to be a good starting point for my argument. “Genetic endowment and cultural heritage evolve according to opposite laws.... Biological evolution sprouts new branches that do not cross-fertilize, branches that never again unite once they have become solid. Culture evolves along another route: its forms are anastomosis; like a river, its waters divide, meander and reunite. Biological evolution remains ungraved while culture implies the memory of things past, which survive only in myth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HAITIAN MUSIC IN THE GLOBAL SYSTEM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Averill</surname>
                           <given-names>Gage</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FEW ISSUES HAVE GENERATED as much academic interest across disciplines in recent years as the process of globalization. The world’s economic, political, demographic, and socio-cultural geography has radically metamorphosed under the impact of technologies and media that shrink time and space in the quest for rapid turnover of capital (Giddens, 1990). Although the long-term effects of globalization on nation states, futures markets, and the drug trade, etc. are unclear at best, none of these approaches the complexities and the problematic status of cultural identity in the globalizing environment.</p>
                     <p>This paper examines the repercussions of globalization for Haitian music and musicians,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CARIBBEAN POPULAR MUSIC AND CIVIL SOCIETY:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CALYPSO ARENA AS VOICE OF THE PEOPLE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Charles</surname>
                           <given-names>Embert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CARIBBEAN POPULAR MUSIC HAS, for centuries, articulated the opinions, the grumblings and the questions of many communities in the Caribbean region which have not been able to make their views known through the formal education system or the mass media. The Flower societies of Saint Lucia in the emancipation and post-emancipation eras, the calypso and reggae in the period of colonization, and the Antillean zouk and kadans in the post-independence era are forms of music rooted in cultural expression, political experience and indigenous languages. These forms have survived political and economic obstacles because of their relevance to the growth of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>COME TO JAMAICA AND FEEL ALL RIGHT:</title>
                     <subtitle>TOURISM, COLONIAL DISCOURSE AND CULTURAL RESISTANCE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ford-Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Honor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE UNITED NATIONS World Tourism Organization forecasts that by the year 2000, tourism will be the single most important global economic activity (Enloe, 1989, p.20.). Internationally, tourism employs more people than the oil industry. In the Caribbean, the hotel, the blue skies and the beach have replaced the great house and the sugar plantation as major foreign exchange earners. Mass tourism is transforming population the physical environment, aspects of sexuality and sexual relations, speech habits, education and forms of representation of the region.</p>
                     <p>I want to argue that representational practices within tourism recycle and adapt old images of colonial domination</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONSTRUCTING CARIBBEAN CULTURE IN TORONTO:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE REPRESENTATION OF CARIBANA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gallaugher</surname>
                           <given-names>Annemarie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CARIBANA, BEGUN IN 1967 as the Caribbean community’s contribution to Canada’s centennial celebrations, has become a major annual summer event in Toronto, attracting some one million people. Inspired primarily by Trinidad’s annual pre-Lenten Carnival, this two-week festival of the arts reflects the diverse expressive traditions of the Caribbean, bringing together a wide range of indigenous songs, dances, masquerade and oral traditions, and also various foods and folkways of the region.</p>
                     <p>In an August 1, 1993 front-page article in the<italic>Toronto Star</italic>reporting on the 26th annual Caribana festival, Mark Zwolinski wrote the following:</p>
                     <p>Metro police Inspector Ernie Beale said barriers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CARTOONING AND DEVELOPMENT IN THE CARIBBEAN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lent</surname>
                           <given-names>John A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>409</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AS A NUMBER OF US PONDERED an ideal role for journalists at the first Philippine Press Institute seminars and workshops in 1964-65, and thus, established the foundation for development journalism, it did not occur to us to broaden the definition of journalists to include graphic artists. In a series of sessions held in Manila, topics ranged from provincial journalists to crime reporting and women’s pages.</p>
                     <p>Throughout the 1960s, the Philippine Press Institute and, later the Press Foundation of Asia, worked out what they thought should be the responsibilities of journalists in developing countries. In short, they defined development journalism as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EDUCATION AND POPULAR CULTURE IN THE CARIBBEAN:</title>
                     <subtitle>YOUTH RESISTANCE IN A PERIOD OF ECONOMIC UNCERTAINTY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Noguera</surname>
                           <given-names>Pedro A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WHILE THE ROLE OF EDUCATION in political socialization and the construction of national identity in the Caribbean has been recognized and studied by several scholars (Bell, 1967; Fagen, 1969; Jansen, 1991; Torres, 1991; Miller, 1991), its relationship to popular culture has received considerably less attention. In part, this is due to the tendency of Caribbean scholars to conceive of educational institutions primarily as instruments of the state to propagate and reinforce the hegemony exerted by domestic and foreign elites over political and economic institutions (Carnoy and Samoff, 1989; Henry and Stone, 1983; Miller, 1989).¹ Curriculum content, student assessment and placement,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>MYTH AND SIGNIFICAT1ON IN PERRY HENZELL’S THE HARDER THEY COME</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yearwood</surname>
                           <given-names>Gladstone L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE HARDER THEY COME (1971) is a chant of black dreams and frustrations. It is the story of a betrayal, the loss of innocence and the intrusion foreign values and technologies into the contemporary Caribbean. Writers Perry Henzell and Trevor Rhone craft a narrative about a mid-20th century Jamaican folk hero Ivanhoe ‘Rhygin’ Martin, whose mythic fight against the established order parallels the day-to-day struggle of society’s disenfranchised. In the film, Ivan is trapped between two worlds—the persistent poverty of Jamaica’s suffering underclass and an alluring metropolitan North American lifestyle. Eventually he dies because of this forced interface.</p>
                     <p>The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ARGENTINE COMMERCIAL CINEMA:</title>
                     <subtitle>INDUSTRY, SOCIETY AND AESTHETICS, 1983-1989</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ciria</surname>
                           <given-names>Alberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>457</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper traces the history of the filmmaking industry in Argentina from 1983 to 1989, during the presidency of Raul Alfonsin. The author examines the industry’s economic as well as artistic development emphasizing the production by the most important filmmakers of that period to bring to light the strong influence of American films and filmmaking processes on the evolution of Argentina’s domestic cinematographic art and industry.</p>
                     <p>L’auteur trace le parcours de I’industrie cinematographique en Argentine pendant la présidence de Raul Alfonsin (1983-1989). En faisant le bilan à la fois du développement économique et de I’activite artistique, il insiste sur le</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>IDENTITY AND DIFFERENCES IN THE CARIBBEAN DIASPORA:</title>
                     <subtitle>CASE STUDY FROM METROPOLITAN TORONTO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yon</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE ISSUE OF IDENTITY, and the questions it evokes, occupies a central place in social, political and cultural theory in the closing decade of the 20th century. In positing this development, in the words of Stuart Hall 1989) as “the question of identity,” I draw attention to the contestation and struggles over what it means to talk about identity and to the identifications that are invoked in the process of talking and writing. The theoretical and other developments leading to the present centering of identity in theory and politics are multiple. They include intense debates around issues of nationalism, ethnicity,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>L’EXPRESSION D’UNE IDENTITÉ À TRAVERS LA POÉSIE ET LES CHANSONS AU NICARAGUA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ortiz</surname>
                           <given-names>Milagros</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>499</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CET ARTICLE TENTERA de répondre aux questions que se posait le poète Pablo Antonio Cuadra:<italic>«¿Sería el Nicaragüense un hombre dividido por la duda?» , «¿o es el nicaragüense la fusión de antagonismos, la unificación de contrastes?»</italic>(1978, p.20).¹ départ, nous nous butons à un premier probléme : de quel Nicaraguayen parle-t-il ? Les conflits armés apportent une partie de la réponse, car ils ont laissé voir qu’il existe plus d’une seule identité nicaraguayenne. Nous tenterons ici de répondré au poète en analysant des chansons et des poémes provenant des Nicaraguayens de la majorité<italic>ladine</italic>«Métisse»,² le peuple qui se</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BEAUTIFUL LIES:</title>
                     <subtitle>LEGITIMATION OF THE NATIONAL IDENTITY IN TWO SERIES OF INDIANIST POEMS OF THE DOMINICAN REPUBLIC, 1877-1882</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vallejo</surname>
                           <given-names>Catharina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>519</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE APPEARANCE OF FOUR MAJOR literary works in the space of five years in Santo Domingo between 1877 and 1882 marks the first flourishing of Dominican literature.¹ Until that time, except for short stories and some legends in verse, only one book-length literary work had been published in the city, an anthology of Dominican poetry in 1874.² The<italic>Fantasías indíjenas</italic>by José Joaquin Pérez, of 1877, is the first volume of poetry published in Santo Domingo by a Dominican author; in 1879 Manuel de Jesús Galván published Part I of the first novel with a Dominican theme,<italic>Enriquillo</italic>(completed in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HISTOIRE ET LITTÉRATURE :</title>
                     <subtitle>LA REPRÉSENTATION DE L’ANNÉE 1938 DANS DEUX ROMANS CHILIENS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pozo</surname>
                           <given-names>José Del</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>535</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>LA PRODUCTION DES ÉCRIVAINS chiliens dans le domaine du roman historique, malgré L’heritage laissé par Blest Gana depuis la publication de<italic>Durante la Reconquista</italic>(Pendant la reconquête) à la fin des années 1890² est assez mince. Ceci contraste avec la fécondité de ce courant dans d’autres pays latino-américains. Mis à part la guerre civile de 1891 qui donna lieu à la publication de plusieurs ouvrages, les autres faits historiques n’ont pas eu le même impact au niveau littéraire (Zamudio, 1973, p.20).</p>
                     <p>Les événements de I’année 1938 ont cependant suscité un certain intérêt chez les écrivains: au moins deux parmi ces</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LA GUADELOUPE DANS L’IDÉARIUM ET LES STRATÉGIES DU DÉCOUVREUR:</title>
                     <subtitle>NOUVELLES APPROCHES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yacou</surname>
                           <given-names>Alain</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>555</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>C’EST LE 4 NOVEMBRE 1493 que Christophe Colomb découvre, comme on sait, I’île que les Indiens caraïbes appelaient Caloucaera et qu’il baptise du nom de Sainte-Marie de la Guadeloupe suivant la promesse qu’il avait faite aux Hiéronymites du monastére du même nom en Espagne.</p>
                     <p>C’est trés exactement à I’embouchure de la rivière du Grand Carbet dans la partie Sud de I’actuelle commune de Capesterre Belle-Eau (Sudest de la Guadeloupe proprement díte) qu’eut lieu le tout premier débarquement des Espagnols dans l’île principale des Caraïbes.</p>
                     <p>C’est done en cet endroit que s’est déroulé ce qu’il est convenu d’appeler la rencontre des</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NAVIGATING THE TEXT:</title>
                     <subtitle>AN EXPLORATION IN COMPARATIVE CROSS-CULTURAL EPISTEMOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Taiana</surname>
                           <given-names>Cecilia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>565</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS PAPER IS AN EXPLORATION of the use of hypertext and its capability of identifying and opening up embedded epistemological traditions present in the text. Two academic course outlines, one from Canada and the other from Argentina, have been chosen to illustrate the discussion.</p>
                     <p>Several researchers have noted the importance of the role of the reader in the process of producing meaning (Jonassen, 1993; Eco, 1992; Derrida, 1976, 1978). This relationship between the author, the text and the reader is further complicated by the use of hypertext. Ted Nelson (as cited in Landow, 1992) coined the term hypertext in 1965,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.cttq93rp.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>583</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
