<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84fhk</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Insights from African American Interpretation</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Smith</surname>
               <given-names>Mitzi J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>POWELL</surname>
               <given-names>MARK ALLAN</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>series editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506400174</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506400175</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506401133</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506401139</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kgqtsd"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this volume in the series Reading the Bible in the 21st Century: Insights, Mitzi J. Smith describes the distinctive African American experience of Scripture, from slavery to Black Liberation and beyond, and the unique angles of perception that an intentional African American interpretation brings to the text today. Smith shows how questions of race, ethnicity, and the dynamics of “othering" have resulted in new reading of particular texts, and describes challenges that scholarship raises for the future of biblical interpretation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="144"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powell</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark Allan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>“What does this mean?”</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>That is, perhaps, the most-asked question with regard to the Bible. What does this verse mean? What does this story mean? What does this psalm or letter or prophecy or promise or commandment mean?</p>
                     <p>The question can arise from a simple desire for information, or the concern may be one of context or relevance: What<italic>did</italic>this mean to its original audience? What does it mean for us today?</p>
                     <p>Someone has said that understanding the Bible is difficult not because meaning is hard to find but because it is so abundant. The problem for interpreters is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introducing African American Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Biblical interpretation is political. And as African Americans well know, biblical interpretation has always been political. The political is inherently hierarchal, in that some people are considered as superior to others who are constructed as inferior and subordinated. The political is concerned with the control of and access to resources, knowledge, and power. The power attributed to the Bible is profoundly demonstrated in the 2010 American postapocalyptic film<italic>The Book of Eli</italic>. Denzel Washington’s character, Eli, has in his possession a powerful, sought-after book that his adversary and local warlord, Carnegie (played by Gary Oldman), will stop at nothing to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Twentieth-Century Foundations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first professionally or academically trained African American biblical scholars emerged in the twentieth century and laid the foundation for African American biblical interpretation as an approach or method for doing biblical interpretation.¹ Most, if not all, of those scholars sought to do biblical interpretation that would both satisfy the needs and desires of their own souls and would be relevant to and resonate with the collective heart and mind of black churches and communities. Those first black biblical scholars had been shaped by and were situated within the elite academic professional guild, whose majority membership consists of mature white</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>African American Biblical Interpretation in the Early Twenty-First Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As more African American scholars have entered the academy, African American biblical interpretation as an interdisciplinary approach to biblical studies is expanding in terms of sheer numbers and of diverse methods and methodologies employed. Nevertheless, what W. E. B. Du Bois declared to be the problem of the twentieth century continues to be an overarching issue in this century: “the problem of the color line.”¹ Race/ethnicity and its mutually impacting social divisions continue to be primary categories of analyses for scholars of color. If it were not for African American interpretation, little, if any, sustained critical engagement about race would</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Slavery, Torture, Systemic Oppression, and Kingdom Rhetoric:</title>
                     <subtitle>An African American Reading of Matthew 25:1–13</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Oppressive structures are often adjusted to accommodate the changing fears and desires of the (neo)colonizers and/or dominant oppressors. The public face of an oppressive system can change (or alternate, at times), between oppressor and oppressed subordinated other; aspects of the new facade may even appear representative of the oppressed. But the death-dealing policies continue to the detriment of the oppressed. Oppressive systems must be exposed and deconstructed or dismantled (even in sacred texts), not simply recycled or cosmetically adjusted to palliate and opiate the oppressed and their allies. Studies have proven that black women and men, the poor, and other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Dis-membering, Sexual Violence, and Confinement:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Womanist Intersectional Reading of the Story of the Levite’s Wife (Judges 19)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The¹ story of the gang rape and mutilation of a Levite’s secondary wife in Judges 19 is indeed a “text of terror,” as Phyllis Trible has argued.² Texts of terror reflect, describe and critique the violence humans inflict upon one another, as well as our ignorance, complicity, and culpability in the brutality and victimization of women and others. Sometimes it is the Divine who is depicted as terrorizing women and their children or as sanctioning violence among humans. We often rationalize that the violence we commit is necessary and different from the violence committed by the internal and external other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqtsd.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
