<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PG3948.V88Z87 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Vynnychenko, Volodymyr Kyrylovych, 1880–1951</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Vynnychenko, Volodymyr Kyrylovych, 1880–1951</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Exile</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Vynnychenko, Volodymyr Kyrylovych, 1880–1951</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Travel</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Exile (Punishment) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Emigration and immigration in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Travel in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Identity (Philosophical concept) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ukraine</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">In literature</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Faces of Displacement</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Writings of Volodymyr Vynnychenko</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SOROKA</surname>
               <given-names>MYKOLA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773540378</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773587670</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pq15d"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"Whom do our people read? Vynnychenko. Whom do people talk about if it concerns literature? Vynnychenko. Whom do they buy? Again, Vynnychenko." So wrote Mykhailo Kotsiubynsky about the young Volodymyr Vynnychenko. An innovative and provocative writer, Vynnychenko was also a charismatic revolutionary and politician who responded to the dramatic upheavals of the first half of the twentieth century by challenging old values and bringing forward new ideas about human relationships. Despite his inseparable association with Ukraine, what is often overlooked is the fact that Vynnychenko wrote the majority of his works outside his native land following his flight from Tsarist and Soviet tyranny. In this ground-breaking study, Mykola Soroka draws on contemporary theories of displacement to show how Vynnychenko's expatriate status determined his worldview, his choice of literary devices, and his attitudes toward his homeland and hostlands. Soroka considers concepts of identity to study the intertwined experiences of the writer - as an exile, émigré, expatriate, traveler, and nomad - and to demonstrate how these experiences invigorated his art and left a lasting impact on his work. The first book-length study in English on Volodymyr Vynnychenko, Faces of Displacement is an insightful examination of an exiled writer that sheds new light on the challenges faced by the displaced.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Vynnychenko Chronology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Displacement and Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The principal point of this study is that all forms of displacement – exile, émigré, expatriate, travel, nomadism, emigration, and diaspora – are not isolated and may overlap. This pluralistic approach may reveal the dominance of one form of displacement over another or their collisions in shaping the identity of displaced writers, alongside other undercurrents of influence such as historical time, geographical place, and the writer’s own personal characteristics. Viewing different forms of displacement in the historical continuum, we can see how they change with the social progress of civilization. “A hundred years ago,” says Czeslaw Milosz, “average people not familiar with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Émigré</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Vynnychenko was born to a poor peasant family on 28 July 1880 in the city of Yelysavethrad (Kirovohrad today) in the steppe region of south-central Ukraine (at that time part of the Russian Empire). After graduating from the gymnasium in 1899, he wandered through the country, a common practice of the revolutionary intelligentsia in the Russian Empire. The goal of “khodinnia v narod” [going to the people] was to observe the life of various strata of the population. Their efforts were also connected with the socialist ideals of the intelligentsia, which aimed to enlighten the illiterate peasantry and improve social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Expatriate/Traveler</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Literary critics have tended to frame Vynnychenko’s stay abroad in terms of two concepts – émigré and exile, which indeed were dominant faces of his displacement. Such critics have also taken for granted Vynnychenko’s orientation towards Ukraine, focusing on hardships of his displacement. They have referred to his time abroad as “difficult” (Doroshkevych, 219), as a “miserable existence” (Richytsky, 11) and, in the Soviet time in a more ideological vein, as part of an “emigrant rubbish heap” (Shabliovsky, 48). Displacement, however, is a complex phenomenon, and I will challenge the established approach to reveal another face of Vynnychenko’s displacement – the face</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Exile</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The practice of exile has its beginnings with the advent of settled and socially organized societies. The first known human experience of exile, the story of Sinuhe (documented on an Egyptian papyrus), dates back to 2000 BC (Tabori, 43). The limited social mobility, settled way of life, and minimal knowledge of the “other” in geographical and cultural terms in early societies meant that physical expulsion from the homeland was one of the most severe forms of punishment, almost equivalent to death.¹ Exile is connected to a range of other important signifiers: separation, loss, alienation, loneliness, and nostalgia. Having undergone “a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Utopist, 1920–1925</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In 1920, Vynnychenko found himself in a new displacement, which would last for more than thirty years until his death in 1951. The writer had plunged actively into politics after his illegal return to Ukraine in 1914, and from 1917 to 1920 he was one of the leaders of the Ukrainian revolution. He was the first Chair of the Ukrainian government, 1917–18, and head of the revolutionary Directory, 1918–19. After the collapse of the Ukrainian People’s Republic (UNR), Vynnychenko left the country and resided briefly in Semmering, Budapest, Lienz, Vienna, and Prague. In the Czech capital of Prague</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Universalist, 1925–1941</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The reactions of displaced writers who remain outside their homelands for a considerable period of time generally range between two extreme groups – isolationism and universalism. According to Rubchak, for writers who belong to the first group, writing becomes either “a vehicle for memories and hopes or a totally self-enclosed shell” (101). Thomas Mann speaks about another extreme which he experienced personally: “Exile has become something quite different from what it once was; it is no longer a condition of waiting programmed for an ultimate return, but rather [it] hints of the dissolution of nations and the unification of the world”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Homecoming, 1941–1951</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The waning years mark a stage in life when it is natural for people to feel nostalgic and recollect their pasts. Kathleen Woodward and Murray Schwartz argue that “aging anticipates loss,” which intensifies the work of memory and fantasy (3). Although it is generally understood that the elderly experience a waning in their ability to remember, the decline mainly affects the recall of new learning, while the capacity to vividly recall episodes from the past may be high and even stronger than that of young adults (Burke, 124–6). Verbal narrative, imagery, and emotions are the three main components of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In order to substantiate displacement as a relevant concept for this study it was necessary to start with a theoretical discussion of the issue of displaced writing in literary discourse. A historical and comparative overview of related terms – exile, émigré, expatriation, travel, emigration/immigration, diaspora, and nomadism – helps us understand displacement as a dynamic migrant experience that may range from being totally negative to very positive. Exiles are reconciled to their present predicament and have nostalgic feelings for the past; émigrés are actively involved in the contemporary literary process in the homeland and seek to return; emigrants/immigrants integrate and adapt themselves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX:</title>
                     <subtitle>Chronological List of Vynnychenko’s Works</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pq15d.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
