<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7hbh97</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">D16.9.N36 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Consciousness</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Narration, Identity, and Historical Consciousness</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Straub</surname>
               <given-names>Jürgen</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782388609</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782388605</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jürgen Straub</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1btbw85"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A generally acknowledged characteristic of modern life, namely the temporalization of experience, inextricable from our intensified experience of contingency and difference, has until now remained largely outside psychology's purview. Wherever questions about the development, structure, and function of the concept of time have been posed - for example by Piaget and other founders of genetic structuralism - they have been concerned predominantly with concepts of "physical", chronometrical time, and related concepts (e.g., "velocity"). All the contributions to the present volume attempt to close this gap. A larger number are especially interested in the narration of stories. Overviews of the relevant literature, as well as empirical case studies, appear alongside theoretical and methodological reflections. Most contributions refer to specifically historical phenomena and meaning-constructions. Some touch on the subjects of biographical memory and biographical constructions of reality. Of all the various affinities between the contributions collected here, the most important is their consistent attention to issues of the constitution and representation of temporal experience.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Series</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rüsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jörn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Straub</surname>
                           <given-names>Jürgen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Until now, psychology has barely dealt with the topics of historical consciousness and historical thought. Although the discipline has given thorough attention to other forms of thought—to other forms of the construction of reality—there is no distinctive tradition with the theoretical or clinical objective of establishing a psychology of specifically historical acts of meaning-construction. Seen properly, this is astonishing. Psychology is commonly considered one of the key modern sciences that aspire to investigate as well as to shape our relationships to others and to the world from a genetic, structural, and functional perspective. However, a generally acknowledged characteristic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Narrative Psychology and Historical Consciousness:</title>
                     <subtitle>Relationships and Perspectives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Polkinghorne</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Postmodern theory has severely undercut the notion that historians can produce objective and accurate descriptions of past episodes. Instead, it proposes that discovering the factual truth about historical events is extremely problematic because knowledge production is relative to the values and agenda of the inquirer. The question of the validity of historical knowledge has informed the general topic “Making Sense of History,” the theme of the book series of which the present volume is a part. The postmodern critique of the modernist epistemology of the humanities and social sciences has produced considerable consternation and disturbance in most of these disciplines.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Past and Present as Narrative Constructions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bruner</surname>
                           <given-names>Jerome S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The usual answer to this question is a kind of doxology delivered in the name of “the scientific method”: Thou shalt not indulge self-delusion, nor utter unverifiable propositions, nor commit contradiction, nor treat mere history as cause, and so on. Story is not the accepted stuff of science and “logic.” If meaning-making were always dedicated to achieving a “scientific” understanding of the world, that would be one thing. But neither the empiricist’s knowledge through the senses, nor the rationalist’s route through necessary truths suffice: neither alone nor both together capture how ordinary people go about assigning meanings to their experiences—</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Telling Stories, Making History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Narrative Psychology of the Historical Construction of Meaning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Straub</surname>
                           <given-names>Jürgen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contemporary discussion of<italic>Geschichte</italic>and<italic>Historie</italic>, of historical consciousness and historical thought, seems infinite.¹ We especially encounter these terms when our collective practice is beset by difficulties, crises, or conflicts over psychosocial or political orientation. In Germany, more than fifty years after the end of the National Socialist dictatorship, there are still very “immediate” reasons for the importance of historical reflection. Whatever may occasion this reflection, historical communication is never simply a “medium” through which<italic>groups</italic>understand themselves—their past, present, and future.<italic>Individuals</italic>, too, understand themselves, that is, their lives, against the horizon of the history in which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Narrative, Moral Identity, and Historical Consciousness:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Social Constructionist Account</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gergen</surname>
                           <given-names>Kenneth J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two decades ago, inquiry into narrative played but a minor role in scholarly deliberation; the relationship between narrative analysis and historiography was little explored; the term “narrative” had scarcely entered the vocabulary of psychological science. Today, the study of narrative concatenates throughout the humanities and the social sciences, and the problems raised by such analyses for our conception of history, along with the historical consciousness of the individual, are profound. Further, there are now many distinct and well-articulated orientations toward narrative: realist, phenomenological, psychodynamic, cognitive, textual, and rhetorical among them. Each raises different implications for our understanding of history, identity,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Narrative Truth and Identity Formation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Abduction and Abuse Stories as Metaphors</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spence</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early in the<italic>Culture of Narcissism</italic>, Christopher Lasch calls our attention to the way in which unremitting self-awareness has become the bane of modern society. We long, he suggests, for the “suspension of self-consciousness.” Modern man, “imprisoned in his pseudo-awareness of the self … would gladly take refuge in an<italic>idee fixe</italic>, a neurotic compulsion, a ‘magnificent obsession’—anything to get his mind off his own mind.”¹ A similar idea can be found in a recent book by Christopher Bollas titled<italic>Being a Character: Psychoanalysis and Self-Experience</italic>. Believing that mental health demands a tolerance for a variety of inner states,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>The Concept of Time and the Faculty of Judgment in the Ontogenesis of Historical Consciousness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brumlik</surname>
                           <given-names>Micha</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historical consciousness originally appeared in human beings, from both the phylogenetic and the ontogenetic perspective, as narrative consciousness. Even myths and cosmologies embedded in a cyclical conception of time require narratives, accounts of things, actions, and events connected with adverbial particles such as “before” and “after,” “later” and “earlier,” “in the beginning” and “in the end.”</p>
                     <p>If we are not simply to ascribe the human ability to articulate narrative, and thus express temporal consciousness, to an a priori kind of anthropological constant, we cannot avoid the empirical study of all the cultural connections where particular forms of narrative were invented,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Historical Consciousness:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Progress of Knowledge in a Postprogressive Age</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Seixas</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A common complaint about history education in both North American and European schools is that it consists predominantly of the memorization of factual information. There is thus a huge gap between the practices of school history and the notions of “historical consciousness” that inform this volume. My purpose in this chapter is to articulate a conception of historical consciousness that might be of use in the reform of the practice of history in the schools, in order that pedagogy might serve more purposefully to develop students’ historical consciousness.</p>
                     <p>Such a conception must do two things. First, it must recognize students’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Empirical Psychological Approaches to the Historical Consciousness of Children</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Billmann-Mahecha</surname>
                           <given-names>Elfriede</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hausen</surname>
                           <given-names>Monika</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Today, historical consciousness is frequently taken as a “central category of historical didactics.”¹ There is nevertheless a lack of empirical investigations on how historical consciousness looks in different age groups and regions in concrete terms, and above all, on how it develops.² Current developmental and social psychological research includes the topic of historical consciousness mostly with reference to adults, and not, however, to children. Yet we have a comprehensive store of investigations that deal with basis competencies of historical consciousness, such as investigations on cognitive development in general, on moral development, on the development of the ability to change perspectives,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>The Psychological Study of Historical Consciousness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wineburg</surname>
                           <given-names>Samuel S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>School children the world over spend countless hours every year learning about the past. In Western countries, the block of the school day devoted to this study is referred to as “history,” “social studies,” “civics,” “government,” or a host of other names. Yet, despite this variety in nomenclature, in practically every case, students are taught something about what transpired before their births. Despite variations in context, different national traditions and curriculuar customs, students from Tokyo to New York, Auckland to Berlin, and Tel Aviv to Toronto all learn something about a movement known as the Renaissance, an event known as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Biography—A Dream?</title>
                     <subtitle>Self-Chronicling in the Age of Psychoanalysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boothe</surname>
                           <given-names>Brigitte</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Psychoanalysis lives on stories: symptoms tell a story, Freudian slips in everyday life reveal stories, and jokes maintain a proverbial relationship to the unconscious. Poets’ stories take their charismatic charm, says Freud, from silent liaisons with the most marvelous and most outrageous wish-fulfilling fantasies. Dreams, which are even closer to wish fulfillment according to the theory, present themselves as mystery stories and riddles.</p>
                     <p>Does psychoanalysis then see dreams, jokes, Freudian slips, and symptoms as<italic>messages?</italic>This conclusion may seem unnecessary, because, after all, “story” and “message” are distant relatives. With an emphasis on “distant,” however, the conclusion proves worthy of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Authenticity and Authority:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Understanding the Shoah</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Métraux</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexandre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay arose from reflections on the question of, and then occasional irritation over, the particular language embedded in popular conceptions of the Shoah. We will first delineate the question, and briefly elaborate on it. In subsequent sections, that is, in the exposition of the theme (circumscribed by the posing of the question), various aspects of the Shoah’s representation by authors, and its understanding in turn by listeners and readers, will be considered. As a next step, the narratives of Primo Levi, understood here as exemplary, will allow us to describe different models of reception, and to more easily conceptually</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Albert Speer’s Memories of the Future:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Historical Consciousness of a Leading Figure in the Third Reich</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Welzer</surname>
                           <given-names>Harald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The description of this hasty departure occurs under the entry for July 13, 1959, in Albert Speer’s prison diary in Spandau. The year 1959 was the thirteenth year of Speer’s twenty-year prison sentence—how did he get to Peking during this period? Quite simply, by walking. And not just to Peking, but to Istanbul, to Vladivostok, to Karachi, and to other exotic regions and cities. Of the 31,816 kilometers of his journey round the earth, he had completed exactly 14,260 when he reached Peking. “If someone had told me then,” reflected Speer, “at the beginning of my walk to Heidelberg,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbw85.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
