<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Exodus and Resurrection</book-title>
         <subtitle>The God of Israel in the Theology of Robert W. Jenson</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Nicol</surname>
               <given-names>Andrew W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451497083</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451497083</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506416830</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506416837</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1b3t751"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Exodus and Resurrection establishes the important place God’s identity as the “God of Israel" has in the systematic theology of Robert W. Jenson. The work demonstrates that the identification of the God of Israel as the agent of Jesus’ resurrection functions as a foundational premise in Jenson’s Trinitarian theology. Andrew W. Nicol argues that a central characteristic of Jenson’s work is not merely his recognition that the same God who rescued Israel from Egypt raised Jesus from the dead, or the related yet distinct step of renovating his theology in a nonsupersessionist fashion, but also his attempt to conceive of the full implications for doing so in Christian theology, in the church’s self-understanding, and in the church’s relation to Israel and continuing Judaism. In this, Exodus and Resurrection provides a clear and critically appreciative account of Robert W. Jenson’s work and offers a new vital architectonic map of Jenson’s systematic vision.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The God of Israel in the Theology of Robert Jenson</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Robert Jenson numbers among the world’s most influential living theologians, and his<italic>Systematic Theology</italic>may yet prove to be one of the most learned and stimulating written in English, or any language, in the last fifty years.¹ As Jenson continues to apply his breadth of knowledge to all manner of theological, ecclesial, and cultural concerns, one theme has attracted much of his energy and focus for over a decade. Indeed, the “theology of Israel” that comes to fruition in the<italic>Systematic Theology</italic>displays Jenson’s determination to work through the implications of a “newly demanding” confrontation with the fact of Judaism.²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Jenson’s Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These questions cut to the very heart of Jenson’s theology. In the words of Brevard Childs, “For the Christian church the continuing paradox of its faith lies in its encounter through the Jewish Scriptures with the selfsame divine presence it confesses to have found in the face of Jesus Christ.”³ Insofar as Jenson’s biblical hermeneutic judges the God of Israel to be crucial to the identification of this one God, this identification is simultaneously Trinitarian. Moreover, his influential contribution to the revival of Trinitarian theology is implicitly reliant on a dynamic account of Jesus’ relation to the God of Israel.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>God in Israel’s Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In biblical Israel’s narrative, there is a telling of God’s identity that is not finally reducible to a mere expression of “normal” religion’s apprehension of deity. This chapter further explicates Jenson’s understanding of this “telling,” of Israel’s history, and the manner in which this drama makes and shapes the gospel promise. In addition, while aspects of Jenson’s account of the God of Israel’s intimate dealings with this people are relatively conventional, others have attracted considerable criticism. This extrapolation seeks to draw attention to innovation and locate Jenson’s characteristic moves within the conceptual nexus that integrates his system, highlighting their significance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The God of Israel and Jesus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>God is whoever raised Jesus from the dead, having before raised Israel from Egypt. This trademark sentence of Jenson’s is, as Stanley Hauerwas observes, both “elegantly simple” and “dauntingly deep.”³ At the heart of this dense slogan is the principle that Christian discourse about God intends and is made possible by a specific reality. “God,” as we have seen Jenson argue, is intrinsically specifiable, because God is known by and with a history. The God Jesus addressed as Father and who raised him from the dead was not a previously unknown deity. Rather, as Jenson states, “It is the God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The God of Israel and the Trinity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The one God of Israel who speaks and acts through Word and Spirit is intimately identified by and with Israel’s life. Can Israel’s Scripture accommodate the gospel so that it is seen that this same God, the God of Israel, speaks by Word and Spirit in and through Jesus Christ? The doctrine of the Trinity is the church’s emphatic answer to this question. In contrast to some assumptions, Jenson insists that the church’s Trinitarianism does not in fact depart from Israel’s interpretation of God.² This is to be observed in the shape of the early Christian mission where primal Trinitarianism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The God of Israel, the People of God, and the Eschaton</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter explores the connections between creation and the God of Israel’s consummating and redemptive purposes in the election of a peculiar people. As has been previously argued, Israel knew herself to be contingent, to be a people formed by God’s gracious intention. As a correlate of this understanding, Israel came to apprehend her God as the Creator of all. Reflecting on this “rule of faith” in Israel, Jenson cites 2 Maccabees: “Look at the heavens and the earth … and acknowledge that God made them.”¹ The new thing the New Testament adds, states Jenson, is that creation is for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Identity of the One and Triune God of Israel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As noted in chapter 1, this book is concerned to assess the impact Jenson’s understanding of the God of Israel has on his wider systematic framework, including its effect on the overall coherence of his thought. In so doing, it also seeks to situate his work within the wider dogmatic tradition, insofar as this illuminates and scrutinizes his work and the importance of the abiding significance of God’s identity as the “God of Israel.” We have seen in earlier chapters that Jenson’s explication of the dogmatic centrality of the God of Israel touches on almost all loci of theology proper.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Jenson, the God of Israel, and Non-supersessionist Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book has attempted to highlight the pervasive significance of the God of Israel in Jenson’s theology. In this final chapter, implications for Jenson’s non-supersessionist proposals are explored in light of the foregoing assessment. In particular, Jenson’s logic for the preservation of the church and the synagogue is extrapolated in order to consider further his significant contribution to self-consciously non-supersessionist dogmatic theology. As has been reiterated regularly, a fundamental premise of Jenson’s theology is the conviction that Christians worship the God of Israel, who is identified by and with exodus and resurrection. Of far-reaching import for Jenson’s Trinitarian theology is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sustained engagement with Jenson’s thinking has issued in deep admiration for the integration of his “system” and his astonishing blend of concision and penetration. This book has sought to bring into relief a thread that undulates throughout his system. At times this thread, the God of Israel, is a prominent identification in Jenson’s formulations, and at other times the identification is below the surface. Even so, it is never absent. I have argued that Jenson’s attention to the centrality of God’s identity as the God of Israel permeates his theology, and its profound importance for Christian theology is convincingly developed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t751.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>296</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
