<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Conception, Reception, and the Spirit</book-title>
         <subtitle>Essays in Honour of Andrew T. Lincoln</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McConville</surname>
               <given-names>J. Gordon</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pietersen</surname>
               <given-names>Lloyd K.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175996</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905579</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Wipf and Stock Publishers</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dfnrc1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A number of distinguished biblical scholars and theologians come together in this volume to honour the life and work of Andrew T. Lincoln. The title of this volume reflects Andrew Lincoln’s lifelong interests in Christian origins, the reception of biblical texts in believing and scholarly communities, and the embodiment of the gospel in believing communities made possible by the Spirit. These essays cover exegetical matters, theological interpretation, and theology and embodiment. Several essays engage directly with Lincoln’s monographs, Truth on Trial, and Born of a Virgin?</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="374"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCCONVILLE</surname>
                           <given-names>J. GORDON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PIETERSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>LLOYD K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are delighted to present this<italic>Festschrift</italic>in honor of our esteemed friend and colleague, Professor Andrew T. Lincoln, on the occasion of his retirement. The title of this volume reflects andrew’s lifelong interests in Christian origins, the reception of biblical texts in believing and scholarly communities, and the embodiment of the gospel in believing communities made possible by the Spirit. Furthermore, his commitment to careful exegesis of biblical texts, combined with a sensitivity to theological interpretation of those texts and a passionate desire to see such theological interpretation worked out in the life and practice of believing communities, result</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Figures in Isaiah 7:14</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCCONVILLE</surname>
                           <given-names>J. G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Matthew 1:23 we read: “Behold, a virgin shall conceive and bear a son, and his name shall be called immanuel” (RSV), in a formula that is immediately recognizable as a central element in Christian liturgy and theology about Jesus Christ. There are curiosities about the passage, not only in its announcement of a virgin birth, but also in the fact that the child that is born is called not immanuel, but Jesus, a first indication (in our present enquiry) that texts do not necessarily say exactly what they mean. This oblique connection between text and meaning is evident in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Rival Group Identities in the Matthean Gospel:</title>
                     <subtitle>Evidence from Matthew 1–2 and 23</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ESLER</surname>
                           <given-names>PHILIP F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout his career andrew Lincoln, happily now my colleague in the University of Gloucestershire and predecessor in the named chair i hold, has undertaken the most perceptive and detailed interpretation of a wide range of new testament texts, especially on John, ephesians, and hebrews. he has also written important thematic studies of pauline eschatology and theology and the virgin birth of Jesus. it is, accordingly, a great privilege to be able to contribute this essay on Matthew to his<italic>Festschrift</italic>, which, in its focus on the Matthean infancy narrative, connects with a passage on which he has written at length</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Let John be John (2)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DUNN</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES D. G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Andrew is by no means a stranger to John’s Gospel, as his great commentary thereon certainly confirms.¹ So</p>
                     <p>I offer in congratulation this reflection on its distinctive christology, drawn principally from my current work on the subject.² For it is undoubtedly John’s christology which constitutes his greatest contribution to the development of Christian theology. But our over-familiarity with it has probably diminished our perception of the radical transmutation that John in fact makes in his portrayal of Christ.</p>
                     <p>it is the prologue to the Gospel (John 1:1–18) that immediately grabs the reader’s (or, originally, listener’s) attention. The claim that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Worlds of Judgment:</title>
                     <subtitle>John 9</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JERVIS</surname>
                           <given-names>L. ANN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Fourth Gospel’s cosmic lawsuit motif has been brilliantly elucidated by andrew Lincoln.¹ in<italic>Truth on Trial</italic>Lincoln clarifies how the narrator of the Gospel of John presents the long-standing battle between light and darkness coming to a head in God’s lawsuit with God’s world.² in this lawsuit, Jesus is the witness and the judge, and those who believe the truth of Jesus’ witness and judgment are liberated from darkness and death into light and life.</p>
                     <p>Lincoln rightly articulates the Fourth Gospel’s conviction that the “lawsuit is not primarily about judging humans for their deeds and punishing them for not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Another Look at “Lifting Up” in the Gospel of John</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILLIAMS</surname>
                           <given-names>CATRIN H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the distinctive ways in which John’s Gospel communicates Jesus’ identity as God’s heavenly revealer on earth is by attributing to him a profoundly enigmatic mode of speech. Figurative vocabulary and riddles feature prominently in the discourses of this “stranger from heaven,” not least in the cluster of declarations whose verbal building blocks consist of words to which more than one level of meaning can be ascribed (e.g., John 3:3–4; 4:10–11). among the most well known, and baffling, of these Johannine cases of<italic>double entendre</italic>is the use of the verb ὑψόω to describe Jesus—in his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>John, Jesus, and “The Ruler of This World”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Demonic Politics in the Fourth Gospel?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One might think that of all the new testament books the least likely to be caught up in debates about anti-imperial politics would be the Gospel of John. The old nineteenth-century prejudices about John linger on. John is a “spiritual” gospel, a “theological” gospel, not like the rough-and-tumble Synoptics, still less like that argumentative fellow paul. John is about the incarnation of the Word, the love of God in sending the Son, and the glory revealed on the cross. at the heart of John we find the Farewell discourses, seen by many as the deepest and richest focus and source</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Land, Idolatry, and Justice in Romans</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KEESMAAT</surname>
                           <given-names>SYLVIA C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a world where the destruction of land and water is the single most threatening issue for human life, it is astounding that biblical scholars still fail to grapple with the depth of biblical concern—including that of paul—with the destruction of arable land and flowing water. By focusing the discussion on such global issues as the melting of the polar ice caps, the warming of the atmosphere, and rising sea levels (which were, of course, not even remotely in the imagination of the biblical writers), it becomes easy to sidestep the biblical call to repent of our lives</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>A New Translation of Philippians 2:5 and Its Significance for Paul’s Theology and Spirituality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GORMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philippians 2:5 remains an exegetical and translational conundrum, yet it is a<italic>“crux interpretum</italic>.”¹ The bridge between a key exhortation in the letter (Phil 1:27—2:4) and its poetic, theological foundation (Phil 2:6–11), phil 2:5, needs to be interpreted well in order to understand the nature of the connection between exhortation and foundation. Furthermore, since the great significance of phil 2:6–11—in multiple respects is universally acknowledged, we will gain the highest degree of clarity about it only if we properly explicate 2:5.</p>
                     <p>In this essay I make an extended case for an interpretation of 2:5 that I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Wine, Debauchery, and the Spirit (Ephesians 5:18–19)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PIETERSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>LLOYD K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A sumang’s confident assertion echoes andrew Lincoln’s conclusion in his magisterial commentary on ephesians, which remains a significant resource for commentators on this letter more than twenty years after its publication. Lincoln has a particularly fine discussion of the verse under consideration in this chapter, Eph 5:18. There he considers whether the prohibition against drunkenness concerns misconduct in the assembly as in 1 Cor 11 or the influence of pagan mystery cults, especially that of dionysus. he is unconvinced by these proposals and instead argues that drunkenness is a prime characteristic of the darkness mentioned earlier (Eph 5:8) and that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Metaphor of the Face in Paul</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARTON</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To ask after the meaning and significance of the human face is to engage with a subject of complexity and wonder.² For we are considering more than the front of the head and related matters of an anatomical kind. Rather, we are dealing with<italic>the self and the self in relation</italic>, that is, matters of a psychological and socio-cultural kind, and ultimately matters of morality and metaphysics. More than any other part of the body, the face is the place, and facing is the action, where the self receives and expresses its identity,</p>
                     <p>character, and values, especially in<italic>relations of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Born of a Virgin?</title>
                     <subtitle>The Conversation Continues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CATCHPOLE</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Andrew Lincoln’s fine book<italic>Born of a Virgin</italic>? represents not only a much-needed evaluation of the diverse evidence in the Gospels concerning Jesus’ origins but also a piece of scholarship that conveys how finely balanced some of the decisions are that that evidence permits or requires. The sensitive and restrained tone of the whole discussion makes it easy to continue the conversation, and that is what i would like to do.</p>
                     <p>The starting point is that the Gospels provide support for at least two of three different reconstructions of Jesus’ parentage: (A) that he had no human father at all,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Historical Criticism, Theological Interpretation, and the Ends of the Christian Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FOWL</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is an enormous honor for me to be asked to contribute to a<italic>Festschrift</italic>for andrew Lincoln. I had been working on my PhD thesis for a couple of years when andrew Lincoln became my supervisor. i doubt very much that he remembers our first meetings to discuss my work; they are, however, vividly stamped in my memory. andrew’s questions were always clear and non-polemical, but also deeply probing. The more he probed, the more it became clear that my thesis lacked a thesis. it was more like a set of disconnected observations. andrew’s clear-eyed reading of my work</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>What Makes New Testament Theology “Theology”?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORGAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question presupposes what the phrase itself implies: that “New Testament theology” is or should be in some sense “theology.” What that contention might mean depends not only on the contested phrase “New Testament theology,” but, prior to that, on how “theology” itself is understood, whether (to condense the range of non-disparaging dictionary meanings) in the strong sense of articulating and perhaps advocating a religious stance by expressing its belief and practice in a rational way, or in the secondary sense of philosophical, historical, and related scholarship describing and analyzing the commitments of others. Both senses imply an adjective indicating</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Who and What is Theological Interpretation For?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PADDISON</surname>
                           <given-names>ANGUS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years “Theological interpretation” has consolidated itself as a key contributor to the series of conversations that make up contemporary theology.¹ as a movement it has spawned commentary and book series, dedicated journals, countless monographs, and edited volumes. amidst this flurry of activity is the particular contribution made by the edited volume that andrew and i produced whilst we worked together at the University of Gloucestershire,<italic>Christology and Scripture: Interdisciplinary Perspectives</italic>. The volume arose out of an intensive and memorable weekend spent in a diocesan retreat house in the company of systematic theologians, church historians, and biblical scholars. at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>The Use of the Old Testament in the Work and Preaching of F.W. Robertson of Brighton</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROGERSON</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Frederick William Robertson— F.W. Robertson of Brighton—died on 15 august 1853 at the age of thirty-seven. he did not live to witness, or take part in, the controversies that were provoked by the publication of<italic>Essays and Reviews</italic>in 1860 and the first volume of J. W. Colenso’s<italic>The Pentateuch and Joshua</italic>in the following year. Two “broad” churchmen, F.D. Maurice and Charles Kingsley, whose names are often linked with that of Robertson, were distressed by these publications. Kingsley responded by publishing, in 1863, a small volume entitled<italic>The Gospel of the Pentateuch</italic>, in the preface to which he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>ὑπὸ πνεύματος ἁγίου φερόμενοι ἐλάλησαν ἀπὸ θεοῦ ἄνθρωποι:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Inspiration of Holy Scripture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEBSTER</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>236</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Christian theological teaching about the inspiration of the Bible is one element in a comprehensive account of the nature and ends of holy Scripture. A fully articulated theology of Scripture will treat five topics.</p>
                     <p>The first and principal topic, from which all the others derive and by which they are governed, is the place of Holy Scripture in the economy of revelation, reconciliation, and regeneration in which God loves creatures by communicating to them a share in his knowledge in the domain of the church, in order that they may know, love, and serve him above all things and so</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Good Sex, Bad Sex:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections on Sexuality and the Bible</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALEXANDER</surname>
                           <given-names>LOVEDAY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many years ago, in conversation with a German biblical scholar, I happened to mention that andrew Lincoln was one of my colleagues in the department of Biblical Studies in Sheffield. “Ah!” said my interlocutor: “paradise Lincoln!” Andrew’s<italic>Paradise Now and Not Yet</italic>was already making a favorable impression on the exacting world of German<italic>neutes-tamentlicher Wissenschaft</italic>. it is a pleasure to contribute to this collegial appreciation of andrew’s academic achievements, recalling those heady days back in 1986, when we had just joined the Sheffield department (Andrew six months ahead of me), and enjoyed together the excitement of testing out new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Spirituality, Ethics, and Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOLDINGAY</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>274</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Remembering is of key importance to spiritual and ethical life. In a class on old testament ethics, one of my students commented that there did not seem to be much written about the link between ethics and memory. he rightly implied that there surely was a link, not least because both old and new testaments make one. The dearth of books that look directly at the question¹ seems especially odd given the way memory has become a topic of interest in a wide range of disciplines over recent decades.</p>
                     <p>Whereas what set me thinking, then, was the question of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Pacing the Cage:</title>
                     <subtitle>Biblical Resonance and Embodied Testimony</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WALSH</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So begins one of Bruce Cockburn’s finest songs.¹ The artist finds himself struggling to read the signs of the time, squinting to interpret the apocalyptic portent that is before him. For Cockburn, that sunset is an angel weeping. it doesn’t<italic>look like</italic>such an angel, nor does it<italic>remind</italic>the artist of such a thing. no, “sunset is an angel weeping.” of that he is sure. And that this angel is holding a bloody sword is also not in doubt. But what does it mean? and where is that sword pointing? “No matter how I squint I cannot/make out what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrc1.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>330</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
