<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j68m87</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ1794.D795Z8 1998</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Durand, Etienne, 1586-1618</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Technique</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Love poetry, French</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">French poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">17th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Petrarchism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Poetics of Inconstancy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Etienne Durand and the End of Renaissance Verse</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROGERS</surname>
               <given-names>HOYT</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780807892602</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781469641676</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1469641674</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Department of Romance Studies</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>CHAPEL HILL</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1998</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Department of Romance Languages. The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5149/9781469641676_rogers"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The transformation of Late Petrarchism from earlier stages reflects a profound shift in cultural values--a 'crisis of the Renaissance' that generated new perspectives in poetic theory and practice. Broadly, this book identifies a distinctive 'poetics of inconstancy' that came to the fore at the end of the sixteenth century and pervaded the love verse of the age. At the same time, as a study based on the inductive method, the book takes as its point of departure a single poet: Etienne Durand. Because of his frequently anthologized 'Stances a l'Inconstance,' Durand is often singled out as 'the poet of inconstancy.' This study, however, identifies the theme of universal change as a hallmark of Durand's contemporaries as well--a signal of a stylistic revolution that heralded the end of Renaissance verse.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="242"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE POET OF INCONSTANCY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Late Petrarchism differs notably from its earlier stages. Its transformation reflects a profound shift in cultural values – a “crisis of the Renaissance”¹ which opens new perspectives in poetic theory and practice. On a broad level, this book will identify a distinctive “poetics of inconstancy” which comes to the fore at the end of the sixteenth century, and which pervades the love verse of the age. At the same time, as a study based on the inductive method, it will take a single poet as its point of departure: Etienne Durand, whose<italic>Poésies complètes</italic>are now widely available for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter I</label>
                     <title>THE PETRARCHIST TRADITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given its date of publication, the love poem cycle of Durand’s<italic>Méditations</italic>belongs inevitably to the Petrarchist tradition. Beginning with Scève,¹ all French love poets of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries draw heavily on the common fund of themes, images, and vaguely Platonic theories inherited from Italy.² Any global definition of Petrarchism would have to include the style and motifs used by Petrarch himself, the classicism of the Bembists, the freer variations of Tansillo and others, and the imitations of all these Italian sources in other languages – with the latter inspiring further imitations in their turn.³ But since the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter II</label>
                     <title>THE RHETORIC OF REPETITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Petrarchism is not a monolith, but an endless series of refractions. The preceding analyses underline the fact that even within a well-established tradition, “content” is no stable quantity: thematic elements take on different meanings according to the context; more importantly, they vary with the tone. The<italic>agencement</italic>of changing moods depends on the fundamental devices of literary discourse: in the end, the notion of theme resolves itself into a problem of rhetoric. The analogy between tropes and<italic>topoi</italic>is close. Both sets of conventions maintain an essential identity from poem to poem, poet to poet, age to age – despite</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter III</label>
                     <title>THE THEME OF INCONSTANCY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his reminiscences of Durand, Guillaume Colletet already singled out the “Stances à l’Inconstance” as “toutes merveilleuses” (p. XVI); the renewal of interest in Durand in the last forty years was originally sparked by this poem alone. Unfortunately, their enthusiasm for the “Stances” has led some critics to dismiss his other verse from serious consideration. To do so is to misunderstand the “Stances” themselves, which take on their full meaning only in relation to the<italic>Méditations</italic>proper, with their emphasis on constancy. Of these poems Yves Bonnefoy writes in his “Préface” (p. III): “Les<italic>Méditations</italic>, c’est l’envahissement d’une poésie qui</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter IV</label>
                     <title>THE POETICS OF INCONSTANCY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The inconstancy praised by Durand and his contemporaries transcends the bounds of simple infidelity: it represents a universal principle of instability and change. The rising popularity of this<italic>topos</italic>toward the end of the sixteenth century reflects a shift, not only in literary poses, but also in literary practice. If the original tenets of Petrarchism are undermined by a new stance toward the beloved, the poetic technique of Durand and other Petrarchists of his time undergoes a parallel evolution. It is revealed, for example, in the treatment of religious motifs within an amorous context, where they function in an appreciably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE END OF RENAISSANCE VERSE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the love verse of Durand and his contemporaries, a wayward rhetoric reverts to ultimate fidelity, only to rebound toward disjunction once again: and so the somersaults proceed, in a ceaseless chain. No matter how obliquely, the thematic subversions, puncturing devices, and playful inconsistencies of this poetry still portray, on a stylistic plane, the inner conflicts of a Petrarchist psychology. But this “metamimetic”¹ allegiance to the traditional<italic>thématique</italic>is also labile; as I noted in Chapter II, all forms of literary repetition circle toward, and<italic>away from</italic>, a central identity. Late Petrarchism differs from its previous stages: in its final</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SELECT BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469641676_rogers.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
