<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Transdisciplinarity</book-title>
         <subtitle>reCreating Integrated Knowledge</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SOMERVILLE</surname>
               <given-names>MARGARET A</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RAPPORT</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID J</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>09</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2002</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773525450</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773586215</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Oxford; UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>EOLSS Publishers Co. Ltd</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zw15"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Transdisciplinarity provides an essential context for understanding some of the most important, complex, and difficult issues we face, whether in environmental protection, maintaining our health care systems, drafting new laws, formulating public policy, accommodating religious and cultural pluralism, or dealing humanely and respectfully with an ageing population.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors and Biographical Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Somerville</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret A</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>David J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Voices of Royaumont</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Klein</surname>
                           <given-names>Julie Thompson</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A stay at Royaumont Abbey, as the original inhabitants intended, is good for the mind and soul. Acquired by King Louis IX in 1228 from nuns of the Saint-Martin-de-Boran priory, the Royaumont estate became the site of a new abbey for the Cistercian order of monks. Subsequently occupied by nuns of the Holy Family of Bordeaux, Royaumont would also become the residence of a wealthy businessman, a hospital for wounded soldiers in World War I, and eventually an international cultural center. The travelers who journeyed in May 1998 to this meeting place of artists and intellectuals were, like Roderick Macdonald’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Doing Transdisciplinarity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McMichael</surname>
                           <given-names>Anthony J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can we (as the Americans might say) “walk the walk” of transdisciplinarity? For most of us, the idea of transcending the conventional boundaries of disciplinary fiefdoms, of exploring bigger ideas, is inherently intriguing and attractive. Nevertheless, most researchers and social analysts also know that there are formidable structures, traditions, and mental roadblocks that limit and compartmentalize our intellectual lives. The attainment of successful transdisciplinary thought and action is demanding.</p>
                     <p>There are no manuals or guidebooks on the practice of transdisciplinarity. Indeed, the manifest elasticity of the term “transdisciplinarity” precludes a “how-to” analysis. In the present volume, many examples of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preamble</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Somerville</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret A</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>David J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to fully appreciate the contributions that make up this section, it is useful to understand their origin. Prior to the conference, we asked each participant to provide us with a text structured in the following manner:</p>
                     <p>(i) A short statement on<italic>your view of transdisciplinarity</italic>(1000–1500 words). We want to leave open what might be included in this text, allowing maximum room for a wide range of perceptions, but issues such as the definition of transdisciplinarity; the need for transdisciplinarity; its history; and the future evolution of the concept, could be addressed.</p>
                     <p>(ii) A short statement (800</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Perspectives from Knowledge Theorists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McDonell</surname>
                           <given-names>Gavan J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How could we put in a few words this reflection on integration to which we have been asked to contribute, a reflection conducted in a monument of the once-integrated tradition of the West? Could we say, perhaps, that we pursue the hope that we can facilitate communication and understanding among the many disciplines (their number growing as we speak) which today form the universe of the sciences and the technologies, especially those related to policy? This relevance to policy is the strand of the theme I will pursue, marking out some difference, at least in emphasis, from others are more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Perspectives from Legal Theorists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                           <given-names>Roderick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most of us are familiar with the story of the tower of Babel. On its traditional reading it teaches that the multiplicity of human languages is a sign of our fall from grace. If we had not been punished by God, scattered across the face of the earth, and confounded by a multiplicity of languages, we could have built to the Heavens. Nothing would have been impossible for us.</p>
                     <p>Numerous lessons may be derived from Babel, and not all of them are lessons of language. But if we turn first to language, the more general lessons are more easily learned.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Perspectives from Social Scientists and Humanists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Krimsky</surname>
                           <given-names>Sheldon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first thing that comes to mind when I hear the term “transdisciplinarity” is problem-centered investigations in contrast to “discipline-centered investigations.” Disciplines provide methods of investigation and therotical frameworks that inform the methods of inquiry. The questions asked are based on what has been accomplished in the past. Natural science is largely incremental. We build on prior work. The lattice of concepts and theories is self-reinforcing. It is only during periods of major paradigm shifts or scientific revolutions when one experiences the collapse of the entire structure. That may mean the theory has been replaced, but it doesn’t necessarily implied</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Perspectives from Natural and Environmental Scientists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>David J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>EO Wilson, in his provocative essay “Back From Chaos” (<italic>Atlantic Monthly,</italic>March 1998) argues for a fundamental unity that underlies all forms of knowledge. Wilson prophesies that the understanding of this fundamental unity is the key that may lead humankind away from the brink of self-destruction, not only of ourselves but of the myriad life forms with which we share our celestial home. His thesis is that ongoing fragmentations of knowledge are not reflections of the real world but “artifacts of scholarship.”</p>
                     <p>I would argue (and no doubt Wilson would agree) that dominant tendency to fragment knowledge by compartmentalizing it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Perspectives from Physicians and Medical Scientists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Benatar</surname>
                           <given-names>Solomon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I understand the concept of transdisciplinarity as an integrated approach to complex problems using the methodology and insights from a range of disciplines with differing perspectives on the problem under consideration. Clearly, the term needs to be distinguished from what is meant by multi- and interdisciplinarity, but these three terms can be seen as a continuum, with transdisciplinarity as the most evolved version of an interaction that transcends individual disciplines.</p>
                     <p>Within science, major advances have been made through inter- and transdisciplinary activities. The example of the progress made within the American Unity of Science movement that emerged after World War</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Perspectives from Public Health Scientists</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Last</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>defines transdisciplinarity as “pertaining to more than one discipline or branch of learning” and “the ultimate degree of coordination in the education/innovation system.” My perception of transdisciplinary is of collaboration and coalition-building among two or more people or groups from different disciplines for a specific purpose; with the aim of advancing knowledge and understanding on a broad front of scholarly activitity; or to solve a particular or general problem that is pertinent to the human situation. A good example is the explosive growth of computer-based technologies and communication systems in the past ten to twenty years.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preamble</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Somerville</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret A</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>David J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The colloquium program was planned with aim of moving through a structured exploration of the theory and practice of transdisciplinarity with the objective of the further development of both of these aspects of the concept. Prior to the colloquium, we summarized our primary goal as being to advance the development of integrative methodologies that could be used to produce integrated knowledge, whether at the theoretical or practical level.</p>
                     <p>There were four plenary sessions on the first day of the colloquium and concurrent workshops on each of these plenary topics on the second day. These sessions and workshops were structured around</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Exploring Transdisciplinarity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Klein</surname>
                           <given-names>Julie Thompson</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                           <given-names>Roderick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the crucial activities in any transdisciplinary endeavor is the process of clarifying assumptions, recognizing commonalities and differences, and formulating a working agreement in order to achieve a particular goal. Our assigned goal was to generate a definition of transdisciplinarity. The working group divided its time into three phases: initial exploratory discussion, a more focused effort to create a single definition, and preparation of an oral report to the colloquium.</p>
                     <p>The meaning of transdisciplinarity varies, because definers being different experiences and values to bear on the task of definition. From the outset, participants agreed that a viable definition should</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Practicing Transdisciplinarity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Rapporteur:</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Benatar</surname>
                           <given-names>Solomon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In making this presentation, I have drawn on the written submissions of John Last, Robert McMurtry, David Rapport, Margaret Somerville, and Solomon Benatar. I shall discuss successes and failures both in medical education and in medical practice. There have been several examples of success in the application of transdisciplinarity in medical education, and some of these are becoming impressive. First, I should like to address these successes in relation to three fields.</p>
                     <p>The rebirth, growth, and evolution of bioethics over the past thirty-five years is a success story in transdisciplinarity. The creation of a multidisciplinary forum in the medical context</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Looking to the Future</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sage</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are many illustrations of how disciplinary fragmentation has generally resulted in bodies of knowledge that are unable to resolve a number of contemporary problems that are of large scale and large scope. As a result of this fragmentation, the “spheres” of knowledge of the typical disciplines show virtually no overlap, as represented in Figure 1. A number of problem-solvers attempt to resolve this dilemma. Generally, this is accomplished by looking for more fundamental contexts for research into, and associated practices for, problem-solving. Two potential solutions emerge. One is associated with knowledge integration such that the formerly separated disciplines are,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Somerville</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret A</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rapport</surname>
                           <given-names>David J</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>256</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We leave this text, in a metaphysical sense, in mid-sentence. But this is appropriate. It will be for many others to write the next paragraphs, chapters, and books in the evolution of transdisciplinarity. Transdisciplinarity is a dynamic process, not a static event, and it is one which will continue to need increasingly deep, broad, and diverse contributions. Transdisciplinarity is an idea whose time has come and one whose time will remain.</p>
                     <p>As we hope can be seen from the diverse perspectives that we have sought to integrate between these covers, there is a range of adjectives that can describe transdisciplinarity.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributing Author Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw15.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
