<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn31ts</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Media and Identity in Africa</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Njogu</surname>
               <given-names>Kimani</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Middleton</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>09</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748635221</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748635214</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>International African Institute</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1r2b0x"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book brings together discussions on the uses and problems of the media - both traditional and modern - in Africa, mostly Eastern Africa, in the current construction of national, class, gender, and individual identities in subject to new economic and political pressures and influences as part of the world-wide process of globalization.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PROLOGUE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Njogu</surname>
                           <given-names>Kimani</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Middleton</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>This brief Prologue is to introduce a collection of papers given at a seminar held in Nairobi, Kenya, from 3 to 7 August 2004, on the topic ‘Media and the Construction of Identity in Africa’. A wide view of the seminar is given by its Chairman, Professor Valentin Y. Mudimbe, in his Epilogue at the end of the book. Here we attempt to summarize some of the arguments put forward by the participants at the seminar itself and later put into writing by them (all have been slightly edited for presentation in book format).</p>
                     <p>The seminar was the most recent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>ORALITY, THE MEDIA AND NEW POPULAR CULTURES IN AFRICA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barber</surname>
                           <given-names>Karin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Print and electronic media have had profound transformative effects in African culture. Nor is this a recent result of late twentieth-century global flows. For more than 100 years, virtually all new popular cultural forms in Africa have been shaped by techniques and conceptions drawn from the media; while older oral genres have been subtly but definitively recast as they have been drawn into new performance spaces on the airwaves or in print. Most of what is now regarded as ‘popular’ – as distinct from ‘traditional’ – in African culture (see Barber 1987, 1997) was forged in colonial and postcolonial contexts deeply entwined</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>THE MEDIA IN SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT IN CONTEMPORARY AFRICA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zeleza</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul Tiyambe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>If communication is the lifeblood of human interaction, the media constitute the veins through which it flows. The media have a multiplicity of forms, functions, and impacts. They exist in oral, literary and visual forms; they are transmitted through print, audiovisual, and digital technologies; and they play communicative, creative, and representational roles. As a whole, or in specific artifacts and genres, the media have varied social, economic and political effects that can promote democracy, development, nation building and inclusion as much as they can sustain authoritarianism, exploitation, conflict and exclusion. Media infrastructures, practices and policies are embedded in the prevailing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>LANGUAGE AND THE MEDIA IN AFRICA:</title>
                     <subtitle>BETWEEN THE OLD EMPIRE AND THE NEW</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mazrui</surname>
                           <given-names>Alamin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Peter Mwaura, former director of the School of Journalism of the University of Nairobi, has argued that ‘if the communication media [in Africa] are to be part of our culture as indeed all effective and meaningful communication should be – then they must use the local language[s] of our culture’ (1980: 27). Mwaura’s reasoning derives from the idea that:</p>
                     <p>Language influences the way in which we perceive reality, evaluate it and conduct ourselves with respect to it. Speakers of different languages and cultures see the universe differently, evaluate it differently, and behave towards its reality differently. Language controls thought and action</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>REFLECTIONS ON THE MEDIA IN AFRICA:</title>
                     <subtitle>STRANGERS IN A MIRROR?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nassanga</surname>
                           <given-names>Goretti Linda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>As a result of advances in information and communication technology (ICT), the world has shrunk to a global village, where we can learn about events happening anywhere in the world as they take place, or soon after, largely courtesy of the mass media. However, although we have all become citizens of the global village, we are not equal partners. There are disparities in access to information and communication channels, as well as disparities in the levels at which individuals may participate in, and benefit from, the production of information.</p>
                     <p>In a typical African village, people were expected to know one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>AFRICA’S MEDIA:</title>
                     <subtitle>DEMOCRACY AND BELONGING</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nyamnjoh</surname>
                           <given-names>Francis B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In popular as well as academic circles, there are varying degrees of certainty about the extent to which media influence Africans. Contrary to the popular understanding of the media as magic multipliers capable of stimulating or dulling the senses of those who receive them, media effects are neither direct, simple nor immediate. The audience, by extension, is neither altogether passive nor helpless, since members of the same demographic often get different messages from the same source. In other words, what people make of particular media contents depends, inter alia, on where their vested interests lie, interests which are not fixed.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>REPRESENTATION OF AFRICA IN THE WESTERN MEDIA:</title>
                     <subtitle>CHALLENGES AND OPPORTUNITIES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wa’Njogu</surname>
                           <given-names>John Kiarie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Most Westerners have never visited and may never visit Africa, yet they hold an image of Africa in their minds (Hawk 1992). Their knowledge of Africa is formed from sources like school textbooks, the news media, church mission reports and the entertainment industry, all produced by fellow Westerners. These images provide the context for Westerners’ interpretation of media coverage of Africa.</p>
                     <p>A common theme running through the Western understanding of Africa is the metaphor of the ‘dark continent’, an illusion not only to the skin colour of its inhabitants, but also to their perceived ignorance (Hawk 1992). Another is that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>MEDIA CONSUMERISM AND CULTURAL TRANSFORMATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aseka</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric Masinde</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The so-called information and knowledge age has been characterized by the dominance of two related movements, which serve the age-old human preoccupation with capitalist accumulation. These movements are economic globalization and the revolution in information and communications technologies (ICT). These are movements that may be seen as the engines of the contemporary global economy. They drive the new information world order, in which most of the continent of Africa is not faring too well. The expansion of globalization and ICT is itself largely driven by the logic of the market (Etta and Parvyn-Wamahiu 2003).</p>
                     <p>This has given rise to a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>AFRICAN INTELLECTUALS IN A HOSTILE MEDIA ENVIRONMENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Munene</surname>
                           <given-names>Macharia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The African intellectual faces a hostile media environment because the media are largely foreign owned or dependent on foreign sources and programming. The symbiotic relationship between foreign-based media ownership and local media providers is one in which the local elites are the agents of the foreign elites. The foreign elites decide what everyone else is to think and, using their local agents, force it on the Africans. Olatunde A. Oladimeji of Nigeria has argued that Africa has been the target of a new kind of ‘war without missiles’, in which the African elites are the ‘victims of the war on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>PUBLISHING IN AFRICA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kimani</surname>
                           <given-names>Cecilia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Many people believe that the surest path to success in the largely capitalistic world economy is through information. Information is the most valuable resource – it is the common denominator for managing other resources. The notion that material poverty is directly related to lack of access to information is gaining credibility, especially in the so-called Third World countries. Africa, perceived as the epitome of human desperation according to some retrogressive minds in the West, is generally depicted as riddled with poverty, illiteracy, poor governance, disease and superstitions. Information about the continent is routinely misrepresented, often deliberately doctored by agents of hate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>PENTECOSTALISM AND THE MODERN AUDIOVISUAL MEDIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Birgit</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In recent years, Pentecostal charismatic churches (PCCs) have gained increasing popularity throughout Africa (Corten and Marshall-Fratani 2001; Gifford 1998; Meyer 2004a). Situated in a genealogy of Christianity in Africa, these churches espouse significant continuities with mission churches, African Independent Churches and even the African religious traditions which they despise as being the realm of the ‘powers of darkness’.¹</p>
                     <p>Nonetheless, a contrast exists between the familiar image of the African Zionist, Nazarite, or Aladura prophet dressed in a white gown, carrying a cross, and praying for the afflicted in the bush, on the one hand, and, on the other, the exuberant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>REKINDLING EFFICACY:</title>
                     <subtitle>STORYTELLING FOR HEALTH</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Njogu</surname>
                           <given-names>Kimani</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Orality has been an important method for self-understanding, creating relationships, and establishing an equilibrium between body, soul and the environment. Through oral narratives, communities have been able to pass on values, attitudes, knowledge and modes of practice to generations. Because ‘story telling occupies a natural role in many African cultures’ (Pillay 2003: 109), it has the potential of functioning as a key strategy for the promotion of health and well-being. In many cases, therapeutic stories are transmitted through the mass media to be consumed by individuals in their homes or by groups in schools, orphanages, prisons, dispensaries, market places, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>THE MEDIA IN EDUCATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ngome</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The role of media in supporting and promoting education has been acknowledged globally and attracts a lot of documentation. The World Conference on Education for All (EFA), held in Jomtien, Thailand, in 1990 recognized this role and underscored the need for nations to involve the media in delivering and advocating for education. The World Forum on EFA held in Dakar, Senegal, in 2000 reaffirmed this position and reiterated the need for involving the media in education campaigns. These two world conferences, it is now acknowledged, gave birth to an expanded vision of education. No longer do we look at education</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>HORN OF AFRICA AND KENYA DIASPORA WEBSITES AS ALTERNATIVE MEDIA SOURCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Biersteker</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Internet websites of Horn of Africa and Kenyan diaspora groups (broadly defined to include exile, transnational, emigrant, expatriate and refugee communities) provide alternative media sources to Kenya and Horn of Africa based media as well as to the media of the United States and Europe. These alternatives affect the internet, print and broadcast media, news and opinion media, and arts and entertainment media. The alternatives presented by these websites address specific diasporic and exile communities, transnational diasporic communities, and African and global audiences. They include what is excluded by other media sources and demonstrate creative use of technology, they challenge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>POPULAR DANCE MUSIC AND THE MEDIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Collins</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The record business in Ghana (and indeed West Africa) began in the mid-1920s, when the British Zonophone/HMV company first issued recordings of West African popular music and local ‘spirituals’; and particularly after 1928, when the United Africa Company (UAC) became their distributor. In 1930 the Zonophone/HMV company sold 181,484 shellac 78-rpm records, and between 1930 and 1933 this company and the German Odeon company (working out of Lagos, Nigeria) sold 800,000 records in West Africa. This was possible because lucrative cash crops (like cocoa and oil palm) enabled many Ghanaian and Nigerians, even farmers, to buy wind-up gramophones and enjoy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>MEDIA PARENTING AND THE CONSTRUCTION OF MEDIA IDENTITIES IN NORTHERN NIGERIAN MUSLIM HAUSA VIDEO FILMS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Adamu</surname>
                           <given-names>Abdalla Uba</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In analyzing Muslim Hausa film viewing habits and the apparent preference for Hindi cinema, Brian Larkin (1997a) has coined the term ‘parallel modernities’ to refer to the coexistence in space and time of multiple economic, religious and cultural flows that are often subsumed within the term ‘modernity’. He builds upon the concept of ‘alternative modernities’, introduced by Arjun Appadurai (1991). As he further argues:</p>
                     <p>This formulation resonates with the term ‘alternative modernities’ . . . but with a key difference. Appadurai links the emergence of alternative modernities with the increased deterritorialisation of the globe and the movement of people, capital</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>‘TO MAKE STRANGE THINGS POSSIBLE’:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE PHOTOMONTAGES OF THE BAKOR PHOTO STUDIO IN LAMU, KENYA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Behrend</surname>
                           <given-names>Heike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The Bakor Studio in Lamu, situated on one of the main streets of the Old Town, was established in the 1960s. The founder, Mr Omar Said Bakor, born in 1932, was a self-made man and brilliant <italic>bricoleur</italic>, who never went to school. His family originated in Yemen. Before opening the studio, he worked for ten years as a street photographer. He experimented with various techniques of montage ‘to make strange things possible and for fun’, as one of his sons, Mr Najid Omar Said Bakor, explained to me in 1996. His father also recorded the history of Lamu in photographs</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>MUSICAL IMAGES AND IMAGINATIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>TANZANIAN MUSIC VIDEOS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Askew</surname>
                           <given-names>Kelly M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In Tanzania, multiple musical and cultural trajectories creatively coexist in music videos to form this decade-old popular art form. Music videos, also called ‘music television’, typically have been analyzed from the perspective of the visual, by people largely coming from cinema studies, with little attention to the music that gives rise to them, the cultures that inform them, or the histories that make them meaningful. Moreover, they equate music television with American and European rock music videos, because these are what the genre came to be defined by when it emerged in the West. The literature is thus badly in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>POLITICAL RIDICULE:</title>
                     <subtitle>MEDIATIZED NOTIONS OF ‘TRANSPARENT CONCEALMENT’</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mwaura</surname>
                           <given-names>Bantu</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In a website with the title ‘art matters’ (<uri xlink:href="www.artmatters.info" xlink:type="simple">www.artmatters.info</uri>), Ogova Ondego publishes articles on arts and culture in Kenya. In one article, he reviews one of Wahome Mutahi’s plays, summarizing Wahome’s theatre as ‘bar trivia and tribal drama’.</p>
                     <p>In the last couple of years before he passed on, Wahome Mutahi was acclaimed for his Gikuyu political plays, which he co-wrote, produced and performed widely across Kenya. However, Wahome was better recognized as a newspaper humour columnist. Indeed, Wahome Mutahi was synonymous with the ever-popular <italic>Whispers</italic> column that he penned every Sunday for more than two decades. The column was social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>NAMES, CLOTH AND IDENTITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>A CASE FROM WEST AFRICA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gilbert</surname>
                           <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the Akwapim kingdom of southeastern Ghana,¹ clothing is used as a form of communication to make statements about personhood and status; to conceal or reveal identity; to express desires and impulses. It may do so directly or indirectly, conventionally or rebelliously. Clothing is owned, bestowed and gives identity. The clothed body expresses the person of the wearer and society’s image of that person. As a result, clothing absorbs the particular times in which it has been worn² and becomes like a relic of these past events.</p>
                     <p>In Akwapim certain kinds of cloth worn by both men and women in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>MUSEUMS IN AFRICA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wandibba</surname>
                           <given-names>Simiyu</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The word ‘museum’ is derived from the Greek word <italic>mouseion</italic>. In ancient Greece, the <italic>mouseion</italic> was the temple of the muses, the goddesses of the arts and sciences, upon whom writers called for inspiration before beginning to work. Thus, as originally conceived, the <italic>mouseion</italic> implied an environment suited to creative inspiration. By about 300 BC, this word was used to designate a library and research area in Alexandria, Egypt. In other words, the earliest known museum in the modern sense of the term was actually built in Africa.</p>
                     <p>Modern museums also have their roots in the private collections amassed during</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>LITERARY PRIZES, BOOK PRIZES AND AFRICAN WRITING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bgoya</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Literary prizes and book prizes do not feature greatly in discussions about writing and publishing, perhaps because there are so few of them in Africa. When they do, the discussion tends to centre on the questions of who funds the few existing prizes, how the winners are selected, how the prizes are administered, and whether or not the administrators of the prizes are located within or outside of Africa.</p>
                     <p>There is a difference between a literary prize and a book prize. The former, as the name implies, is about works of literature – novels, short stories, poetry, drama, children’s literature. On</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>INNOVATING ‘ALTERNATIVE’ IDENTITIES:</title>
                     <subtitle>NAIROBI<italic>MATATU</italic>CULTURE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mungai</surname>
                           <given-names>Mbugua wa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>This is an anecdote from my street notebook, circa 2000, when I was doing doctoral dissertation research:</p>
                     <p>I am standing right inside the Old Nation roundabout, looking up along Tom Mboya Street. All round me there is a bustle of activity, as passengers dash from the roundabout into the circuit road . . . in the process, eliciting a stream of choice epithets and gestures from <italic>matatu</italic> driver crews. ‘How utterly disorderly these <italic>matatu</italic> can be. No wonder they sport such fearsome names like Notorious and Nasty Boys!’ exclaims a neatly dressed man standing next to me. Above the din</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>BRINGING CHANGE THROUGH LAUGHTER:</title>
                     <subtitle>CARTOONING IN KENYA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gathara</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wanjau</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary Kabura</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Popular culture can both entertain and contribute to social change. Cartoons and comics constitute a pop-cultural tool of visual communication that is gaining in popularity and use. The modern daily newspaper strip and political cartoon participates in what is, in fact, an ancient art form and mode of expression.</p>
                     <p>Cartoon images are generally impressionistic and economical, communicating through the visual invocation of experience shared by both the creator and the intended audience. The visual presentation constitutes a kind of shorthand, allowing the cartoonist to alternately raise questions, make statements, appeal and persuade. When done by an artist with strong social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>DEMONIC TRADITION:</title>
                     <subtitle>REPRESENTATIONS OF OATHING IN NEWSPAPER COVERAGE OF THE 1997 CRISIS IN COASTAL KENYA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ciekawy</surname>
                           <given-names>Diane M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>During the last four months of 1997, the Coast Province of Kenya was under a state of national emergency. Collective and individual acts of violence occurred in both urban and rural areas, some of which were perpetrated by members of a loosely organized movement that did not have a consistent name or set of objectives. Throughout the following year, the investigations of the Kenya Human Rights Commission (KHRC) and the Judicial Commission of Inquiry led by Justus Akiwumi² convincingly showed that most of the initial collective acts of violence were planned and executed with the assistance of people loyal to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE:</title>
                     <subtitle>IN THE NAME OF SIMILITUDE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mudimbe</surname>
                           <given-names>V. Y.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>‘I lie, I speak’, such is the beginning of ‘La pensée du dehors’, by Michel Foucault, published in a 1966 issue of <italic>Critique</italic>. To apprehend the singularity of contemporary fiction, and to think of this fiction in its own right, instead of claiming to relate it to an absolute truth, the French philosopher invokes the old argument of Epimenides about a liar. Charles Manson, in interviews conducted by Neul Emmons and transcribed in <italic>Manson in His Own Words</italic> (1988), said: ‘The more I speak, the more I lie; the less I speak, the less I lie.’ Manson’s rapport with Epimenides’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r2b0x.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
