<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Between Vision and Obedience - Rethinking Theological Epistemology</book-title>
         <subtitle>Theological Reflections on Rationality and Agency with Special Reference to Paul Ricoeur and G.W.F. Hegel</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ille</surname>
               <given-names>George</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174265</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902189</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>George Ille</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf5zz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The present study seeks to respond theologically to current discussions about ideas of self from the perspective of God’s action in and towards the world. Its aim is to trace a view of rationality that follows the drama of God’s engagement with the world, thus involving dying and resurrection, ascesis and abundance, suffering witness and Eucharistic communion. Since, as Calvin notes, knowledge of God and knowledge of self are intimately bound together, this exercise of discerning the shape of a theological rationality in the present arena of competing promises of meaning and truth is carried out on two levels: the theological and the anthropological.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="306"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The discussions about subject and validation in our late modernity tend to oscillate between the “weak” self of post-modernity (“empty” or “rhetorical”) and neo-Cartesian versions trying, as they do, to recover a discredited foundation. Correspondingly, the solutions advanced range from calls for a new Enlightenment (in the face of the resurgence of myth and the irrational), to attempts to “re-enchant the world” (in the face of the growing threat of an impersonal instrumental Reason).</p>
                     <p>The present study seeks to respond theologically to such a situation from the perspective of God’s action in and towards the world. Its aim is to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The work of Paul Ricoeur has inspired an impressive amount of literature. The formidable breadth of his philosophical compass, including as it does, fields as diverse as literary criticism and analytic philosophy, psychoanalysis and biblical interpretation, not only recapitulates the battles and aspirations of his own generation, but witnesses to the living tension between reflection and action, past and present, academic vogues and enduring truths. In a century of turmoil, marked by alternations of unprecedented bursts of hope for a reconciled humanity and unfathomable sources</p>
                     <p>of disquiet, Ricoeur’s writings display a specific alertness. Because the “world lieth in evil,” responsible</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Search for Foundation:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Reflexive Philosophy to Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a beginning philosopher, Ricoeur found himself at the juncture of three major philosophical orientations: the French reflexive philosophy, the philosophy of existence of Gabriel Marcel and Karl Jaspers, and Husserl’s descriptive phenomenology.¹ French reflexive philosophy appears in Ricoeur’s own description as a way of thinking which can be traced back to the Cartesian<italic>cogito</italic>, through Kant and the French post-Kantianism, having Jean Nabert as its most prominent figure.² If preoccupation with epistemological issues, translated in the predominance of matters of justification and certitude, has been the overriding concern of such a line of thought, what Ricoeur retains from reflexive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Ontological Horizon:</title>
                     <subtitle>Preface to a Transcendental Poetics?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his “Intellectual Autobiography,” with a visible uneasiness, Ricoeur attempts to explain the absence of the promised “Poetics of the Will” from his anthropological project. He goes on to say, however, that</p>
                     <p>I would not . . . say that nothing was accomplished of what I then termed a poetics.<italic>The Symbolism of Evil, The Rule of Metaphor</italic>,<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>do aspire in several ways to the title of poetics, less in the sense of a meditation on primordial creation than in that of an investigation of the multiple modalities of what I will later call an ordered creation,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Hermeneutics, Creation, and the “Re-enchantment” of the World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does Ricoeur’s proposal enable us to experience the world as “Creation”? Can we, following the indication of his thought, not only “think” the truth but know it? With these questions we have reached a turning point. Our investigation so far, while mainly “descriptive,” has already raised a number of theological questions in an effort to ground theologically our experience of the world in general, Ricoeur’s philosophical undertaking in particular. Since, in the Apostle Paul’s words, it is indeed in God that “we live, and move, and have our being” (Acts 17:28), no serious concern for experience and meaning can genuinely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So typically romantic were those verses that few could have guessed that Hegel would be able to turn this hopeless feeling of the “poverty of words” into the bliss of Absolute knowledge. Indeed, Hegel’s philosophy appears to be no less than an initiatory ascent, confident that it can break the silence, and make us hear the Truth again, or perhaps even more, stare it in the face and dwell in its presence. We were left, at the end of the previous section with a rather nostalgic subject. A subject in desperate need for Revelation, “ready to receive it with joy”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Hegel the Philosopher of Revelation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this chapter is to set Hegel in context. I shall formally adopt a historical-systematic approach without delving too deeply into the details of Hegel’s conceptual intricacies. Nonetheless, some general clarifications will be attempted about both content and method, the nature of the subject matter, and the nature of the approach itself. By looking at the kind of claims Hegel makes within both the overall perspective of his philosophy and the general intellectual climate of his day, a particular interpretative position will come to view, pleading for the centrality of the theological framework of interpretation, if a holistic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Unfolding of God’s Story:</title>
                     <subtitle>Revelation, History, and Rationality in Hegel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was Gadamer who suggested that Hegel may become more important for hermeneutics than Schleiermacher.¹ This may come as a surprise for those who know Hegel as the author of the absolute system, the “conceptual” Hegel, the philosopher who thought he could think God’s thoughts “before the creation of nature and of finite mind.”² As it is well known, immediately after his death, Hegel’s disciples divided among themselves, and the division has continued ever since, as nobody has succeeded in showing convincingly how Hegel’s system works in actual fact.</p>
                     <p>One of the ironies of Hegelian criticism is perhaps this unanticipated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Trinitarian Description between Metaphysics and Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For since, in the wisdom of God, the world did not know god through wisdom, it pleased God through the folly of what we preach to save those who believe. For Jews demand signs and Greeks seek wisdom, but we preach Christ crucified, a stumbling block to Jews and folly to Gentiles, but to those who are called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God and the wisdom of God. For the foolishness of God is wiser than men, and the weakness of God is stronger than men.</p>
                     <p>Our time may not be propitious for reopening epistemological discussions,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Epiphanies of Presence:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the “Return to the World”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theological discourse, whether implicitly or explicitly, is in search of some kind of justification. It was because of its contamination by various intellectual heresies, old and new, that often this justificatory practice rather than letting the discourse flow beyond itself, tended to lead it into the fortress of a regulatory concept, practice or institution or a contingent or illusory foundation. But as history so often witnesses, it is precisely when discourse guards itself most securely that it must face the most formidable objection because it loses its ecstatic character, ceasing thus to reflect the overriding feature of its source.</p>
                     <p>How</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Conclusions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Towards a Theological Epistemology Informed by a Trinitarian View of Agency</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen in the course of our argument that by following the adventures of the modern subject, within the framework created by a mere dispute between the “inside” and the “outside” one cannot adequately speak of the emergence of Truth. That is why neither the expressivist, “constructive” self nor its “receptive” counterpart configured by the “outside” is ultimately able to convey the full dimension of this emergence. I have suggested here that a theological reply to this epistemological decision must question the more general framework of its theological assumptions. My proposal has gradually emerged as a response to what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf5zz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
