<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8c5d</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Mutual Cultivation of Self and Things</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Contemporary Chinese Philosophy of the Meaning of Being</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Guorong</surname>
               <given-names>Yang</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moeller</surname>
               <given-names>Hans-Georg</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Meyers</surname>
               <given-names>Chad Austin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253021076</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253021199</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253021197</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1b7x4qv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Yang Guorong is one of the most prominent Chinese philosophers working today and is best known for using the full range of Chinese philosophical resources in connection with the thought of Kant, Hegel, Marx, and Heidegger. In The Mutual Cultivation of Self and Things, Yang grapples with the philosophical problem of how the complexly interwoven nature of things and being relates to human nature, values, affairs, and facts, and ultimately creates a world of meaning. Yang outlines how humans might live more fully integrated lives on philosophical, religious, cultural, aesthetic, and material planes. This first English translation introduces current, influential work from China to readers worldwide.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="326"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                     <subtitle>Contexts and Concepts: Yang Guorong’s Concrete Metaphysics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOELLER</surname>
                           <given-names>HANS-GEORG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Yang Guorong is one of the most creative and prominent Chinese philosophers of our time. He is a truly “Chinese” philosopher not because of his citizenship, ethnicity, or workplace, but because of the nature of his work. Yang makes ample use of the complete range of sources provided by the Chinese philosophical tradition, including all its periods and all its schools (in addition to his reliance on the Western philosophical canon). Thus to call him, for example, a “Confucian” would not do justice to the breadth of his approach. More important, however, Yang is also truly a “philosopher,” because he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That which human being faces is neither an already-completed world nor primordial beings in-themselves.¹ From human being’s perspective, the world is incomplete by nature and in appearance. By “the world” we mean actual beings relative to the being of humans. Beings in-themselves are indeed really there, but they might not be actual for human beings. To be actual, beings must become objects of human being’s cognition and practice, and consequently, present actual meaning to human being. In this sense, actuality is characterized by becoming. The transformation of beings in-themselves into actuality is thus a historical interaction. In ancient Chinese, this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Meaning in the Context of Accomplishing Oneself and Accomplishing Things</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things is a concrete historical process of knowing the world and knowing oneself and reforming the world and refining oneself, which simultaneously generates meaning and produces a world of meaning. The world in-itself cannot pose for itself the question of meaning, which is to say that there is no way to dissociate meaning from one’s own being. Humans question the meaning of the world and the meaning of their own being; therefore, the genesis of meaning owes its origin to the “being” of humans. As the introduction to this book has already demonstrated, from the perspective</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Human Capacities and a World of Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Directed at the genesis of a world of meaning, accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things unfolds throughout the whole process of one’s being. But as the basic way in which human being exists, how is this process possible? The question “How is it possible?” primarily concerns grounds and conditions. Here, the capacities of human being intrinsically condition the genesis of a world of meaning as the internal conditions of accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things. Similar to “wisdom,” the phrase “human capacities” has its everyday connotations, but as a concept, it has philosophical meaning as well. In everyday terms, just as being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Systems of Norms and the Genesis of Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The historical process of accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things, as we have seen, is internally conditioned by human capacities, but many forms of normative systems condition it as well. On the one hand, accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things concretely unfolds as a process of knowing and practicing, which involves different senses of normativity. On the other hand, the knowledge and wisdom formed through this process further constrain knowing and practicing by means of externalizing, transforming into universal systems of norms. Directed at knowing the world and the self and changing both the self and the world, norms not only involve</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Meaning in the World of Spirit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Conditioned by the interrelation of human capacities with systems of norms, accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things constitutes human being’s basic way of being and mode of being. In the historical unfolding of accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things, the presentation of things and the directionality of intentions reciprocally interact; the world enters the realm of ideas through this interaction and henceforth becomes being with meaning. As noted earlier, the problem of meaning does not occur to the world in-itself; rather, the source of meaning lies in the historical process of one coming to know the world and oneself while transforming both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Meaning and Reality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the process of accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things, meaning is not only presented at the level of ideas in the act of cognizing and evaluating; when grounded in practical activity, meaning is also externalized as the world of actual beings or the real world. As the externalization or actualization of meaning, this domain of being, which is generated through the process of knowing and practicing could also be seen as the actual or external formation of a world of meaning, whose actual content is the Nature for-humans or things-for-us as social reality or the living world.</p>
                     <p>A world of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Meaning and the Individual</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Grounded in the historical process of accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things, a world of meaning may take shape into different forms. Whether it is exhibited internally in the form of ideas or unfolds externally into humanized reality, a world of meaning is always inseparable from the being of humans. Now, when considering the relation between the being of humans and a world of meaning, the individual or the person is an important aspect that cannot be ignored, because a world of meaning is first opened up and presented to the concrete individual or person. At a much broader level, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Accomplishing Oneself and Accomplishing Things:</title>
                     <subtitle>Value in a World of Meaning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Free individuality, human capacities, and inner state of mind most directly involve the personal space of the self but also in a broader sense the distinction and interaction between the individual domain and the public sphere. As interrelated aspects of the social world, the individual domain and its connection to the public sphere also sets the concrete background for the historical process of accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things. As the actual mode of being, accomplishing oneself and accomplishing things is never separable from diverse social resources, and the acquisition, possession, and distribution of resources involves the issue of social justice.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b7x4qv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
