<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125wf1</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">chro17958</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HX806 .P64 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Utopias</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political science</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Political Uses of Utopia</book-title>
         <subtitle>New Marxist, Anarchist, and Radical Democratic Perspectives</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CHROSTOWSKA</surname>
               <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>INGRAM</surname>
               <given-names>JAMES D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780231179584</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231544313</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231544316</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/chro17958"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Utopia has long been banished from political theory, framed as an impossible-and possibly dangerous-political ideal, a flawed social blueprint, or a thought experiment without any practical import. Even the "realistic utopias" of liberal theory strike many as wishful thinking. Can politics think utopia otherwise? Can utopian thinking contribute to the renewal of politics?In<italic>Political Uses of Utopia</italic>, an international cast of leading and emerging theorists agree that the uses of utopia for politics are multiple and nuanced and lie somewhere between-or, better yet, beyond-the mainstream caution against it and the conviction that another, better world ought to be possible. Representing a range of perspectives on the grand tradition of Western utopianism, which extends back half a millennium and perhaps as far as Plato, these essays are united in their interest in the relevance of utopianism to specific historical and contemporary political contexts. Featuring contributions from Miguel Abensour, Étienne Balibar, Raymond Geuss, and Jacques Rancière, among others,<italic>Political Uses of Utopia</italic>reopens the question of whether and how utopianism can inform political thinking and action today.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Utopia and Politics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>INGRAM</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Utopia, we might think, is nothing if not political. Its best-known examples, from Plato via More, Campanella, and Bacon to Owen, Morris, and Bellamy, present cities, the political form of life par excellence, organized to remedy the defects their authors perceived in their own. To this extent they offer up political solutions to political problems. At the same time, however, utopias are forever being criticized for seeking to escape or eliminate politics, and not without reason. For if utopias present solutions to political problems, by building the common good into the design of the worlds they depict, they do away</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE HISTORY OF UTOPIA AND THE DESTINY OF ITS CRITIQUE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ABENSOUR</surname>
                           <given-names>MIGUEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This text, written in late 1971 and early 1972, is only the first part of a larger whole. Its ambition is to propose another model of interpretation than that of the classical problematic, or that of Marx and Engels’s critical operation with respect to utopias, which appears as a double salvage by transplant: rescuing the utopian orientation toward the future, and rescuing the inclination toward alterity. Marx’s theory is not the place utopian energy comes to die in order to make way for science; it is where socialist-communist utopia grows and is transformed into critical communism. Marx is not the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>IS THE CLASSIC CONCEPT OF UTOPIA READY FOR THE FUTURE?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SAAGE</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anyone discussing utopia today has to know that there is no consensus on how the concept should be understood. This dilemma can be seen exemplarily in the social sciences, where it is above all the intentional, totalitarian, and classical concept that has become canonical.</p>
                     <p>The origins of the intentional conception go back to Gustav Landauer. In his study<italic>Revolution</italic>from 1907, Landauer interprets utopia as a decisive explosive charge of the revolutionary upheavals in Europe that have happened since the sixteenth century.¹ He seeks to isolate its mechanism in the fact that social development always swings between two “states of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>UTOPIA AND NATURAL ILLUSIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BUEY</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCISCO FERNÁNDEZ</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first edition of Thomas More’s great work appeared in London in 1516 under the title<italic>De optimo republicae statu deque nova insula Utopia</italic>[<italic>Nusquam</italic>], in Latin, based on an inaccurate text. It was also almost simultaneously published as<italic>Libellus vere aureus, nec minus salutaris quam festivus de optimo reipublicae statu deque nova Insula Utopia</italic>(Lovaina, T. Martens, 1516), then as<italic>De optimo republicae statu deque nova Insula Utopia</italic>(Basilea, J. Froben, 1518, new edition revised by Erasmus). It was translated into Italian in 1548, French in 1550, English in 1551, Low German in 1562, and Spanish in 1637 with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>MARX AND UTOPIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FISCHBACH</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before any discussion of the relation between utopia and Marxism, it is necessary to consider Marx’s own relation to utopia. Let us start by recalling that the philosophical, notably Hegelian, tradition inherited by Marx is very hostile to utopianism. Marx knew by heart the preface to the<italic>Elements of the Philosophy of Right</italic>, in which Hegel virulently opposed those who, in matters of political philosophy, build castles in the air, which is to say, think or imagine the political and social world as it should be, and thus dispense with knowing it as it is.¹ Marx had incontestably inherited this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>GENERAL WISH OR GENERAL WILL?</title>
                     <subtitle>Political Possibility and Collective Capacity from Rousseau Through Marx</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HALLWARD</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In well-run oligarchic societies, the best and simplest way to dismiss egalitarian challenges has long been to deride them as impracticable or “utopian”—and I use the word “utopian” here in the most banal sense, to mean an abstract notion or project that might be viable only in another place or time, or if undertaken by actors unlike ourselves.¹ A society without exploitation, hierarchy, or discrimination might be all very well in theory, but appropriately maintained ideological reflexes ensure that everyone knows that such fancies are not feasible in practice, here and now. Egalitarian ideals seem too demanding for selfish</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>AFTER UTOPIA, IMAGINATION?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BALIBAR</surname>
                           <given-names>ÉTIENNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It seems to me that the main problem facing us at the turn of the century consists of taking leave of utopia while setting free the powers of the imagination. This thesis is not original, I freely admit, but it could be that it would allow us to get beyond the sterile oppositions between an ethics of conviction and an ethics, or politics, of responsibility. My reason for this will be developed on three, tightly connected registers. First of all, utopia—be it individualist or collectivist—traps us and the imagination within the alternative of realism and unreality, whereas realism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>A STRANGE FATE FOR POLITICS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jameson’s Dialectic of Utopian Thought</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRANT</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Must utopia remain utopian, or can it be achieved without at the same time announcing its own end? This question helps to orient an examination of Fredric Jameson’s engagement with utopia and the critical insights about society that come with it. In early work such as “Reification and Utopia in Mass Culture” (1979), Jameson articulates how cultural artifacts contain twin utopian and ideological components, with the latter never managing to preclude the former. In more recent work such as “The Politics of Utopia” (2004), Jameson claims that utopian thinking flourishes when we find politics has been suspended. This raises a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>THE REALITY OF UTOPIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RIOT-SARCEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHÈLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Uopia unsettles. Even in the writing of history one has tried to sort out impossible reforms from signs of progress, the illuminism of the former from the realism of the latter. As Miguel Abensour underlines concerning the Marxist critique of utopias, “the critique of utopia is situated at the culmination of a real theoretical revolution—the production of a theory of history,”¹ and, whatever the political options or ideological choices of historians, this critique strongly marked the schools of historiography. Utopia in the doctrinal sense is itself a partial criticism of society, incomplete and, by the same token, unable to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>NEGATIVITY AND UTOPIA IN THE GLOBAL JUSTICE MOVEMENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LÖWY</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The global justice movement is without a doubt the most important phenomenon of antisystemic resistance of the beginning of the twenty-first century. This vast, nebulous “movement of movements,” which has taken visible form since the regional or world social forums and the great protest demonstrations—against the WTO, the G8, or the imperial war in Iraq—does not correspond to the usual forms of social or political action. A large decentralized network, it is multiple, diverse, and heterogeneous, joining trade unions and peasant movements, NGOs and indigenous organizations, women’s movements, as well as ecological associations, intellectuals, and young activists. Far</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>UTOPIANISM AND PREFIGURATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KINNA</surname>
                           <given-names>RUTH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For anarchists, utopias are about action. As Uri Gordon argues, utopias are “umbilically connected to the idea of social revolution.”¹ The kind of action utopia describes is a matter of debate. This essay examines how utopian thinking shapes anarchist thought and highlights some recent shift s in the political uses of utopia. Utopianism is not treated as an abstract concept or method, or as a literary genre or place—because that is not how anarchists have understood the idea. Utopia, Gordon notes, “has always meant something more than a hypothetical exercise in designing a perfect society.” As a revolutionary idea,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>THE SENSES AND USES OF UTOPIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RANCIÈRE</surname>
                           <given-names>JACQUES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I will present here a few very general hypotheses concerning a simple question, the simplest that could be asked about utopia: that of its prefix. I will leave to one side the question of whether this<italic>u</italic>-comes from<italic>ou- or eu-</italic>, whether the word “utopia” originally meant the<italic>nonplace</italic>or the<italic>good place</italic>. If the former interpretation is already established, it is because the<italic>good place</italic>was not thought except as a<italic>nonplace</italic>. The problem crystallizes around the sense of a negation. How can we interpret its virtue? What is the topos denied or displaced by u-topia?</p>
                     <p>There are two</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>REALISM, WISHFUL THINKING, UTOPIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GEUSS</surname>
                           <given-names>RAYMOND</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The short monograph<italic>Philosophy and Real Politics</italic>represents my attempt to give a sketchy answer to the question of how a political philosophy that can be taken seriously might look today.¹ As an explicitly programmatic work, the book certainly does not claim to contain a complete political philosophy, if completeness would even be a meaningful demand in this domain. Rather, it includes only a few positive and a few negative pointers: positive pointers as to where one could possibly continue the investigation, and negative pointers concerning approaches and modes of inquiry that have proven to be not especially promising, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>DESIRE AND SHIPWRECK:</title>
                     <subtitle>Powers of the Vis Utopica</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TASSIN</surname>
                           <given-names>ÉTIENNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The world has long dreamed of possessing something of which it has only to be conscious in order to possess it in reality,” writes Marx in a letter to Ruge from September 1843.¹ For the dream to become reality, it is sufficient that, here and now, humanity be aware of its ancient desire in order to give it existence, to actualize and see the birth of a new society.”</p>
                     <p>In this letter to Ruge, Marx opposes this becoming-aware to the utopian projects of Étienne Cabet.² There is no need for a Voyage to Icaria to create from scratch, in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>UTOPIA, ALIBI</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CHROSTOWSKA</surname>
                           <given-names>S. D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our problematic in this volume on the “uses of utopia for politics” brings together what commonly comes in separate packages. To be sure, mainstream readings of modern Western political history support the attribution of a utopian dimension to left–radical politics, and, conversely, of radical, if covert, political motives to utopia. The historic conflation of utopianism and political radicalism does not, however, explain the internal crisis of the Left any more than it explains today’s generalized political apathy. Neither does it absolve this apathy’s dispirited sufferers of their tendency to equate legitimate politics with a crude, calculating realism, one that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">chro17958.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
