<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">E98.R3P493 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indian mythology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">North America</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians of North America</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ghosts</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">North America</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ghosts in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Phantom Past, Indigenous Presence</book-title>
         <subtitle>Native Ghosts in North American Culture and History</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited &amp; with an introduction by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Boyd</surname>
               <given-names>Colleen E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Thrush</surname>
               <given-names>Coll</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803211377</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803236189</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803236182</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska Paperback</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LINCOLN; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1df4h07"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The imagined ghosts of Native Americans have been an important element of colonial fantasy in North America ever since European settlements were established in the seventeenth century. Native burial grounds and Native ghosts have long played a role in both regional and local folklore and in the national literature of the United States and Canada, as settlers struggled to create a new identity for themselves that melded their European heritage with their new, North American frontier surroundings. In this interdisciplinary volume, Colleen E. Boyd and Coll Thrush bring together scholars from a variety of fields to discuss this North American fascination with "the phantom Native American."</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Phantom Past, Indigenous Presence</italic>explores the importance of ancestral spirits and historic places in Indigenous and settler communities as they relate to territory and history-in particular cultural, political, social, historical, and environmental contexts. From examinations of how individuals reacted to historical cases of "hauntings," to how Native phantoms have functioned in the literature of North Americans, to interdisciplinary studies of how such beliefs and narratives allowed European settlers and Indigenous people to make sense of the legacies of colonialism and conquest, these essays show how the past and the present are intertwined through these stories.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="360"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Tables</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bringing Ghosts to Ground</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOYD</surname>
                           <given-names>COLLEEN E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THRUSH</surname>
                           <given-names>COLL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a story that is familiar to most modern North Americans. When unexplained, sinister, or violent things happen in the landscapes and communities we inhabit, one explanation seems to satisfy us more than many others. Whether accounting for the haunted house down the dirt lane, the spectral woods behind the subdivision, or the seemingly cursed stretch of highway up the canyon, one kind of story in particular helps us make sense of these places:<italic>Didn’t you know? It was built on an Indian burial ground</italic>. It is the stuff of countless local legends told around campfires and at teenage</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Sherman Alexie’s Indian Killer as Indigenous Gothic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BURNHAM</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHELLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Sherman Alexie’s controversial 1996 novel<italic>Indian Killer</italic>, a six-year-old boy named Mark Jones, “the first-born son of a white family” (192), is kidnapped from his bedroom by someone identified only as “the killer.” The killer, who possesses a knife inlaid with turquoise stones that has already been used to stab and scalp a white, male victim, leaves after the crime a calling-card of blood-stained white owl feathers. Intent on completing “a powerful ceremony that would change the world” (192), the killer remains not only menacingly anonymous and indecipherable, even to the very conclusion of Alexie’s book, but is described</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Violence on the Home Front in Robinson Jeffers’s “Tamar”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GANO</surname>
                           <given-names>GENEVA M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>World War I was not “the Good War.” Americans in general were reluctant to become involved in what was widely viewed as a “European war” (Wilson’s successful presidential campaign slogan in 1916 was “He kept us out of war”), and the draft did not help foster general enthusiasm for it. Among artists and intellectuals, the war was even less popular. Randolph Bourne, an influential writer and critic associated with the radical little magazine<italic>Seven Arts</italic>, declared that “war is the health of the state,” and Jane Addams, the progressive reformer and peace activist, maintained that war in general is destructive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Hauntings as Histories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Indigenous Ghosts and the Urban Past in Seattle</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THRUSH</surname>
                           <given-names>COLL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Do places have spirits?</p>
                     <p>Another way to frame this question is to ask whether places—physical locations and the multiple human histories embedded in them—have distinct identities and are capable of agency. Can a single place be home to a certain kind of history, persistent and cohesive, even across boundaries of time and cultural regime? Can the nonhuman, in the form of organisms, climate, or other entities, define the shape of a place and even its meaning? Can remnants of past societies—ruins, ecological footprints, artifacts—“speak” in active ways for the histories they represent? And can we include</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Anatomy of a Haunting:</title>
                     <subtitle>Black Hawk’s Body and the Fabric of History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WATERMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ADAM JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In January 1863 the members of the State Historical Society of Iowa inaugurated the publication of their journal<italic>Annals of Iowa</italic>with an article they called “The History of Scott County.” Serialized over three issues, the article established one of the most basic conceits of midwestern history; namely, its ostensible banality. One of the first counties in the State of Iowa, in 1863 Scott County was most notable as the home of the oldest white settler communities in the state. Anglo-Americans had started to settle land in what would become Scott County by the early nineteenth century; their numbers exploded</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Baldoon Mysteries</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PHILIPS</surname>
                           <given-names>LISA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCDOUGALL</surname>
                           <given-names>ALLAN K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shortly after the British–U.S. border dividing the Great Lakes was established by the 1783 Treaty of Paris, the respective governments began treaty processes with the highly respected and powerful First Nations in the Old Northwest, in an attempt to accommodate the needs of the First Nations in anticipation of an influx of settlers to the regions. Prior to that time, contact with the First Nations in the Great Lakes region was extensive, largely through fur-trading operations and Catholic missions. Priests and traders from Lower Canada and Europe had built close relations with the First Nations. Indeed, many of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Haunting Remains:</title>
                     <subtitle>Educating a New American Citizenry at Indian Hill Cemetery</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAVANAGH</surname>
                           <given-names>SARAH SCHNEIDER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the morning of September 30, 1850, a crowd of Middletown, Connecticut, residents, including the mayor, city authorities, several full choirs, and “citizens generally” gathered at a local church and began a march through their small city.¹ The march concluded at the crest of a nearby hill known to the marchers as “Indian Hill.” The name “Indian Hill” was given to the site by local whites because of the hill’s history as a community and government center for the Wangunk, the first people of central Connecticut.² The Wangunk, however, knew the hill by a different name: “Wune Wahjet,” meaning “at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>“We Are Standing in My Ancestor’s Longhouse”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Learning the Language of Spirits and Ghosts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOYD</surname>
                           <given-names>COLLEEN E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One early evening in June, I stood with my husband, John, and one of his maternal uncles, near a small patch of woods on the edges of the Lower Elwha Klallam Reservation. We encountered Uncle while walking after dinner. He was excited to tell us about the little<italic>mowitch</italic>¹ with tiny spikes he had spotted earlier that afternoon at the very spot where we now stood. As we talked, my nose slowly became aware of a foul odor—a smell halfway between rotting fish and feces. The small patch of woods is a few feet from “the end of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Indigenous Hauntings in Settler–Colonial Spaces:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Activism of Indigenous Ancestors in the City of Toronto</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FREEMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>VICTORIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At a multi-faith event in the fall of 2005, a group of Indigenous and non-Indigenous activists reclaimed one of the Toronto Islands as “Spirit Island,” reconsecrating and reactivating the land as a sacred site for healing ceremonies and teachings by elders. During that ceremony, an Indigenous elder from Greenland sang a healing song passed down from his great-great-grandmother. He sang it for the sculptor who hoped to create a healing garden for children on the site, which he envisioned as a medicine wheel of sculptures by Indigenous artists. The sculptor spoke of being raised white and only later in life</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Shape-shifters, Ghosts, and Residual Power:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Examination of Northern Plains Spiritual Beliefs, Location, Objects, and Spiritual Colonialism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LANDRUM</surname>
                           <given-names>CYNTHIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1991, a Hunkpapa Lakota Sioux tribal member, Don Tenoso, was scheduled to provide a routine demonstration of traditional doll-making techniques in the Native American exhibition hall at the National Museum of Natural History of the Smithsonian Institution in Washington dc. At the time, I was a museum technician with the Department of Anthropology and was working in the Natural History building. Since we were about to begin the work of conserving and moving the Plains Indian collection that was in storage, I was curious to see what he had to say about the cultural significance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Ancestors, Ethnohistorical Practice, and the Authentication of Native Place and Past</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRADY</surname>
                           <given-names>C. JILL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the turn of the twenty-first century, scholars produced a series of analyses that addressed the literary works written about Native American ghosts (Brogan 1998, Bergland 2000, Richardson 2003). These critics constructed the analyses by relying primarily upon the Euro-Western philosophical and social theories of Freud and Marx, with scant attention given to the extant ethnohistorical and anthropological analyses that pertain to cross-cultural and multicultural studies. Anthropologists and ethnohistorians have long recognized the significant roles played by ghosts in Native American social organizations and belief systems, though they hesitate to apply analytical theories to those roles. It is my intent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1df4h07.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
