<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN345.2.C75 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnohistory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Methodology</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Critical Junctions</book-title>
         <subtitle>Anthropology and History beyond the Cultural Turn</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kalb</surname>
               <given-names>Don</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tak</surname>
               <given-names>Herman</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782389620</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782389628</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Don Kalb</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Herman Tak</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1btbxqc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The "cultural turn" has been a multifarious and pervasive phenomenon in Western universities and modes of social knowledge since the early 1980s.</p>
         <p>This volume focuses on the conjunction of two disciplines where both the analytic promises as well as the difficulties involved in the meeting of humanist and social science approaches soon became obvious. Anthropologists and historians have come together here in order to recapture, elaborate, and criticize pre-Cultural Turn and non-Cultural Turn modes of analysing structures of experience, feeling, subjectivity and action in human societies and to highlight the still unexploited possibilities developed among others in the work of scholars such as Norbert Elias, Max Gluckman, Eric Wolf, E.P. Thompson and Raymond Williams.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Critical Junctions—Recapturing Anthropology and History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kalb</surname>
                           <given-names>Don</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tak</surname>
                           <given-names>Herman</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This collection of studies and essays seeks to address the pitfalls of, and the alternatives to, what has become known as the “cultural turn” (or the “historic turn”) in the social and human sciences. The cultural turn has been a multifarious and pretty pervasive phenomenon in Western universities and modes of social knowledge since the early 1980s, when, in Bill Sewell’s phrasing, a “kind of academic culture mania has set in” (Sewell 1999: 36). It embraced parts of anthropology, sociology, social theory, gender studies, literary studies, various branches of history, and science studies and laid the philosophical groundwork for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Microhistorical Anthropology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Prospective Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Handelman</surname>
                           <given-names>Don</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relationship between anthropology and history is one of inequality. This is no less so for the relationship between anthropology and microhistory. History, one of the noble disciplines in the “history” of Western thought, has as an emblem the muse, Clio. Anthropology has anyone who at times is everyone, at times someone, so often nameless and unvoiced. In their relationship, anthropology is the junior partner, a Johnny-come-lately to the professional telling of pastness within intellectual worlds whose denizens believe in the existence and importance of the time-depths of history, probably since these also are perceived as the sources of knowledge.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>The Past in the Present:</title>
                     <subtitle>Actualized History in the Social Construction of Reality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Giordano</surname>
                           <given-names>Christian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having been trained as both a sociologist and an anthropologist, I have in my research consistently been oriented toward the present. While carrying out fieldwork projects, however, I have often been confronted by opinions, questions, answers, convictions, reasoning, reflections, and concrete forms of social behavior that cannot be untangled and articulated exclusively in terms of the “here and now.” It would be all too easy to develop a tendency to underestimate the past by viewing it as a dead hand upon the present, rather than an active, operating force. There is, however, more to the presentist orientation in social research</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Figurations in Historical Anthropology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Two Kinds of Structural Narrative about Long-Duration Provenances of the Holocaust</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rebel</surname>
                           <given-names>Hermann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The danger of transforming consequences into their own causes dogs any attempted history, but particularly one whose final objects of interest are as overwhelming as the orgies of murder that took place in East-Central Europe during the 1940s, altogether constituting those experiences and memories of insane horrors that we have come to call the Holocaust.¹ This has become a more acute logical problem as the historical field where we are currently “free” to look for the Holocaust’s provenances has steadily narrowed, even as it appears, however coincidentally, that the very global corporate and financial entities on which we all depend</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Beyond the Limits of the Visible World:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remapping Historical Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carbonella</surname>
                           <given-names>August</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anthropologists, it seems, return anew to the question of scale at least once in every generation. For illustrative purposes this question can be posed in a couple of ways. Should we study communities as isolated microcosms or as small replicas of national or global entities? To what degree, if any, do villagers represent larger class or social formations? These variants of the scale question, while sharply drawn, indicate a lingering tendency among anthropologists to tacitly attribute a remarkable degree of coherence and solidity to communities. Herein lies the problem. The way we pose the question automatically reifies both the locus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>“Bare Legs Like Ice”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Recasting Class for Local/Global Inquiry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kalb</surname>
                           <given-names>Don</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Few serious social researchers would deny the inescapability of pondering the conundrum of class—a conundrum because, while steadily contested, politically compromised, and conceptually inflated, the unsettling suspicion keeps surfacing that class involves inequality, power, culture, exploitation, accumulation, struggle and action, being in history and the making of history, being in place and the making of space, all in the same moment. Class, power, time, and space together form a huge program that has haunted social inquiry since Marx. Disciplined social science, on the other hand, has been a recurrent escape from its embrace, and understandably so, since it is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>Prefiguring NAFTA:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Politics of Land Privatization in Neoliberal Mexico</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Musante</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eric Wolf ’s emphasis on interconnected, global processes in<italic>Europe and the People Without History</italic>(1982) provides a model for bringing the concerns of history, geography, and anthropology together to study the political economy of globalization, both past and present. To his list of “thingified” concepts I would add the local or the<italic>community</italic>which have been, and continue to be, reified within anthropological discourse and practice. The boundaries of the local or the community—however broadly they may be defined or imagined—are often taken as a given, and hence naturalized. This tendency continues even as anthropologists increasingly broaden</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>Historical Anthropology through Local-Level Research</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Silverman</surname>
                           <given-names>Marilyn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gulliver</surname>
                           <given-names>P. H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a common assumption today that two paradigms typify the growing nexus between history and anthropology. One paradigm, which typifies history, is “a movement away from social history … and towards a new cultural history” (Kalb, Marks, and Tak 1996: 7). In its concern with epochs, mentalities, and collective representations, it uses anthropology as a repository of concepts, methods, and empirical data that historians can raid. The other paradigm, which typifies historical anthropology, is the one through which anthropologists operate in order to do history, using a central method of local-level research¹ and exploring issues related to “autonomy, deviance,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>Anthropology and History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Opening Points for a New Synthesis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sider</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>1. The conjunction of history and anthropology (and similarly, the peculiar specialist discipline of “ethnohistory”) remains undeveloped. Much has been written about history and anthropology; indeed, the topic became a fad that is now fortunately coming to an end. Most of the writings on this conjunction have not proved useful analytical bases for understanding or developing strategies against the intensifying expansion of exploitation and domination. Yet the potential of this conjunction may still be significant, but the interweaving of the two disciplines—or better, projects—probably needs to be rebuilt from scratch. And the conjunction, as the title of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbxqc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
