<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN173.K33 1994</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">RHETORIC</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">1500–1800</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">MACHIAVELLI, NICCOLÒ, 1469–1527</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">POLITICAL AND SOCIAL VIEWS</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">MACHIAVELLI, NICCOLÒ, 1469–1527</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">CRITICISM AND INTERPRETATION</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">POLITICS AND LITERATURE</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Machiavellian Rhetoric</book-title>
         <subtitle>From the Counter-Reformation to Milton</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kahn</surname>
               <given-names>Victoria</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>1994</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691034911</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691034915</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400821280</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400821282</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1994</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY PRESS</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c99bcq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Historians of political thought have argued that the real Machiavelli is the republican thinker and theorist of civic virtù.<italic>Machiavellian Rhetoric</italic>argues in contrast that Renaissance readers were right to see Machiavelli as a Machiavel, a figure of force and fraud, rhetorical cunning and deception. Taking the rhetorical Machiavel as a point of departure, Victoria Kahn argues that this figure is not simply the result of a naïve misreading of Machiavelli but is attuned to the rhetorical dimension of his political theory in a way that later thematic readings of Machiavelli are not. Her aim is to provide a revised history of Renaissance Machiavellism, particularly in England: one that sees the Machiavel and the republican as equally valid--and related--readings of Machiavelli's work.</p>
         <p>In this revised history, Machiavelli offers a rhetoric for dealing with the realm of de facto political power, rather than a political theory with a coherent thematic content; and Renaissance Machiavellism includes a variety of rhetorically sophisticated appreciations and appropriations of Machiavelli's own rhetorical approach to politics. Part I offers readings of<italic>The Prince, The Discourses,</italic>and Counter-Reformation responses to Machiavelli. Part II discusses the reception of Machiavelli in sixteenth-and seventeenth-century England. Part III focuses on Milton, especially<italic>Areopagitica, Comus,</italic>and<italic>Paradise Lost.</italic>
         </p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>V. K.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS AND NOTE ON SPELLING AND TRANSLATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AS THE EVENTS of the English civil war were unfolding, the royalist Edward Hyde, Earl of Clarendon, recorded his thoughts in his<italic>History of the Rebellion</italic>.¹ Reflecting on the struggle for power between Cromwell and the Presbyterians in 1647, after the imprisonment of Charles I in Carisbrooke Castle, Clarendon described Cromwell with a characteristic mixture of appreciation and biting irony. In Clarendon’s judgment, Cromwell was a true Machiavellian: a brilliant tactician who was governed by considerations of necessity rather than morality, and who did not hesitate to use force and fraud to serve his purposes. Those who condemn Machiavelli for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART ONE: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE EARLY Italian reception of<italic>The Prince</italic>and the<italic>Discourses</italic>shows that, from the outset, Machiavelli’s readers recognized and responded to his distinctive rhetorical flair. They were shocked (or pretended to be) by his brutal examples of practical politics; they resented his exposure of the inefficacy of the traditional virtues. They saw that the dramatic effect of Machiavelli’s work depended on his subversion of the conventions of humanist treatises on politics.¹ And some, like Guicciardini, recognized that, precisely because of this, Machiavelli was more of a humanist than he would have his reader believe.</p>
                     <p>Writing to Benedetto Varchi in 1549,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>THE PRINCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MACHIAVELLI scandalized his Renaissance reader not because he advised the prince to use force and fraud but because he refused to cloak his advice in the rhetoric of scholastic or Christian humanist idealism. Instead, he insisted that the prince acts in a world in which there are “no prefigured meanings, no implicit teleology,”¹ in which order and legibility are the products of human action rather than the a priori objects of human cognition. To recognize this, he argued, is to acknowledge the truth of power, as opposed to an idealistic notion of truth conceived in terms of representation, as correspondence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>THE DISCOURSES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WHILE<italic>The Prince</italic>illustrates the role of rhetorical politics in principalities, the<italic>Discourses</italic>argues that this rhetorical flexibility is a structural feature of the life of republics and the reason for their superiority to other forms of government:</p>
                     <p>una republica ha maggiore vita ed ha piú lungamente buona fortuna che uno principato, perché la può meglio accomodarsi alla diversità de’ temporali, per la diversità de’ cittadini che sono in quella, che non può uno principe. Perché un uomo che sia consueto a procedere in uno modo, non si muta mai, come è detto; e conviene di necessità che quando e’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>RHETORIC AND REASON OF STATE:</title>
                     <subtitle>BOTERO’S READING OF MACHIAVELLI</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN 1531 and 1532 the<italic>Discourses</italic>and<italic>The Prince</italic>were published by Blado in Rome with the papal imprimatur. By 1559 Machiavelli’s works appeared—along with those of Erasmus, Boccaccio, and Savonarola—on the papal index of prohibited books.¹ The Counter-Reformation was in full force and Machiavelli was censured as an enemy to religion in treatise after treatise in Spain and Italy. In particular, Machiavelli was condemned as the proponent of reason of state—the use of any and all available means, however immoral, to preserve the state and to increase the power of its ruler. For many Counter-Reformation theorists,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART TWO: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DECADES before the condemnation of Machiavellian reason of state in Counter-Reformation treatises of the 1590s and early 1600s, Cardinal Pole provided a quick sketch of the Machiavel in his<italic>Apologia ad Carolum Quintum</italic>(1539). He tells us that Machiavelli’s works “stink of the malice of Satan” (malitiam Satanae redolent) and that<italic>The Prince</italic>was written “by Satan’s hand” (Satanae digito). He also offers a synopsis of Machiavelli’s rhetorical politics, noting that the prince must learn to simulate and dissimulate according to the age-old rhetorical criteria of time, place, and audience. And he condemns Machiavelli’s divorce of ethics from politics and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>READING MACHIAVELLI, 1550–1640</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN THIS chapter I propose a typology of sixteenth-century English interpretations of Machiavelli, ranging from the “domesticated” Machiavelli—the assimilation of his more obviously shocking recommendations to the mainstream of political thought and the appropriation of Machiavellian topics for English political debate—to the “methodical” Machiavelli, whose rhetorical method of arguing by example is seen to be particularly appropriate to the exigencies of political life, to the “dialectical” Machiavelli, who is read both as a Machiavel and as a critic of tyranny. At one end of the temporal spectrum, Stephen Gardiner understands the Machiavellian dimension of arguments for the divine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>MACHIAVELLIAN DEBATES, 1530–1660</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WHEN Andrew Marvell sought to describe Cromwell’s troubling<italic>virtù</italic>in the “Horatian Ode,” he chose a Machiavellian rhetoric of de facto political power, of terrifying natural energy whose capacity to create seemed inextricably linked to its capacity to destroy. He also imitated Machiavelli’s own rhetoric, at once dispassionate and critical, with his description of Cromwell as a man who “Could by industrious Valour climbe / To ruine the great Work of Time.” Marvell’s Machiavellian rhetoric can serve as an emblem of generations of Renaissance Englishmen who identified Machiavelli with political innovation—with ruining and remaking the great Work of Time.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART THREE: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MILTON provides one of the best challenges to the usual histories of Renaissance Machiavellism and one of the best examples of the revised definition of Machiavellism proposed in this book. In the usual account, Milton figures as one of the happy few who read Machiavelli as a theorist of republicanism rather than as the arch-hypocrite, rhetorician, and atheist we know as the paradigmatic Machiavel.¹ Among the texts adduced to support this view are Milton’s commonplace book, which includes numerous references to Machiavelli’s<italic>Art of War</italic>and<italic>Discourses</italic>; the possible allusion to Machiavelli in the sonnet to Vane; the discussions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>A RHETORIC OF INDIFFERENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN THIS chapter, I consider Milton’s intervention in the debate concerning things indifferent in his prose works. As we will see, in enlarging the sphere of things indifferent and giving the individual conscience discretion in such matters, Milton departs from the usual puritan position, according to which “nothing is indifferent.” At the same time, he develops the principle of indifference into a rhetoric, thereby dramatizing his awareness that the sphere of indifference is the sphere of rhetoric, in which persuasion and action may take place. Milton’s Machiavellism in his prose works is both general and specific. In reflecting on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>VIRTUE AND VIRTÙ IN COMUS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>BORROWING from J.G.A. Pocock’s description of Machiavelli’s<italic>The Prince</italic>as “an analytic study of innovation and its consequences” (<italic>MM</italic>, 156), we can describe<italic>Comus</italic>as an analytic study of virtue and its consequences or, to rephrase this in the humanist vocabulary of the time, of virtue and power (<italic>virtus</italic>and<italic>vis</italic>). In<italic>Comus</italic>the problems of agency we observed in<italic>Areopagitica</italic>are signaled in two ways. On the one hand, the conflict between the Lady and Comus can be read as the allegorical opposition of Virtue to Force and Virtuosity, with the result that virtue comes to seem “unexercised and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>MACHIAVELLIAN RHETORIC IN PARADISE LOST</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>BETTER than any other single figure, Satan in<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>exemplifies the intersection of rhetoric, theology, the Machiavel, and the republican that we have been exploring in this book.¹ Perhaps the most famous nondramatic Machiavel of the Renaissance, Satan is a skillful orator and casuist, who uses rhetorical force and fraud to wheedle and coerce his fellow fallen angels. Not surprisingly, the topics of Machiavellism—the relation of<italic>virtù</italic>or virtue to success, means to ends, persuasion to coercion, force to consent—appear regularly in his speeches. What is surprising, or truly diabolical, however, is the way Satan attributes the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CODA:</title>
                     <subtitle>RHETORIC AND THE CRITIQUE OF IDEOLOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THIS BOOK began as a study of the “other” tradition of Renaissance rhetoric—not the tradition of dialogue, debate, and consensus but of conflict, disunion, and dissent. Familiar with the argument that Machiavelli courted and then mocked the assumptions of humanist political discourse, I assumed Machiavelli was disturbing to Renaissance readers in part because of his attack on the humanist rhetoric of consensus. And I assumed that Renaissance readers of Machiavelli would accordingly identify him both with the subversive or critical potential of rhetoric and with political dissent. I was not sure whether I agreed with Pocock that “the truly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX:</title>
                     <subtitle>A BRIEF NOTE ON RHETORIC AND REPUBLICANISM IN THE HISTORIOGRAPHY OF THE ITALIAN RENAISSANCE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bcq.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
