<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">Z39.48-1992</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Divination’s Grasp</book-title>
         <subtitle>African Encounters with the Almost Said</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Werbner</surname>
               <given-names>Richard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253018816</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253018953</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253018951</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Richard Werbner</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt17t7592"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Richard Werbner takes readers on a journey though contemporary charismatic wisdom divination in southern Africa. Beginning with the silent language of the divinatory lots, Werbner deciphers the everyday, metaphorical, and poetic language that is used to reveal their meaning. Through Werbner's skillful interpretations of the language of divination, a picture of Tswapong moral imagination is revealed. Concerns about dignity and personal illumination, witchcraft, pollution, the anger of dead ancestors, as well as the nature of life, truth, cosmic harmony, being, and becoming emerge in this charged African setting.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="356"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Light and Dark, Small and Big, the Archon’s Wisdom and Reflected Dignity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rhino is standing in the sun,” runs the praise poetry in Botswana for the Tswapong divinatory tablets. “His shade is his ears. He flaps over those dwelling beneath.” As with that powerful being the rhino, so too with the ancestors, who provide the canopy. If you dwell in their shade, you are blessed and protected; your “shadowiness” is actually cast by them for you. Abandoning them leaves one bereft of powerful dignity, shunned by the dead and so shunned by the living, diviners argue.</p>
                     <p>In agreement with that, Tswapong insist that “shadowiness” or “shade” is innate. It is a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Deep Dialogue with Evans-Pritchard</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter reconsiders Edward Evans-Pritchard’s<italic>Witchcraft Oracles and Magic among the Azande</italic>(1937) as an open work with a remarkably controversial reception, still problematic, still richly illuminating. In it, Evans-Pritchard deliberately gave no academic citations to display theoretical sources and intellectual origins; he added no footnotes to tell who matters for the arguments. Hence a final interpretation must escape us. Instead, the present analysis, which discloses a deep dialogue, primarily with Malinowski and Lévy-Bruhl, rescues Evans-Pritchard’s textual method, and not merely his praise for observation.</p>
                     <p>Even further, this account recovers Evans-Pritchard’s regard for ethics and personhood, for alterity or otherness</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>In Praise of the Moral Imagination</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The moral imagination encounters a powerful challenge in wisdom divination. It is at once visual, tactile, and verbal—to draw on an oral archive of archaic praise poetry and to make small things—the divinatory lots—speak with much moral significance about elusive and often ill-defined concerns. Many images are brought to bear with the poetry and the lots; the juxtapositions are sometimes paradoxical, not easily fused together. Yet there is a promise of getting wise guidance from an expert—the experienced diviner. What a diviner and his clients seek to grasp escapes ordinary knowledge—it concerns the occult in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Acrobatic Stylistics, Agonistic Vision</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Tswapong wisdom divination, the aesthetically pleasing way from the surface of things, including the divinatory lots, to their inner significance passes through poetry. The genre to which this poetry belongs is rich and widely found across Africa and, very prominently, in southern Africa—the oral poetry of praises,<italic>maboko</italic>, singular,<italic>leboko,</italic>derived from the verb<italic>boka</italic>“honour by giving titles to a person in poems, sing the praises of” (Schapera 1965, 1, citing Brown 1931, 26); and the praise-poet is called<italic>mmoki.</italic>¹ It is eulogy—a poetry that glorifies things, from trees, crops, rivers, hills to many scenic features</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Poetics and Archives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, my approach turns to a more integrated, formal analysis. The need for this move comes from a comparative interest. Across considerable time, distance, and much cultural difference in southern Africa, a remarkable family of resemblances prevails in classic wisdom divination, in its poetry and its imaginative interpretation by diviners. What is very broadly shared is a common framework, similar standards of significance, like stereotypes, archetypes and imagery, roughly the same sociologic of patriarchy and male dominance.</p>
                     <p>To provide a basis for the much needed comparison, this chapter examines more closely and more systematically the verses and interpretations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Family Séances:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rhetoric, Deliberations, and Decisions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter crosses a frontier in divination research by showing the<italic>practice</italic>of wisdom divination through a series of séances. On the basis of my earlier account of Moatlhodi’s archive, I turn to divination as an interpretive process of highly artful deliberation about moral peril. This makes persuasive reasoning and argument the focus, rather than the so-called politics of divination, the mere jockeying of interested parties to get a preferred outcome, for example, a witchcraft accusation (see chapter 1). Such manipulation, now all too familiar in divinatory studies, remains in the background, although still evident.</p>
                     <p>For the sake of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Cosmic and Personal Understandings:</title>
                     <subtitle>Diviners, Headmen, Strangers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Accounts of collaboration between diviners, of how they hear a séance together or cooperate and not merely compete, are rare in our literature. Instead, conventional wisdom reflects the diviners’ awareness of rivalry, heightened by their clients’ own “jockeying” and “shopping” for a self-interested outcome in the “politics of divination.” Clients do go back and forth from one diviner to another, including Christians using the Bible or with inspiration from the Holy Spirit (Werbner 2011a, chapter 5). Clients turn to distant diviners, not merely for a special occasion or a crisis, but sometimes routinely to one local diviner one day, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>A Charismatic Diviner’s Archive:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hooved Divination</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Can anyone fly climbing a tree? You are not a bird, climb where your parents did, by the trunk, it is the order of creation,<italic>tlholego</italic>,” Morebodi told me. Before us was the fall for the Patriarch, Moremogolo, Legwame. Morebodi’s image of the trunk was a reminder of the way to understand things of the taola , the lots’ directives, from the ground up. He extended this understanding directly to the significance of Patriarch for me personally, as if speaking in the Patriarch’s voice to anticipate my old age: “You are my child, you will grow and grow, by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Cross-Over:</title>
                     <subtitle>Originality, Hybridity, Metamorphosis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I explore the second archive, that of hooved divination, in its actual re-creations. First, as a source for one whole poem, this archive appears in the diviner’s presentation of personal significance and his own identity. Second, there is a charismatic crossover, encompassing diverse modes along with classic wisdom divination. In the city, some diviners originally from Moremi village, have very recently combined wisdom divination with exotic forms, including Christian spiritual practices. Young prophets in Gaborone’s Apostolic churches, who reform received Christianity, are also engaging, somewhat uneasily, with legacies from divination, (see Werbner 2008, 2011a, 2011b). But at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Charismatic Séance:</title>
                     <subtitle>Arguments, Intimacy, and Intimations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>254</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines how a charismatic séance by Morebodi worked on several fronts at once: on the practical, material, and physical realities, on the sense of spiritual inspiration, and on the subjective person of each of his clients. In turn, they were oriented, at least in the diviner’s rhetoric, as persons in an ordered cosmos that included invisible beings. Here, my main interest is in the vicissitudes of consultation. My account traces shifts from moment to moment, in an actual and filmed séance and later in post-séance events, some of which reconstitute the meaning of the séance in the eyes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>In Comparison</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My aim in this chapter is comparison across Africa. Primarily, I want to locate Tswapong divination within a spectrum, including modes of divination that I call mimetic at one extreme, and textual at another, as I explain below. Figure C.1 illustrates this specturm with African examples.</p>
                     <p>Turning to Central Africa takes us to mimetic modes. Such modes bring mimesis and miming, together with words and interpretive speech around collections of treasured objects, small things as icons and indexes. At least two things distinguish such collected treasuring of bits across a vast stretch of Central Africa, a region centered on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t7592.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
