<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN671.N5 H69 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Papua New Guinea</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Senses and sensation</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Papua New Guinea</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Body, Human</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Papua New Guinea</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Papua New Guinea</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Sensual Relations</book-title>
         <subtitle>Engaging the Senses in Culture and Social Theory</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HOWES</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472098460</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472026227</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>ANN ARBOR</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2003</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.11852"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>With audacious dexterity, David Howes weaves together topics ranging from love and beauty magic in Papua New Guinea to nasal repression in Freudian psychology and from the erasure and recovery of the senses in contemporary ethnography to the specter of the body in Marx. Through this eclectic and penetrating exploration of the relationship between sensory experience and cultural expression, Sensual Relations contests the conventional exclusion of sensuality from intellectual inquiry and reclaims sensation as a fundamental domain of social theory.David Howes is Professor of Anthropology, Concordia University, Montreal, Quebec.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>IX</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foretaste</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XI</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is about the life of the senses in society, and the challenges posed to both classical and contemporary social and cultural theory by reflecting on the ever-shifting construction of the sensorium in history and across cultures. The title, “Sensual Relations,” indicates that the focus will be on the interplay of the senses rather than on each sense in isolation. Too often studies of the senses will consider each of the five senses in turn, as though sight, hearing, smell, taste, and touch each constituted a completely independent domain of experience, without exploring how the senses interact with each</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XXV</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Taking Leave of Our Senses</title>
                     <subtitle>A Survey of the Senses and Critique of the Textual Revolution in Ethnographic Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anthropology’s engagement with the sensuous has shifted over the last century and a half from a concern with measuring bodies and recording sense data to an interest in sensing patterns, then from sensing patterns to reading texts, and finally from reading texts to writing culture. In the course of the latter shifts, the content of anthropological knowledge has changed from being multisensory and social to being spectacularly stylized and centered on the individual ethnographer. The result is that ethnographic authority now depends more on the “reflexivity” with which one writes than the accuracy with which one “represents” a culture (e.g.,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Coming to Our Senses</title>
                     <subtitle>The Sensual Turn in Anthropological Understanding</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1980s, just as the textual revolution was entering its secondary phase and sweeping the discipline, a few anthropologists began to question the disembodied nature of much of contemporary ethnography and its conceptual reliance on language-based models of analysis. Their work prepared the ground for a sensual turn in anthropological understanding—that is, a move away from linguistic and textual paradigms toward an understanding that treats cultures as ways of sensing the world. This chapter documents this countertradition within the anthropology of the 1980s and 1990s, which culminated in the emergence of the anthropology of the senses.</p>
                     <p>In the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>On the Pleasures of Fasting, Appearing, and Being Heard in the Massim World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Massim region of Papua New Guinea is known for the natural beauty of its volcanic islands, coral reefs, and emerald lagoons. It also has a reputation for being the site of the “Isles of Love”—a reputation based on Bronislaw Malinowski’s depiction of the erotic beliefs and practices of the Trobriand Islanders in<italic>The Sexual Life of Savages</italic>and the reprise of this motif in Paul Theroux’s<italic>The Happy Isles of Oceania.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>Malinowski’s enforced stay in the Trobriands, where he was interned as an enemy alien by the Australians during World War I, started the tradition of anthropological fieldwork.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>On Being in Good Taste</title>
                     <subtitle>Gustatory Cannibalism and Exchange Psychology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Massim way of sensing the world, the sense that is subject to the most restrictions is that of taste. In this chapter, we first examine how the repression (or constant deferral) of gustation is related to the centrality of exchange in Massim society, with the result that foods are classified and valued by reference to their presentability rather than their delectability. It also shows how Massim food preferences are ordered by a principle of likeness to humanity, as in the case of pork, which is reputed to be the next best thing to human flesh—at least in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>The Visible and the Invisible in a Middle Sepik Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Washkuk Hills are situated in the Ambunti District of East Sepik Province. They are inhabited by the Kwoma. John Whiting’s<italic>Becoming a Kwoma</italic>is probably the best known source on this Middle Sepik society. The Kwoma have also been studied by Christian Kaufmann, Margaret Holmes Williamson, and Ross Bowden, whose excellent book<italic>Yena: Art and Ceremony in a Sepik Society</italic>and recent<italic>Dictionary of Kwoma</italic>contain much information of relevance to the present inquiry into the Kwoma sensory order. The following brief ethnographic description is based partly on Bowden’s books and partly on notes I took during the time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Comparison of Massim and Middle Sepik Ways of Sensing the World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this chapter is to present a synthetic account of the ways in which the senses are customarily distinguished, characterized, and articulated to each other in the sensory orders of the Massim and Middle Sepik regions of Papua New Guinea. Comparison of the two sensory orders will in turn bring out how the manner in which the senses are socialized (or “enculturated”) mediates the ways in which society and the cosmos are sensed. In effect, the systematic relationships between sensations within and among different modalities provide the model in terms of which selves are constituted and the relationships</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Oedipus In/Out of the Trobriands</title>
                     <subtitle>A Sensuous Critique of Freudian Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Trobriand Islands are one of the most famous testing grounds of Freudian theory. It was on the basis of data gathered there in the 1910s that Malinowski shook the psychoanalytic establishment by questioning the universality of the Oedipus complex. In the Trobriands, Malinowski (1924) claimed, it is not the case that the male child wishes to kill his father and marry his mother, but rather that he wishes to marry his sister and kill his mother’s brother. Malinowski represented this alternative complex as consistent with the matrilineal social organization of the Trobrianders and suggested that the Oedipus complex proper</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>The Material Body of the Commodity</title>
                     <subtitle>Sensing Marx</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marx</surname>
                           <given-names>Sensing</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The production of guides to reading the work of Karl Marx has become an industry unto itself over the years, with some of the finer titles including<italic>For Marx</italic>(Althusser 1969) and<italic>Reading Marx Writing</italic>(Kempel 1995). This chapter proposes not another reading but a sensing of Marx’s life and works, keyed to the play of the senses in Marx’s writings and personal circumstances. It traces the origin of some of his most critical insights into the life of the senses under capitalism to the works of the materialist philosopher Ludwig Feuerbach and the utopianist Charles Fourier. It then the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.11852.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
