<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7hbg3w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC574.2.F8C47 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Liberalism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectuals</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Political activity</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                     <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
                  </subj-group>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>French Intellectuals Against the Left</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Antitotalitarian Moment of the 1970s</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Christofferson</surname>
               <given-names>Michael Scott</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782389743</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1782389741</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michael Scott Christofferson</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1btbz84"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In the latter half of the 1970s, the French intellectual Left denounced communism, Marxism, and revolutionary politics through a critique of left-wing totalitarianism that paved the way for today's postmodern, liberal, and moderate republican political options. Contrary to the dominant understanding of the critique of totalitarianism as an abrupt rupture induced by Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn's<italic>The Gulag Archipelago</italic>, Christofferson argues that French anti-totalitarianism was the culmination of direct-democratic critiques of communism and revisions of the revolutionary project after 1956. The author's focus on the direct-democratic politics of French intellectuals offers an important alternative to recent histories that seek to explain the course of French intellectual politics by France's apparent lack of a liberal tradition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="306"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>French Antitotalitarianism in Comparative Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the latter half of the 1970s a critique of left-wing totalitarianism took French intellectual life by storm. In books and pamphlets, in the press and on television, antitotalitarian intellectuals loudly and dramatically denounced Marxist and revolutionary politics as fatally affiliated with totalitarianism. Originating within the intellectual Left and facing minimal opposition from it, antitotalitarianism rapidly marginalized Marxist thought and undermined the legitimacy of the French revolutionary tradition, paving the way for the postmodern, liberal, and moderate republican political alternatives of the 1980s and 1990s. Antitotalitarianism also radically altered the political judgments and<italic>engagements</italic>of intellectuals of the noncommunist Left,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>From Fellow-Traveling to Revisionism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fate of the Revolutionary Project, 1944-1974</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The experience of war and occupation profoundly shaped the politics of French intellectuals in the years after the Liberation. The sacrifices and suffering of the war years created a popular “expectation of justice”¹ and a desire for radical social and political change among intellectuals. The wartime division of friend and enemy, resistor and Nazi, between whom no middle ground was possible, brought intellectuals into a Manichean world in which refusal to choose sides became a choice for an intolerable status quo. Political violence and historicist ideas of political justice gained legitimacy following the violence of the Occupation and the vindication</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>The Gulag as a Metaphor:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Politics of Reactions to Solzhenitsyn and The Gulag Archipelago</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to most analyses,<italic>The Gulag Archipelago</italic>was a decisive, revelatory text in the transformation of French intellectual politics in the 1970s.¹ For example, in his synthesis<italic>Political Traditions in Modern France</italic>Sudhir Hazareesingh, a historian of French intellectual politics in the 1970s, writes, “long after the rest of the Western world had seen through the pompous veneer of Soviet-style socialism, French intellectuals remained fascinated by the Leninist experience. Their awakening was brought about by the publication of Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn’s<italic>Gulag Archipelago</italic>in 1974.”² Pierre Grémion, another influential historian of this period, finds that<italic>The Gulag Archipelago</italic>was a revelatory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Intellectuals and the Politics of the Union of the Left:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Birth of Antitotalitarianism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The significance of Solzhenitsyn’s<italic>The Gulag Archipelago</italic>in the emergence of French antitotalitarianism has—as the preceding chapter has argued—been misconstrued.<italic>The Gulag Archipelago</italic>was not a revelatory text; it was the PCF’s attacks on it and its author that gave it a special prominence in French debates. Still,<italic>The Gulag Archipelago</italic>was eventually attributed a decisive influence in the evolution of the politics of the French intellectual Left because doing so allowed French intellectuals to critique the Union of the Left in universal terms, harshly condemn communism, and magnify the threat that communism posed in France by highlighting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Dissidence Celebrated:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intellectuals and Repression in Eastern Europe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By 1977 the shifts in intellectual politics induced by the debate over the Union of the Left and manifested in the emerging critique of totalitarianism became plainly visible to even the most casual of observers. The year 1977 was a year of dissidence in French intellectual politics. At the 21 June reception for Soviet dissidents at the Théâtre Récamier in Paris, and at the Biennale de Venise on East European dissidence of 15 November to 15 December, the leading figures of the noncommunist French intellectual Left visibly and firmly manifested their support for their persecuted confreres beyond the iron curtain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Antitotalitarianism Triumphant:</title>
                     <subtitle>The New Philosophers and Their Interlocutors</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In French intellectual politics 1977 was the year of the “new philosophers,” notably Bernard-Henri Lévy and André Glucksmann, whose books attacking the revolutionary and progressive politics of the Left became runaway bestsellers, selling as many as 80,000 copies each within a year.¹ Omnipresent in the mass media, Glucksmann, Lévy, and their books were at the center of the political debates of French intellectuals in 1977. Their triumph marks the coming of age of French antitotalitarianism.</p>
                     <p>The new philosophers’ critiques of the politics and ideology of the Left were, even in their exaggeration, timely. New philosophy entered the spotlight in French</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Antitotalitarianism Against the Revolutionary Tradition:</title>
                     <subtitle>François Furet’s Revisionist History of the French Revolution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By the end of 1977 antitotalitarianism clearly dominated the politics of the noncommunist intellectual Left. Intellectuals, fearing the worst from the parties of the Left in power, found threats of totalitarianism in all but the most impotent political projects. The political logic of their critique of the PCF and of the Union of the Left favored analyses that were focused on ideology and divorced from the concrete realities of contemporary France or Soviet history. While unconsciously drawing on resources within French republican political culture to combat the supposed totalitarian threat, they asserted that the apparent past blindness of French intellectuals</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue and Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between 1977, the year of the new philosophers, and the Left’s coming to power in 1981 the critique of totalitarianism made further progress in French intellectual life, recasting intellectual politics and the lines of demarcation between the different currents within it. For one, the critique of<italic>tiers-mondisme</italic>, which had emerged in 1976 and 1977, took off in 1978 and 1979. Critiques of revolutionary<italic>tiers-mondisme</italic>, such as Gérard Chaliand’s<italic>Mythes révolutionnaires du tiers monde</italic>(1976) and the<italic>Deuxième retour de Chine</italic>(1977) of Claudie Broyelle, Jacques Broyelle, and Evelyne Tschirhart, were followed by the mea culpas of Jean Lacouture (<italic>Survive le</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography of Secondary Sources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1btbz84.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
