<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The humanities and the Irish university</book-title>
         <subtitle>Anomalies and opportunities</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>O’Sullivan</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781526112071</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1526112078</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michael O’Sullivan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1mf70vj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This is the first book-length study of the humanities and the Irish university. Ireland was a deeply religious country throughout the twentieth century but the colleges of its National University never established a religion or theology department. The official first language of Ireland is Irish but the vast majority of teaching in the arts and humanities is in English. These are two of the anomalies that long constrained humanities education in Ireland. This book charts a history of responses to humanities education in the Irish context. Reading the work of John Henry Newman, Padraig Pearse, Sean O Tuama, Denis Donoghue, Declan Kiberd, Richard Kearney and others, it looks for an Irish humanities ethos. It compares humanities models in the US, France and Asia with those in Ireland in light of work by Immanuel Kant, Pierre Bourdieu and Jacques Derrida. It should appeal to those interested in Irish education and history.The first book-length study of the humanities and the Irish university</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>defining the humanities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The phrase the ‘crisis in the humanities’ has been appearing in American academic circles at the very least since the founding of the Irish state in 1922. In that year, art historian Josef Strzygowski lectured in Boston on ‘The Crisis in the Humanities as Exemplified in the History of Art’, the same year James Joyce published<italic>Ulysses</italic>and changed the literary landscape of the humanities in Ireland forever (Bell, 2010:69). The humanities is, of course, a recognized disciplinary and institutional field in the Irish university system, but the humanities in the Irish context has not received anything like the critical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The humanities in the Irish context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ireland was a deeply religious country throughout the twentieth century,¹ but its National University never established, or provided public support for, a theology or religion department. The of ficial first language of Ireland is Irish but virtually all teaching in the universities is done in English.² These are two of the paradoxes that lay at the heart of the Irish university experience in the humanities in the twentieth century. The debates over the religion and language questions plagued early political efforts to found representative universities in Ireland. When Ireland became independent, the charters binding the constituent colleges of its National</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Newman and the origins of the National University</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John Henry Newman is regarded by many as the most eloquent champion of the liberal education the university must impart. For Newman, ethics and civic virtue are bound up with an education in theology.¹ Newman’s<italic>The Idea of a University</italic>, a series of discourses delivered to mark the inauguration of the Catholic University in Dublin in 1852, is widely regarded as the most influential work ever to have been written on university education. In his celebrated introduction to the Oxford edition, I. T. Ker writes: ‘if it can be said without gross exaggeration that “modern thinking on university education is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The emergence of an Irish humanities ethos</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because the language question was such an important issue for education policy especially in the early years of the State, it is important to look at the work of some of the educationalists and university academics who worked extensively on Irish language literature. One of the first professors of English at University College Cork (UCC), Daniel Corkery, who later spent a great deal of time working on Irish literature, writes in<italic>The Hidden Ireland</italic>that the ‘soul of a people is most intimately revealed, perhaps, in their literature’ (1984: 7). The next sections will therefore examine perspectives on a humanities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>International comparisons</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The work of leading French academics such as Pierre Bourdieu and Jacques Derrida on education points to key differences in emphasis in the Irish and French university systems. However, the French university system did share, only much earlier, many of the key changes that have come to Irish universities since the 1980s. It experienced a surge in university numbers slightly earlier than its Irish counterpart. Alain Bienayme notes that the French experienced its ‘unprecedented growth in its student population’ (1984: 152) in the 1960s. In 1963, 5% of the French eighteen-to twenty-six-year-old age group was in university. This had risen</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The transformation of the humanities in Ireland</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Implicit in what humanities learning represents is a willingness to overcome disparate national interests so as to embody a civic, ethical and cultural ethos that can speak across boundaries and uncover a common regard for enquiry. It speaks for a common good, or<italic>sensus communis</italic>, which, as Hans-Georg Gadamer explains, ‘founds community’ and gives the ‘human will its direction’ not through the ‘abstract universality of reason’ but through the ‘concrete universality represented by the community of a group, a people, a nation, or the whole human race’ (1995: 21). However, because a respect for difference is also implicit in what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1mf70vj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
