<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Radical Theology</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Essay on Faith and Theology in the Twenty-First Century</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dalferth</surname>
               <given-names>Ingolf U.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451488814</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451488815</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506416847</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506416845</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1b3t6tc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Ingolf U. Dalferth develops a “radical theology" that unfolds the orienting strength of faith for human life from the event of God’s presence to every present. In a concise and clear manner, Dalferth outlines the theological and philosophical approaches to hermeneutics in the modern era, in order to promote a convincing and defensible theology for the twenty-first century, critically carrying on Martin Heidegger and Rudolf Bultmann, without forgetting Karl Barth. The result of his reconstruction is a “radical theology" that neither glorifies premodern theology in an antimodern attitude nor seeks a mystical deepening of the secular, but argues for a radical change in theological perspective of the possible. In doing so, theology unfolds “limit concepts" that restrict the claims of science and philosophy critically, and develops “ideas of orientation" that illumine the ways in which human life is understood and lived in radically new ways in faith. From here, Dalferth unfolds the reality of revelation and the Christian sense of an unconditional hope that fundamentally transcends all beliefs based on mundane realities and orients the world on something beyond its own temporal horizon—its loving Creator.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dalferth</surname>
                           <given-names>Ingolf U.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is a contribution to hermeneutical theology in the twenty-first century. It offers a critical analysis of this important movement within twentieth-century Protestant theology. The purpose of the analysis is not to assign this movement a place within the history of theology, thus consigning it to the past as theology moves on to face changing issues and new challenges. Rather, it is to make its concerns understandable and to point out their validity for the present. Hermeneutical theology in all of its versions has never attempted to adapt to the trends and fashionable topics of the time, but has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Hermeneutical Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Everything has its time. Hermeneutical theology had its time—in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s. That is a significant duration. In contrast to some other theological movements, it did not simply remain an announcement and an agenda; it actually has a history that is worth remembering. But does it have a present that is worth mentioning? Or any future at all? Are there reasons to continue that which students of Rudolf Bultmann such as Ernst Fuchs, Gerhard Ebeling, and Eberhard Jüngel—and their own students—began two or three generations ago? And what would there be to continue, if one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Trends within Twentieth-Century Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In all of its versions, hermeneutics is the practice and theory of an art: the<italic>art of a detour to understanding through interpretation</italic>(hermeneutics as interpretative practice),¹ and the theory of this art, the<italic>poetics of understanding through interpretation</italic>(hermeneutics as theoretical reflection of interpretative practices).²</p>
                     <p>We can understand, and sometimes we actually do. Yet we do not always understand, and we do not need to understand all the time in order to live our lives. Much of what we do in our shared worlds of meaning is governed by daily routines that we perform without understanding what they are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Guiding Ideas of Understanding</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Understanding can occur only within a specific context, under particular conditions, and with some guiding assumptions. A central task of critical hermeneutics is to consider these factors and address their impact. The (mostly unthematized) contextual conditions of the attempt to understand show up in many places: in the standpoint of the interpreter, in the process of interpretation, in that which is assumed to be already understood, and also, most decisively, in how the<italic>interpretandum</italic>is defined. How one defines what one is trying to understand determines which questions of understanding arise and are investigated. The guiding preunderstanding, which is manifest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Theological Hermeneutics and Hermeneutical Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theological hermeneutics is not the hermeneutics of a particular field (religion) or set of sacred texts (the Bible) such as biblical hermeneutics (<italic>hermeneutica sacra</italic>) or the hermeneutics of religion(s)¹ but of everything that we can (or cannot) understand in a theological perspective—the perspective of the creative presence of God.² If the fundamental problem of philosophical hermeneutics is the understanding of understanding, then the fundamental issue of modern theological hermeneutics is the<italic>understanding of the understanding of God</italic>.</p>
                     <p>This is an ambiguous formulation in need of clarification. For what is the meaning of the term<italic>God</italic>here, and how are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Hermeneutical Way of Thinking:</title>
                     <subtitle>Language as Word-Event</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bultmann largely remained with Heidegger’s existential-ontological analysis from the 1920s. Later developments in Heidegger’s thought, which took place after his return to Freiburg and the alienation that resulted from their differing responses to the rise of Nazism, were not reflected in Bultmann’s theology.</p>
                     <p>The generation of Bultmann’s students was different, as they were clearly influenced by the linguistic reflections of the later Heidegger (as in the case of Fuchs) and Gadamer’s effective-history hermeneutics of tradition (as in the case of Ebeling). For them, language is not simply the human means of speaking about all that is possible and real, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Toward a Critique of Hermeneutical Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The hermeneutical approach outlined emphasized the self-interpretation of being or the self-interpretation of God in language, either of which is to be distinguished in principle from all linguistic self-interpretations of persons and from their interpretation of being or God. This drew massive criticism: it was seen as inherently aporetic, based on a problematic combination of differing hermeneutical models, guided by an inadequate understanding of language, and failing to provide a methodology for reliably identifying such self-interpretations intersubjectively or for distinguishing between “true” and “false” interpretations and theological reconstructions in some verifiable way. Theological teaching and argument within hermeneutical theology were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>On Hermeneutical Theology’s Hermeneutical Approach</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The universal, comprehensive, and exclusive employment of the word-event model is also the basis for the characteristic and fundamental hermeneutical orientation of hermeneutical theology. Its primary goal is to understand the understanding of God and to understand everything else in the light of this understanding.</p>
                     <p>It sought to reach this goal by way of a consequential exegesis of the experience of faith as witnessed in Scripture, and of all other experiences in light of this experience of faith. The intent was that faith would understand God, the world, and us as we, the world, and God are understood by God.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Hermeneutical Theology as Radical Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The aporia stated at the end of the last chapter is not the final word about hermeneutical theology. There is a way out of the dilemma if hermeneutical theology remembers its roots and develops itself rigorously as a radical theology. Bear in mind that hermeneutical theology, as was mentioned at the beginning, is not a unified whole. While Bultmann’s hermeneutical approach concentrated first on human understanding and self-understanding and then on the understanding of God that could be developed on that basis, hermeneutical theology after Bultmann had a different focus. Picking up themes from Barth and Luther, it focused first</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Radicalizing Modernity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Georg Wünsch was asked to write the article “Heidegger” for the second edition of the encyclopedia<italic>Die Religion in Geschichte und Gegenwart</italic>, he turned to Rudolf Bultmann for advice. On December 29, 1927, Bultmann wrote to Heidegger about this project. Two days later, Heidegger responded:</p>
                     <p>I find the article on ‘H.’ rather amusing, since I am just beginning to crawl. Other than as a list of motifs that have been, so to speak, pulled together, the matter would be hard to present. Regarding content, all one could say is that my work aims at radicalizing ancient ontology while at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Phenomenology and Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the very first semester of Heidegger’s five years of teaching in Marburg, in 1923, he participated in Bultmann’s seminar on the ethics of Paul. What began as a working relationship soon led to friendship. When Heidegger left for Freiburg in 1928, the two agreed to address each other using the informal<italic>Du</italic>rather than the formal<italic>Sie</italic>. Despite all the reciprocal fruitfulness of their relationship, the theologian clearly was and remained a theologian while the philosopher was and remained a philosopher. Bultmann did not understand philosophy simply as the handmaiden of theology, nor did Heidegger attempt to subsume theology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Resonance Analysis of Revelation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The differences in understanding theology adumbrated in the foregoing were developed with exemplary, and complementary, one-sidedness by Bultmann and by Barth. The two were in agreement that Protestant theology would become superfluous as a distinct intellectual endeavor if conceived as a history-of-religions theory about Christianity and not as a resonance analysis of revelation. However, while the one developed this resonance analysis as a theology of faith, the other conceived it as a theology of revelation.</p>
                     <p>Bultmann sought to ground his theology in the responsive structure of faith, which confessed itself to be based on God’s revelation. God’s revelatory action is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Radical Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Radical theology develops and reflects on the anaphoric-cataphoric dynamic of faith, looking back to its whither and looking forward to its whence. It describes no new phenomena (experience), but instead describes all phenomena anew (experience with experience). It thus develops a<italic>new point of view</italic>(standpoint and horizon) from which all phenomena are to be newly seen and understood.</p>
                     <p>From other standpoints, this new point of view may appear to be merely a<italic>different</italic>viewpoint, one other variant within a series of (cultural or religious) phenomena. This is not wrong. In fact, that it can be seen in this way</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t6tc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
