<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">zaba18348</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Why Only Art Can Save Us</book-title>
         <subtitle>Aesthetics and the Absence of Emergency</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ZABALA</surname>
               <given-names>SANTIAGO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780231183482</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231544962</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231544960</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/zaba18348"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The state of emergency, according to thinkers such as Carl Schmidt, Walter Benjamin, and Giorgio Agamben, is at the heart of any theory of politics. But today the problem is not the crises that we do confront, which are often used by governments to legitimize themselves, but the ones that political realism stops us from recognizing as emergencies, from widespread surveillance to climate change to the systemic shocks of neoliberalism. We need a way of disrupting the existing order that can energize radical democratic action rather than reinforcing the status quo. In this provocative book, Santiago Zabala declares that in an age where the greatest emergency is the absence of emergency, only contemporary art's capacity to alter reality can save us.<italic>Why Only Art Can Save Us</italic>advances a new aesthetics centered on the nature of the emergency that characterizes the twenty-first century. Zabala draws on Martin Heidegger's distinction between works of art that rescue us from emergency and those that are rescuers<italic>into</italic>emergency. The former are a means of cultural politics, conservers of the status quo that conceal emergencies; the latter are disruptive events that thrust us into emergencies. Building on Arthur Danto, Jacques Rancière, and Gianni Vattimo, who made aesthetics more responsive to contemporary art, Zabala argues that works of art are not simply a means of elevating consumerism or contemplating beauty but are points of departure to change the world. Radical artists create works that disclose and demand active intervention in ongoing crises. Interpreting works of art that aim to propel us into absent emergencies, Zabala shows how art's ability to create new realities is fundamental to the politics of radical democracy in the state of emergency that is the present.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since Martin Heidegger said that “only a God can still save us” in a legendary interview with<italic>Der Spiegel</italic>, many have interpreted the word “God” too literally.¹ They have ignored that to Heidegger “God” was simply another realm where Being takes place, as he had explained thirty years earlier in “The Origin of the Work of Art.”² In that famous essay he indicates not only how art embodies an ontological struggle between the self-concealing earth and the illuminating world but also that the event of truth can happen in different acts, such as the “essential sacrifice,” “founding a state,” or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE EMERGENCY OF AESTHETICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Heidegger reformulated as an ontological question Hegel’s judgments on the end of art by asking: “Is art still an essential and necessary way in which that truth happens which is decisive for our historical existence, or is this something that art no longer is?”¹ In doing so, he was trying to overcome the emergency of aesthetics. This emergency does not lie in the “end of art” proclaimed by Hegel but rather in the reduction of art to representable objects to be felt, contemplated, and reproduced as we please. These objects are not simply forms corresponding to the world but also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>EMERGENCY THROUGH ART</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essential emergency of art is not a consequence of the emergency of aesthetics that we outlined in the previous chapter but rather of the absence of events, disruptions, and emergencies in an age that has seen the completion of the global technological organization of the world. Works of art, like events and emergencies, have become remnants of Being, that is, ontological or existential alterations that aim to shake our logical, ethical, and aesthetic assessments of reality. These alterations take place at the margins of culture because they represent not only a resistance to its values but also, as Heidegger</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>EMERGENCY AESTHETICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The twelve works of art I discuss in chapter 2 thrust us into essential emergencies and call into question our comfortable existence. The emergency aesthetics I limn does not simply overcome measurable representations and indifferent beauty but most of all creates the conditions that enable us to respond to the existential call of art in the twenty-first century. If this call offers any opportunity for us to save ourselves, it does so not by indicating where the danger is but rather by itself being the danger. As Martin Heidegger says, what is most dangerous is when danger conceals “itself as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Attentive readers may have noticed how the three epigraphs of this book, from Arthur C. Danto, Jacques Rancière, and Gianni Vattimo, relate to the text. The first pointed out how Martin Heidegger liberated aesthetics from “beauty’s traditional limitation to calm detachment” and situated “beauty as part of the ontology of being human,”¹ the second presented works of art that aim to “produce a new perception of the world” and “create a commitment to its transformation,”² and the third recovered art’s claim to truth and its “theoretical and practical bearing”³ through hermeneutics.</p>
                     <p>Along with these philosophers, there are two other groups</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">zaba18348.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
