<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR4148.M82D3</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Blake, William, 1757-1827</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Myth in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Symbolism in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Symbol and Truth in Blake's Myth</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Damrosch</surname>
               <given-names>Leopold</given-names>
               <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400853731</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400853737</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1980</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zvh3g"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In a controversial examination of the conceptual bases of Blake's myth, Leopold Damrosch argues that his poems contain fundamental contradictions, but that this fact docs not imply philosophical or artistic failure.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1981.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="410"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book attempts to elucidate some fundamental problems in Blake’s myth and in the theory of imagination on which it is implicitly founded. Despite years of trying earnestly to see the myth as philosophically coherent, I have come to believe that it contains serious inconsistencies and owes its lines of development to Blake’s unceasing effort to reconcile them. I am deeply indebted, as will be obvious, to the rich variety of insights available in Blake scholarship, but I shall argue against both prevailing views that assume coherence in Blake’s myth: the orthodox claim that it never changed, and the revisionist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Vision and Perception</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any attempt to understand what Blake’s poems mean must begin by considering how they mean, for he and his modern interpreters assert that his meanings are fundamentally symbolic and are to be understood in a special way. In the twentieth century symbolism has been intensively studied in a wide range of disciplines, including anthropology, depth psychology, linguistics, and philosophy, not to mention literary criticism (usually drawing on one or more of the above). Blake, by contrast, had no such developed body of theory to work with, although he was of course familiar with the speculations of mythographers and iconographers. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>The Truth of Symbols</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even when we have understood that Blake’s theory of perception is grounded in the Divine Body of Jesus, an unresolved antinomy remains. Are symbols arbitrary and inadequate images from the fallen world that will be superseded in Edenic perception, or are they the very basis of experience and the guarantee of truth? Blake’s answer, ultimately, is that symbols become true by being organized into myth, where they take on conceptual form and are available to imaginative interpretation. But before we consider how his myth works, we need to examine closely the basis of its symbols in a theory of perception.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Symbol, Myth, and Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus far we have concentrated on the epistemological and psychological basis of Blake’s symbols. We shall now move toward an examination of the myth in which he organized them, and raise more directly the problem of interpretation in its dual form: Blake’s understanding of his symbols’ meaning, and the various kinds of understanding that modern readers bring to them. I propose to begin by considering some representative modern theories of symbolism, taking care at each point to note essential differences from Blake’s theory, but at the same time establishing perspectives that will help to illuminate the peculiar difficulties of his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Zoas and the Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Blake’s myth is above all else psychological. His cosmology, theology, and even epistemology are all transpositions of the central inquiry into the self. This is no disinterested quest. Like many in his age Blake was haunted, if not obsessed, by dividedness within the self and between self and world. As Hegel said in his first published work, division or discord<italic>(Entzweiung)</italic>“is the source of the need for philosophy.” And both Hegel and Blake were convinced that harmony must be achieved by restoring the fruitful interaction of opposites, not by abolishing them. “When the power of unification disappears from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Problem of Dualism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Was Blake a dualist or a monist? If that question had a simple answer this book would not have been written. The answer is highly complex because in certain respects Blake was both, and because neither term has much meaning until it is illuminated by a specific context. Throughout his career Blake firmly opposed at least one form of dualism, the Cartesian distinction between mind (or soul) and body. “Man has no Body distinct from his Soul for that calld Body is a portion of Soul discernd by the five Senses, the chief inlets of Soul in this age”<italic>(MHH,</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>God and Man</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen, the problem of the divine is ubiquitous in Blake. Jesus is the Divine Body who sustains the life of symbols, the savior who restores the lost unity of the Zoas, and (as in Christian theology in general) the force that binds together the otherwise disjoined elements of a dualistic universe. With these contexts established we can now consider the symbolic and philosophical significance of Blake’s God.</p>
                     <p>It is obvious that Blake hated Puritan morality while retaining, as Frye remarks, the “Nonconformist conscience”; it is apparent also that he shared in the Romantic tendency to produce theories</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Blake and Los</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>302</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have seen that Blake’s myth is founded in vision, by which he means a mode of perception that sees through symbols rather than with them.</p>
                     <p>Now I a fourfold vision see</p>
                     <p>And a fourfold vision is given to me.</p>
                     <p>(E693/K818)</p>
                     <p>To ask in what sense it is “given” is to approach the final complex of problems that will occupy us, those surrounding the work of the prophetic poet who labors to mediate his vision to other human beings. Ultimately the pictures and poems are intended to lead us to the brink of an inner apocalypse which each must experience</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>Blake and the Reader</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have been concerned throughout this book to understand the shape of Blake’s thought, both as a structure of ideas and as a warfare of antitheses whose tremendous energy constantly threatens to break that structure apart. It will be obvious that I admire Blake most deeply for the intransigence of this ever-reconstructed vision, which defiantly rejects all of art’s customary accommodations with conventional ways of interpreting reality. But it would be idle to pretend that Blake’s prophetic poems are not, in the end, very strange as well as very difficult. In trying to come to terms with Blake's claims to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                     <subtitle>Los, Mulciber, and the Tyger</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvh3g.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>396</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
