<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1njjmz</collection-id>
      <volume>70</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Art and Its Uses in Thomas Mann's 'Felix Krull'</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schonfield</surname>
               <given-names>Ernest</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781905981052</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781880722</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Modern Humanities Research Association</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Modern Humanities Research Association</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>the Institute of Germanic and Romance Studies, University of London</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt32b997"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The turn of the twentieth century was a time of identity crisis for the upper and middle classes, one in which increased social mobility caused the blurring of traditional boundaries and created a need for reference works such as the British Who's Who (1897). At the same time, the rise of a new leisure industry and an increase in international travel led to a boom period for confidence men, who frequently operated in hotels and holiday resorts. Thomas Mann's "Felix Krull", written between 1910-13 and continued (though never completed) in 1951-54, uses contemporary accounts of these figures as a starting-point from which to explore the aesthetics of society. The early Krull marks an important stage in Mann's development in a number of respects.In writing it, Mann acquired a more flexible conception of identity and a new understanding of the relation between artist and public. Krull also signals a deeper engagement with Goethe and a shift in Mann's work towards a more open treatment of sexuality. The novel presents art as being central to the development of the individual and to social interaction. While Krull is nominally a confidence man, he is more of a performance artist, a purveyor of beauty who relies upon the complicity of his audience. The later Krull takes up where Mann left off and continues the justification of art as an essential human activity. This study draws upon unpublished material in order to provide a comprehensive reading of "Felix Krull". It examines the novel within the context of Mann's work as a whole, and, in doing so, it seeks to demonstrate the remarkable continuity of Mann's creative achievement.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="202"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>E. S.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>x</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In his study <italic>The Age of Empire</italic>, Eric Hobsbawm describes the period between 1875 and 1914 as a time of profound identity crisis for the upper and middle classes, one in which social mobility reached unprecedented levels.¹ As a result, there arose a confusion about ‘who was who’, and it was in this period that reference volumes about persons of status in the nation, such as the British <italic>Who’s Who</italic> (1897), first appeared.² The growth of the modern city added to the confusion about identity. As Georg Simmel remarked in his essay ‘Die Großstädte und das Geistesleben’ (1903), the dominance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Art and the Notation of Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In this chapter I will argue that the early work on <italic>Felix Krull</italic> represents a creative watershed in Mann’s career. It marks the moment when Mann realized that he could imaginatively expand his identity to the extent that he could identify with persons and characters far removed from his own experience and disposition. I will seek to show that <italic>Felix Krull</italic> offers a creatively adaptable model of identity, and that it presents art and aesthetics as being central to the development of the individual subject.</p>
                     <p>The debate about the formation and cultivation of the self goes back to classical antiquity;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Art and the Notation of Community</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Much has been written about the structural dichotomy of <italic>Bürger</italic> and <italic>Künstler</italic> in the early works of Thomas Mann. In this early phase, the <italic>Künstler</italic>, as the representative of <italic>Geist</italic>, finds himself isolated from, and opposed to, the coarse realities of bourgeois life (<italic>Leben</italic>); and the possibility of conciliation between these two spheres appears remote. By the time Mann came to write the autobiographical <italic>Tonio Kröger</italic> (1903), however, he was beginning to realize that this opposition was too simplistic, and that a person could contain both types within himself. Tonio Kröger is both artist and ‘verirrter Bürger’ (VIII, 305), torn</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Narrative Performance in <italic>Felix Krull</italic>
                     </title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>So far I have considered <italic>Felix Krull</italic> thematically. However, it is only possible to assess the full effect and scope of the novel by examining how it operates on a stylistic level. I therefore intend to analyse the novel from the point of view of technique, in order to show how the novel’s formal elements reinforce its exploration of art’s contribution to both individual identity and community. Formally, the most remarkable aspect of <italic>Krull</italic> is the way in which the narrator continually pauses to address the reader. At the heart of this chapter is therefore section (iv), which analyses the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The main argument of this book is that, in <italic>Felix Krull</italic>, art and aesthetics are shown to be central to the life of the mind and to the life of society. The Müller-Rosé episode offers a paradigm of how art works: <italic>not</italic> as an imposed illusion, but as a mutually agreed, deliberate pretence.¹ The crucial point of this episode is that art is not a deception, but an imaginative exchange which relies upon an intersubjective arrangement. Müller-Rosé requires the ‘stillschweigende[s] Einverständnis’ (294) of his audience in order to succeed. Mann, like Coleridge, is advocating a willing suspension of disbelief,² in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt32b997.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
