<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">F1219.54.M59J36 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Manuscripts, Mixtec</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mixtec Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mixtec Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Genealogy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mixtec Indians</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Archaeology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Encounter with the Plumed Serpent</book-title>
         <subtitle>Drama and Power in the Heart of Mesoamerica</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jansen</surname>
               <given-names>Maarten</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jiménez</surname>
               <given-names>Gabina Aurora Pérez</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780870818684</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781607327103</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University Press of Colorado</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Boulder, Colorado</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University Press of Colorado</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1wn0rc9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Mixtec, or the people of Savi ("Nation of the Rain God"), one of the major civilizations of ancient Mesoamerica, made their home in the highlands of Oaxaca, where they resisted both Aztec military expansion and the Spanish conquest. This book presents and interprets the sacred histories narrated in the Mixtec codices, the largest surviving collection of pre-Columbian manuscripts in existence. In these screenfold books, ancient painter-historians chronicled the politics of the Mixtec from approximately a.d. 900 to 1521, portraying the royal families, rituals, wars, alliances, and ideology of the times. By analyzing and cross-referencing the codices, which have been fragmented and dispersed in far-flung archives, the authors attempt to reconstruct Mixtec history. Adding useful interpretation and commentary, Jansen and Perez Jimenez synthesize the large body of surviving documents into the first unified narrative of Mixtec sacred history.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carrasco</surname>
                           <given-names>Davíd</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moctezuma</surname>
                           <given-names>Eduardo Matos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <role content-type="editor">General Editors</role>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Just as religious convictions determined social ethos and the way Native Americans behaved toward nature, ideology provided the frame for the recording and interpretation of history itself. . . . We see this reflected in the archetypal king of the archetypal civilized kingdom: Quetzalcoatl of Tollan.” So writes Maarten Jansen and Gabina Aurora Pérez Jiménez at the end of the first chapter in the long-awaited, innovative, and significant<italic>Encounter with the Plumed Serpent: Drama and Power in the Heart of Mesoamerica</italic>. The Mesoamerican Worlds series has two other books whose titles include the famed name of Quetzalcoatl: Davíd Carrasco’s<italic>Quetzalcoatl</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>The Mat and the THRONE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mexico Tenochtitlan, The day 8 Wind , The 9Th day of The month Quecholli of the year 1 Reed in the Mexica (Aztec) calendar, which may correspond to A.D. November 8, 1519. In a dramatic first confrontation, the Mexica ruler Motecuhzoma Xocoyotzin greeted Hernán Cortés, the Spanish invader, with a respectful speech. The rendering of his words by Cortés himself, based on the difficult intercultural translation by his female interpreter Malintzin, was not done without particular interest. The conquistador selected and shrewdly highlighted the convenient elements, so that a polite welcome became transformed into nothing less than a recognition of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>STORYTELLING and RITUAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>History was recalled and communicated mainly in the Heart of the community, the ceremonial and administrative center. Actually, no clear descriptions of such events in Ñuu Dzaui have come down to us, but they can be reconstructed on the basis of patterns observed in the Classic Maya cities. There, the important historical statements are inscribed as images with hieroglyphic texts on stelae and tablets and are directly related to temples, palaces, and similar structures. Their reading, therefore, always took place in the presence of the Gods, the Ancestors, and those who held important offices in the sovereign community. History was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>DESCENT of the PLUMED SERPENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human history, according to the Mesoamerican worldview, started with the First Sunrise. Before, there was darkness, a mysterious time of origins. The most impressive and complete expression of this concept is found in the Popol Vuh, the sacred book of the Quiché in Guatemala. The story begins in darkness and night (<italic>chi quecum chi acab</italic>). The divine plan of creation is to bring about germination and dawn (<italic>ta chauaxoc, ta zaquiroc</italic>), connecting and even identifying the natural cycle of fertility with the cycle of day and night. Humanity, which exists within these cycles, is referred to as “people of light”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>FOUNDING MOTHERS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Seven Caves of heaven are the point of departure for an intriguing story about the events of a remote past recorded in the Ñuu Dzaui manuscripts (Codex Tonindeye, 14–21). Heaven, we now understand, is both the general sacred living space of the Gods and an actual sanctuary on a mountaintop near Yuta Tnoho. The seven caves (Chicomoztoc) are a metaphor for earthly origin. At the same time, they may refer to actual caves in the area with ceremonial functions. In this case, a pair emerges: Lady 3 Flint ‘Shell Quechquemitl, Plumed Serpent’ (“Power and Strength of the Plumed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>The RISE of ÑUU TNOO</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of the lineages begins with the warmth and energy of the first rising of Lord Sun (Iya Ndicandii), who, with his rays of life-giving power and his call to work and glory, created a human world of knowledge and seeing while the past became a time of darkness and mystery, solid and cold as stone. The<italic>Iya</italic>and<italic>Iyadzehe,</italic>who had their origin in Yuta Tnoho, were children of light and heat; the earlier populations were reduced to immobile rock formations in their new landscape. As it was in the beginning, this process of awakening and coming to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>LORD of the TOLTECS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the day 13 Flower, the seventh day of the year after the death of his father, 6 Reed (1083), Lord 8 Deer ‘Jaguar Claw’ went hunting on the Mountain of the Temple of Heaven, where offerings of knotted grass and shells—spondylus and strombus—had been made in preparation for this act. With his arrows he shot a coyote.¹ Lord 8 Deer and his elder half-brother, Lord 12 Movement, both painted black with the hallucinogenic ointments of priests, sacrificed the coyote and a deer for a celestial spirit, Lord 13 Reed, who spoke to them from Heaven. Codex Iya</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>TRIUMPH and TRAGEDY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the day 11 Death, the Sun God (or his high priest) Granted Lord 4 Jaguar and Lord 8 Deer a vision.¹ They climbed the impressive and beautifully decorated pyramid that reached into the heavens—it is easy to visualize here the older phase of the Castillo in Chichén Itzá. There the Heaven, place of sacrifice and ecstasy, opened, and they saw three temples or houses. This image probably referred to the idea of a Triple Alliance. Indeed, the first house was that of the Plumed Serpent at Tollan-Cholollan. But facing it were not—as one would have expected—the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>FLUTE of the DIVINE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The pictorial manuscripts of Ñuu Dzaui give Detailed and important information on the nature of rulership in the ancient society that produced them. In general, political agency involves different sources of power: “<italic>Objective</italic>sources include wealth and factors of production, while<italic>symbolic</italic>sources include elements of a cognitive code, including religion and ritual” (Blanton et al. 1996: 3).</p>
                     <p>The symbolic source, with its cognitive code, is crucial in assigning and explaining (“legitimating”) the power of the noble houses that ruled the precolonial village-states. We clearly see this in the way the contents of these chronicles are organized along three main</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Nine</label>
                     <title>The CROWN of MOTECUHZOMA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The icon of the Toltec ruler as manifestation ( ) of the Plumed Serpent is the impressive feather headdress, the<italic>quetzalapanecayotl</italic>. It appears in the Ñuu Dzaui codices as a diagnostic attribute of Lord 4 Jaguar. Lord 8 Deer was considered worthy to wear it in death; his mummy bundle was adorned with it when laid to rest in the dark and sacred cave. At several occasions Mexica emperors, such as the triumphant Tizoc, distinguished themselves in this manner. Motecuhzoma sent one such headdress to Cortés upon his arrival, together with the turquoise serpent mask of Quetzalcoatl and other divine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wn0rc9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
