<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Lyric Cousins</book-title>
         <subtitle>Poetry and Musical Form</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sampson</surname>
               <given-names>Fiona</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474402927</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474402934</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fiona Sampson</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g0501b"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Today, poetry and art music occupy similar cultural positions. This is a study of these two formal craft traditions that is concerned with the similarities in their roles, structures, projects and capacities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Little Conversation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A book like this should start with a disclaimer. At least, that seems to be the convention. Introducing<italic>Musical Elaborations</italic>(1991), a series of lectures in critical theory that he had given at the University of California, Edward W. Said makes clear that his volume ‘is meant as neither a contribution to systematic musicology nor a series of literary essays about music as it relates to literature’.¹</p>
                     <p>The same could be said of this book which, like Said’s, started life as a series of ‘three consecutive lectures’ given in a non-musicological context, in this case as the University of Newcastle’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>About Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At dusk, the afternoon ‘Express’ from Bucharest to Budapest travels slowly through Transylvania, on a curving route that allows the passenger who leans out of the window to see the other carriages running ahead and behind across the plain. As it rattles past remote villages, the train starts storks from their nests and startles small boys from the trackside scrub. It’s a noisy business. The rolling stock is left over from Cold War days, and the whistle sounds like something from a black-and-white movie.</p>
                     <p>The region it’s passing through seems equally unchanged by the passage of time; though in fact</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Abstract Form</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a poet, the notion that abstract form – not ‘meaning’, but pure<italic>shape</italic>– can play a key role in what she writes is seductive. On the one hand, it implies the possibility of developing and experimenting with the kinds of sophisticated formal patterning that we traditionally associate with verse, such as the way stanzas ‘chunk’ a ballad’s story, or a rhyme scheme creates a network of meanings that crisscross and link up within a poem. On the other, it also appeals to something more primitive. For it suggests that poets can – and perhaps even should – do</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Drawing the Line</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Igor Stravinsky’s<italic>Rite of Spring</italic>opens with one of the most famous solos in the orchestral canon. In fact, it starts with just one note, itself instantly recognisable within the Western tradition: a single high C on the bassoon. This is of course a wind instrument and its reedy, wooden timbre evokes the wind, reeds and woods that make up the endless Russian<italic>taiga</italic>(see Fig. 3.1).¹</p>
                     <p>Like that wilderness, the opening note seems as though it could go on for ever (and it’s marked with a pause sign). Instead, it lapses into a figure that resembles a turn, one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Chromaticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1879 Hubert Parry wrote, in<italic>Grove’s Musical Dictionary</italic>, that: ‘Secular music has long displayed the very free use of chromaticisms similar to the modern style of writing’ (by which he meant musical composition). In turn, the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>has quoted this entry to demonstrate how the idea of ‘chromaticism’ is used: for<italic>Grove’s</italic>is still, as it was when Parry contributed to it, the key reference encyclopaedia for British musicians.¹ Sure enough, thinking of tonal or harmonic variations in terms of colour – as<italic>chromaticism</italic>does – may have its literal origins in synaesthesia, but such thinking is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Density</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We probably shouldn’t be surprised if visual artists think with greater sophistication than musicians and poets about the resources of the material world. After all, such resources are their artistic alphabet. The printmaker doesn’t just enjoy the tones created by cross-hatched lines, he understands the effects of acid. The maker of bronzes knows how that metal behaves during the casting process.</p>
                     <p>The same resources are also their vocabulary: a colour study is<italic>about</italic>the colours it’s made from. In<italic>On Modern Art</italic>, Paul Klee distinguishes between colour, weight and tone:</p>
                     <p>Colour is primarily Quality. Secondly, it is also Weight, for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>The Meaning of ‘Meaning’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We resist new forms of meaning. We’re even resistant to the<italic>idea</italic>of them. It simply<italic>is</italic>difficult to conceptualise ways of understanding that we haven’t thought through before, or that differ from our usual ways of thinking. This is something we have to<italic>work</italic>at: as all school pupils can attest. To ‘get your head round’ something: even the cliché conveys a sense of effortful rearrangement. From such practical difficulty flow the many religious, philosophical or ‘commonsensical’ beliefs – some of them notorious – which in turn reinforce these resistances.¹</p>
                     <p>Our own resistances are hardest of all to spot.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Song</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While I’ve been working on this book I’ve frequently found myself explaining that I’m not writing a study of song. Yet music and poetry do<italic>meet</italic>in song. What we know of human prehistory suggests that they share an overlapping origin, in live performance, as material that was improvised and memorised, and that relied on traditions of collective transmission. But I’m no archaeologist, and specialists – like those working on the bone flutes of the early Neolithic site at Jiahu in Henan Province, China for example, or in the Acoustics and Music of British Prehistory Research Network – are articulating</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>And Story Came Too:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Epic to Opera</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unlike song, opera is a highly specialised form; one that’s frequently portrayed, by both admirers and critics, as having at least as much cultural significance off-stage as on-. It’s at the opera that Anton Chekhov’s ‘The Lady with the Dog’ is reunited with her lover. Their key scene takes place ‘On the narrow, gloomy staircase over which was written “Entrance to Circle”’.¹ In today’s Kyiv, the contemporary Ukrainian poet Yuri Burjak has a remarkably similar encounter ‘At the Rear of the Circle’:</p>
                     <p>Just in front of me</p>
                     <p>at the rear of the Circle</p>
                     <p>I saw your eyes, as they are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Closer Still:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Total Artwork</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Richard Wagner’s operas are often characterised by his own expression,<italic>Gesamtkunstwerk</italic>, which English musicologists translate as ‘total artwork’. But Wagner himself only ever used the term in two essays, both published in 1849. ‘Art and Revolution’ and ‘The Artwork of the Future’ were both written from political exile; the first in Paris and the second in Zürich. The still young-ish Wagner (he was born in 1813) had supported the revolutions of 1848 and was an active, if not especially important, participant in the 1849 May Revolution in Dresden. As a result, he was to spend almost a decade in exile</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>The Consolations of Tradition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the millennium, certain trends in Anglophone poetry have echoed the ‘turn’ in Western art music away from what we might think of as mid-century ‘scholasticism’ towards such conventional musical rewards as readily detectable patterning, or euphony. Artistic credibility and a response by non-specialist audiences no longer appear inimical. It has once again become possible to develop serious original work using traditional verse forms such as the ballad (which we saw at work in Chapter 6), or musical tropes as familiar as the rising or falling scale on which Arvo Pärt’s famous<italic>Fratres</italic>is built.¹</p>
                     <p>This shift, from the complex</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>Radical Measures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, the idea of ‘the poem’ has been pulled in polarising directions. In the last chapter, we began to see how an ideological debate is under way that echoes what’s taken place in Western art music since the middle of the twentieth century. This is not just a question of style. Poetic ‘sense’, already a complicated, unstable concept, is being challenged and transformed.</p>
                     <p>As we saw in Chapters 5 and 6, poetry has traditionally used language in ways that allow a ‘surplus’ of implied or possible meanings and sensory experiences to pull against its grammatically and semantically coherent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 12</label>
                     <title>Performance:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Role of the Audience</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I write this, on an InterCity Express racing through snowy Austria, my gaze is repeatedly drawn to the woman sitting opposite me. Her mini-skirt and thigh boots create an eccentric ensemble with her deeply wrinkled pensioner’s face. She holds the headphones of an old-fashioned Walkman tight against her ears as if to squeeze even closer to an experience that leaks out, anyway, in the high notes of an operatic aria. It must be on maximum volume. Her eyes are closed; her expression is shockingly private. Who’s to say why she’s moved – or why by Guiseppe Verdi? The point</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g0501b.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
