<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ht4x4s</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HV1568.D65 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">People with disabilities</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Rhetoric</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Disability Rhetoric</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dolmage</surname>
               <given-names>Jay Timothy</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780815652335</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">081565233X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Syracuse University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Syracuse, New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Syracuse University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j2n73m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Disability Rhetoric is the first book to view rhetorical theory and history through the lens of disability studies. Traditionally, the body has been seen as, at best, a rhetorical distraction; at worst, those whose bodies do not conform to a narrow range of norms are disqualified from speaking. Yet, Dolmage argues that communication has always been obsessed with the meaning of the body and that bodily difference is always highly rhetorical. Following from this rewriting of rhetorical history, he outlines the development of a new theory, affirming the ideas that all communication is embodied, that the body plays a central role in all expression, and that greater attention to a range of bodies is therefore essential to a better understanding of rhetorical histories, theories, and possibilities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prothesis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I will begin this book with three moments, three spaces.</p>
                     <p>First, here we are in Periclean Athens, following the Ten Years’ War. Many Athenians have been wounded and disabled. The city must be rebuilt. A huge festival is held to celebrate Hephaestus, the Greek god of metallurgy, a god with a physical disability, his feet twisted and pointed in opposite directions. In this “new” Athens, there will be a need for craftspeople like Hephaestus—everyone will have to get to work. There is also a shift toward new bodily values. Hephaestus becomes the figure for new forms of ingenuity and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Disability Studies of Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this first chapter I want to make two initial moves to align disability studies and rhetoric. First, I want to explore the rhetorical history of the disability studies concept of normativity. Then, I want to chart some popular and persistent disability myths.</p>
                     <p>I will begin by suggesting that, as historian Martha Rose writes, “ideas about disability in the ancient world are part of our [contemporary] common consciousness” (2003, 2). We have always had disability myths, and these myths have always been rhetorically significant and rhetorically contested. I would suggest that common contemporary ideas about disability are always prefaced by,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTERCHAPTER:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Archive and Anatomy of Disability Myths</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As Rosemarie Garland-Thomson writes, “Seeing disability as a representational system engages several premises of current critical theory: that representation structures reality, that the margins constitute the center, that human identity is multiple and unstable, and that all analysis and evaluation has political implications” (1997b, 19). With this in mind, I will pause here to create a quick overview of some of the myths of disability that are ubiquitous across cultures and eras and that condition our understanding of disability (and thus of all identity and all bodies). This investigation of disability myths is an extension of my interrogation of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Rhetorical Histories of Disability</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To begin this chapter, I will offer a compressed overview of disability in antiquity. This overview is important historically and for the “narrative” of this book. But my hope is not just to start telling a story here, but instead to establish, through this quick scan of the role of the body in antiquity, a lexicon and a critical repertoire that is much more far-reaching. This compression is intended to simplify, to make a vast expanse of time accessible, but also to create density and force. My hope is to explain and illustrate the ubiquity and impact of normativity as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Imperfect Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rhetoric can be seen as the function of power within language, and I connect it to the body because the body is what has been traditionally defined and (thus) disciplined by rhetorics of disability, while at the same time our bodies speak back, insisting (prosthetically) upon the impossibility of a normative essence. Saying this, however, introduces static. Who owns and what constructs—what owns and who constructs—the disabled body? In order to assert that<italic>all</italic>bodily rhetoric is<italic>mētis</italic>, these questions of power and agency must first (and continuously) be addressed. In this chapter I will further examine ways</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTERCHAPTER:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Repertoire and Choreography of Disability Rhetorics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goal of<italic>Disability Rhetoric</italic>is to instantiate an expanded sense and a more inclusive framework through which we might view the rhetorical body. In introducing terms like<italic>aphrona, anmut, apate,</italic>and<italic>pseilos,</italic>I am not trying to establish a new lexicon, but rather I am working to show that we could choose to view a history in which disability and rhetoricity were consubstantial, in which this connection was fully theorized, when we screen our stories again. In the next chapter I will expand on these enabling approaches to embodiment through the stories of<italic>mētis</italic>. But, as I promised at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Mētis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far I have offered a brief guided tour through rhetorical history, a moving through and with the bodies of this history. I have suggested that we can read embodied rhetoric and bodied rhetorical history as powered by tension around normativity. I have also explored disability myths and disability rhetorics. My argument is that disability has myriad meanings, many of them positive and generative.<italic>Mētis</italic>, I will show, is the craft of forging something practical out of these possibilities, practicing an embodied rhetoric, changing the world as we move through it. The key examplar of<italic>mētis</italic>is the disabled Greek</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Eating Rhetorical Bodies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The celebration of Hephaestus, his craft, his cunning, his ability, as well as the deification of his disability are means of challenging held perceptions about the mythical character, but also about all of us—defined as we all are by concepts of ability, by rhetorics of normalcy. An epideictic and forensic exploration of his myths does not just martial praise or blame through his body or question the truth or falsity of rhetorical history; this rhetorical work should shift body values and roles, becoming a deliberation on embodied possibilities.</p>
                     <p>I have argued that rhetoric will not admit it has a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>“I Did It on Purpose”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The recent Oscar-winning film<italic>The King’s Speech,</italic>because it focuses on public speaking, on pedagogy, and on the body, is a movie about rhetoric. More specifically, the film is about disability rhetoric. Therefore, it is an excellent space in which to try out many of the questions and ideas of this book—and to thus argue that the questions have real, contemporary significance. My method in this final chapter will be to employ<italic>mētis</italic>as I explore not just how the film was actually made, or how it was popularly received, but also how it has been argued over. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prosthesis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I began this book with three moments, three spaces: Periclean Athens, following the Ten Years’ War; in the aftermath of World War II; and here, today. I suggested that now, as in these historical spaces, bodies continue to change, as do attitudes about them, and the rhetorical entailments of these bodily transformations continue to be negotiated. I argued, deliberatively, that a “futuristic” disability studies will not be about eradication of disability, but about new social structures and relations, made possible by new rhetorics. Somewhat ironically, these disability futures, I hope I have shown, can be made possible through disability historiography.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j2n73m.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
