<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9m0s24</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Faith in a Hidden God</book-title>
         <subtitle>Luther, Kierkegaard, and the Binding of Isaac</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PALMER</surname>
               <given-names>ELIZABETH</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506432731</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506432748</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis, MN</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tm7gw5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The story of the binding of Isaac both challenges and inspires people who seek to live faithfully in relationship with a God who surpasses our understanding. Combinding the history of exegesis with a theological exploration of the meaning of faith in the face of suffering, this book examines Luther‘s and Kierkegaard‘s lively--and very different--interpretations of Genesis 22 to demonstrate how the way we read the Bible is crucial to the life of faith.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="330"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Pedagogy and Anagogy in Twentieth-Century Readings of Genesis 22</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his renowned literary comparison of Genesis 22 with Homer’s account of Odysseus’s homecoming, Erich Auerbach reminds readers that the most provocative interactions between a reader and a religious text may play out in the silences in the story, the spaces that elude narrative logic and move the reader from certainty toward the frightening aporia that underlies the relationship between humans and their God.</p>
                     <p>In the story of Isaac, it is not only God’s intervention at the beginning and the end, but even the factual and psychological elements which come between, that are mysterious, merely touched upon, fraught with background;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Luther’s Reading of Genesis 22:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Lectures on Genesis in Historical and Theological Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter explicates Luther’s reading of Genesis 22 in the<italic>Lectures on Genesis</italic>in his exegetical and historical context, focusing on the theological and exegetical moves by which he simultaneously softens the story and intensifies its problematic elements. In particular, the doctrine of the resurrection of the dead as an example of<italic>creatio ex nihilo</italic>serves as a hermeneutical key to both God and Abraham. It resolves the tension between God’s promise and command and it provides a response to ethical critiques of Abraham’s behavior. But the concept of resurrection fails to solve the underlying theological problems of who God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Faith as Movement in Relation to the Lectures on Genesis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luther’s concept of faith as trust in God’s promises stands in opposition to the medieval categories of faith in which he had been schooled, particularly those views that posited faith to be contingent upon a particular knowledge on the part of the believer. Medieval theologians, reading the Abrahamic narratives in light of the Pauline claim that Abraham was justified by faith, attempted to define precisely the kind of faith that had justified Abraham (and by extension promises to justify Christians): unformed or formed by love; acquired by works or infused by God; implicit or explicit in the mind’s assent to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Kierkegaard’s Reading of Genesis 22:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fear and Trembling in Historical and Theological Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>as a work of exegesis in order to reveal consistencies, ambiguities, and tensions in the way Kierkegaard’s pseudonymous author exegetes Genesis 22 in relation to claims about Christian faith as it relates to ethics, reason, and speech. After an examination of the historical, social, and intellectual forces that influenced Kierkegaard during the time of the pseudonymous authorship, the chapter engages in a close reading of<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>, examining the ways in which Johannes de Silentio uses variations, silences, and obscurities to enhance the difficulties and complexities inherent in the story. Insisting that it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Faith as Movement in Relation to Fear and Trembling</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is Kierkegaard really attempting to do or say with this text? This question must be posed in relation to larger claims about faith in Kierkegaard’s perspective before the effects of the text upon its readers in relation to their own perception of God can be accurately examined. In light of the complexities of the meaning of Kierkegaardian faith, this chapter demonstrates how<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>’s proclivity for multiple readings both contributes to the text’s anagogical effect and sabotages it.</p>
                     <p>It is as difficult to discern the meaning of faith and its relation to ethics in<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>The Value of Anagogical Exegesis for Faith</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The performative dimensions of Luther and Kierkegaard’s readings of Genesis 22 have been evaluated in light of each thinker’s concept of faith as perceptual movement in relation to the hiddenness and revelation of God. Such performative movement can be called anagogical when it moves the reader into deeper understanding of God. Both the<italic>Lectures on Genesis</italic>and<italic>Fear and Trembling</italic>move their readers in ways that resemble a movement of faith: toward a trustworthy God for the former, and into the abyss of God’s ineffability for the latter. Not every reader will be moved in such a way, but both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Biblical References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gw5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>320</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
