<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="ita">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7gw</collection-id>
      <volume>XXVII-1</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Karl Jaspers e la molteplicità delle visioni del mondo</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">a cura di</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Achella</surname>
               <given-names>Stefania</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schlimme</surname>
               <given-names>Jann E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9788822900760</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9788874629800</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Quodlibet</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Macerata</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Quodlibet</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1p5f306"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Sommario: Stefania Achella, Jann E. Schlimme, Presentazione / PARTE I. GENEALOGIE, CONCETTI, CONFRONTI: Roberto Garaventa, All’origine dell’idea jaspersiana di Weltanschauung / Giuseppe Cantillo, L’ambivalenza delle Weltanschauungen tra ragione ed esistenza / Csaba Olay, Jaspers’ Begriff der "Weltanschauung“ im Anschluss an Dilthey und Weber / Oliver Immel, Heideggers Stellungnahme zur "Psychologie der Weltanschauungen“ als Wegmarke der Jaspers’schen Existenzphilosophie / Michael Steinmann, Wertung und Wertwiderstand. Selbsterfahrung und die antinomische Struktur der Existenz bei Jaspers und Heidegger / Stefania Achella, Il concetto di “mondo" nella Psychologie der Weltanschauungen / Elena Alessiato, Weltanschauungen e politica / Andrea Staiti, Naturalism as Weltanschauung / PARTE II. PRATICHE E ORIENTAMENTI TEORICI: Jean-Claude Gens, Die Weltanschauung zwischen Ideenflucht und Wahnsinnigkeit / Reinhard Schulz, Praktiken des Verstehens und Weltanschauungsanalyse / Anna Donise, Gli involucri tra forma e vita: per una difesa dell’inautentico / Borut Škodlar, Jan Ciglenečki, Multiple Orientations within the Worldviews in Psychosis and Mysticism: Relevance for Psychotherapy / Jann E. Schlimme, Wahnsinns-Erzählungen. Weltanschauung und lange anhaltende Psychoseerfahrung / Burkhart Brückner, Samuel Thoma, Wahn, Weltanschauung und Habitus. Zur sozialwissenschaftlichen Kritik der Theorie des Wahns im Werk von Karl Jaspers</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>ita</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Presentazione</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Achella</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefania</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schlimme</surname>
                           <given-names>Jann E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>La scelta del tema al centro di questo volume, il concetto di<italic>Weltanschauung</italic>, o meglio della molteplicità delle<italic>Weltanschauungen</italic>, nasce dall’esigenza di confrontarsi con uno dei principali fenomeni del nostro tempo: lo scontro tra diverse e contrastanti visioni del mondo che pretendono una validità oggettiva. La<italic>Psicologia delle visioni del mondo</italic>, pubblicata da Karl Jaspers nel 1919, reagiva allo stesso problema. In un momento di crisi dell’Europa, legata alla perdita di un’idea universale e unica di verità e all’emergere di diverse forme di fanatismo, l’opera jaspersiana si proponeva un’analisi fenomenologica delle visioni del mondo, attenta non solo al lato soggettivo,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>All’origine dell’idea jaspersiana di Weltanschauung</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garaventa</surname>
                           <given-names>Roberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>1. Allorché Jaspers tenne, presso la Facoltà di filosofia dell’Università di Heidelberg in cui era incardinato come professore straordinario di psicologia, il corso di lezioni da lui poi pubblicato nel 1919 col titolo<italic>Psicologia delle visioni del mondo</italic>(Jaspers 1919), il tema<italic>Weltanschauung</italic>(“intuizione del mondo” o “visione del mondo”) aveva già acquisito un’indiscutibile centralità nella riflessione accademica. Ne sono testimonianza le numerose pubblicazioni dedicate a questo argomento nella seconda metà del XIX e nei primi due decenni del XX secolo, come ad esempio il volume<italic>Visione del mondo. Filosofia e religione</italic>(Frischeisen-Köhler 1919), che contiene, oltre il celebre studio</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>L’ambivalenza delle Weltanschauungen tra ragione ed esistenza</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cantillo</surname>
                           <given-names>Giuseppe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper aims to understand the meaning and role that Jaspers attributes to worldviews. By analysing the nature of the<italic>Weltanschauungen</italic>, the paper shows how Jaspers, inspired by Dilthey, alludes to a fundamental stratum of the Weltanschauung that goes beyond every objective construction, every shell (<italic>Gehäuse</italic>) and every doctrine, and which is identified with the process of the existential experience. The antinomicity of the lived process and the ambiguity that characterises the worldviews becomes clearer where Jaspers introduces the notion of limit situation. By analysing the relationship between the<italic>Weltanschauungen</italic>and the philosophical faith, the paper shows that the<italic>Weltanschauungen</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jaspers’ Begriff der „Weltanschauung“ im Anschluss an Dilthey und Weber</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Olay</surname>
                           <given-names>Csaba</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of „worldview“ is one of the basic categories of Jaspers’ thought, even if it gets marginalised in the later work. Worldview is considered in the secondary literature primarily in connection with the concept of shell (<italic>Gehäuse</italic>) Jaspers took from Max Weber. In the paper I defend the claim that Jaspers’ conception of „worldview“ unites motives from Wilhelm Dilthey and Max Weber, constructing a weberised Dilthey. After some conceptual clarifications I treat first the specific contribution of Dilthey and Max Weber to Jaspers’ theory, and discuss the latter afterwards. Finally, I show that despite its dissappearance in the later</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Heideggers Stellungnahme zur „Psychologie der Weltanschauungen“ als Wegmarke der Jaspers’schen Existenzphilosophie</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Immel</surname>
                           <given-names>Oliver</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper focuses on the genesis of Karl Jaspers’ concept of existential philosophy by discussing the intention of Jaspers’<italic>Psychologie der Weltanschauungen</italic>and the impact of Martin Heidegger’s review „ Anmerkungen zu Karl Jaspers’ Psychologie der Weltanschauungen“ on Jaspers’ later works. By analyzing personal statements, letters and the consequences of Heidegger’s critique for Jaspers’ subsequent philosophical publications, particularly<italic>Die geistige Situation</italic>der Zeit and the three-volumed<italic>Philosophie</italic>, I want so show in which respect Heidegger’s review made the<italic>Psychologie der Weltanschauungen</italic>retrospectively appear as historically „ the earliest work of the later so-called modern existential philosophy“, as Jaspers put it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Wertung und Wertwiderstand. Selbsterfahrung und die antinomische Struktur der Existenz bei Jaspers und Heidegger</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Steinmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essay discusses Karl Jaspers’ concept of limit situations in his<italic>Psychology of Worldviews</italic>. In limit situations, individuals experience their finite existence in an essential way. The essay shows that the concept had great influence on Martin Heidegger, who gives two of the situations, death and guilt, a decisive role in the phenomenological analysis of human existence in<italic>Being and Time</italic>. For Jaspers’<italic>Psychology</italic>, the main emphasis lies on the individual’s spiritual counter-reaction to the experience of limit situations, which leaves the overall status of the situations unclear. The essay also shows that for Jaspers limit situations are devastating because</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Il “mondo” nella Psychologie der Weltanschauungen</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Achella</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefania</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The aim of this paper is to analyse the concept of “world” in Karl Jaspers’<italic>Psychology of Worldviews</italic>, to show how the tension between the theoreticalcontemplative and existential approaches finds evident expression in the different roles that the “world” plays in the first and second parts of this work. In the first part, the world is still the object of a subject, although this relationship is neither evaluative (as in the<italic>Wertphilosophie</italic>) nor only gnoseological, but is also the result of an Erlebnis, thus presenting itself as a lived world. In the second part, beginning with the section on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Weltanschauungen e politica</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alessiato</surname>
                           <given-names>Elena</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present contribution examines the relationship between<italic>Weltanschauungen</italic>and politics. With reference to Karl Jaspers’ first political text (<italic>Politische Stimmungen</italic>, 1917) different types of political behaviours are presented here. They correspond to the ways by which human beings experience (or can experience) the world view in the political world. In Jaspers’ picture of the political sphere we find the type of the apolitical man as the political leader, the pure politician as the fanatic of the pure ideal. By presenting different political moods, Jaspers expounds ideas about the world view, about its relationship with the whole and with the individual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Naturalism as Weltanschauung</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Staiti</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this paper I discuss Jaspers’ theory of worldviews with regard to the contemporary problem of naturalism. In particular, I consider the frequent characterization of naturalism as a worldview. First, I situate Jaspers’ conception of worldviews in the context of the philosophical debate of his time. I then turn to Jaspers’ distinction between substantial worldviews and derivative shapes of worldviews and present his construal of naturalism as a derivative shape of what he calls the sensoryspatial<italic>Weltbild</italic>. I then argue that contemporary naturalism still fits Jaspers’ description and can thus be considered a derivative shape, rather than a genuine worldview</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Die Weltanschauung zwischen Ideenflucht und Wahnsinnigkeit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gens</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Claude</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is generally recognized that Karl Jaspers was the first to define the three main criteria for a belief to be considered delusional: certainty, incorrigibility and impossibility of content. But the fundamental point for Jaspers is that we have to think of delusion not as an isolated phenomenon but as a modification of the way we live in the world, or – in Heideggerian words – of our being-in-the-world. Which kind of event could explain such a modification? Our human life is structured by worldviews, which are not mere “views” or theoretical representations but basically also moods that give its specific aspect</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Praktiken des Verstehens und Weltanschauungsanalyse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schulz</surname>
                           <given-names>Reinhard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper focuses on the relationship between Karl Jaspers’ early work and practice theories of Foucault and Bourdieu. Compared with the hermeneutical tradition (Dilthey, Gadamer, Merleau-Ponty) world views seem outdated after the end of a normative understanding of hermeneutics. As a consequence we need to turn to plural practices of understanding instead. Looking on Jaspers’<italic>Psychopathology and Psychology of Worldviews</italic>a change of perspective from and beyond Jaspers leads to a future-oriented conception of psychopathology. Practices of understanding enable an emancipatory-practical potential of therapeutic practices as well as of hermeneutic understanding in the sense of “a realization of freedom unburdened</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Gli involucri tra forma e vita:</title>
                     <subtitle>per una difesa dell’inautentico</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Donise</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present essay analyses Jasper’s concept of “<italic>Gehäuse</italic>”. The<italic>Gehäuse</italic>, “cases” or “shells”, are the forms that define subjectivity, which we work very hard to construct. When the subject experiences change or development, though, the “shell” can become too rigid and suffocating, so the subject feels the need to get out of that form, at the risk of ending up like “an oyster without the shell”. In Jaspers’ perspective, however, these “casings” are unavoidable and their dismissal is a question of “metamorphosis” rather than veritable “destruction”: as soon as one form is rejected, another one is constructed. This paper in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Multiple Orientations within the Worldviews in Psychosis and Mysticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Relevance for Psychotherapy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Škodlar</surname>
                           <given-names>Borut</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ciglenečki</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Prodromal and pre-psychotic states are characterized by pervasive instabilities on all levels of experience and could lead to what Karl Jaspers calls limit-situations (<italic>Grenzsituationen</italic>). In the process of defending against such existential instabilities or limit-situations, different strategies and mechanisms are employed to provide a shelter or enclosure (<italic>Gehäuse</italic>). In this article, we explore the transition from the limitsituations to enclosures in psychotic and mystical states. In both we can differentiate multiple orientations. Many individuals, who experience psychotic and mystical states, have in fact experiences of both, at least to some extent. Together with everyday, common-sense level of experience we can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Wahnsinns-Erzählungen.</title>
                     <subtitle>Weltanschauung und lange anhaltende Psychoseerfahrung</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hase</surname>
                           <given-names>Birgit</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schlimme</surname>
                           <given-names>Jann E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Living with ongoing psychotic experiences requires a constant reflective alignment between the parallel psychotic reality (para-actuality,<italic>Nebenwirklichkeit</italic>) and the socially shared reality (<italic>sozial geteilte Wirklichkeit</italic>). A fine-grained phenomenological analysis of this manner of living describes the required amount of reflective activity in combination with a loss of certain common-sensical habitualities, the often missing option to communicate one‘s experiences and the necessity to reframe the metaphysical insights as world-view (<italic>Weltanschauung</italic>), besides the psychotic experiences themselves, as major pitfalls and challenges of ongoing psychotic experiences. In this sense, persons with ongoing psychotic experiences are just like everybody else persons in an adventurous</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f306.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Wahn, Weltanschauung und Habitus.</title>
                     <subtitle>Zur sozialwissenschaftlichen Kritik der Theorie des Wahns im Werk von Karl Jaspers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brückner</surname>
                           <given-names>Burkhart</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thoma</surname>
                           <given-names>Samuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Karl Jaspers’ theory of delusion (<italic>General Psychopathology</italic>, 1913/1946) is still widely discussed today, much unlike his theory of worldviews, laid out in his 1919 work<italic>Psychology of Worldviews</italic>, which has more or less fallen into oblivion. Based on Jaspers’ casuistic observations of nihilistic delusion and nihilistic worldview, as presented in 1919, we first analyze the relationship between delusion and worldview – a relationship analogous to that between “psychotic process” and “development of personality” in his concept of psychopathology. We then scrutinize this categorical distinction and its underlying methodical assumptions and consider possible links between delusion and worldview. Our conclusion is that,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
