<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125vm0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">onfr17126</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BJ1491.O54413 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hedonism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ontology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Hedonist Manifesto</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Power to Exist</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ONFRAY</surname>
               <given-names>MICHEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated with an introduction by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McClellan</surname>
               <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231538367</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231538367</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/onfr17126"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Michael Onfray passionately defends the potential of hedonism to resolve the dislocations and disconnections of our melancholy age. In a sweeping survey of history's engagement with and rejection of the body, he exposes the sterile conventions that prevent us from realizing a more immediate, ethical, and embodied life. He then lays the groundwork for both a radical and constructive politics of the body that adds to debates over morality, equality, sexual relations, and social engagement, demonstrating how philosophy, and not just modern scientism, can contribute to a humanistic ethics.</p>
         <p>Onfray attacks Platonic idealism and its manifestation in Judaic, Christian, and Islamic belief. He warns of the lure of attachment to the purportedly eternal, immutable truths of idealism, which detracts from the immediacy of the world and our bodily existence. Insisting that philosophy is a practice that operates in a real, material space, Onfray enlists Epicurus and Democritus to undermine idealist and theological metaphysics; Nietzsche, Bentham, and Mill to dismantle idealist ethics; and Palante and Bourdieu to collapse crypto-fascist neoliberalism. In their place, he constructs a positive, hedonistic ethics that enlarges on the work of the New Atheists to promote a joyful approach to our lives in this, our only, world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="232"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TRANSLATOR’S INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I discovered Michel Onfray, as I suspect many have, by accident. In the summer of 2010, as an impecunious graduate student attending courses at the Sorbonne in Paris, one of the few activities I could afford was to browse bookstores. Tilting my head and crouching in the aisles, I would whittle away afternoons admiring, from A to Z, the names and titles of the remarkable French literary canon. During the course of these adventures, I lingered when I reached the Os, struck by the column of titles by this earnest-looking man named Onfray. Beyond the sheer volume of his writing—</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxxix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>A Philosophical Side Path</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Classical historiography of philosophy is constructed by wishful thinking. Strangely, the apostles of pure reason and transcendental deduction all agree in the mythology that they create and that they perpetuate with a vengeance by teaching, compiling, lecturing, writing, and publishing fables. Through repetition, these become gospel truths. Scholarly looting, unmarked citation, conceptual regurgitation of other’s work—these are the happy practices of those who edit encyclopedias, conceive lexicons, and otherwise write the history of philosophy and the textbooks in which it is inscribed.</p>
                     <p>A staggering uniformity reveals itself in this field. It is always the same entries, the same texts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Bodily Reason</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Other powerful lineages populate the history of philosophy. There are other binaries to describe the issues and people at work in the tradition. Of course, there is Idealism and Materialism; the ascetic Ideal and the hedonist Ideal; and transcendence and immanence. But equally, there is denigration of the “I” and writing about the self. On the one hand, the philosophers I have listed did not seem to value autobiographical confession or little details derived from personal experiences. On the other hand, their lives fed their thought and they acknowledged drawing lessons from life. Some are messengers who efface themselves, trying</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>A Philosophical Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idealist tradition manifests in an ad hoc way. Plato practiced a schizophrenic pedagogy: he had an oral esoteric discourse intended for elites, while offering an exoteric teaching to a greater number of people. This is an aristocratic practice of philosophy. The Academy professes that Plato is for everyone, that nothing prohibits us from taking a course on Plato. What we call his complete corpus comes from that one accessible, exoteric transmission.</p>
                     <p>There was also that secret course lavished upon chosen students, those picked from the elites of the esoteric stratum. It was presumably taught after years of training in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>An Atheological Morality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most people say they are atheist these days, but they are fooling themselves. Most atheisms are overtly nihilistic. What makes them so? European nihilism—so well described by Nietzsche—presupposes the end of the universe and the difficulty of finding another one. In the meantime, atheistic nihilism struggles between two visions of the world: the Judeo-Christian and something not yet defined, which we’ll call post-Christian, for lack of a better term—we do not fool ourselves with that, it is for lack of a better term. Only time and progress through the century will permit us to discover it. For</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>A Rule of Immanent Play</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As long as God is in charge, morality is a subsection of theology. Ever since Sinai, the True, the Good, the Positive, and the Just all come from the Decalogue. No need to philosophize, to look for foundations, a genealogy, or origins. God serves as an explanation for all of them. The tablets of the Law, Torah, Gospels, and Pauline Epistles have had their time. When God bothers to show himself, or when he delegates this mission to his most dedicated envoys (who dictate all behavior between the self and itself, the self and others, and the self and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>A Hedonist Intersubjectivity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given the existence of the neuronal machine, it has to have content, since it cannot function in a vacuum. The brain is an instrument, a means, but never an end in itself. If neuronal training proceeds according to the potentialities of the nervous system, it has to have an aim. What does one train? Why? According to what criteria? Education has to have a plan. Without a clearly defined objective, ethics is useless. What rules of the game are worth the trouble of following? What makes the game appealing?</p>
                     <p>The answer: a peaceful, joyous, happy intersubjectivity; a peace of mind</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>The Ascetic Ideal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Twenty centuries of wholesale Judeo-Christianity has left its mark on the Western body. Recycling the Pythagorean tradition and, above all, that of Plato has made the Christian European body schizophrenic. It hates itself, and it harbors the extraordinary fiction of an immaterial and immortal soul. It delights in the death drive that the dominant ideology cultivates.</p>
                     <p>If, as suggested by Crébillon,¹ analysts’ sofas or sexologists’ chairs could speak, we would likely understand many things that confound us about the gendered use of the flesh, the ways and detours of the libido, and what I call a general sexual wretchedness that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>A Libertarian Libido</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to get rid of sexual wretchedness, we must put an end to the perverse logics that enable it. These include the notion of desire-aslack; considering pleasure (in the form of the fusional couple) to be the nadir of this alleged lack; ignoring the natural necessity of the family and turning it into a concession for the libido, which is itself a problem; glorifying the monogamous, loyal couple that shares the same hearth every day; sacrificing women and the feminine within them; and the transformation of children into the ontological truth of the parents’ love. These fictions are useful</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Carnal Hospitality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The logic of instincts, passions, and impulses is undeniable. Every-one knows it, senses it, sees it, and experiences it. But there is also a rarer kind of erotic reason that is able to sculpt these blocks of savage energy. It permits us to not let nature have its brutal way, transforming humans into animals that submit to a fate determined by acephalous laws. Erotic culture combines with biological sex to produce ethical artifices, aesthetic affects, and joys that are unheard of in the jungle, cowshed, or pit.</p>
                     <p>Here, as elsewhere in ethics, as we have discussed, contracts define intellectual, civil,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>An Archipelagic Logic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some clever people, camping out in their aesthetic marketplaces and doing their philosophical commerce, actually think that a history of art is possible … As long as you keep it concise! They dissertate about concepts divorced from any context; they gloss, like Plato’s contemporaries, ideas about Beauty-in-itself, the essence of Beauty, ineffable and unspeakable Beauty, or Beauty as a vector of transcendence; that is, they insist on the truth of its existence. From it, they can derive God, who they carefully guard from danger. They get a great deal out of a schema that is so philosophically easy.</p>
                     <p>The reactionaries</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>A Psychopathology of Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary art galleries often complacently exhibit nothing but the defects of our time. Why are we obligated to admire something on a pedestal that we would despise outside of the limited context of the artistic world (confines considered sacred these days, just as religious spaces were for so long)? How can we explain this kind of schizophrenia? We condemn liberal capitalism, criticize the domination of the market, and fight against American imperialism, while simultaneously adoring symbols, icons, and emblems produced by that very world we supposedly execrate. Following the old Aristotelian principle of catharsis, we try to distance ourselves from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>A Playful Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a vulgar cynicism in this religion of merchandise. However, if we put it up against Diogenes’s philosophical cynicism, we may be able to imagine an escape from nihilism, at least within the context of aesthetics. Against its negativity, we can contrapose the positivity of Diogenes’s<italic>great cheerful health, transmission of codes,</italic>and the<italic>communicative acts</italic>. This tradition leads to a<italic>rematerialization of the real</italic>and fights, at every turn, against pathology, autism, and the rarefaction of immanence.</p>
                     <p>Ancient cynicism is hurt in many ways by its position in the dominant historiography—Hegel’s historiography. Always verging on nonsense, Hegel,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>De-Christianized Flesh</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We still have too much of a Platonic body. What does that mean? It’s a schizophrenic body, cut in two irreconcilable pieces. Moreover, we’re told that one reigns over the other: the flesh dominates the soul, matter possesses the spirit, and emotions submerge reason—all of which affirm the tenets of the ascetic ideal. On the one hand, we have the evil of incarnation; on the other hand, we have the possibility of salvation in immateriality, which, in a nonsensical paradox, we are told is invisible, impossible to identify or to locate, yet it resides<italic>in</italic>the substance all around</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>An Art of Artifice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ever since humans started humanizing themselves, they made themselves artificial, emancipating themselves from their natural condition. The first trepanations and cataract procedures proved that nature was not to be celebrated as a sweet and good provider of nothing but positivity, like some cornucopia. It also contains death, sadness, suffering, conflict, claws, beaks, and condemnation of the weak to death.</p>
                     <p>Transcending nature creates humanity. In its first stuttering movements, medicine rejected physical and psychic suffering; it invented conjurations involving different concoctions and crushed plants; it combined powders, herbs, and essences; it brought together brews with incantations and magical thinking; it used</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>The Faustian Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every existence entails an emergence from nothing, and the only prospect is to return to it someday. Life unfolds between two nothings. But the boundaries are blurred; it is very difficult to speak clearly about later, previously, down the way, before, and after. Nobody denies that a being comes from a spermatozoid and an ovum, but what are the philosophical statuses of those two separate objects? Half-alive things? Things that are potentially alive? Are there two complementary forces that are alive, but that must come together to produce another living being, one that is finally real, finally true?</p>
                     <p>Our millions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>Mapping Poverty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two centuries after the French Revolution, as an extraordinary marker of the bicentenary, the Berlin Wall toppled—torn down between the East and the West. The pope had nothing to do with it, nor did Western leaders, still less European intellectuals. The drive behind it came not from the outside, but from the inside. The Soviet system did not explode; it imploded like a machine whose internal parts had corroded. Falsely revolutionary—neither socialist nor communist—and wholly totalitarian and bureaucratic, the Soviet Union and its empire collapsed because it was not dialectical, that is, it failed to appreciate the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVENTEEN</label>
                     <title>Hedonist Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where is the Left? It is an appropriate question, but there is something more fundamental about it. When was it born? How do we find it? What defines it? What battles does it pick? What does its history look like? Who are its great figures? What are its watershed events? What are its failures, limits, and blind spots? Of course there is Socialism, Communism, Stalinism, Trotskyism, Maoism, and Bolshevism, but what is there in common between Jaurès and Lenin? Stalin and Trotsky? Mao and Mitterrand? Saint-Just and François Hollande?<italic>Theoretically,</italic>they share a desire to eliminate poverty, wretchedness, injustice, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHTEEN</label>
                     <title>A Practice of Resistance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nobody believes anymore in Blanqui’s method of insurrectional revolution. Even liberal capitalism has renounced the coup d’états theorized by Malaparte.¹ There is zero credence in the Marxist idea that changes to the economic infrastructure automatically lead to modifications of ideological superstructures. Collective and violent appropriation of the means of production doesn’t change anything: ideology originates from a logic different from the physiological processes of the modes of production.</p>
                     <p>Capitalism is fluid. It does not give up its existence or admit defeat without first having recourse to all kinds of tricks and means. We still need to do a history of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">onfr17126.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
