<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ht4xff</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">D804.66.T76U57 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Trocmé, André, 1901–1971</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Trocmé, Magda, 1901–1996</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Trocmé, André, 1901–1971</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Trocmé, Magda, 1901–1996</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Righteous Gentiles in the Holocaust</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Le Chambon-sur-Lignon</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Biography</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Pacifists</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Le Chambon-sur-Lignon</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Biography</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust, Jewish (1939–1945)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Le Chambon-sur-Lignon</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">World War, 1939–1945</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Jews</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Rescue</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
                  <subj-group>
                     <subject content-type="lcsh">Le Chambon-sur-Lignon</subject>
                  </subj-group>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">World War, 1939–1945</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Underground movements</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Le Chambon-sur-Lignon</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Le Chambon-sur-Lignon (France)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Portrait of Pacifists</book-title>
         <subtitle>Le Chambon, the Holocaust, and the Lives of André and Magda Trocmé</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Unsworth</surname>
               <given-names>Richard P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>WITH A FOREWORD BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROSE</surname>
               <given-names>PETER I.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780815651826</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0815651821</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Syracuse University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Syracuse, New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Syracuse University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j1vzwx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Explores the lives of heralded Holocaust rescuers Andre and Magda Trocme, and the people of Le Chambon-sur-Lignon France who saved thousands of Jews from the Nazis</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSE</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER I.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My Dutch wife and her older sister were hidden in an Amsterdam cellar for nearly four years during World War II. They owed their lives to the selfless sacrifice of a modern-day Good Samaritan, Cathoos Koolhaas Revers-DeWitt. Known to the children as Tante Toos, their protector was later to have another sobriquet: “Righteous Christian.” She was one of a courageous few who risked their lives to save Jews during the dark days of the Holocaust.</p>
                     <p>André and Magda Trocmé were also “Righteous Christians” who rescued, hid, and protected Jewish children—in their case, hundreds of refugee children. But unlike Tante</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author’s Note on the Memoirs</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pacifism in the Twentieth Century</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since this is a book about two remarkable twentieth century pacifists, it will be useful to understand the complexity of pacifism as it played out in the western world during their century. Two world wars and wars in Korea and Vietnam dominated the period. Roughly one hundred and fifty million people died in those wars. This country’s prolonged Cold War with the Soviet Union involved few casualties but many threats and endless tension about nuclear weapons. If you look for periods of peace, there are only twelve years of the whole twentieth century without one nation or empire being at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations and Terms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Remembering:</title>
                     <subtitle>June 1971</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was a fine Saturday morning in June, a time of the year when Geneva is at its most pleasant—a walking city with eight o’clock sunsets, temperatures in the 70s, and on most days a decent breeze off the Lac Léman. By now one could see how the garden would look, enjoy the languorous evenings, and be grateful that Geneva wasn’t yet as noisy and humid as it would be when all the windows were open in search of fresh air.</p>
                     <p>For the last five weeks, alone in his room in the Cantonal Hospital, André Trocmé had tried to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Life after June 5</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Magda had been looking forward to June and her own retirement. She had been as busy as André during these years in Geneva, teaching Italian in the Lycée d’Annemasse and as a second job teaching aspiring young linguists at the University of Geneva’s Interpreters School. In Geneva’s nest of international agencies and organizations a trilingual person like herself was much in demand. But now it was her retirement year, and she had plans for the garden and their house in Petit-Lancy, a quiet suburb on the high slopes southwest of downtown Geneva. Number 30 Avenue du Plateau was a modest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Pacifism Discovered</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>André grew up near the Belgian border in St. Quentin, where the Franco-Prussian War of 1870–71 shadowed his early years: a disaster for France, for St. Quentin and for André’s family. Then World War I dominated his teenage years, with the destruction and evacuation of St. Quentin, and with his experience as a refugee.</p>
                     <p>By the end of the Great War, his direction was set. Even though he was too young to have been conscripted, he had seen enough of war to understand its horrors, enough to question its rationale, and enough to know he would never accept it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Fathers and Sons</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>André Trocmé had a father whose influence on him was great—sometimes for better, sometimes for worse, but always substantial and nearly always burdensome. The burden of being a Trocmé, however, was not Paul Trocmé’s invention, for he had a father (Eugène) who in turn had a father (Jean-Pierre Eugène), and each one laid that burden of family reputation on the next. It seemed to them all that being a Trocmé involved a responsibility to history as well as to family. For hundreds of years, Trocmé fathers had been laying down expectations for their sons, and it was no different</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Out of Siberia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Magda Trocmé’s independent spirit and her habit of practical response to human needs came straight out of her Siberian heritage. Her ancestors on both the Italian and the Russian side were aristocratic people born to wealth and privilege, but the Russians in her family tree were notable for not allowing privilege to blind them to the human misery at the bottom of society, a misery endured by the moujiks (slaves) to serve the interests of the rich. Not so her Italian ancestors. They were much more inclined to assume that privilege was their birthright and poverty was other people’s fate.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>A Renegade Gentleman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When on that snowy day in February of 1917 André and his family were deposited in the Flemish countryside of southwest Belgium, they qualified as refugees. They had been uprooted and thrown out of their home and country. Now they had to scratch out a living by some combination of their own wit and the kindness of others, others who owed them nothing beyond a shared humanity.</p>
                     <p>André realized that among the forms of wealth he enjoyed as a child was a broader network of connections than most, a network he took for granted. It was his father’s task to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Military Misadventure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>André knew he was a renegade, but it wasn’t a status he aspired to. He was at home as a member of the haute bourgeoisie Protestante. While the Protestant upper class was bourgeois and not noble, it was a sort of nonroyal aristocracy, exemplifying the meaning of the original Greek term: the morally and intellectually best who act in the interest of all. At the same time he was deeply conflicted about many things that came with upper class standing. His issue was straightforward: could he continue to enjoy his social status without running afoul of the religious and ethical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Turnaround Year</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1925 both Magda and André left for New York, Magda in August and André in September. Both were searching and escaping: searching for wider dimensions to their intended careers and escaping from the family and the cultural constraints that constricted their future. Neither one was ready to comply with conventional expectations.</p>
                     <p>André was on his way to New York because he had won a scholarship to Union Theological Seminary. He took it, but without great enthusiasm. It was actually a third choice. His first was archeological study in the Near East, but he lost out on that scholarship when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Real Church, Actual Church</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some days it felt very confining for André to be returning to the bosom of a family whose bourgeois values were the bars that had caged his freedom. He had not defined freedom as liberty from duty or anything of the sort. Alexandre Vinet, the man on whom his thesis was focused, had written a mandate that expressed André’s vision: “I want a man to be a complete, spontaneous individual, in order that he may submit, as a man, to the general interest” (A. Vinet 1837, 178; see also A. Trocmé 1926, 42). It was André’s dream to fulfill his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Le Chambon in the Thirties</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Soon after André’s return to Sin-le-Noble, a letter came from Roger Casalis, a minister friend who had begun to feel restless in this isolated rural parish. He had no car, nor would the parish provide him with a motorbike to get to his meetings and pastoral calls. By now he wanted out. To the church council, he presented urgent health problems as the reason for leaving. He did not want them to be without a minister, however, so he was searching for a replacement. Would André be interested? André knew only a bit about the area, and what he knew</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Understanding Catastrophe:</title>
                     <subtitle>1939–1941</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The years from 1939 to 1944 are sometimes referred to as the heroic period in the story of Le Chambon-sur-Lignon and its surrounding towns. Yet the very word “heroic” is one that local people would never use to describe their own actions in creating a city of refuge. It goes against the grain of their Huguenot heritage.</p>
                     <p>The same was true for Magda and André Trocmé. In their view, being true to the principles of nonviolence was nothing heroic. Yet there were some courageous undertakings, some which involved high risk and others that involved little more than stubborn refusal to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>The War Worsens:</title>
                     <subtitle>1942–1943</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the opening months of 1942, Marshal Pétain was still popular in sectors of this new French State. Church authorities were still willing to regard some of the more odious actions the government took (e.g., the Jewish Statute of October 3) as necessary compromises made in exchange for the Vichy government’s independent status. Pétain’s emphasis on the three virtues of work, family, and fatherland was accepted as a commonplace template for the moral reform of the French nation. Church publications made repeated favorable comment on this celebrated triptych. The president of the ÉRF, Pastor Boegner, was still in support of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Climax and Denouement:</title>
                     <subtitle>1943–1944</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once liberated from the concentration camp, Trocmé and Theis went about their business in Le Chambon, more aware that they were being watched, but seemingly immune to the paralysis of fear. On the Sunday after their return, the two parsons and Darcissac told the congregation their story of Saint-Paul d’Eyjeaux. The pews were full and the atmosphere was a warm one. It was clear that all three men had earned the admiration of the parishioners. Unfortunately, however, LeForestier’s assurance to Trocmé, Theis, and Darcissac that the duck would keep on walking automatically in their absence was a metaphor overtaken by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>The Bridge from War to Peace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At age twenty, a young German-speaking Swiss by the name of Hans-Ruedi Weber was looking for a project, something that would help him sort out his future. He had heard about the work of the Secours Suisse aux Enfants in Le Chambon-sur-Lignon, and offered his services if they would have him. He was accepted and arrived in Le Chambon in January of 1944.</p>
                     <p>Hans kept a diary during the nine months of his service. His entry for June 14 notes the return of André Trocmé from his months in Château de Perdyer. He also records hearing the British airplanes that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Versailles:</title>
                     <subtitle>The IFOR Years</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Trocmés’ final four years in Le Chambon-sur-Lignon were also their first years of new and different responsibilities. Only a few of his parishioners shared Trocmés’ understanding that the hard work of reconciliation was as important as the courage of resistance.</p>
                     <p>This was also a unique opportunity for Magda. She was clearly identified as a partner in this new ministry. The masthead of the MIR said “Secrétaires: André Trocmé et Magda Trocmé.” And when Magda filled a speaking engagement, she was introduced as “co-director of the Maison de la Réconciliation.” These were small but not petty acknowledgments that said to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Versailles:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rebuilding Peace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Italian visits were, like those in Germany, a return to familiar nations and networks, and the Trocmés had a handle at least on what had happened there during the decade from 1935 to 1945. America was another story. Both Trocmés had done their graduate studies there. Both felt at ease in the United States and in the English language, but they were not nearly as familiar with what had transpired in America during the two decades since their single year as foreign students there.</p>
                     <p>Although an ecclesiastical pariah in France, André found himself something of a celebrity in American</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Geneva and Beyond</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In May of 1960, André and Magda left Versailles and made the move to Petit-Lancy, a small suburb on a hill just southwest of Geneva. A generous Quaker had rented them a house there at a reasonable price. The move turned out to be just the right one, both for the St. Gervais parish and for the Trocmés.</p>
                     <p>The Swiss Reformed church had no anti-pacifist policy concerning its clergy, nor did it forbid its ministers to speak of public and political issues when interpreting the Gospel for today’s world. Further, at the time André joined the other clergy at St.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Partial Chronology of the Trocmés’ Lives and Events</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1vzwx.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
