<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN49.W552 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anne (Mother of the Virgin Mary), Saint</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">In motion pictures</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Thomas, à Becket, Saint, 1118?–1170</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">In literature</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kolbe, Maximilian, Saint, 1894–1941</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">In literature</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christian saints in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christian saints in art</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Saints in motion pictures</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Saints in opera</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christian hagiography</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Saints Alive</book-title>
         <subtitle>Word, Image, and Enactment in the Lives of the Saints</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WILLIAMS</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773537088</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773590991</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1q5zsz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>David Williams shows that images associated with saints are not simply illustrations of written accounts, nor are the gestures, prayers, and liturgical practices of devotees of saints' cults simply derivative of them. Rather, images and enactments expand and complete the text, adding visual and dramatic dimensions. Williams demonstrates his ideas through discussion and case studies of three saints: the biblical figure of Saint Anne, mother of the Virgin; the medieval English martyr Saint Thomas Becket; and Saint Maximillian Mary Kolbe, who gave his life to save that of another in the Auschwitz concentration camp. A remarkable study of text, image, and enactment, Saints Alive presents a complete study of the depiction of saints that will change the way they are understood.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The etymology of the word “text,” like all etymology, reveals buried connotations that haunt the contemporary meaning beneath the level of active memory. For most of us, “text” means the written document, and even in the more nuanced semiological concept, texts are “sign-systems, linguistic or non-linguistic” (<italic>Concise Oxford Dictionary of Literary Terms</italic>), the plural “systems” suggesting the disintegration of the unified concept of “text” into texts of different kinds: verbal, visual, aural, gestural, and so on. The etymology of the word, however, seems to resist divisions, indicating integration and unification: the participle of the verb, <italic>textus</italic>, from which we get</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>WORDS, IMAGES, AND ENACTMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The great power of words consists in their ability to represent thought as language, enabling the speaker to communicate complicated intellectual processes and extensive discursive descriptions. No other sign system achieves this. The image, although more effective than the word in presenting in a solitary, contained way what it represents, cannot comment on its object or analyze its own method of representation as language can. Similarly, gesture, or enactment, while performing what it represents and, in this sense, closer to its object, cannot reflect upon itself or the nature of its own operation. Words can talk about words; images and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>SAINT ANNE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>For a figure with no historical basis, to whom there is no reference in scripture, whose very existence depends on logical deduction, Saint Anne has had a remarkable career. Although her life cannot be verified by any historical source, we are sure she existed, if only because Mary, the mother of Jesus, had to have had a mother herself. Her Hebrew name, Hannah, is probably derived from identification with the prophetess Hannah, and the foundation for the rest of her rich and complex history is found in the <italic>Protevangelium of James</italic>, a second-century apocryphal Greek document. A Latin text of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>SAINT THOMAS BECKET</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Few Lives of mediaeval saints are more voluminously documented than that of the twelfth-century Archbishop of Canterbury, murdered in his cathedral by four knights acting on the wishes of King Henry II. The force of the historical in Thomas’s <italic>Vita</italic> is assured by the fact that the principal authors of his first biographies were men who knew him and were present at his martyrdom. There are many accounts of the murder as well as of other aspects of Thomas Becket’s life, most of which are available in James Craigie Robertson’s <italic>Materials for the History of Thomas Becket, Archbishop of Canterbury.</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>SAINT MAXIMILIAN KOLBE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>With the last saint to be discussed, we have a modern figure historicized according to modern standards. There is ample documentation concerning his parents, his childhood, his youth and mature years, and his death. There are many letters, articles, conferences, and other documents written by him and a host of eyewitnesses who knew him, some still living. His life is documented in a twentieth-century manner. In comparison to the saints we have discussed, however, our twentieth-century saint possesses a much smaller cult and what might be called an incipient iconography. Thus the historical dimension of the text that is Saint</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The idea of an ancient loss of an original symbiosis of the arts is a recurrent one, and there have even been attempts to retrieve that unity. Such was behind Wagner’s theory of the <italic>Gesamtkunstwerk</italic> and may have been on the mind of the young Stephen Daedalus, as well. The desire to bring into mutuality the verbal, the visual, and the gestural has behind it a lingering sense that the divorce of these forms is somehow a limitation, not an expansion, of human expressivity. Yet there is a loss more ancient than that which occurred within the arts: the loss</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1q5zsz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
