<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Personhood, identity and care in advanced old age</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Higgs</surname>
               <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gilleard</surname>
               <given-names>Chris</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>05</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781447319078</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1447319079</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Policy Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bristol, UK; Chicago, IL, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Policy Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1t89766"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How do we sustain agency and identity amidst the frailty of advanced old age? What role does care play in this process? Pushing forward new sociological theory, this book explores the theoretical and practical issues raised by age and infirmity. It begins with a theoretical examination of the fourth age, interrogating notions of agency, identity and personhood, as well as the impact of frailty, abjection and ‘othering’. It then applies this analysis to issues of care. Exploring our collective hopes and fears concerning old age and the ends of people’s lives, this is essential reading on one of the biggest social issues of our time.Pushing forward new sociological theory, this book explores the theoretical and practical issues raised by ageing, and the associated problems of mental and physical frailty in later life.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Old age and the fourth age paradigm</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The world’s population is ageing at an unprecedented rate. If an ‘ageing society’ is defined as one where at least 10% of the population is aged 65 years and above, the number of such ageing societies is projected to increase from 59 in 2010 to 138 in 2050 (UN, 2014). By 2050 the world will be home to some 1.5 billion people aged 65 and over, more agedness than the world has ever experienced. Not only are there increasing numbers of ageing societies (Hyde and Higgs, 2016), but some of the already ageing societies are undergoing a process of ‘hyper-ageing’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Interrogating personhood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fourth age imaginary embodies fears of dependency, frailty and the gradual loss of our sense of agency, identity and our status as persons. This fear, particularly as it is represented in the fear of ‘losing one’s mind’ or of developing Alzheimer’s, brings to the fore questions of agency, identity and personhood. When we first wrote about the fourth age, we described it as ‘ageing without agency’ (Gilleard and Higgs, 2010), treating mental decline as a decline in ‘agency’. By so doing we wanted to acknowledge how closely allied fears are of an unwanted old age with fears of losing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Agency, identity and personhood in the social sciences</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we outlined the various ways that terms like ‘agency’, ‘identity’ and ‘personhood’ have been understood within philosophy, and how such understandings have been applied particularly in response to the problems of mental infirmity in later life. We argued that the de-construction of the term ‘person’ into the separable issues of agency and identity may provide a more useful framework through which to interpret these problems than by approaches based on the more generic term ‘personhood’. Irrespective of their ‘powers’ to express agency and identity, the common humanity of people with infirmities can serve as the underlying</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Frailty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The emergence of what has been called a ‘hyper-cognitive’ society (Post, 1995) and its structural individualisation (Beck and Beck-Gernsheim, 2002) has made the body a key site of identity and embodied difference. The ‘corporeal capital’ that could be said to be associated with owning a fit body has become a critical resource throughout life (Higgs, 2012). In later life, being fit and healthy enables effective participation in the cultures of the third age, and serves as a key point of reference for older people in judging how well they are doing and how effectively they are managing to age at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Understanding abjection</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If frailty has come to signify the vulnerability of older people, abjection reveals the distaste associated with such frailty. In the past, as long as charity was in part a matter of conferring spiritual benefits onto potential donors, the cause and character of the recipients’ impoverishment was largely irrelevant. When poverty and dependency represented the collective fate of so many of the common population, the presence of so many poor provided a ready means by which elites could add spiritual value to their existing material resources (Himmelfarb, 1984; Fraser and Gordon, 1994; Jütte, 1994). This pre-modern ‘sacral’ view of poverty</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>The moral imperative of care</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We began this book by outlining our formulation of the fourth age as the cultural reconfiguration of all those aspects of old age that are most associated with fear and disgust. Such a social imaginary, we argued, draws on past and present representations of age as frailty, abjection and loss. The feared loss of agency, identity and independence that constitutes a pervasive element of this social imaginary is now centred on age-associated mental decline linked to ‘Alzheimer’s disease’ (Cutler, 2015). To provide a fuller context to the representation of this anticipated ‘loss’ within the fourth age’s social imaginary, we reviewed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Care work</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we explored care and its generic realisation in a variety of social relations. Although care can be viewed through the lens of moral philosophy – as a moral duty that is realised through a set of practices embodying distinct virtues – care itself, we argued, can only ever be socially realised within particular forms of relationship. Questions such as who should receive and who should provide care, how and where care should be delivered, and what care means to those who are carers and to those who are cared for will elicit different answers at different</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Care without limits</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous two chapters we addressed the nature of care, conceptualised variously as a labour of love, a contractual relationship, a professional practice or as a moral and material imperative. While we have represented the person being cared for as already old, frail and potentially abject, we have recognised that the degree of any person’s ‘frailure’ can be magnified or minimised by the narratives and practices of care within which their frailty is embedded. While pervasively present within any care relationship, the social imaginary of the fourth age can be challenged, kept at bay or actively resisted, just as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whatever the balance between successful and unsuccessful ageing that is achieved by a particular generation or society, each success creates in its shadow new possibilities of failure. As more people age there are more examples, of both success and failure. The presence of the unsuccessfully aged, whether framed as the ‘aged and infirm’ or as those ‘impotent through age’ sees them become the objects of what we have called society’s moral imperative of care. Where once their numbers were few and their circumstances more amenable to resolution, in contemporary ageing societies their predicament has become more challenging as the later</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t89766.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
