<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125xmw</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">sche17138</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BQ2607.S35 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mahānāma, active 5th century. Mahāvaṃśa</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Buddhist literature, Pali</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading the<italic>Mahavamsa</italic>
         </book-title>
         <subtitle>The Literary Aims of a Theravada Buddhist History</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Scheible</surname>
               <given-names>Kristin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231542609</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231542607</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/sche17138"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Vamsa</italic>is a dynamic genre of Buddhist history filled with otherworldly characters and the exploits of real-life heroes. These narratives collapse the temporal distance between Buddha and the reader, building an emotionally resonant connection with an outsized religious figure and a longed-for past. The fifth-century Pali text<italic>Mahavamsa</italic>is a particularly effective example, using metaphor and other rhetorical devices to ethically transform readers, to stimulate and then to calm them.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Reading the Mahavamsa</italic>advocates a new, literary approach to this text by revealing its embedded reading advice (to experience<italic>samvega</italic>and<italic>pasada</italic>) and affective work of metaphors (the Buddha's dharma as light) and salient characters (<italic>nagas</italic>). Kristin Scheible argues that the<italic>Mahavamsa</italic>requires a particular kind of reading. In the text's proem, special instructions draw readers to the metaphor of light and the<italic>nagas</italic>, or salient snake-beings, of the first chapter.<italic>Nagas</italic>are both model worshippers and unworthy hoarders of Buddha's relics. As nonhuman agents, they challenge political and historicist readings of the text. Scheible sees these slippery characters and the narrative's potent and playful metaphors as techniques for refocusing the reader's attention on the text's emotional aims. Her work explains the<italic>Mahavamsa</italic>'s central motivational role in contemporary Sri Lankan Buddhist and nationalist circles. It also speaks broadly to strategies of reading religious texts and to the internal and external cues that give such works lives beyond the page.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A NOTE ON TRANSLITERATION AND TRANSLATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the study of religions, we find that certain key texts come to define their interpretive communities, for both the communities themselves and the scholars who study them.¹ Texts are an appealing source for the cultivation of understanding; they seem stable and fixed in a way that a religious community, comprising people who change through time and contexts, simply is not. But a text is not a source unless it is brought to life through reading and interpretation, irrespective of the vicissitudes of time and context. Reading and interpretation necessarily negate, to some extent, the stability or fixedness of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>INSTRUCTIONS, ADMONITIONS, AND ASPIRATIONS IN VAṂSA PROEMS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The proems (introductory verses) of both the<italic>Dīpavaṃsa</italic>and the<italic>Mahāvaṃsa</italic>call for their audience’s active participation through the act of reading or hearing the stories. The<italic>Dīpavaṃsa</italic>clearly aims for what I am calling “religious satisfaction” (<italic>pasāda</italic>)—namely, the feeling of confidence and inclusion in the Buddha’s<italic>sāsana</italic>that results from the performed reading by “good people” (<italic>sujana</italic>).¹ The text suggests that the act of reading or hearing will be transformative for the right reader-hearer; the Dipavamsa’s proem constructs and anticipates a certain expected community of reception and transformation. The<italic>Mahāvaṃsa’s</italic>proem recapitulates this construction of a “textual community”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>RELOCATING THE LIGHT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The hearer is primed by the explicit directions given in each proem, but the<italic>Mahāvaṃsa</italic>further elaborates on the transformative power of the text through its masterful use of metaphor to conjure the desired emotional states named in the proem. The Mahāvaṃsa does not just repeat the<italic>Dīpavaṃsa</italic>’s charge to the readers but extends it through the narrative of the text itself in its treatment of the metaphor of light in the story of the transformation of the<italic>nāgas.</italic>The<italic>nāgas</italic>are no longer read as simply the catalysts for the loving compassion and attention of the Buddha (as in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>NĀGAS, TRANSFIGURED FIGURES INSIDE THE TEXT, RUMINATIVE TRIGGERS OUTSIDE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why<italic>nāgas</italic>? Just as the conception of the other gives rise to a deepened awareness of self, the understanding of the<italic>nāga</italic>in the<italic>Mahāvamsa</italic>urges the reader to assume a certain understanding of himself or herself. The sense of self that is derived from reading this narrative peppered with<italic>nāgas</italic>is a temporally bounded one and ultimately provokes the reader into realizing his or her own immediate and urgent responsibility and agency toward his or her own moral development. As we saw in chapter 1, the proems of the two<italic>vaṃsas</italic>I focus on enunciate the reader’s work in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>NĀGAS AND RELICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As liminal characters, the betwixt and in-betweeners,<italic>nāgas</italic>mediate the dark and the light. They are characters precisely poised to be interpreters for the outside reader-hearer through the text. As we have seen,<italic>nāgas</italic>often act as attention getters within the text, functioning as red flags to denote important passages, but that is not all they do. In the previous chapter, we saw<italic>nāgas</italic>in close proximity with the living Buddha. In the case of Bhūridatta, this proximity is in fact a shared ontology of sorts and a window into the eventual soteriological aptitude of even the lowest born—the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>HISTORICIZING (IN) THE PĀLI DĪPAVAṂSA AND MĀHAVAṂSA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As histories, the<italic>vaṃsas</italic>are explicitly concerned with linking the “good people” of the textual community to the Buddha through both narratives and the actual presence of relics. The Pali<italic>Mahāvaṃsa</italic>is at once historical and literary—the former because it was written in a particular cultural and temporal moment about other events in the deep recesses of the collective imagination or inherited cultural memory of its community of production; the latter because it employs devices such as metaphor and plot development to tell that story to its audience. But the categories “history” and “the literary” are far from mutually</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The pāli Mahāvaṃsa has survived through fifteen hundred years of history to become a seminal text of Sri Lankan Buddhism. It has survived thanks in part to the scribes who were charged along the way with copying it (palm-leaf manuscripts do not hold up indefinitely in the Sri Lankan climate). It survived the early translation performed by George Turnour and the consequent attention it garnered from Western Orientalists. And it survived through numerous other intervening interpretations, finally making its way into the hands of modern interpretive communities and scholars alike. Modern scholars must be grateful to all these scribes and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">sche17138.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
