<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD638.G25 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Time</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Given World and Time</book-title>
         <subtitle>Temporalities in Context</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Miller</surname>
               <given-names>Tyrus</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789639776272</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9786155211591</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Budapest; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Tyrus Miller</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7829/j.ctt2jbmxx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The interconnections of time with historical thought and knowledge have come powerfully to the fore since the 1970s. An international group of scholars, from a range of fields including literary theory, history of ideas, cultural anthropology, philosophy, intellectual history and theology, philology, and musicology, address the matter of time and temporalities. The volume’s essays, divided into four main topical groups question critically the key problem of context, connecting it to the problem of time. Contexts, the essays suggest, are not timeless. Time and its contexts are only partly “given” to us: to the primordial donations of time and world correspond our epistemic, moral, and practical modes of receiving what has been granted. The notion of context may have radically different parameters in different historical, cultural, and disciplinary situations. Topics include the deep antiquity, and the timeless time of eternity, as well as formal philosophies of history and the forms of histories implicit in individual and community experience. The medium specific use of time and history are examined with regard to song, image, film, oral narration, and legal discourse.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="378"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Tyrus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In his 1991 novel <italic>Time’s Arrow</italic>, the British writer Martin Amis, playing a postmodern “narrative game with time” (as Paul Ricoeur would say) explored the implications of a very simple narrative twist for our historical and moral perception. How would some key twentieth-century historical event, an event as ineluctable as the Nazi seizure of power and the unfolding of Nazi genocide, appear from a radically different temporal perspective? And what might this perspective shift tell us about the way our historical and moral judgments carry along with them, enfolded into their conclusions, assumptions about the relation of time and its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Walking Backwards into the Future:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Conception of Time in the Ancient Near East</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maul</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefan M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>If we regard the Akkadian (i.e., Assyrian–Babylonian)¹ terms that designate “past” and “future” as more than simple equivalents to the corresponding English terms, we make an astounding discovery. An examination of temporal terms such as “earlier” (Akkadian: <italic>pāna</italic>, <italic>pān</italic>; <italic>pānānu</italic>(<italic>m</italic>); <italic>pāni</italic>; <italic>pānû</italic>(<italic>m</italic>)) or “former times, past” (Akkadian: <italic>pānātu</italic>; <italic>pānītu</italic>(<italic>m</italic>), <italic>pānū</italic>) shows that these are all related to the Akkadian <italic>pānum</italic>, or “front,” plural <italic>pānū</italic>, or “face.” The Sumerian² equivalents to the Akkadian terms for the past are formed with the word <italic>igi</italic>, which means “eye,” “face” and also “front.” In the Akkadian and Sumerian terms for the past, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Epic Remains:</title>
                     <subtitle>Seeing and Time in the<italic>Odyssey</italic>
                     </subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bassi</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>When we think about the various visible objects that comprise the landscape of the ancient Greek epic, the first to come to mind are the Shield of Achilles, the scepter of the Achaians, and the bed shared by Penelope and Odysseus. These objects—whether unique or of a general class—are like snapshots in the epic narrative. Individually, they have been the focus of extensive scholarship on the poems, principally in terms of their metonymic relationship to the narrative at large (<italic>ecphrasis</italic>), their expression of vividness (<italic>enargeia</italic>), or their function in the exposition of character and social status. But the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Fourier and the Saint-Simonians on the Shape of History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beecher</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>One of the main intellectual consequences of the French Revolution was to leave many Europeans with the sense that the optimistic, rationalistic and egalitarian ideology of the Enlightenment had exhausted itself and been discredited with the failure of the radical phase of the revolution. There was a sense on many sides that the Enlightenment had been “on trial” during the French Revolution and that the understanding of human nature and history offered by the Enlightenment had proved inadequate. The period that followed the French Revolution was therefore marked by an intellectual reaction leading in two directions. First, to the belief</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>World History According to Katrina</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dimock</surname>
                           <given-names>Wai Chee</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>How does Hurricane Katrina change our understanding of the United States, the lengths and widths of its history, as well as its place in the history of the world? As a catastrophe that casts into doubt the efficacy and security of the nation-state, what alternatives does it suggest, what other forms of shelter, what other ways to organize human beings into meaningful groups? And how might these nonstandard groupings challenge American Studies as a discipline, given their deviations from the foundational norm, and the shape of the future they portend?</p>
                     <p>The nation-state seems “unbundled” by the hurricane in ways both</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Intricate Temporalities:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Transfiguration of Proper and “Improper” Sounds from Christian to Jewish Environments</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HaCohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Three modes of communication situate the background of this paper. They relate to three realms of experience and to the intersections and conflations of their respective configurations. These modes are music, narrative, and ritual. All three engage us in the real present—they call our attention at a certain moment, they demand from us a blank duration for the projection of their inhering experiences, and they launch us into “unreal” presents whose mental fabrication they stimulate.² When we hear a story, listen to a piece of music, or attend a ritual, we are often willingly interpreting their messages by assuming</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Quoting from the Past, or Dealing with Temporality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Duelke</surname>
                           <given-names>Britta</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In her famous essay on Walter Benjamin, Hannah Arendt summarized his theoretical reflections on history, tradition and authority in the following formula: “Insofar as the past has been transmitted as tradition, it possesses authority; insofar as authority presents itself historically, it becomes tradition.”² We will never know whether Benjamin himself would have endorsed these lines, which clearly show the hand of Arendt. Yet the formula does have the appearance of something that comes close to Benjamin’s very own style of thinking and writing, to such an extent that one could easily take it for a quotation of the “real” Benjamin.³</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Taking Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>Temporal Representations and Cultural Politics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Terdiman</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>On the one hand, the exhilarating temporality of revolution. On the other, the baleful “burden of the past.” These images identify—at their polar limits—two contrasting projections of time. Of course they are very different. But both are grounded in the materiality of social life. Here I contrast them with a conflicting conception of time that emerges in the projection of Postmodernism. My objective is to suggest what is at stake, theoretically and politically, in contemporary representations of time.</p>
                     <p>The past’s dead hand, and our experience of the inertia with which it weighs us down, clashes with one of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Image-Times, Image-Histories, Image-Thinking</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Soussloff</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Derived from the Latin, i.e., <italic>imago</italic> (f. noun) and <italic>imagines</italic> (pl.), the terminology and the concepts adhering to “image” have both fascinated and perplexed scholars, most of them philosophers, psychoanalysts, and historians of religion, art, and film. To explore these etymologies today, however, seems superfluous since the term has an expanded significance in all media studies and practices, including computer technologies, digital and analog photography and film, television, and video. While the conceptual intricacies associated with the image and its cognates in the Western tradition stretch back to ancient Greece and have led to a wide discrepancy of views regarding</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Documentary Re-enactments:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Paradoxical Temporality That Is Not One</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nichols</surname>
                           <given-names>Bill</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Re-enactments, the more or less authentic recreation of prior events, provided a staple element of documentary representation until they were slain by the “verité boys” of the 1960s (Ricky Leacock, D.A. Pennebaker, David and Albert Maysles, Fred Wiseman and others) who proclaimed everything, except what took place in front of the camera without script, rehearsal or direction, to be a fabrication—inauthentic. Observational or direct cinema generated an honest record of what would have happened had the camera not been there, or what did happen as a result of recording what happens when people are filmed. Observational temporality possessed the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Time and Progress—Time as Progress:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Enlightened Sermon by William Robertson</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kontler</surname>
                           <given-names>László</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the introductory studies of his seminal <italic>Futures Past</italic>, Reinhart Koselleck offers an engaging and succinct illustration of the course of what he calls the “temporalization of history” in European thought during the early-modern period. Koselleck conceives the process as a whole in terms of the changes in the perception of the “compression” (or “acceleration”) of time that, supposedly, precedes the onset of the future in the thought of these past generations: “For Luther, the compression of time is a visible sign that, according to God’s will, the Final Judgment is imminent, that the world is about to end. For</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Religious Revivals:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Binds of Religion and Modernity in Friedrich Nietzsche’s<italic>The Anti-Christ</italic>and Richard Wright’s<italic>The Outsider</italic>
                     </subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wegley</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>One linchpin that holds together Western modernity, the secularization thesis, is crucial in narrating the historical progress of society away from religious control to individual determination. The thesis can be seen as comprising six components: 1) the creation of different institutional apparati that separate religion from politics, 2) the depoliticization and privatization of religion, 3) the decline in religious belief, 4) the development of cultural identity, 5) the rise of the state as governmental form, and 6) the production of capitalist markets.¹ Together these components describe the new phenomenon that constitutes modernity as different from religious and traditional cultures. Moving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Hetero-Temporalities of Post-Socialism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rofel</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Time has, if you will forgive the paradoxical phrasing, long been a terrain for projects of social justice and utopian dreams. As Susan Buck-Morss has recently pointed out, this function of time is self-consciously true in historically sedimented ways for the praxis of formerly socialist nation-states.¹ What has become of time in the aftermath of socialism? My answer to this question will focus on China, a country whose continuously radical transformations have coursed through the twentieth century and now into the twenty-first. Unlike in the countries of eastern Europe, China’s Communist Party still holds the reins of state power. Yet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>The Politics of Temporality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Heidegger, Bourdieu, Benjamin, Derrida</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hoy</surname>
                           <given-names>David Couzens</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>“The time of our lives”—this expression condenses into one phrase a series of questions that could require much more than one lifetime to answer. Is the time of our lives a function of a life as a whole, a life-time, or can it be condensed into a single moment of vision? Does a life have a unity that runs through it, or is the unity of time, and of a life, a narrative, a story, a fiction, or even an illusion? In this essay the question that particularly interests me is, what notion of time is the time that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Eternity No More:</title>
                     <subtitle>Walter Benjamin on the Eternal Return</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Tyrus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>On January 6, 1938, Walter Benjamin wrote to Max Horkheimer from San Remo to report on a remarkable development in his thinking about his Baudelaire studies and about the larger framework of the <italic>Passagenwerk</italic>, Benjamin’s decade-long historical research about nineteenth-century Paris, a project that he described as an <italic>Urgeschichte der Moderne</italic> (an archaic history of modernity). The occasion of this development was his encounter with a largely forgotten text by the famous insurrectionist Auguste Blanqui, entitled <italic>L’éternité par les astres</italic> (Eternity According to the Stars). This short book comprised a set of cosmological speculations written in prison by the old</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>A Microscope for Time:</title>
                     <subtitle>What Benjamin and Klages, Einstein and the Movies Owe to Distant Stars</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clausberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Karl</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In today’s day and age, upheavals in human worlds of image and media are preferably traced back to technical achievements. The history of optical media—camera obscura, photography, the cinema, television, etc.—seems meanwhile firmly established as a prime example of such means of viewing. But how well do these perspectives of progress fit the “nature” of humankind, which has somehow struggled through the channels of anthropological predispositions, neurobiological influences, <italic>et al</italic>. to the peaks of civilization? Using a short and anonymously published text from the mid-nineteenth century by a Berlin lay-astronomer, whose considerable impact is suggestively illustrated in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>365</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbmxx.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
