<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Theology in the Flesh</book-title>
         <subtitle>How Embodiment and Culture Shape the Way We Think about Truth, Morality, and God</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sanders</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506408422</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506408427</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506408439</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506408435</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1b3t7k7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Metaphors and other mental tools are used to reason (not just speak) about God, salvation, truth, and morality. Figurative language structures our theological and moral reasoning in powerful ways. This book uses an approach known as cognitive linguistics to explore the incredibly rich ways our conceptual tools, derived from embodied life and culture, shape the way we understand Christian teachings and practices. The cognitive revolution has generated amazing insights into how human minds make sense of the world. This book applies these insights to the ways Christians think about topics such as God, justice, sin, and salvation. It shows that Christians often share a set of very general ideas but disagree on what the Bible means or the moral stances we should take. It explains why Christians often develop a number of appropriate but sometimes incompatible ways to understand the Bible and various doctrines. It assists Christians in understanding those with whom they disagree. Hopefully, simply better understanding how and why people think the way they do will foster better dialogue and greater humility.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One might wonder what difference it makes whether we think of divine transcendence as God “above” us or as God “ahead of” us. It matters because we use these simple words to construct deep theological meaning. In this case, they are distinctive metaphors that lead us to very different ways of thinking about God’s relationship to us. Those who think of God as above us tend to conclude that our language never “reaches” up to God, and so, God is fundamentally unknowable. However, if one thinks of God as ahead of us on a path, then, though we may never</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>From Embodiment to Mental Models</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The recent revolution in cognitive science has investigated how human minds make sense of our experience, uncovering the ways we find meaning in everything from various shapes to blinking lights. Cognitive linguistics is part of this revolutionary discovery. The study of cognitive linguistics began in the 1970s and is an influential approach to meaning construction used by an international body of scholars.¹ Cognitive linguistics examines how we think about the entire range of human experience, including causation, motion, time, relationships, entities, and emotions.² The research is interdisciplinary in nature, involving fields such as psychology, anthropology, neuroscience, philosophy, sign language, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Metaphors and Other Conceptual Structures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter continues the survey of some of the important mental structures used by everyone to make meaning: image schemas, conceptual metaphors, conceptual metonymy, and conceptual blending.¹</p>
                     <p>Concepts such as balance and containment are fundamental to our thinking. Politicians speak of a “balanced approach” to government revenues and spending. We speak of balanced personalities, the balance of power, balance of viewpoints represented, the balance of justice, and so on. Containers have an interior and exterior, such that what is inside the container is separated from what is outside. We apply the conceptual structure of containment to notions such as time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Truth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Truth is an important concept for humans and cognitive linguistics helps us think about various aspects of truth discussed in theology and philosophy. The following discussion consists of four sections: (1) the range of meanings of truth, (2) the importance of human embodiment for understanding truth, (3) the meaning of objective truth or truth from God’s perspective, and (4) an examination of panhuman truth, with a special focus on concepts of time.</p>
                     <p>For many languages, the concept of<italic>truth</italic>has a range of meanings. In English, we speak of<italic>discovering, covering up, distorting</italic>, and<italic>twisting</italic>the truth, which employ the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Meaning in Community</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We know what it is like to read a text, hear speech, or see gestures and understand their meaning. Some of the implications of a cognitive linguistics account are developed here in contrast to some alternative views regarding how meaning arises. Though this chapter makes use of what was discussed in chapters two and three, most of that material is not repeated here. The various contexts from which meaning arises will first be examined. This is followed by a discussion of the contentious debate between what is literal and metaphorical. The final section focusses on the ways in which Christian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Moral Reasoning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter examines our moral reasoning in light of embodied cognition, metaphor, prototypes, and frames. Morality here is broadly construed in the sense of what communities consider to be good and of value. The purpose is not to propose an ethical theory, but simply, to explore how cognitive linguistics can assist us in understanding what is involved in some aspects of moral reasoning and explain why Christians in general—and American Christians in particular—agree on some basics, yet disagree on many issues. It also draws upon some recent work in cognitive science to suggest the importance of exemplars for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Christian Doctrines</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thinking about theological topics such as sin and salvation makes use of the ordinary embodied cognitive processes we use every day. There is not a particular area of the brain or specific pattern of brain activity associated with religious experiences. Rather, as Brown and Strawn suggest: “there are a multitude of forms of body and brain activity that can mediate and embody religious experiences and the sense of the presence of God, but any particular brain-body event is experienced as religious or not based on the person’s expectations and ways of understanding their subjective experiences.”¹ The way we understand theology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Reading the Bible</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Biblical writers used the same cognitive processes available to us. They made use of image schemas, frames, idealized cognitive models, prototypes, conceptual metaphors, metonymy, and conceptual blending. Biblical texts manifest the conceptual conventions present in their languages and cultures. This includes everything from grammar to moral reasoning to cosmology. Much can be learned about how different biblical writers conceived various topics by paying attention to the conceptual structures prompted by the texts.</p>
                     <p>According to New Testament scholar Bonnie Howe, “Cognitive linguists approach what happens when people engage written text—reading—as fundamentally an encounter between minds. The dynamic encounter of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Conceiving God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Do we have to think of God using human categories? If we do, which characteristics should be attributed to God? Is God more like a person or more like a force, such as gravity? Can we escape anthropomorphism? Is all of our thinking about God metaphorical or is any of it literal? This chapter examines these questions from a cognitive linguistics approach and argues that humans have to use anthropogenic (human originating) and species-specific concepts for God. The real debate is about which concepts various religious communities believe are appropriate for God. The concept of God is a graded category</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human embodiment and culture deeply shape the way we think about topics such as sin, salvation, divine judgment, and the nature of truth. The particular kind of body humans have helps produce ways of thinking about the world that are specific to the human species. The concepts available for humans to understand our experience are deeply dependent upon the particular sort of body we have. We use these mental structures to reason about and understand all of our experiences, including religious ones. Whether we think about God, morality, salvation, or truth, our concepts are anthropogenic.</p>
                     <p>Our embodied cognition constrains what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7k7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
