<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13kh4md</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Vigil of Quebec</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DUMONT</surname>
               <given-names>FERNAND</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="translator">TRANSLATED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FISCHMAN</surname>
               <given-names>SHEILA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HOWARD</surname>
               <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>1974</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780802061843</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442654013</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1974</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/j.ctt1gxxrms"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book was first published in French in the wake of events which have come to be known in Quebec as the 'October crisis of 1970.' Dumont's thoughtful reflections on Quebec's social and political life invite 'les Anglais' to a new view of Quebec.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="150"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A letter to my English-speaking friends</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DUMONT</surname>
                           <given-names>FERNAND</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is not a portrait of Quebec. Nor does it even offer an explanation for the change in all areas that has characterized what is generally known as the ‘Quiet Revolution.’ I am concerned less with isolating the forces at work than with looking for the attitudes I ought to adopt as I confront the destiny of that fragile community which is my own.</p>
                     <p>Different approaches, more objective or more neutral, are certainly legitimate. In my practice of philosophy or sociology I frequently have occasion to employ them. However, the questions I was asking in these essays suggested another</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are in the midst of a crisis whose outlines cannot yet be isolated, whose dénouement cannot be glimpsed. This will be news to no one: Quebec has been shaken up over the past ten years, far more so than most other societies. We have experienced rapid change, from at least seeming religious solidarity to rapid dechristianization, from ignorance to mass education, from Duplessis to independentism, from the challenges of<italic>Cité libre</italic>to the tutelage of Trudeau, and all this was enough to make any one feel that he had got lost in a time of general confusion. However, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The time of the elders</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1930s, at the time when Saint-Denys Garneau, Jean-Louis Gagnon, André Laurendeau, and others were beginning to do their writing, I was just a little boy, carefully protected from books by my working-class milieu. I was more concerned about stealing apples from the neighbouring farmers than participating in the intellectual or political confrontations of the period. As I develop, however, I feel myself increasingly involved in those past events. They have changed, but only in appearance. Today, like yesterday, we are circling the same difficulty or<italic>empêchement</italic>(the term is that of Jean Le Moyne): we are always prowling</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>After the war:</title>
                     <subtitle>the search for a new awareness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the war broke out in 1939 powerful forces of change were at work in our midst, but for a long time their activity was subterranean. We did not become really aware of them until the period from 1940 to 1960, and men in our society are still busy looking for the consequences of these changes.</p>
                     <p>We talk about urbanization and industrialization as a general indication of these mysterious forces. It is important always to stress the extraordinary suddenness of these phenomena in our midst and how weak were the means, psychological as well as economic, available to deal with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A story of freedom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At first sight, we ought to make some kind of survey of the history of French Canada either to trace out a particular route taken by freedom or to map or describe the obstacles in its way. In doing this in so little space, one could only reveal one’s prejudices and pin down with a handful of vague historical reminiscences the more or less arbitrary choices we are now making. On the other hand, it is not at all clear that we have to involve the past in any debate on freedom. I have the strong impression that, for many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Is there a future for the French Canadian?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the moment, there is still a French Canadian. He is difficult to isolate and define - slightly more so, no doubt, than the American or the Frenchman. But it is enough to travel in the Beauce or Charlevoix and even in certain sections of our big cities to recognize this singular being, and to feel one’s own heart leap in that unmistakable way. Is there point in this curious variety of human fauna continuing to exist? That is the real question, the most trivial and the stupidest; but I am surprised not to hear it more often in those</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Canada and the United States:</title>
                     <subtitle>an ominous proximity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three-fifths of Canada’s production is at present under foreign control. This is unique among all the industrialized nations. The United States plays an enormous role in this economic dependence. In 1964 Canada’s total debt to other nations was $32.8 billion, if we include short-term foreign investments and certain other liabilities. By 1967 this debt had reached $36 billion, of which $30 billion was in the form of long-term investments. American investment in Canada is not, of course, a new phenomenon. It was already considerable at the beginning of the century, but so were British interests at that time. During the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tasks before the nationalist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us stop to consider some current criticism. At first sight, our nationalist associations have no future, and this is a statement one often hears made. Until fairly recently, so the claim goes, they did excellent work, but now they are out of date. For a long time they were active in the general area of social problems; however, in the past few years a number of new organizations with specific objectives have appeared. What purpose can a national association serve in a minor supporting role? Again, like many Québécois, these associations have come to the independentist choice. There is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Our culture:</title>
                     <subtitle>between past and future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can we evaluate the development of our culture during the past decade? What new challenges confront it? In connection with such questions we can only put forward here some hypotheses for reflection. Therefore I shall not draw up another balance sheet of our intellectual production over the past ten years, or even of educational reform. They have both been done often enough in books or periodicals. But I wonder to what extent, in these various attempts, we have succeeded in working out a new cultural debate. What changes have we made in the meaning of our collective utterance? Into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The co-operative ideal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Elites and planning: at first glance, these two terms suggest an irreconcilable opposition. In fact, planning implies co-ordinating activities and defining long-term projects on a basis of technical criteria. The latter should be more or less imposed on the multiplicity and incoherence of individual wants and goals. The elite, on the contrary, represents an authority delegated spontaneously by groups. The leader is not a ‘good talker’ or even necessarily a ‘learned man,’ but he who proposes a representation of his own milieu and objectives for action in which other men may recognize their own viewpoint and desire for change. While</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The struggle against poverty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What general social changes are implied by the struggle against poverty and against social injustice in general? Leaving aside the strictly economic aspects that are dealt with elsewhere, the question could be reduced to this very generalized formula: in what way does poverty pose a challenge not only to our good intentions, our ‘good deeds,’ and even our politics, but to the whole of our society? At first glance, the question in this form is ambiguous. The most basic transformations cannot be guilelessly defined in terms of poverty alone. Thus poverty is in danger of being lost sight of. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Socialism is utopia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That socialism is Utopia is quite obvious. It is so for very realistic reasons -because it does not want to abandon the collective future to the interplay of blind forces or interests; because there is no other way in which a society can gain some little ascendancy over its situation than by projecting itself into a full and solid image of its future. Thus political choices are not dependent only on disparate sets of circumstances and surface compromises, but also find coherence and perspective in more clearly fixed alternatives.</p>
                     <p>Our contemporary societies have never needed Utopia so badly. The growing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Socialism for Quebec</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We all know how the problem of economic power is traditionally looked at in our milieu. As we have never had a substantial bourgeoisie of our own, and control almost none of the big machinery of capitalist growth, our ideas on these lines could only sway between the contestation of the modern economy in the abstract, and claims launched in the name of the national collectivity. Inevitably the class struggle has escaped us, all the more so as the economic powers that could have been challenged by our working class were, because of the nationality of the holders of power,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What is a political program?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our society may be working out a serious kind of political thinking, but we are still groping, as it is particularly difficult to relate together such disparate requirements as our economic weakness and our desire for independence, our democratic aspirations and our socialist inclinations. These difficulties are reflected in the program of the Parti québécois. Not surprisingly, it gives rise to a type of thinking that, though committed, is still critical. Combining political conviction and free inquiry, unconnected with election-time manoeuvring, is no doubt one indication among others that things can change in Quebec’s political life.</p>
                     <p>We are hardly in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The crises and the crisis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We can and must arrange and classify the many crises that have hit us during the last ten years. A primary task is to try to understand this country on the basis of what it has been able to tell about itself, through such apparently different events as De Gaulle’s visit, the Montreal police strike, the demonstrations against Bill 63, and many others; this task brings together the symbols of the hopes and dilemmas in which Quebec has been attempting to fix its course over the past decade.</p>
                     <p>The immediate causes of these disorders have not been the same; they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Crisis and symbols</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can a collectivity shape its future?</p>
                     <p>I doubt whether anyone expects an outline plan for Quebec’s economic development, or prophecies about our cultural future. I cannot do such things, lacking competence in such diverse matters. Anyhow if such projects are to appeal to the collectivity, they must originate in the collectivity as well.</p>
                     <p>Besides, the October crisis has taught us nothing new about the economic or other problems which continued, after it as before, to push us towards a more advanced planning for which we already had at our disposal wide technical knowledge and competent men of science. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Democracy and speech</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the many often obscure pretexts furnished us by governments to sanction the imposition of the War Measures Act, one deserves our attention. At the beginning the federal Minister of Justice spoke of ‘a kind of disintegration of the will of the people.’ He returned to this later, insinuating that the hypothesis antedates the arrival on the scene of the few individuals who proposed to save Mr Laporte’s life, that it had been accepted for a fairly long time, and remained the most plausible hypothesis once the ‘parallel governments’ and pseudo-data on the ‘insurrection’ had gone up in smoke.</p>
                     <p>An</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What is politics?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The collective planning of a future can never be identified primarily with a political party program. Not that political parties are to be scorned: they represent collections of opinions, interests, and ideas that have surfaced in a combination of historical circumstances and, at the risk of hardening, have sometimes gone under later on. But political parties have their own logic, originating in the needs of their struggle to reach power. They skim the projects emerging in their vicinity, even though they make more discreet accommodations with those more subtle forces at work in the collectivities.</p>
                     <p>When we examine the fate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conflicts and futures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despair is not a political motive. It requires that symbols, words, and acts fall into place in accordance with sudden confrontations. A society is threatened with death pangs when it is divided thus into armed camps, not only because political projections are replaced by physical or verbal violence, but because aspirations, words, conflicts are no longer understood, mobilized as they are in schemes that remove their significance and authenticity.</p>
                     <p>If we want to return to democracy, or rather attain it, men who are still reasonable must, to the last detail, forbid persecution in the name of despair or reasons of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What is to be done?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Crises, whether personal or collective, should not be given more than they can return. We have got a great deal already if we can find in them the motive to fall back on some elemental intuitions and an opening, one that is as large as possible, on the future. If it is true that the October crisis placed us more distinctly than ever before a drama that is blurring the symbolism of a society, we must use it to throw light on our near future, and in this same way.</p>
                     <p>As I have already said, I have no contempt for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gxxrms.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
