<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Crucifixion of the Warrior God</book-title>
         <subtitle>Volumes 1 &amp; 2</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Boyd</surname>
               <given-names>Gregory A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506420752</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506420753</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506420769</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506420761</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Gregory A. Boyd</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kgqv00"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In an epic constructive investigation, The Crucifixion of the Warrior God addresses the tension between Scripture’s violent depictions of God and the non-violent, self-sacrificial God that was supremely revealed on the cross. Over two volumes, author Gregory A. Boyd develops a theological interpretation of Scripture that he labels a “cruciform hermeneutic," and he argues that this cruciform way of reading Scripture reframes its violent divine portraits in a way that subverts their violence and that discloses how they bear witness to the revelation of God’s non-violent love in the crucified Christ.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="1492"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The “Magic Eye” of the Crucified Christ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxvii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For reasons that will become clear later on in this book, I have come to believe that Jesus revealed an<italic>agape</italic>-centered, other-oriented, selfsacrificial God who opposes violence and who commands his people to refrain from violence (e. g., Matt 5: 39–45; Luke 6: 27–36).¹ I also believe in the divine inspiration of the Old Testament (OT), primarily because I have good reason to believe Jesus treated it as such. Since I confess Jesus to be Lord, I do not feel free to disagree with him on this matter.² Yet I and everyone else who shares these two convictions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Faith of Jacob:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wrestling With “Strange” and “Alien” Portraits of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goal of this chapter is to lay the groundwork for all that is to follow by discussing three foundational issues. First, since my concern in this volume is to develop and defend a particular hermeneutic of Scripture, I need to go beyond what was said in the introduction and spell out a bit further my understanding of what is entailed in the confession that all Scripture is “God-breathed” (2 Tim 3: 16).</p>
                     <p>Second, throughout this volume, as well as the one that follows, I will be encouraging readers to honestly wrestle with Scripture’s violent portraits of God. Yet, I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The True Face of God:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Absoluteness of the Revelation of God in Christ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goal of this as well as the following four chapters is to establish that the revelation of God in the crucified Christ is not merely the greatest of all revelations in Scripture; it is the supreme revelation to which all others are intended to point and the culminating revelation through which all others are to be interpreted.⁴ The reason I feel the need to spend five chapters on this material prior to examining the OT’s problematic portraits of God is that I believe it is only by becoming convinced that the cross is the full revelation of God’s character</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Finding Jesus in the Old Testament:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Christocentric Hermeneutic of the Early Church</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the individual authors of the NT display a range of perspectives on Jesus, we saw in the previous chapter that the NT as a whole understands Jesus to be the supreme revelation of God that culminates and supersedes all others.³ While most Bible interpreters throughout church history have acknowledged this and have thus held that all Scripture bears witness to Christ, it is my conviction that this insight has not been applied in a thorough and consistent manner. And, as I mentioned in the introduction, the primary evidence of this is that after the fifth century, no attempts have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Cruciform Center, Part 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Cross as the Supreme Revelation of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the previous two chapters, I have argued that the NT as well as the church throughout history has to one degree or another advocated for a Christocentric approach to the OT. While the entire Bible is “God- breathed,” it is not to be interpreted in a flat way (viz. as if every part of it was equally authoritative for us). Rather, since Jesus culminates and supersedes all previous divine revelations, the OT must be interpreted in the light of him, never placed alongside of him as though it was a supplementary revelation. Indeed, I have argued that if we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Cruciform Center, Part 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Cross as the Thematic Center of the Gospel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While space considerations do not allow anything like an exhaustive treatment of this theme, in this chapter I will review the most important ways Jesus’s sacrificial death is centralized in the Synoptic Gospels, followed by the Gospel of John, the Pauline Epistles, and several other books of the NT. I will then attempt to demonstrate that the thematic centrality of the cross entails that nonviolent<italic>agape</italic>-love lies at the heart not only of God’s will for humans but of God’s eternal nature.</p>
                     <p>The most obvious indication of the thematic centrality of the cross in the Synoptic Gospels is the fact</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Is the Centrality of the Cross Thesis Defensible?</title>
                     <subtitle>Responding to Objections</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I will respond to two major objections that can be raised against my claim that the NT, and the early proto-orthodox church as a whole, understood the cross to be the thematic center of Jesus’s mission and thus the central revelation to which all Scripture bears witness.</p>
                     <p>First, a number of contemporary scholars argue that “among the symbols” used in the artwork of Christians during the first four centuries of church history, “we find nothing that signifies suffering, death, or self-immolation.”³ “Jesus does not suffer or die in pre-Constantinian art,” Graydon Fisher Snyder argues. “There is no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Dark Side of the Bible:</title>
                     <subtitle>Taking a Hard Look at Scripture’s “Texts of Terror”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In part 1 of this volume, I attempted to demonstrate that the revelation of God’s undifferentiating love and unconditionally nonviolent nature on the cross should be understood as the revelation to which all Scripture ultimately points. Hence, however we account for the violent depictions of God in the OT that we will be reviewing in this chapter, and even if we were to conclude that there is no adequate explanation for this material, I submit that these violent divine portraits should never be allowed to undercut, compromise, or qualify in any way the portrait of God we are given in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Wrestling with Yahweh’s Violence, Part 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Dismissal Solution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of relating the Old and New Testaments is as old as the church itself, and the incongruity of the OT’s violent divine portraits with the nonviolent, self-sacrificial, enemy-embracing agape -love of God revealed in the crucified Christ represents the apex of this challenge. The various responses to this problem that theologians have proposed throughout history can be broadly grouped into three categories. The first proposal, to be addressed in this chapter, was put forth by a second-century preacher named Marcion. He was uniformly branded a heretic by the proto-orthodox theologians of the time because he solved the problem</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Wrestling with Yahweh’s Violence, Part 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Synthesis Solution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While theologians within the historic-orthodox church have always viewed Christ as the most important revelation of God, they have, especially since the fifth century, also generally assumed that the plenary inspiration of Scripture entails that the OT’s violent portraits of God must be accepted as accurate revelations alongside of Christ. Rather than seeking for ways to reinterpret the violence found in these portraits as a means of preserving a nonviolent conception of God, the way Origen, Nyssa, and others had done, these theologians sought for ways to justify the violence these portraits ascribe to God. Consequently, the dominant portrait of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>A Meaning Worthy of God:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Reinterpretation Solution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thus far I have attempted to demonstrate the absoluteness of the revelation of Christ crucified (part 1) and the inadequacy of two ways of responding to the problematic OT portraits of God that conflict with this revelation (part 2). If, as I have argued, all Scripture must bear witness to the crucified Christ, and if we can neither dismiss nor simply embrace the OT’s violent divine portraits, our only remaining option is to look for a way of interpreting these portraits that discloses how they reflect the self-sacrificial love of God revealed on Calvary. Hence I label this third option</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Through the Lens of the Cross:</title>
                     <subtitle>Finding the Crucified Christ in Violent Depictions of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>463</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I will provide an overview of the Cruciform Hermeneutic, which I will further nuance in the following chapter by placing it in the context of the contemporary Theological Interpretation of Scripture (TIS) movement. Since all theological reflection must be done in dialogue with others, past and present, I will first set the stage for my development and defense of the Cruciform Hermeneutic by briefly discussing the views of six scholars whose thinking, to one degree or another, reflects foundational aspects of this hermeneutic.³ I will then proceed to outline three closely related distinctive aspects of the Cruciform</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Interpreting Scripture as God’s Word:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Cruciform Hermeneutic and the Theological Interpretation of Scripture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>513</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter I fleshed out three distinctive aspects of the Cruciform Hermeneutic. Yet, a more nuanced understanding will prove helpful to fully appreciate the manner in which this hermeneutic will interpret the variety of violent divine portraits we find in the OT. Inasmuch as Christian reflections on all things pertaining to God must be done in dialogue with the wider body of Christ, I believe the most faithful and effective way to accomplish this is to place the Cruciform Hermeneutic in dialogue with the contemporary Theological Interpretation of Scripture (TIS) movement, for, as will become clear, my hermeneutical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix I:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Alleged Anti-Judaic Attitude of the Gospels</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>553</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix II:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jesus and Violence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>563</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix III:</title>
                     <subtitle>Violence in the Pauline Epistles</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>583</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix IV:</title>
                     <subtitle>Violence in the Book of Revelation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>593</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Something Else Is Going On</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>629</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To set the stage for what I will be attempting to accomplish in this volume, I would like us to imagine a story. Suppose I am walking downtown and happen to spot my lovely wife, Shelley, on the other side of a busy and noisy street.¹ I am absolutely certain the woman I see is my wife because I have a clear view of her, and she not only looks exactly like my wife, she is even wearing the distinctive-looking coat and hat that I recently gave her as a birthday present. I shout out her name and wave my</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The “Masks” of a Humble God:</title>
                     <subtitle>Revelation and the Eternal Outpouring of the Triune God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>641</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goal of this and the following chapter is to develop and defend the first of the four principles that comprise the Cruciform Thesis. For reasons that will become clear in a moment, I label this principle the Principle of Cruciform Accommodation. In this chapter, I will first demonstrate the manner in which this principle is rooted in the paradoxical truth that the cross is simultaneously the supreme revelation of God and the supreme example of God accommodating the sin and curse of humanity. I will then defend the intelligibility of this paradox by discussing the manner in which this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>The Heavenly Missionary:</title>
                     <subtitle>Yahweh’s Accommodation of the Law, Nationalism, and Violence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>701</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have been acquainted with several people who have worked as missionaries to tribes in Third World countries that had not yet heard the gospel. I am told that serving in these contexts often requires a great deal of patience and flexibility. One sometimes encounters centuriesold customs such as “female circumcision” that are, by western Christian standards, utterly inhumane.³ The missionary cannot simply point out the inhumanity of these ancient customs and expect the tribe to abandon them. If the missionary ever hopes to have the tribe eventually embrace the gospel and abandon their inhumane customs, they must rather initially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Divine Aikido:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Cross as the Revelation of God’s “Wrath”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>767</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aikido means “the way of peace” or “the way of the harmonious spirit.” Developed by Morihei Ueshiba in the 1920s and 30s, Aikido is a martial arts technique that trains “warriors” to engage in nonresistant combat, turning the force of aggressors back on themselves in order to neutralize their opponent and hopefully to enlighten them regarding the evil in their heart that fueled their aggression.³ The second of the four principles that comprise the Cruciform Thesis—the Principle of Redemptive Withdrawal—essentially stipulates that the cross reveals that God wisely uses an Aikido-like strategy in judging sin and overcome evil.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Crime and Punishment:</title>
                     <subtitle>Divine Withdrawal and the Self-Destructive Nature of Sin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>805</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After demonstrating how the Principle of Redemptive Withdrawal is anchored in Christ’s abandonment on the cross, the previous chapter aimed at fleshing out the concept of “wrath” as it is revealed on the cross. With this in place, this chapter will demonstrate how the Principle of Redemptive Withdrawal, which is centered on this concept of “wrath,” is confirmed throughout the written witness to God’s covenantal faithfulness. I will begin with a review of various ways this principle is reflected in the teachings and ministry of Jesus as well as in the other sections of the NT. I will then demonstrate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Doing and Allowing:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Crucicentric Significance of Scripture’s Dual Speech Pattern</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>851</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I will address a widespread feature of narratives in the OT that I believe further confirms not only of the Principle of Redemptive Withdrawal but also of the previously discussed Principle of Cruciform Accommodation. It concerns the curious fact that biblical authors frequently depict God engaging in acts of violence that their own narratives and/or the broader canon make clear God merely allowed. I will refer to this as Scripture’s “dual speech pattern.” I will argue that by acknowledging that God merely allowed the actions they elsewhere ascribe directly to God, these OT authors confirm both that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>A Question of Divine Culpability:</title>
                     <subtitle>Responding to Objections to the Principle of Redemptive Withdrawal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>891</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having fleshed out the biblical material that confirms God’s Aikido-like method of judging sin and overcoming evil on the cross, I will in this chapter address four possible objections to the Principal of Redemptive Withdrawal. The first objection is theological in nature, the second and third are philosophical, while the fourth is a pragmatic concern. As will become clear, my responses to these objections will afford me an opportunity to further nuance my understanding of precisely how God does and does not participate in bringing about the violent judgments recounted in the OT. First, a number of theologians, especially in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Defending Divine Genocide:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Inadequacy of Traditional Defenses of the Conquest Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>917</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2003, Zondervan published a book entitled<italic>Show Them No Mercy: 4 Views on God and Canaanite Genocide</italic>.² Of all the episodes of God commanding and/or engaging in violence in the OT, why did Zondervan single out the conquest narrative as the one worth soliciting four different views on?³ The answer is that this narrative, with its terrifying depiction of God commanding the merciless slaughter of “everything that breathes” in certain areas within Canaan (Deut 20:16), stands out as the Bible’s most horrific and most prolonged portrait of divine violence. As Jerome Creach notes, “ this portion of Scripture seems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>When God’s Nonviolent Plans Fail:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Cruciform Interpretation of the Conquest Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>961</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, I argued that both lines of defense that Copan employs to assuage the horror of the genocidal portrait of God in the conquest narrative are problematic. Even if one of these defenses had accomplished this task, however, it nevertheless would have failed at the most important hermeneutical task, which is to disclose how all Scripture bears witness to the saving revelation of God’s self-sacrificial love that took place Calvary and that was confirmed in Christ’s resurrection (Luke 24:25–27, 32, 44–46; cf. John 5:39–40, 45–47; 1 Cor 15:3). Demonstrating this for the conquest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>The Battle of the Gods:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmic Conflict and the Old Testament</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1005</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To set a context that will help us appreciate the significance of the third principle of the Cruciform Thesis, I would like to return to the story of my wife’s bizarre behavior toward an apparently disabled panhandler on the other side of the busy city street that I first shared in the Introduction. Imagine that after witnessing my wife mistreat this disabled panhandler and walking around downtown for several hours in a confused stupor, I finally decide to return home. I walk through the front door and discover Shelley with a dozen or so well-dressed men and women wearing Department</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>Caught in the Cross Fire:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cosmic Conflict and the New Testament</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1041</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having demonstrated how the cosmic conflict motif permeates the OT, we must now consider the much more intense way this motif is reflected in the NT, and especially how it is supremely illustrated in the crucifixion. I will first review the various ways the NT intensifies the OT conviction that our world is engulfed in forces of destruction that must be perpetually held at bay for death and destruction to be averted. For only when we fully appreciate the intensity of this warfare world view can we appreciate the central role the cross plays in it within NT theology. Having</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>When Hell Breaks Loose:</title>
                     <subtitle>Redemptive Withdrawal and Cosmic Conflict</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1099</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have thus far seen that humans who are bent on violence are not the only agents that afflict people when God decides he must withdraw his protective presence to allow one form of evil to punish another form of evil. Rather, as the cross supremely illustrates, and as the Principle of Cosmic Conflict expresses, Satan and other cosmic powers are also present, looking for every opportunity to kill, steal, and destroy. Hence, whenever God stops holding these “raging waters” at bay (Ps 124:4–6), they too become a means by which people experience the destructive consequences that are inherent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>The Dragon-Swallowing Dragon:</title>
                     <subtitle>Examples of Cosmic-Level Aikido Warfare</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because of my commitment to treat all Scripture as “God-breathed” as well as my commitment to the Conservative Hermeneutical Principle, it is not enough for me to demonstrate how violent depictions of God bear witness to the cross. Since the cross leads me to deny that God acted violently in any biblical narrative of divine judgment, I must offer some alternative account of who brought about the violence that is attributed to God in these narratives. We have seen that this is unproblematic in narratives in which violently inclined people function as instruments of God’s judgments (vol. 2, chs. 16</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>Mauling Bears and a Lethal Palladium:</title>
                     <subtitle>When Divine Power Gets Misused</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is one final category of violent divine portraits in the OT that yet need to be assessed through the lens of the cross. How are we to interpret biblical depictions of certain OT heroes that display God’s power in violent ways? What are we to make of Elisha pronouncing a supernatural curse on forty-two boys that caused them to be mauled by two bears (2 Kgs 2:23–24), or of Elijah using his supernatural power to have fire from heaven annihilate one hundred men, even though these men meant him no harm (2 Kgs 1:10–12)? And what are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Postscript:</title>
                     <subtitle>Unlocking the Secret of the Scroll</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When John looks at the OT’s militant image of the Messiah as “the Lion of the Tribe of Judah” (Gen 49: 9), what he sees is a slain lamb that battles foes by offering up his life on their behalf (Rev 5:5–6). So too, when John looks at the OT’s image of Yahweh as a warrior returning from battle, covered with the blood of the enemies he has slain (Isa 63:3), what he sees is Yahweh covered by his own blood prior to a battle, signifying that this warrior engages in battle not by slaying enemies but by being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix V:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Escalation of Violence in the Promised Land</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix VI:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hardening People’s Hearts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix VII:</title>
                     <subtitle>Can Satan’s Kingdom Be Divided against Itself?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix VIII:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Quail Plague</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix IX:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Testing of Abraham</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix X:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Issue of Supersessionism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Suggested Readings on Central Topics in The Crucifixion of the Warrior God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boyd</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1341</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Authors and Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Scripture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv00.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1446</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
