<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Contextual Theology</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Drama of Our Times</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Matheny</surname>
               <given-names>Paul Duane</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>18</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227680124</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227901045</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Paul Duane Matheny</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf9rs"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>For centuries, the global understanding of Church has been shaped by Western theological imperatives. Yet today, the decline of institutional religion in the West, and the extraordinary growth of the Church of the global South mean that a radical movement beyond such theologies is required. In this book, Paul Matheny argues that the Church would benefit by becoming more contextualized and less Western. Contextual Theology is an attempt to address that issue and to examine how a reassessment of the relationship of the Gospel to cultural context can advance this critical and necessary development. Through an accessible and critical approach, Matheny considers the historical background to contextual theology. In the same way, he aims to show how to use contextual methods to think theologically and act missiologically in different cultural contexts.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="140"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hopes that the future of theology lies among the new “contextual” theologies of the “new Christianity” abound. Could these theologies replace the theologies of the Atlantic cultures with their roots in ancient theology and doctrine? For some this hope has given carte blanche to any theology from the global South that calls into question traditional “Western” theology. For others the emergence of non-Western Christian thinking is insignificant for it seems to have little to add to the theological debate. I believe these claims to be misleading and disingenuous. The theologies of the “new Christianity” cannot be easily pigeonholed in anti-traditional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Church Looks to the Future:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Encouragement of Contextual Methods in Theology?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of Christianity has exhibited surprising and dramatic turning points during the last century. A century ago, commentators declared that the twentieth century would be the most hopeful and promising of any period in history. William Temple, the Archbishop of Canterbury, declared early in the century at his installation as Archbishop of Canterbury that Christianity was a worldwide reality.¹ He and others speculated about this new turn of events and prophesied great and exciting changes. At the beginning of the century John Mott wrote a classic of the times. The title says it in a nutshell:<italic>The Evangelization of</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Contextual Methods within the Theological Processes of Christian Churches</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Missiologists, such as Lamin Sanneh and Andrew Walls, have made it clear that the migratory nature of Christianity is evident today in a dramatic way. We are facing a new Christianity centered geographically, socially, culturally, economically, and politically in environments unfamiliar to the West, such that our theological work is called upon to think creatively in terms of the ideas and cultural life, the beliefs and practices of the churches of the new center.¹ The reality of a new Christianity in the offing is the stimulus for a commitment to an ecumenical and ecclesial theology and praxis of mission. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Helpfulness of Theology in the Life of the Church</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The rise of the “new Christianity” has led Christian theologians to retrieve insights within Christian traditions that are helpful as the faith takes root and forms new and vital communities and practices. According to these traditions, good theology is not a search for universal truths that can be applied in all contexts and times, but rather an engagement with the lives of peoples and communities. The eschatological framework of Christian thinking and the centrality of theological theories of God’s grace ensure the openness of Christian thinking to new contexts. The creation of new Christian communities is a social and cultural</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Contextual Theology Becomes an Issue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a “new Christianity” began to unhinge from dependency upon the Christian institutions of the Atlantic churches, the awareness that new ways of doing theology would emerge grew gradually and in some circles begrudgingly. In time the search for insights from Christian thinking led to engagement. Theologians such as Karl Barth, Paul Lehmann, and Visser ’T Hooft addressed the theoretical side of problems that had to be faced, such as the form an ecumenical theology can take and the relation between dogma and ethics. The key, it was believed, is found in the deceptively simple principle that faith informs theological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Sources and Processes:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contextual Theology and the Emergence of a Christian Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An argument of this book is that the proper theological use of contextual methods is healthy and promotes and enriches the life of faith among Christians around the globe. As the theological process is enriched by contextual methods, the community is enriched and empowered to greater service of God in Christ. This is a claim that needs to be illustrated and defended. In this chapter, I will attempt to examine this thesis.</p>
                     <p>By recalling here a biblical story, I believe that I can demonstrate a contention of contextual theology that the biblical text is the catalyst for the formation of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Theology, Both Local and Ecumenical:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tradition and Authority within the Christian Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historical and social realities provide textual meaning with its temporal and cultural limits and possibilities. We experience our world because we are part of a world. For our faith to have meaning it must be meaningful in a particular historical, cultural, and social context. The question of whether and how the meaning of the beliefs and practices of Christian faith can be translated into those that share the same truth in other cultures becomes acute. For the claims of Christian conviction to be true they must be commensurable. All this leads to an assertion: once the faith has been shared,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9rs.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
