<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9m0s24</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1ggjhd0</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Acting for Others</book-title>
         <subtitle>Trinitarian Communion and Christological Agency</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kušnieriková</surname>
               <given-names>Michaela</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hinlicky</surname>
               <given-names>Paul R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506423432</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506423434</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506409016</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506409016</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ggjhd0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book explores why the metaphor of the church as a family is insufficient. Taking up Arendt’s notions of action and her criticism of privatization, the author examines community, relation, and human subjects through the work of Bonhoeffer and Stăniloae. Synthesizing Bonhoeffer and Stăniloae, Christian calling is unfolded not only as acting for others, but also with others as Trinitarian participatory response—response to the words and deeds of the three divine Persons acting in communion.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="228"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hinlicky</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Michaela Kušnieriková, in this welcome study, takes her place in the rising generation of theologians theorizing Christianity after Christendom. She does this work, fittingly enough, from the religious crossroads of Europe: between East and West, to be sure, but also the battle site of the Wars of Religion between North and South that so devastated and discredited the church. Kušnieriková grew up in the spiritually vacated place where all the subsequent bloody contests between the would-be ideological replacements of religion exchanged totalitarianisms.</p>
                     <p>A particular maladaptation to this diminished life of surviving Christianity in modernity has been the predominance of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Christian communities tell and interpret the biblical stories, and in that telling, a certain picture of the world and of God emerges to those within their communities and to those outside of them.</p>
                     <p>After the dissolution of Christendom in Europe, churches in the West lost their political power, authority, and sometimes, their voice. Bonhoeffer characterized this development as a part of a breakdown of the unity of the West, accompanied by the loss of structures, authority, and orientation in the world. He thought it was a time with no future and no past.³ In Arendt’s view, this situation places us</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Church as a Family in Arendt</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hannah Arendt discusses the church often in connection with its space in the world and its specific activity. Both of these motives are found together in her explication of the familial imagery of the church that centers on Early Christianity’s attempt to express the uniqueness of its community consisting in love as the bond between its members over against the public-political space.</p>
                     <p>Since there are three main realms interconnected in Arendt’s discussion of this topic, the relation between the familial and the political will be explicated before following her argument regarding the image of an unworldly church as a family.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Church as a Patriarchal Family in Bonhoeffer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bonhoeffer¹ compared the church to a patriarchal family in trying to express the church-community as a distinct sociological type which the empirical church embodies. He applied this familial metaphor for the church in a different way than that of the early Christians that Arendt focused on.</p>
                     <p>It is important to ask in what ways Bonhoeffer uses this image of the church and how he explains it. Does it express the atmosphere of love and care in the church? What place do individuals and their uniqueness have in it? Does the adjective patriarchal mean that the church is a place of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Christian Acting in Bonhoeffer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bonhoeffer’s¹ theology of Christian agency is shaped by his notion of “being for others,” formulated also as living or existing for others. In this chapter, the interpersonal dimensions of action will be put into the foreground. With that aim, the following questions will be raised: what moves Christians to act? Does such acting necessarily entail fatherly and obedient approach of a dependent within and outside of the church? How is Christian acting interconnected with Christian freedom and equality? Since Christian acting is to find its fullest expression in the church, is there a connection between his understanding of Christian acting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Christian Acting in Stăniloae</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human persons are invited and mercifully empowered by God to participate in the movement of love between the divine Persons, believes Stăniloae¹. What happens with a concept of action, when the life of the Trinity is one of its underlying foundations? In this chapter, I will trace the way in which Stăniloae’s theology of the Trinity as being for-one-another and also with-one-another has consequences for viewing acting as a communal and also common venture, open for a participation of others. This new feature of acting will constitute a crucial addition to this debate.</p>
                     <p>First, acting of the immanent as well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>A Place of Acting:</title>
                     <subtitle>Arendt, Bonhoeffer, and Stăniloae in Conversation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After establishing interpersonal dimensions of Christian acting, outlined as a communal and common activity, its visible and public scope, a place of that storm, remains open. Therefore, this chapter explores the relation of acting of Christians and of the church to the world in an attempt to perceive the story it unfolds in its complexity.</p>
                     <p>As I concluded in the previous chapters, all of the three thinkers from this conversation—Arendt, Bonhoeffer, and Stăniloae—think that some aspect of acting remains invisible, and thus, unworldly. According to Bonhoeffer, equality between human beings should not be realized in the world because</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Christian Agency and Christian Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Up until this point, I have concentrated on the church’s familial metaphor separately from reflecting on Christian action, which is embodied in it, and its challenges. In this final chapter, I will place the church’s understanding expressed in the family metaphor within the context of its calling to a specific kind of action—in terms of communal and common action. What is reflected in it? Is the church compared to a family still pertinent or does Christian acting of equals delineate another metaphor of the church?</p>
                     <p>I will begin with a summary of the previous chapters in order to provide</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjhd0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
