<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR878.P66B58 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English prose literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Urban poor</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Great Britain</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social classes in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Masculinity in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sex role in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poverty in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poor in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The IMAGINATION OF CLASS</book-title>
         <subtitle>THE VICTORIAN MIDDLE CLASSES AND THE LON</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bivona</surname>
               <given-names>Dan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Henkle</surname>
               <given-names>Roger B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780814210192</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780814272497</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Ohio State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Columbus</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Ohio State University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kgqw73"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Description not available.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bivona</surname>
                           <given-names>Dan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brantlinger</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the contributors’ page for the Spring 1992 issue of NOVEL, the editors list Roger Henkle, whose article on George Gissing, Arthur Morrison, and urban poverty in late-nineteenth-century British fiction it contains. Following Roger’s name, they indicate that he “was at work on a book-length study of the fiction of urban poverty in late-Victorian England before his untimely death on October 5, 1991.” Thanks to Professor Daniel Bivona of Arizona State University,<italic>The Imagination of Class</italic>is at last the completed version of that book-length study. I am certain that Roger, our mutual friend and Dan’s former mentor and dissertation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The poor were always with the English. Poverty had been of broad social concern since the Elizabethan period at least: the topic of ongoing debate, periodic legislation, sporadic philanthropy. But the London poor of the nineteenth century—particularly from the 1840s on—seemed to present a different phenomenon. The spectacle of poverty and associated degradation in Central and East London, and later in South London, gave rise to a new set of imaginative and cultural representations. It developed from and in turn created new relationships between an ascending urban middle class and the worst victims of the metropolis. Poverty became,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Sensational Journalism, Male Detachment, and the Feminized Victim</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the aftermath of Mayhew, representations of the urban poor become prominent features of journalistic discourse in the 1860s and 1870s. In this chapter we are particularly interested in exploring how this discourse constructs a certain type of reader, a reader poised to appreciate both the detached perspective of the male author and how he distances the threat of permeable boundaries represented by the abject poor in his representations.</p>
                     <p>The key figure is the Amateur Casual himself, James Greenwood. Greenwood had established his fame with “Night in the Workhouse,” published in 1866 in the new evening paper, The Pall Mall</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Culturalism, the Feminized Poor, and the Land of Deadened Affect</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It may seem odd to focus a chapter in a book like this on a woman—in this case, a very prominent and unusual woman. However, Beatrice Webb is an important figure in this text for a variety of reasons, and her dilemma is one that is emblematic of that facing many male professionals in the nineteenth century with a concern for solving the problem of poverty. She exemplifies, in more than one way, both how the hope of fighting urban poverty fired the imaginations of an idealistic generation and how those hopes were menaced by the threat of enervation.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Morrison, Gissing, and the Stark Reality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early 1890s a stark vision of life in the East End emerges from the pens of two writers with a close acquaintance with life there: Arthur Morrison and George Gissing. Morrison was born in Poplar in 1863, the son of an engine fitter who worked on the docks. His father died of consumption when Arthur was a boy, and his mother raised the three children by running a haberdasher’s shop in Grundy Street. Arthur himself took a job early as office boy in the architect’s department of the School Board of London at a weekly salary of seven</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Hell Hath Its Flâneurs:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Discourse of the Abyss</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gissing’s response to East End poverty was, like Hardy’s to rural poverty, to associate energy with antisocial behavior and enervation with the requirements of goodness. There was a type of active energy that writers could deploy, however: the energy required by social investigation and reporting. The combination of culturalist critique, moral judgment, and risk-taking that these activities required and called forth signifies a change in the conceptualization of working and lower class life among male intellectuals in the 1890s, especially among those we associate with what we are calling the “discourse of the abyss.” If the model of the earnest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                     <subtitle>Representing the Poor and Forestalling Abjection</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is about the intersection of gender and class. More specifically, our contention in this book has been that the interests of a predominately male professional class, which was in the process of formation throughout the nineteenth century, strongly influenced, indeed determined, the ways in which the Victorians represented poverty in the city of London. London was in the process of unprecedentedly rapid growth in the nineteenth century, and this rapid growth entailed many painful social adjustments. Although London was not the center of the First Industrial Revolution (the northern cities were), it was the center of British trade,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw73.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
