<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Revelation and Convergence</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bosco</surname>
               <given-names>Mark</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Little</surname>
               <given-names>Brent</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813229423</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813229430</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kk665x"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Revelation &amp; Convergence</italic>brings together professors of literature, theology, and history to help both critics and readers better understand Flannery O'Connor's religious imagination.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>O’Connor’s Prayer Journal and the Life of Faith</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bosco</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Flannery O’Connor’s fiction stands as a singular achievement of twentieth-century American literature, yet scholars and enthusiasts of her novels and short stories have been inevitably drawn to her posthumously published critical essays,<italic>Mystery and Manners</italic>(1969), and to her personal letters to friends and colleagues,<italic>The Habit of Being</italic>(1979). Reading these texts one gleans further insight into the extraordinary clarity of vision that inspired and focused O’Connor’s talent. In<italic>Mystery and Manners</italic>one appreciates the context of O’Connor’s southern Catholic experience, allowing the reader to connect the dots between her erudite statements about the craft of fiction with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Revelation in History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Displaced Persons, Léon Bloy, and Exegesis of the Commonplace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schloesser</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although it has been twenty-five years since Linda Schlafer investigated the seminal importance of Flannery O’Connor’s encounter with the work of Léon Bloy (1846–1917), scholars have been slow to follow her lead.² Yet Bloy’s literary style, indelibly marked by rhetorical violence and vitriolic humor, sounds much like characterizations of O’Connor’s own “language of apocalypse” and “imagination of extremity.”³ Moreover, Bloy’s privileging of “suffering” as redemption apparently responded to O’Connor’s felt need for what Ralph Wood has called a “darker reading of human misery, a more startling revelation of transcendent hope.”⁴ Perhaps most important, Bloy’s symbolist vision of history—the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Breaking Bodies:</title>
                     <subtitle>O’Connor and the Aesthetics of Consecration</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Murphy</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>George Bernanos, the great French writer (or “scribbler,” as he called himself) of the twentieth-century French Catholic literary revival, wrote in the “Sermon from an Agnostic on the Feast of St. Therese of Lisieux” episode from his 1938 work<italic>The Great Cemeteries under the Moon</italic>the following: “Because you do not live your faith, your faith has ceased to be a living thing. It has become abstract—bodiless. Perhaps we shall find that the disincarnation of the Word of God is the real cause of all our misfortune.”¹ This propensity—the tendency to idealize experience and “disincarnate” theological phenomena from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Mysterious Heart:</title>
                     <subtitle>Maritain, Mauriac, Chrétien, and O’Connor on the Fictional Knowledge of Others</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lewis</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his 1925 book<italic>Trois réformateurs</italic>(<italic>Three Reformers: Luther, Descartes, Rousseau</italic>), in the section devoted to Jean-Jacques Rousseau, Jacques Maritain denounced the modern fiction writer’s “shameless” claim to provide the reader with knowledge of the secret and innermost interiority of a human being’s “heart,” in the biblical sense of the term. Such knowledge of another’s heart, writes Maritain, is “hidden from the angels, and open only to the priestly knowledge [<italic>la science sacerdotale</italic>] of Christ.” Maritain continues: “A Freud to-day attempts to violate [these secrets] by psychological tricks. Christ looked into the eyes of the adulterous woman and pierced to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>O’Connor’s “Pied Beauty”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Gerard Manley Hopkins and the Aesthetics of Difference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bosco</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a 2010 essay on the use of color in the works of Flannery O’Connor, the scholar Bruce Gentry offers a striking list of words that populate O’Connor’s texts: rat-colored, chocolate purple, dead-silver, dried yellow, fox-colored, freezing-blue, gold sawdust, gray-purple, a green that was almost black or a black that was almost green, green-gold, mole-colored, monkey white, polluted lemon yellow, sticky-looking brown, sweet-potato-colored, toast colored, and tobacco-colored. Gentry further highlights the way O’Connor describes skin tones, white or otherwise: burnt-brown, cinnamon, coffee, gray, purple, red, tan, yellowish, mottled, speckled, clay pink, purple-faced, and almost-gray.¹ O’Connor’s palette recalls the powerfully evocative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>“The Baron Is in Milledgeville”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Friedrich von Hügel’s Influence on O’Connor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bruner</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Flannery O’Connor was in the midst of revising her soon-to-be-published second and last novel,<italic>The Violent Bear It Away</italic>, when she wrote the letter highlighted above to Fannie Cheney in May 1959.³ She was clearly in a less sardonic mood than when she wrote to Betty Hester in 1955, highlighted at the chapter opening. Baron von Hügel’s writings had already proved to be an invaluable companion to, and crucial influence on, O’Connor’s growing storehouse of theological knowledge, and her latest foray into his first book,<italic>The Mystical Element of Religion as Studied in Saint Catherine of Genoa and Her Friends</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>The “All-Demanding Eyes”:</title>
                     <subtitle>St. Augustine and the Restless Seeker</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garavel</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Parker’s Back,” which Flannery O’Connor wrote as she was dying at the age of thirty-nine, is a story of conversion in which God’s grace overwhelms the title character, O. E. Parker, after years of wandering, denial, and dissatisfaction. The present reading points out significant affinities between this narrative and the conversion of St. Augustine of Hippo (354–430) recounted in his<italic>Confessions</italic>, a text that exerts a considerable influence on O’Connor’s story.¹ “Parker’s Back,” in its author’s words, “dramatiz[es] a heresy” that figures importantly in Augustine’s work.² In addition, the theory of illumination set forth in<italic>The Confessions</italic>can help</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Mrs. May’s Dark Night in O’Connor’s “Greenleaf”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Piggford</surname>
                           <given-names>George</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shortly before her baptism into the Catholic Church on March 31, 1956, Elizabeth Hester received from her friend Flannery O’Connor a present in the mail: the final copy of O’Connor’s latest short story, “Greenleaf,” which would be published that summer by John Crowe Ransom in the<italic>Kenyon Review</italic>.² My intention in this essay is to situate the composition of that story in the context of O’Connor’s burgeoning friendship with Hester, to note the powerful influence of Evelyn Underhill’s<italic>Mysticism</italic>(1910) on O’Connor and most especially O’Connor’s understanding of St. John of the Cross, and to trace the interconnectedness of O’Connor’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>O’Connor’s Unfinished Novel:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Beginning of a Modern Saint’s Life</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilson</surname>
                           <given-names>Jessica Hooten</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Flannery O’Connor never finished her third novel—<italic>Why Do the Heathen Rage?</italic>Her<italic>Collected Works</italic>includes a teaser from the incomplete manuscript, an excerpt that<italic>Esquire</italic>published in 1963. A decade later, Stuart Burns visited O’Connor’s archives at Georgia College and State University, hoping to discover a treasure like James Agee’s<italic>A Death in the Family</italic>or F. Scott Fitzgerald’s<italic>The Last Tycoon</italic>waiting for the right editor to sift through and compile the pieces. However, Burns was disappointed by what he found: “All in all, there are about a half-dozen episodes, each extensively revised, most of them connected, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk665x.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
