<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GR72.3.N56 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Storytelling</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Oral tradition</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Folk literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Homo Narrans</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Poetics and Anthropology of Oral Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Niles</surname>
               <given-names>John D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780812221077</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780812202953</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press, Inc.</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Pennsylvania Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt3fh9rr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>It would be difficult to imagine what human life would be like without stories-from myths recited by Pueblo Indian healers in the kiva, ballads sung in Slovenian market squares, folktales and legends told by the fireside in Italy, to jokes told at a dinner table in Des Moines-for it is chiefly through storytelling that people possess a past. In<italic>Homo Narrans</italic>John D. Niles explores how human beings shape their world through the stories they tell. The book vividly weaves together the study of Anglo-Saxon literature and culture with the author's own engagements in the field with some of the greatest twentieth-century singers and storytellers in the Scottish tradition. Niles ponders the nature of the storytelling impulse, the social function of narrative, and the role of individual talent in oral tradition. His investigation of the poetics of oral narrative encompasses literary works, such as the epic poems and hymns of early Greece and the Anglo-Saxon<italic>Beowulf</italic>, texts that we know only through written versions but that are grounded in oral technique. That all forms of narrative, even the most sophisticated genres of contemporary fiction, have their ultimate origin in storytelling is a point that scarcely needs to be argued. Niles's claims here are more ambitious: that oral narrative is and has long been the chief basis of culture itself, that the need to tell stories is what distinguishes humans from all other living creatures.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Making Connections</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Oral narrative, or what we call storytelling in everyday speech, is as much around us as the air we breathe, although we often take its casual forms so much for granted that we are scarcely aware of them. It is also an ancient practice. The early Greeks called it <italic>mûthos,</italic> a word that we often translate “myth” but that encompassed storytelling in many forms. To judge from the cuneiform records of ancient Sumeria, the papyri of early Egypt, the earliest bamboo and bronze inscriptions of ancient China, and other records that have come down to us from the dawn of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Somatic Communication</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The alien quality of much archaic and oral literature should not be allowed to recede from sight. One classicist has spoken of the culture shock some people experience when approaching the <italic>Iliad</italic> for the first time (Nagler 1987:425).¹ How easy it is for readers to feel disoriented when trying to grasp that poem’s stylized aesthetic system and alien world of feeling, so different from anything to be found in recent fiction. Two brutes arguing over rights to a slave girl . . . a corpse pulled through and through the dust. . . . Some readers must find the central</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Poetry as Social Praxis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>“Poetry makes nothing happen.”¹ People familiar with the marginal status that poetry enjoys in most quarters today are likely to agree with this blunt assessment, whether or not they lament it and whether or not they perceive the irony that emerges when Auden’s words are read in context, as part of a poem that celebrates the memory of William Butler Yeats—for Yeats’s cadenced words, like those of Auden himself, have made momentous things happen in the minds of people from all parts of the globe.</p>
                     <p>The art of poetry has not always been practiced at the margins of society,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Oral Poetry Acts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>People have speculated a good deal about who Homer, the <italic>Beowulf</italic> poet, the author of the <italic>Chanson de Roland</italic> or the <italic>Nibelungenlied,</italic> and similar shadowy persons from the past were and when and where they lived. Such questions have an obvious bearing on our understanding of texts that reveal key aspects of earlier modes of thought and cast light on many aspects of mythology, legendry, and popular belief, at the same time as they put the art of poetry on magnificent display. Although some curiously exact opinions about the authorship, audience, date, and provenance of such narratives have been expressed,¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>
                        <italic>Beowulf</italic> as Ritualized Discourse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Faced with the problem of making sense of a literary work from a very different epoch, composed according to stylistic criteria that differ markedly from those in fashion today—a poem that combines worship and narrative pleasure like the Homeric <italic>Hymn to Demeter,</italic> let us say, or a poem that presents dry lists of names within a glamourous legendary framework like the Old English poem <italic>Widsith,</italic> or an “impressive bit of showmanship” (Edel 1983:259) like the virtuoso medieval Welsh tale <italic>Culhwch ac Olwen,</italic> or a mythlike narrative on a monumental scale like the Old Irish <italic>Táin Bó Cúalnge,</italic> which is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Context and Loss</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>One afternoon during the summer of 1984 I had a memorable visit with Hamish Henderson in his fourth-floor walk-up office at the School of Scottish Studies, George Square, Edinburgh. At ease among his mounds of books and tapes, his dog Sandy at his feet, he was in excellent storytelling form, content to have an interested “Yank” (as he called me) to talk with despite having to defer the nearby pleasures of Sandy Bell’s pub, where Shetland fiddler Aly Bain was holding an impromptu session that afternoon.</p>
                     <p>Among the many stories with which Henderson entertained me that day was the tale</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Strong Tradition-Bearer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In older days it was usual to think of tradition as a kind of perpetual-motion machine, a train that keeps on running. We are more accustomed now to the stops and starts of tradition. As Hobsbawm and others have reminded us, new traditions come into being all around us every year, and likewise old traditions die and no one may miss them.¹ Tradition is no hypostatic entity, airy and transcendent. Nor can we think of it as something hard and durable, like an old chair passed down from hand to hand. What it boils down to is a series of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wordpower Wells from Deep in the Throat</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Anthony Seeger has written a fascinating book, <italic>Why Suyá Sing,</italic> about the Mouse Ceremony of the Suyá Indians of the Amazon basin (1987). In it he discusses what an ethnomusicologist can learn about Suyá society from a consideration of their singing. While this is no place to review his findings in detail, his response to the question implied in his title is worth citing here, in a book that takes oral narrative as its topic. Not only does Seeger’s response accord with my own experience in the field and at home; it has a sprightliness about it that goes well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh9rr.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
