<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS153.152T73 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Indian authors</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Characters and characteristics in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians of North America</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Intellectual life</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Indians in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Transatlantic Voices</book-title>
         <subtitle>Interpretations of Native North American Literatures</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PULITANO</surname>
               <given-names>ELVIRA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803237582</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803256453</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803256450</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LINCOLN; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1djmc5d"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Transatlantic Voices</italic>is the first collection of critical essays by European scholars on contemporary Native North American literatures. Devoted to the primary genres of Native literature-fiction, nonfiction, drama, poetry-the essays chart the course of recent theories of Native literature, delineate the crosscurrents in the history of Native literature studies, and probe specific themes of trauma and memory as well as changing mythologies. These essays also incorporate incipient transnational and transcultural methodologies in their approach to Native North American writing.</p>
         <p>Blending western critical approaches-from cultural studies to postcolonialism and trauma theory-with indigenous epistemological perspectives, the contributors to<italic>Transatlantic Voices</italic>advocate "the inescapable hybridity and intermixture of ideas" proposed by Paul Gilroy in his study of black diasporic identity. Native North American writers forcefully suggest that the study of American ethnicities in the twenty-first century can no longer be confined to the borders of the United States. Given the increasing transnational aspect of American studies, a collection such as<italic>Transatlantic Voices</italic>, presenting scholars from countries as diverse as Germany, France, Bulgaria, Switzerland, Italy, the United Kingdom, and Finland, offers a timely contribution to such border crossing in scholarship and writing.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PULITANO</surname>
                           <given-names>ELVIRA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Transatlantic Voices: Interpretations of Native North American Literatures</italic>brings together fourteen scholars from Europe. These scholars have contributed original, critical studies of contemporary literature by Native North Americans in the past few years. The essays in this collection present their most recent critical interventions on Native North American literary studies.</p>
                     <p>European critical practices and theoretical discourses transcend the boundaries of nations, disciplines, and academic traditions. A collection of essays on Native North American literatures by scholars in Europe takes the Atlantic as a site of cross-cultural exchange and circulation of ideas, a bridge linking the Old and New Worlds, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“They Have Stories, Don’t They?”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Doubts Regarding an Overused Theorem</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ISERNHAGEN</surname>
                           <given-names>HARTWIG</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The notion of<italic>story</italic>, or<italic>narrative</italic>(the two terms will be taken to be synonymous for purposes of this argument), is so central in the practice, criticism, and theory of Native American literature that around it gather — or it actively attracts to itself — many of the major issues in that literature. At the same time, the notion is necessarily modified by interaction with those issues, as they provide the larger contexts for its use. This essay will attempt to trace some such interactions and contexts as well as to place the entire complex within the wider context of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Plotting History:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Function of History in Native North American Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RIGAL-CELLARD</surname>
                           <given-names>BERNADETTE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Trying to understand the function of History in Native American and Canadian literature is a rather challenging process for Europeans. We live indeed on the continent supposed to have invented “History” as opposed to “Myth,” the continent that furthermore brought History to America and imposed it upon the Natives through the violence of the Conquest. History and Myth have always collided in myriad directions that have found their way into contemporary literature, and in a particularly forceful way in the writings of many Native North American authors. History can be briefly defined as a narration about the past based on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Transculturality and Transdifference:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of Native America</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BREINIG</surname>
                           <given-names>HELMBRECHT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a number of years cultural theory has discussed multiculturality no longer exclusively as a condition of selected nation-states such as Canada and the United States but as a global phenomenon.¹ Indigenous peoples have not made it, however, to the center of the debates on multiculturalism, nor do they figure prominently in postcolonial theory or any other branch of cultural studies, including general discussions of interculturality and transculturality. They remain doubly marginalized because their claims to land, language, ethnogenetic survival, or even sovereignty are often at odds with the interests not only of the respective dominant society but also of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>American Indian Novels of the 1930s:</title>
                     <subtitle>John Joseph Mathews’s Sundown and D’Arcy McNickle’s Surrounded</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PRAMPOLINI</surname>
                           <given-names>GAETANO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John Joseph Mathews’s<italic>Sundown</italic>and D’Arcy McNickle’s<italic>The Surrounded</italic>were published in 1934 and 1936, respectively, and were favorably if not widely noticed but — not unlike many other valuable books that appeared during the Depression years — very soon afterward sank into oblivion, to resurface only in the late 1970s, in the wake of the interest aroused by the novels of a younger generation of American Indian writers. Yet, since their reissue, they do not seem to have reached a very large readership beyond the one ensured by their adoption as textbooks in Native American Studies university programs, nor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Transatlantic Crossings:</title>
                     <subtitle>New Directions in the Contemporary Native American Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GEORGI-FINDLAY</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIGITTE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How much are Native Americans part of the project of American identity? How have Native American novels contributed to it, particularly in the context of recent debates over multiculturalism? Considering the growing popularity of Native American literature in Europe, how far have Europeans become an implied audience? How “American” or “cosmopolitan” are Native American novels? These are the questions that led me to look at some recent novels by Native American authors. I was also curious about whether we can detect certain trends or new directions in Native American works of fiction. I will argue that many recent novels explore</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Of Time and Trauma:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Possibilities for Narrative in Paula Gunn Allen’s The Woman Who Owned the Shadows</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MADSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>DEBORAH L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the introduction to her 1998 essay “Contemporary Two-Spirit Identity in the Fiction of Paula Gunn Allen and Beth Brant” Tara Prince-Hughes observes that for Native American writers the “struggle for identity has required writers to engage actively and dispute dominant Western fictions of ‘Indianness’ and to express the fragmentation experienced by people of mixed ancestry” (9). In this essay I want to address the way in which Paula Gunn Allen, in<italic>The Woman Who Owned the Shadows</italic>(1983), actively engages and disputes dominant Western fictions of “trauma” in a Native American context. In a central sequence of episodes in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>“Keep Wide Awake in the Eyes”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Seeing Eyes in Wendy Rose’s Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRAY</surname>
                           <given-names>KATHRYN NAPIER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her most recent collection of poems,<italic>Itch Like Crazy</italic>, Wendy Rose imagines a fleeting connection over space and time with her European great-great-grandfather: “Andrew MacInnes, You Look West Just at the Moment I Look East” (43–44). This title grasps the ambiguity and ambivalence of the line of vision between Rose and MacInnes, and we are left to consider the possibility that they are, at once, looking at and beyond each other. In the three MacInnes poems, and in the other ancestral portraits included in this collection, which take the form of photographs and poems, Rose uses ambiguous eye</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Anamnesiac Mappings:</title>
                     <subtitle>National Histories and Transnational Healing in Leslie Marmon Silko’s Almanac of the Dead</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TILLETT</surname>
                           <given-names>REBECCA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Generating some notable critical hostility upon its publication in 1991,¹ Leslie Marmon Silko’s contentious novel<italic>Almanac of the Dead</italic>has since been hailed as “a radical, stunning manifesto” that offers a graphic, brutal, and highly political analysis of America and the Americas at the turn of the twenty-first century.² Confronting the willful amnesia that pervades contemporary U.S. society regarding the history of settlement and of subsequent Anglo-Indian relations, Silko offers an anamnesiac consideration of the trauma of contact and a celebration of the significance of memory in the face of cultural assimilation and of the power of remembrance to heal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Vizenor’s Trickster Theft:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pretexts and Paratexts of Darkness in Saint Louis Bearheart</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TAYLOR</surname>
                           <given-names>PAUL BEEKMAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“When I was seeking some meaning in literature for myself,” Vizenor recalls, “some identity for myself as a writer, I found it easily in the mythic connections” (quoted in Owens,<italic>Other Destinies</italic>239). His earlier autobiographical essays, collected in<italic>Interior Landscapes: Autobiographical Myths and Metaphors</italic>, equate fact with myth and myth with truth in accordance with the etymology of<italic>myth</italic>: “word, truth, speech” (Greek<italic>muthos</italic>&gt;*Indo-European<italic>mudh</italic>, “to think, imagine”). In early Greek usage myth designates an oral pronouncement made to an audience, and Vizenor follows this mold as a maker of myth, neither in the Tolkien political or C.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“June Walked over It like Water and Came Home”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cross-Cultural Symbolism in Louise Erdrich’s Love Medicine and Tracks</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHACKLETON</surname>
                           <given-names>MARK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The opening section of<italic>Love Medicine</italic>(1984, rev. 1993) closes with the death of June Kashpaw, “a long-legged Chippewa woman,” on the eve of Easter Sunday: “The snow fell deeper that Easter than it had in forty years, but June walked over it like water and came home” (1, 7). Such overt Christian symbolism has prompted the Native American poet and critic Elizabeth Cook-Lynn (Crow Creek Sioux) to criticize Erdrich for her supposed adulteration of aboriginal writing and “the myths and metaphors of sovereign nationalism” with “Christian-oriented” prose (84, 85). The majority of critics, however, read Erdrich’s use of Christian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Encounters across Time and Space:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Sacred, the Profane, and the Political in Linda Hogan’s Power</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KRASTEVA</surname>
                           <given-names>YONKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1994, when I was completing a research grant at the University of Arizona, I attended N. Scott Momaday’s classes. I was surprised to learn that he had visited Bulgaria twice during Communism, on invitations from the Bulgarian Union of Writers. We talked about the similarities between Bulgarian and Native peoples’ folk songs and stories, especially about stories featuring bears, Momaday’s favorite animal. In the course of our discussions, and as my knowledge of Native American traditions grew, I began to perceive a mode of reciprocity between Bulgarian traditional literature and that of Native peoples and the way the two</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Double Translation:</title>
                     <subtitle>James Welch’s Heartsong of Charging Elk</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HASELSTEIN</surname>
                           <given-names>ULLA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a well-known essay William Bevis put forward a theory of Native American literature by juxtaposing Western and Native American plot structures. “American whites,” he observed, “keep leaving home” in search of better opportunities “in a newer land” (581). These (gendered) stories typically portray an individual striving for success, trying to stand up to the test of unforeseen hardships and conflicts by keeping true to himself. The existential pathos of living in a hostile world is only slightly modified by the hero’s ability to build relationships with others; as Bevis notes, romantic love typically serves as an antidote to isolation,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Clowns, Indians, and Poodles:</title>
                     <subtitle>Spectacular Others in Louis Owens’s I Hear the Train</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PELLERIN</surname>
                           <given-names>SIMONE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I met Louis Owens in his Parisian hotel lobby some seven or eight years ago, he was on a tour organized by his French publishers, Albin Michel, to promote the French translation of one of his novels. I had been a translator, off and on, for the same publishing house for some time, and, though the translation of<italic>The Sharpest Sight</italic>, to my great disappointment, had not been “given” to me, the editor of the “Terre indienne” collection had informed me of the fact that Owens would be “free” on that afternoon and arranged a meeting for my benefit.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Oklahoma International:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jim Barnes, Poetry, and the Sites of Imagination</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEE</surname>
                           <given-names>A. ROBERT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Issish ibakana</italic>, a Choctaw phrase Jim Barnes himself glosses as “mixedblood from Oklahoma” in his fine-grained prose and verse autobiography<italic>On Native Ground: Memoirs and Impressions</italic>(169), offers a point of departure. For if he has dwelt fondly upon his American family plait of Native, Welsh, and English origins, at the same time, and likely not a little in consequence, it has been accompanied by the insistence on not being bound to any single categorization. To his often self-acknowledged consternation this includes Native American writer. Rather, with Native America but one realm of lineage — however wholly and without doubt</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1djmc5d.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
