<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B105.B64 F3513 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human body (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human body</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Lord’s Supper</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Real presence</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Wedding Feast of the Lamb</book-title>
         <subtitle>Eros, the Body, and the Eucharist</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hughes</surname>
               <given-names>George</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823270408</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823270439</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d391qf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Emmanuel Falque's The Wedding Feast of the Lamb represents a turning point in his thought. Here, Falque links philosophy and theology in an original fashion that allows us to see the full effect of theology's "backlash" against philosophy. By attending closely to the incarnation and the eucharist, Falque develops a new concept of the body and of love: By avoiding the common mistake of "angelism"--consciousness without body--Falque considers the depths to which our humanity reflects animality, or body without consciousness. He shows the continued relevance of the question "How can this man give us his flesh to eat?" (John 6:52), especially to philosophy. We need to question the meaning of "this is my body" in "a way that responds to the needs of our time" (Vatican II). Because of the ways that "Hoc est corpus meum" has shaped our culture and our modernity, this is a problem both for religious belief and for culture.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="328"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Translator’s Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Opening</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ghent Altarpiece, or, The Adoration of the Mystic Lamb</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Swerve of the Flesh</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The traditional dualism of body and soul is now considered dated, but we have put a new binary structure in its place: that of flesh and body. Certainly this is an important step forward and one that has proved fruitful. When we talk of the “flesh” we describe the<italic>lived experience</italic>of our bodies, and we bring into view what we actually do, while we also bracket off the<italic>organic</italic>quality of the “body,” seeing it as an obstacle to the body’s subjectivity. But there are some questions that we still need to consider: Hasn’t philosophy forgotten the<italic>material</italic>and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART I Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We descend ever deeper into the abyss, because the chasm that opens before us is so profound. As we lose ourselves there we find also an extraordinary sensation of proximity. Those who plunge beneath the surface of the Earth are witness to this effect. From the stagnant pool (“<italic>la souille</italic>”) in Michel Tournier’s<italic>Friday, or, The Other Island</italic>to the explorations of subterranean caves (at Padirac, in France, for example), submerging in the depths of the Earth is a way of reuniting with an “underground” self, or perhaps a “mezzanine” self, that we cannot ignore.² Some people call this the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Philosophy to Its Limit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To do philosophy<italic>to its limit</italic>is probably to reach the limits of doing philosophy. One can philosophize to its limit, in the sense of a limit to what remains to be done, because no other solution seems possible (as when I have to miss a rendezvous even<italic>at the very limit</italic>of the deadline because something more important has come up). More significantly, philosophers have been trying recently to do philosophy<italic>at its limit</italic>, precisely because they would then reach the limit of philosophy (rejecting the ascendancy of a predicative discourse, in phenomenology, as in analytic philosophy). Going to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Staging of the Last Supper</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ever since Vatican II, public discussions of the eucharist (not to mention library shelves devoted to the topic) have been dominated, quite appropriately, by reflections on the eucharist either as a meal (a “repast”) or an “action of grace” (<italic>eu-charis</italic>): the food that gives us strength; the sharing with fellow guests; the one who presides, and so on. A curtain has been drawn, however, over the meaning of what is to be eaten—probably because the significance of transubstantiation, something inherited from medieval categories, is not simple to explain. If the eucharistic Passover is certainly<italic>bread broken for a new</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Eros Eucharisticized</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We can find confirmation in the tradition of the Church for what has been suggested here—relating the banquet and the<italic>consumption</italic>of the eucharistic body at that banquet with the<italic>consummation</italic>between spouses through the body (“consummation” being the term used to confirm the sacrament of marriage).¹ We could cite in this connection one of many examples in the commentary on the Song of Solomon (or Song of Songs) written by St. Bernard, along with his brother Guillaume de Saint-Thierry, for the Abbey of Clairvaux, when the two shared a sick-room in 1124. “I must ask you to try</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Apocalypse, in the Book of Revelation, opens with a vast introductory program of the nuptial festivities of the Lamb (Rev. 19:7) (see Part I). God takes part with humankind in the Apocalypse—they are to sojourn with him—in a sense to dwell here: “‘See the home of God is among mortals. He will dwell with them; they will be his peoples, and God himself will be with them’” (Rev. 21:3). It is not enough to call on us to dwell with God, nor even to participate in the act of the eucharist as an appropriate place for remaining or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Animal That Therefore I Am</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>scriptural</italic>figure of the sacrificial lamb, on the site of the animality in us that is taken on and transformed by God (Chapter 2), leads us now to<italic>philosophical</italic>consideration of our own metaphysical animality and to our biological roots. The question of the animal origin of humankind is not simply scientific, nor even simply ethical. We can certainly celebrate quite a few anniversaries related to the topic (e.g., publication of<italic>The Origin of Species</italic>by Darwin). Heidegger points out, “The animality of man has a deeper metaphysical ground than could ever be inferred biologically and scientifically by reffering</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Return to the Organic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From “The Animal That Thus I Am” (Chapter 4), or rather from the animality in myself that is called upon to be subsumed and converted in the act of the eucharist, we return to the organic, to this<italic>bodying life</italic>that we have already seen in the Kantian “mass of sensations” and in organs of the body as the site of drives (§ 4).¹ The organic, however, this time does not point simply to the<italic>manner</italic>, but to the<italic>matter</italic>, the organicity (or ensemble of phenomena associated with the organ), as well as the materiality (organic matter). It is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Embrace and Differentiation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The body on its own, whether we consider it as organic or as manifesting itself in flesh, is still not enough to define the content of the eucharist. The eucharisticized body is, first of all, a<italic>body given</italic>. The oblation in the eucharist belongs analytically to love, not in what theology or liturgies proclaim it to be, nor in what the benevolence of charity demands. The<italic>way of the body</italic>is that it gives itself: if it does not, it perishes in the wish to take and be taken. The carnal embrace (<italic>eros</italic>) is part of the most spiritual a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like birth or resurrection, the eucharist denotes first of all a passage. It is a passage of body to body in a transubstantiation (of bread to body and of wine to blood), an assimilation (of God in man through manducation), and an incorporation (of man in God through the mystery of the Church, of spouses). It brings about a Passover (<italic>pèsah</italic>) on the day of the Passover, or rather, it speaks the Passover. After that time when everything centred solely on the assumption of the body of Christ in the consecrated Host, we have now come to a time for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Passover of Animality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first movement of incorporation of God corresponds to humankind’s initial stage of animality. I am referring to the introduction and transformation of our animal part—made up of interior Chaos, or passions and drives (Chapters 1 and 4)—into the Word himself, who takes responsibility for all our humanity as far as and including the preserve, or district, of “that which can no longer be said” (Chapters 2 and 7). Our animality, present and offered in the bread of the eucharist, also awaits its Passover; indeed, it awaits its metamorphosis into a humanity that will recognize its divine filiation.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>“This Is My Body”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am not going to attempt here a history of the doctrine of transubstantiation. This is neither the place nor the time to attempt something that has been done perfectly well and fully discussed by others.¹ The thread of my argument here leads me instead to try to think through the transformation of our embodiedness in the act of the eucharist (eucharistic<italic>content</italic>), having rooted it in an animality that is converted into humanity through recognition of its filiation (eucharistic<italic>heritage</italic>), and before performing the donation in an agape that loses nothing of its erotic genesis even in relinquishing its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Plunging Bodily</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a paradox here: The body finds itself all the more when it is lost, or when it plunges unreservedly into something. Or at least, we can say that the body is most present when it surrenders itself. This is common knowledge. Nothing blocks a gift more than the knowledge that it is a gift; Christ’s words to the Samaritan woman—“If you knew the gift of God” (John 4:10)—are less a sign of nostalgia for ancestral knowledge than thoughtfulness concerning a desire that, in essence, could destroy the gift. As Jean-Luc Marion has pointed out, “The words</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Flesh in Common</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Ite, missa est</italic>. Go forth, the Mass is ended.¹ Or, rather, our bodies have been thrown and taken into the “enlarged body” of the Son and the Church, where the “supplement of soul” will not now fail us.² I have written the three books in this triptych; thus, there are three conclusions containing “the flesh,” one in each part. First, I discussed “the silent flesh,” or the figure of the<italic>in-fans</italic>(speechless one) in the form of a paroxysm of suffering and death waiting to be transformed (<italic>Passeur de Gethsémani</italic>[The guide to Gethsemane]). I looked then at a a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d391qf.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
