<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JZ1305 .M55 2002</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">International relations</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Millennial Reflections on International Studies</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brecher</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Harvey</surname>
               <given-names>Frank P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472112739</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472023943</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2002</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.17045"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Forty-five prominent scholars engage in self-critical, state-of-the-art reflection on international studies to stimulate debates about successes and failures and to address the larger question of progress in the discipline. Written especially for the collection, these essays are in hardcover in the form of an easy-to-use handbook, and in paperback as a number of separate titles, each of which consists of a particular thematic cluster to merge with the range of topics taught in undergraduate and graduate courses in international studies.</p>
         <p>The themes addressed are realism, institutionalism, critical perspectives, feminist theory and gender studies, methodology (formal modeling, quantitative, and qualitative), foreign policy analysis, international security and peace studies, and international political economy.</p>
         <p>This collection provides an accessible and wide-ranging survey of the issues in the field as well as an invaluable bibliography, and will undoubtedly determine the shape of future research in international studies for the millennium.</p>
         <p>Paperbacks for course adoption:</p>
         <p>Realism and Institutionalism in International StudiesMichael Brecher and Frank P. Harvey, Editors</p>
         <p>Conflict, Security, Foreign Policy, and International Political Economy:Past Paths and Future Directions in International StudiesMichael Brecher and Frank P. Harvey, Editors</p>
         <p>Evaluating Methodology in International StudiesFrank P. Harvey and Michael Brecher, Editors</p>
         <p>Critical Perspectives in International StudiesFrank P. Harvey and Michael Brecher, Editors</p>
         <p>Contributors are: Steve J. Brams, Davis B. Bobrow, Michael Cox, Robert W. Cox, Bruce Bueno de Mesquita, Joseph M. Grieco, Ernst B. Haas , Peter M. Haas, Kal J. Holsti, Ole R. Holsti, Patrick James, Robert O. Keohane, Edward A. Kolodziej, Louis Kriesberg Robert T. Kudrle, David A. Lake, Yosef Lapid, Russell Leng , Jack S. Levy, L. H. M. Ling, Zeev Maoz, Lisa L. Martin, John J. Mearsheimer, Manus I. Midlarsky, Linda B. Miller, Helen Milner , Michael Nicholson, Joseph Nye, V. Spike Peterson , Jan Jindy Pettman, James Lee Ray , James Rosenau, Harvey Starr, J. David Singer, Steve Smith, Christine Sylvester, J. Ann Tickner, John Vasquez, Yaacov Y. I. Vertzberger, R. B. J. Walker, Stephen G. Walker , Jonathan Wilkenfeld, Oran Young, Marysia Zalewski, and Dina A. Zinnes.</p>
         <p>Michael Brecher is R. B. Angus Professor of Political Science, McGill University, and former president of the International Studies Association.</p>
         <p>Frank P. Harvey is Professor of Political Science and Director, Center for Foreign Policy Studies, Dalhousie University.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="720"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Essence of Millennial Reflections on International Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brecher</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harvey</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Michael Brecher was introduced to international relations (IR) at Yale in 1946, the field comprised international politics, international law and organization, international economics, international (diplomatic) history, and a regional specialization. The hegemonic paradigm was realism, as expressed in the work of E. H. Carr, Arnold Wolfers, Nicholas Spykman, W. T. R. Fox, Hans Morgenthau, Bernard Brodie, and others.¹ The unquestioned focus of attention was interstate war and peace.</p>
                     <p>By the time the other editor of this collection, Frank Harvey, was initiated into international relations at McGill in the late 1980s, the preeminent paradigm was neorealism,² but there were several</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Realism, the Real World, and the Academy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mearsheimer</surname>
                           <given-names>John J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Realism, with its emphasis on security competition and war among the great powers, has dominated the study of international relations over the past fifty years. Hans Morgenthau and Kenneth Waltz, in particular, have towered over the field during that period. Years from now when the history of the discipline in the twentieth century is written, two books will stand out above the rest: Morgenthau’s<italic>Politics among Nations and Waltz’s Theory of International Politics</italic>. They have few serious competitors.</p>
                     <p>Many Americans and Europeans, however, believe that realism has a dim future. With the end of the cold war, so the argument</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Modern Realist Theory and the Study of International Politics in the Twenty-first Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Grieco</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Participants in the millennial reflections panels held under the auspices of the 2000 annual meeting of the International Studies Association were invited to offer self-critical reflections about the state of different elements of the field of international relations and to put forward recommendations on how these different elements might push forward most productively in the years ahead. Toward that end, I present ideas about some of the main contributions of modern realist theory to the study of world politics, a few of its main problems as an approach to international studies, and a sample of its most promising areas of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Realism and the Study of Peace and War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vasquez</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Appraising realist theories or evaluating the realist paradigm from which they are derived is a very important topic; indeed it is one that has given rise to intense debate within the field from time to time. It is, however, too broad and complicated a topic for a short essay like this one. Therefore, I shall focus on realist explanations of two specific topics—peace and war—with an emphasis on the classical realism of Morgenthau, the neorealist work of Waltz and Gilpin, and the “offensive realism” of Mearsheimer.¹</p>
                     <p>If appraising theory and evaluating paradigms is going to lead to fruitful</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Performance and Perils of Realism in the Study of International Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holsti</surname>
                           <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A long tradition of research, interpretation, and speculation about international politics goes under the name of realism. Although some dispute the pedigree as simply a “construction” of contemporary analysts, in fact a number of writers whose roster includes Machiavelli, Rousseau, Meinecke, von Gentz, Morgenthau, and Waltz, to name just a few, share a number of common themes such as their images of the world, their understanding of historical processes, the dilemmas and paradoxes that are peculiar to states that exist in a condition of anarchy, and the normative primacy of security in such an environment. They each made unique contributions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Realism and the Democratic Peace:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Primacy of State Security in New Democracies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Midlarsky</surname>
                           <given-names>Manus I.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For all of the now vast amount of research done on the democratic peace, there is still a chasm in that research that has only been very partially filled. Simply put, it is the virtual absence of the international security setting. This is all the more surprising because of the growth of international security as a field and the rather obvious concern that scholars in the field should have for the<italic>international</italic>in international relations. Perhaps it is a reaction to the emphasis on polarity during the long cold war period when structural relations dominated much of the thinking in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Systemism and International Relations:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Reassessment of Realism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>James</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay introduces the important concept of<italic>systemism</italic>as an alternative to the extremes of holism and individualism as a point of departure for theorizing about international relations. Systemism means a commitment to understanding a system in terms of a comprehensive set of functional relationships. In the context of international relations, systemism allows for a full range of connections between and among international and domestic “matters” as articulated by Waltz in the first quotation at the outset of this essay.¹ Thus the approach stands in opposition to either a “black box” or some form of reductionism, which result, respectively, from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Progress in International Relations:</title>
                     <subtitle>Beyond Paradigms in the Study of Institutions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lake</surname>
                           <given-names>David A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Progress is hard to measure, especially in one’s own era. There is certainly no consensus on the general meaning of the term, even less so when applied to scholarly inquiry. Moreover, the implications of new ideas or concepts can take generations to become apparent. It is doubtful that many of the early experimenters with electricity envisioned the role harnessing that force would eventually play in modern life. Nor did Adam Smith, writing against the mercantilist orthodoxy of his day, expect economic theory to develop its axiomatic form or become the new orthodoxy two centuries later. As a subject, progress is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Institutional Theory in International Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keohane</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert O.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joseph S. Nye has discussed our joint work on “transnational relations and interdependence” in his paper for this volume. We accordingly agreed that I would focus on my own work on institutional theory and cooperation, exemplified most clearly in my<italic>After Hegemony: Cooperation and Discord in the World Political Economy</italic>,¹ and subsequent work by myself and others. These lines of work are closely related. Our joint analysis of asymmetrical interdependence and power, and “complex interdependence,” describes the context of contemporary world politics within which my institutional theory is set. Furthermore, some of the key elements of that institutional theory appear</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Transnational Relations, Interdependence, and Globalization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nye</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph S.</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was a graduate student, I took a course taught by Hans J. Morgenthau. I was impressed by the power of the realist model and remain so. When I was in a policy position and responsible for reconstructing American alliance relations in East Asia, I relied heavily on realism.¹ In my textbook<italic>Understanding International Conflicts</italic>, I insist that students begin by understanding the realist model before they turn to liberal and constructivist theories.² But even in the early 1960s, I was equally impressed by the notion that realism captured only part of what was important in world politics. Ideas,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Are Institutions Intervening Variables or Basic Causal Forces?</title>
                     <subtitle>Causal Clusters versus Causal Chains in International Society</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Young</surname>
                           <given-names>Oran R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How should we think about the roles that institutions play as determinants of the content of collective outcomes in international society? Many mainstream analysts, whether they embrace the precepts of neorealism or lean toward the tenets of neoliberalism, assume (often implicitly) that we can understand these outcomes by envisioning causal chains in which institutions emerge as proximate forces coming into play only in the later stages of specific chains. They conclude, on the basis of this perspective, that institutions should be treated as intervening variables in contrast to basic causal forces.1 But this is by no means the only way</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Alternative and Critical Perspectives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Steve</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter is a rewritten version of the paper originally presented on one of the millennial reflections panels, but the basic argument and structure of the paper remain the same. I have kept the argument and structure largely because I was one of the few who wrote my paper in exactly the format requested by the organizers; that is, I wrote a paper that addressed each of the six questions the panel organizers asked. My fellow panelists interpreted the invitation in different, and equally legitimate, ways, but none of them answered the precise exam paper they had been sent! At</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Universality in International Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Historicist Approach</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cox</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the problems in participating on a panel entitled Alternative and Critical Perspectives is that the very nature of “alternative” is diversity and nonconformity. There can be no single alternative perspective nor any alternative school. Nor can I think of alternative as a “subfield.” Alternative is a residual category for all who are not considered to be “mainstream.” It has a clearer exclusionary meaning for those who consider themselves to be mainstream than it does for those who are so excluded. As a participant in an alternative panel, I can only write about the intellectual problems that confront me</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Continuing Story of Another Death Foretold:</title>
                     <subtitle>Radical Theory and the New International Relations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cox</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If international relations is to be judged by its capacity not just to understand the world as it is but by its proven ability to anticipate future global trends—a not unreasonable demand—then by any measure it has to be judged to have been one of the more dismal of the social sciences. The list of its failures is too long to bear repetition here and is possibly best forgotten. Others, however, might not let us forget quite so easily. As a senior editor of a leading foreign policy magazine once reminded us, consider what we, the so-called experts,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How We Learned to Escape Physics Envy and to Love Pluralism and Complexity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haas</surname>
                           <given-names>Ernst B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haas</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is cumulative knowledge and progress possible in international relations (IR)? While this essay focuses on international institutions, it may be taken as a mere illustration of much wider issues in the field of IR and social science more generally.</p>
                     <p>Students of IR remain divided on the implications of international institutions for the understanding of contemporary international relations. This is largely due, we believe, to the incommensurate epistemological and ontological positions within the discipline of IR that characterize most studies and interpretations of international institutions. In this essay we try to frame a pragmatic-constructivist approach for the study of international institutions,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>En Route to Knowledge:</title>
                     <subtitle>Is There a “Third Path” (in the Third Debate)?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lapid</surname>
                           <given-names>Yosef</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A third path leads beyond modern and postmodern methodological debates in the social sciences, history, and the humanities. It turns out that choices between the routes of science and interpretation, history and theory, objectivism and relativism are more illusionary than real.¹</p>
                     <p>Notwithstanding the general understanding that the end of the millennium may well represent an arbitrary or insignificant temporal marker, few scholarly disciplines (international relations [IR] included) have been able to resist the temptation of using this festive occasion as a pretext for another round of extensive and vigorous stock taking. Michael Burawoy, a Berkeley sociologist, perceptively notes that at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Alternative, Critical, Political</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walker</surname>
                           <given-names>R. B. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper offers a necessarily highly condensed argument about what it might mean to make judgments about the state of international relations or international studies as a scholarly discipline from some kind of alternative or critical perspective. I begin by sketching some tentative grounds on which I would presume to make judgments about judgments in this context. I then identify what I take to be four among many possible areas of convergence among the heterogeneous literatures that are currently identified, and disciplined, as alternative and critical. I then conclude by emphasizingmyoverall concern with practices of authorization, both in a specific</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Globalization of Globalization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rosenau</surname>
                           <given-names>James N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As one whose professional life exceeds that of the International Studies Association, I have mixed feelings about the invitation to reflect critically on the accomplishments, failures, debates, standards, approaches, and future agendas of international relations (IR) and its subfields. On the one hand, I have no doubt that our shared past is marked by enormous growth and progress. The conceptual and methodological equipment with which IR is probed today is far more elaborate, incisive, and diverse than was the case at the outset—back in the 1950s when a few isolated, non–Ivy League scholars first came together around common</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Fish and the Turtle:</title>
                     <subtitle>Multiple Worlds as Method</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ling</surname>
                           <given-names>L. H. M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once upon a time, there lived a colorful and proud little fish. He had lots of friends and loved the water surrounding him. He swam swiftly, quickly, and gracefully—and was very agile at getting his food. One day he met a turtle, an old friend whom he had not seen in a long time.</p>
                     <p>The fish greeted the turtle. “Hello, Sister Turtle, how are you? I have not seen you in a long time. Where have you been?”</p>
                     <p>The turtle replied, “I am fine, thank you, Fish. I was away on earth for an errand.”</p>
                     <p>“Oh, really? What is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On the Cut(ting) Edge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Peterson</surname>
                           <given-names>V. Spike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I would first like to thank the editors for inviting me to contribute to the Millennial Reflections Project. In preparing my remarks I have had the benefit of reading the essays presented at the “Feminist Theory and Gender Studies” and “Alternative and Critical Perspectives” panels. Indeed, my remarks often build on points elaborated by my colleagues and are especially indebted to Marysia Zalewski’s essay. The latter inspired the themes and the title of my own contribution. Rather than repeat arguments already articulated,myessay focuses on identifying the strengths of feminist international relations (IR)—what renders it “cutting edge”—and considering how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Critical Paradigms in International Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bringing It All Back Home?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pettman</surname>
                           <given-names>Jan Jindy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a daunting task to respond to the challenge to assess the state of the art of international studies (IS), or more particularly, feminist IS: to reflect on where we’ve come from and where we are now (and indeed who “we” are); and to ask, What’s at stake here? For me, writing as a feminist in IS, there is always a double edge, asking both what happens to the international when we take feminism seriously in IS and what happens to women, sex, gender, and feminism when we take the international seriously. I argue that IS needs feminism, to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Progress” as Feminist International Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sylvester</surname>
                           <given-names>Christine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the questions put to us by the organizers of the millennial panels at the 2000 International Studies Association (ISA) conference concerns progress: what might we, from our particular positions within a field, say about the progress of international relations (IR) in general? As it happens, I have been ruminating about progress lately, quite independently of this particular query from the ISA. I have done so mostly in the context of productions of women and progress in Zimbabwe¹ but also with respect to feminist IR and whether it has brought us—and who is that?—progress. “Progress” is an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Feminist Theory and Gender Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections for the Millennium</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tickner</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Ann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A forty-year retrospect is a difficult challenge for feminist theory and gender studies. For thirty of those years there was almost total silence on gender issues in international relations (IR); women were barely visible as scholars and foreign policy practitioners, as well as in the subject matter of the discipline. The invisibility in the discipline was not because gender was, and for some still is, irrelevant but because international relations, in both its theory and practice, was so thoroughly gendered that, in Cynthia Enloe’s words, no one noticed that women were missing.¹ So clearly, feminist approaches to IR have come</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Feminism and/in International Relations:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Exhausted Conversation? or Feminists Doing International Relations: The Cut(ting) Edge of Contemporary Critical Theory and Practice?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zalewski</surname>
                           <given-names>Marysia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>330</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In common with the other presenters on the millennial reflections feminist theory panel, I found the task at hand something of a challenge. At one level this should not be surprising; writing any academic paper usually is—and should be—a challenge. But there was something about the kinds of questions we were being asked to consider that clearly troubled our group. J. Ann Tickner, for example, suggested that the questions asked were not ones that “ feminists would ask when engaging in self-evaluation.”¹ Jan Jindy Pettman claimed that “it is a daunting task to respond to the challenges laid</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Formal Methods in International Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nicholson</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Approaches to the analysis of international relations using formal methods are now well established. Models of international relations problems appear frequently in many of the leading journals. While there are still those who hold that formal methods only manage to render obscure what had hitherto been clear, the achievements of such methods, commonplace in all the other social sciences, make such positions hard to justify. The purpose of this paper is to discuss the principles behind formalization. I also wish to justify its extensive use, mainly by conceptual argument and by referring very briefly to some of the achievements. These</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cumulation, Synthesis, and Research Design for the Post–Fourth Wave</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Starr</surname>
                           <given-names>Harvey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is both fitting and useful for the International Studies Association to ask its members to reflect on where we are in the study of international/ transnational/global politics and relations, and where the study might be going. It is similarly useful to think about areas of advance as well as the puzzles and problems that remain, and how we can do better. It is also appropriate to do so at the start not only of a new century but a new millennium. Thus, in a memo to the participants in the millennial reflection panels held at the 2000 International Studies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Accomplishments and Limitations of a Game-Theoretic Approach to International Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Mesquita</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce Bueno</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>374</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Game-theoretic reasoning emerged as an important form of analysis in international relations, especially regarding security studies, with the publication in 1960 of Thomas Schelling’s<italic>The Strategy of Conflict</italic>. The remainder of the 1960s saw a proliferation of carefully reasoned, policy-relevant studies grounded in the techniques of formal logic and rational choice modeling. A small sampling includes Daniel Ellsberg’s application of expected utility reasoning to deterrence strategy, Martin McGuire’s investigation of secrecy and arms races, Anatol Rapoport and Albert Chammah’s examination of the prisoner’s dilemma in the context of cooperation and conflict, Bruce Russett’s study of the calculus of deterrence, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Game Theory in Practice:</title>
                     <subtitle>Problems and Prospects in Applying It to International Relations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brams</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>392</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last twenty or so years, there has been a surge of interest in modeling both national security and international political economy issues using the tools of game theory.¹ I will not try to cite this now extensive literature here but instead will (1) outline four major theoretical problems that have bedeviled various attempts at game-theoretic modeling of international relations (IR) and (2) propose an alternative approach, called the “theory of moves,” that is grounded in game theory and that I and others have found attractive in modeling dynamic play. I argue that it captures the thinking of decision</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reflections on Quantitative International Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zinnes</surname>
                           <given-names>Dina A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like other members of the millennial reflections panels, I received a set of questions to guide my comments. To a large extent, however, I found the questions hard to answer within the context of a panel on quantitative methods. I am not, for example, sure that there are “unresolved debates” in regard to quantitative methods; I don’t know what “theoretical insights” we have had regarding methodology; nor am I clear as to the meaning of “a fruitful synthesis of approaches” within this context. So while I will reflect on the uses and abuses of methodology in the general field of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reflections on Millennia, Old and New:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Evolution and Role of Quantitative Approaches to the Study of International Politics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ray</surname>
                           <given-names>James Lee</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>410</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we enter the new millennium, the time seems right for a broad retrospective, introspective, and prospective analytical review of all categories of human endeavor, even including the academic study of international politics. This paper focuses on the evolution of the subfield of international politics over the last forty years, with a particular emphasis on the development of quantitative approaches. It focuses on its shortcomings but also points out what to this author at least seem worthy of being considered some accomplishments. It concludes with a few brief prescriptions for the future. It is presumptuous of me (and, to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Quantitative International Politics and Its Critics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Then and Now</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leng</surname>
                           <given-names>Russell J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>420</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One way to provide an accounting of the state of quantitative international politics at the turn of the millennium is by evaluating its record against the skepticism of its early critics. Traditional international relations scholars, in fact, took a rather jaundiced view of the scientific study of world politics when the subfield was in its infancy at the beginning of the second half of the twentieth century. One of the most skeptical critiques came from the British classicist Hedley Bull who argued that the scientific approach was “likely to contribute very little to the theory of international relations, and in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Qualitative Methods in International Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Levy</surname>
                           <given-names>Jack S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>432</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three decades ago, Sartori complained about the number of “unconscious thinkers” in the field of comparative politics, and the same could be said of the study of international relations.¹ Most qualitative analyses were idiographic rather than nomothetic,² historically specific rather than theoretically driven, and too little concerned with the logic of inference and questions of generalizability. Scholars gave little attention to the problem of how to control for extraneous variables in situations in which the number of variables typically exceeded the number of cases, or to the question of whether there are alternative methods for validating causal inferences in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Case Study Methodology in International Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Storytelling to Hypothesis Testing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maoz</surname>
                           <given-names>Zeev</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>455</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Case study is arguably the most common methodology in international studies—including both international relations and comparative politics. It is also the most widely used across subfields of the discipline. Whereas other methodologies are more likely to be associated with certain substantive subfields than others, the case study methodology appears to be sufficiently flexible so as to apply to almost all subfields. For example, it is difficult to imagine the application of game theory or rational choice models to a constructivist analysis of change in international politics, but a case study employing the concepts and tools of constructivism can be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreign Policy Analysis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Steady Progress and a Half-Empty Glass</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vertzberger</surname>
                           <given-names>Yaacov Y. I.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Foreign policy analysis (FPA), broadly defined, is a field of study that describes and investigates the structures, processes, and outcomes of the purposeful policy initiatives and responses that are conceived by sovereign political entities and directed toward other political units (not necessarily sovereign states) beyond their borders. The boundaries of the FPA domain are porous and cannot be strictly drawn, and thus it is not uncommon for some of the literature to belong in more than one field of study (e. g., security studies and FPA). Furthermore, FPA as a field of study emerged over the last four decades unbound</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Beliefs and Foreign Policy Analysis in the New Millennium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walker</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>502</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A main axis of intellectual tension in the area of foreign policy analysis over the past forty years is the issue of the importance of “beliefs”¹ in the explanation and prediction of foreign policy decisions and outcomes. The seminal decision-making approach to foreign policy articulated by Snyder, Bruck, and Sapin at midcentury was partly in reaction to a skewed emphasis by the realist tradition on external circumstances (e. g., the balance of power) and the omission of beliefs in explaining foreign policy decisions.² Snyder and his colleagues argued that this strategy of explanation came at the expense of neglecting the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Public Opinion and Foreign Policy Analysis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Where We Were, Are, and Should Strive to Be</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holsti</surname>
                           <given-names>Ole R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>514</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay examines perspectives on public opinion and foreign policy, first during the formative years of the International Studies Association and, second, at the beginning of the new millennium. Because of limited space, the essay necessarily focuses on some main currents of theory and research at the expense of drawing subtle distinctions between various perspectives on the subject. The concluding section identifies some areas that should be near or at the top of our research agendas during the coming years.</p>
                     <p>When the International Studies Association was founded in 1958, the cold war was a dominant fact of international relations. To</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Simulation and Experimentation in Foreign Policy Analysis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Personal Observations on Problems and Prospects</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilkenfeld</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>529</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While many in the field of foreign policy analysis associate me most closely with the systematic study of foreign policy behavior in general, and conflict and crisis decision making in particular—most notably, the International Crisis Behavior (ICB) Project¹—I have chosen to highlight a somewhat different direction that my recent research has taken. During the past two decades, almost as a sideline, I have been heavily involved in the conceptualization and development of simulation approaches to the teaching of international politics and foreign policy. The network-based, distributed foreign policy simulations offered by the International Communications and Negotiations Simulations (ICONS)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Security Theory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Six Paradigms Searching for Security</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kolodziej</surname>
                           <given-names>Edward A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>547</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This survey of security theory is divided into two parts. The first defines security as a political concept and phenomenon. This discussion provides a point of departure for reviewing prevailing security theories. The second, and longest, section briefly examines and evaluates the claims of six competing research programs concerned directly or indirectly with security. These include realism, neorealism, economic liberalism, liberal institutionalism, behaviorism, and constructivism. These research programs can be distinguished on the basis of their ontological, epistemological, methodological, and evidentiary assumptions about actors and their behavior. Given space constraints, the discussion will identify only the principal differences between these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Security and Peace:</title>
                     <subtitle>Understanding, Production, and Work Style</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bobrow</surname>
                           <given-names>Davis B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>569</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The most attractive accomplishment of security and peace studies and policies would be for them to become historical curiosities akin to alchemy, Victorian-era plumbing, or vanquished diseases. A second best would be signs of progress on that road marked by improved understanding and early diagnosis, and—even better—more available and less costly means for prevention and treatment, containment and cure. To extend the medical metaphor, we would then see in the present or in confident prospect reductions in the incidence and severity of insecurity, destruction, casualties, and deaths, and in the opportunity costs of measures to achieve such reductions.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Convergences Between International Security Studies and Peace Studies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kriesberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Louis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>584</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>International security studies and peace studies are not a single subfield of international relations. Analysts in security studies and those in peace studies have generally viewed themselves and been viewed by others as working in quite different domains. Some persons in each area have been critical or dismissive of the efforts of those in the other. Nevertheless, many persons across both areas actually share significant concerns and questions, such as how to avoid or to limit wars and other violent conflicts. Furthermore, the work being done in each of these domains is increasingly overlapping. To enhance the possibilities of beneficial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Accounting for Interstate War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Progress and Cumulation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Singer</surname>
                           <given-names>J. David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>598</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This turn of the millennium certainly offers us another opportunity—and incentive—to get more serious about trying to explain, and perhaps reduce the incidence of, that brutal, stupid, and destructive form of collective behavior known as war. In almost every epoch and almost every corner of human civilization, we find the politicians and the priests calling for an end to such barbarous behavior. But time after time, their prescription is to demand that the other party give up its aggressive behavior and meet the demands of our reasonable and accommodating brethren.</p>
                     <p>This recurrent pattern is nicely captured by Mark</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes from the Underground:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Tale of Three Perspectives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Linda B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>616</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The invitation to participate in a millennial reflections panel on international security and peace studies and to publish these remarks arrived at a propitious moment. The public opportunity to reappraise my own academic career as I was already doing privately meant a chance to ruminate in a way that might have value for younger scholars at earlier stages of their careers. And since my own trajectory closely parallels that of the International Studies Association (ISA) in terms of time, such an overview should be of general interest to the membership.</p>
                     <p>In that spirit, I offer what I have titled “Notes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reflections on the Field of International Political Economy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Milner</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>623</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The academic field of international political economy (IPE) is a relatively young one. As an established part of international relations (IR), it rose to prominence in the late 1960s and early 1970s. Scholarly writings that would now be called IPE date back much further,¹ but they were not widely-recognized as part of a distinct field until the 1970s.² This means that the field is only about thirty years old. The period of oil shocks in the developed countries beginning in the early 1970s provided a strong impetus to the organization of the field. It brought to the fore a set</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Some Thoughts on International Political Economy in the Context of Public Policy Education</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kudrle</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>637</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early 1980s I tried to develop an approach to international economic relations for Humphrey Institute public policy students that would combine parsimony with comprehensiveness; I was also serving on the editorial team of<italic>International Studies Quarterly.</italic>Both activities led me to think more systematically about the connections between economics and politics than I had done before. I saw no advantage in abandoning the basic theory that seemed reasonably successful in my own discipline of economics, and I had to consider the students. Public policy students with an interest in international affairs care little about the disciplinary origin of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>International Political Economy:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Paradigmatic Debates to Productive Disagreements</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>653</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In their instructions to the millennial reflections panel participants, the organizers of these panels suggested that they were necessary, in part, because of the increasing diversity of subfields and sections in the International Studies Association. They wrote that this diversity “has made increasingly difficult the crucial task of identifying intrasubfield consensus about important theoretical and/or empirical insights.” In this essay, I take issue with the organizers’ claim.</p>
                     <p>International political economy (IPE), perhaps in contrast to the field of international relations (IR) more broadly, is today characterized by growing consensus on theories, methods, analytical frameworks, and important questions. This is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusions:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Assessment of Millennial Reflections on International Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harvey</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brecher</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>661</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The questions posed to each contributor at the outset of the Millennial Reflections Project were designed to elicit self-critical reflections on the state of international studies (IS) at the dawn of a new millennium. We asked more than forty distinguished scholars to evaluate the current status and future prospects of the discipline, to assess the extent to which we have acquired significant theoretical insights, to tell us where we stand on unresolved debates and why we have failed to resolve them, to evaluate the standards we should use when selecting and applying appropriate methodologies, and to address the broader question</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.17045.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>685</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
