<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hc05</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Local Knowledge, Global Stage</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DARNELL</surname>
               <given-names>REGNA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GLEACH</surname>
               <given-names>FREDERIC W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803288102</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803295186</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803295189</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dxg7dv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Histories of Anthropology Annual presents localized perspectives on the discipline's history within a global context, with a goal of increasing awareness and use of historical approaches in teaching, learning, and conducting anthropology.This tenth volume of the series,<italic>Local Knowledge, Global Stage</italic>, examines worldwide historical trends of anthropology ranging from the assertion that all British anthropology is a study of the Old Testament to the discovery of the untranslated shorthand notes of pioneering anthropologist Franz Boas. Other topics include archival research into the study of Vancouver Island's indigenous languages, explorations of the Christian notion of virgin births in Edward Tylor's<italic>The Legend of Perseus</italic>, and the Canadian government's implementation of European-model farms as a way to undermine Native culture. In addition to Boas and Tylor, the essays explore the research and personalities of Susan Golla, Edwin Sydney Hartland, and others.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="368"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EDITORS’ INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DARNELL</surname>
                           <given-names>REGNA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GLEACH</surname>
                           <given-names>FREDERIC W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume rounds off what would have been a decade of<italic>Histories of Anthropology Annual</italic>if we had met the ideal in producing an annual volume. In actuality it has taken a couple of extra years to reach this point.<italic>HoAA</italic>began in the book division at the University of Nebraska Press, then moved to the journals portfolio, and then returned to the book division with a renewed emphasis on the stand-alone character of each volume. Each volume now has a unique title, albeit still within the mandate of<italic>HoAA</italic>to provide an outlet for work in the history of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Anthropologists and the Bible:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Marett Lecture, April 2012</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KUPER</surname>
                           <given-names>ADAM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A young philosophy don, a Jerseyman at Oxford, Robert Ranulph Marett was intrigued by the subject set for the 1893 Green Prize in Moral Philosophy: “The ethics of savage races.” He immersed himself in the literature on primitive religion, won the prize, and was befriended by the only anthropologist at Oxford University, E. B. Tylor.</p>
                     <p>Tylor was the father figure of the new anthropology that had emerged in the 1860s. It was a baggy, ambitious discipline, and Tylor himself wrote about race and technology and language and marriage, but especially about religion, and this became Marett’s main interest too. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Dead and Living Authorities in The Legend of Perseus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Animism and Christianity in the Evolutionist Archive</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSA</surname>
                           <given-names>FREDERICO D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Edwin Sidney Hartland (1848–1927) was a British solicitor and politician whose proficiency as a self-made folklorist and evolutionary anthropologist went far beyond dilettantism, following in the footsteps of his principal mentor, Edward B. Tylor (1832–1917). Hartland was a prominent figure in the Folklore Society, which he presided over at the turn of the century. Indeed, he was one of the members of the “Great Team” of British late Victorian folklorists, to use the expression coined by Richard Dorson (1968:202). Between 1884 and 1924 Hartland’s prolific production included his magnum opus: a three-volume work titled<italic>The Legend of Perseus:</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Anthropology in Portugal:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of the Portuguese Society of Anthropology and Ethnology (SPAE), 1918</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DE MATOS</surname>
                           <given-names>PATRÍCIA FERRAZ</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, several works have been published on the history of anthropology in specific national contexts (e.g., Stocking 1974, 1995; Kuklick 1991; Barth et al. 2005; Ranzmaier 2011) but little on the history of anthropology in Portugal—and the exceptions have largely been written from and for the Portuguese community (e.g., Areia and Rocha 1985; Branco 1986; Pereira 1986, 1998; Pina-Cabral 1991; Leal 2000, 2006; Roque 2001; Santos 2005; Sobral 2007; Matos 2013). Even then, with the exception of some authors such as Guimarães (1995), Pereira (1998), Roque (2001), Santos (2005), and my own work (Matos 2013), it has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A View from the West:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Institute of Social Science and the Amazon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FAULHABER</surname>
                           <given-names>PRISCILA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I focus on the significance of frontier in the history of social anthropology, especially fieldwork in the Amazon supported by the Institute of Social Science (ISS) of the University of California at Berkeley (UCB). I understand that subventions for scholarly research in the western part of the United States resonate in the scientific field of moving-frontier theories. ISS supported projects on “economic and cultural boundaries,” relocating to the social domain the former biological metaphor of botanical germination. This institute supported projects that went beyond domestic U.S. issues, embracing social problems in other countries such as Mexico and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Scientific Diplomacy and the Establishment of an Australian Chair of Anthropology, 1914–25</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GRAY</surname>
                           <given-names>GEOFFREY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the first decades of the twentieth century, Australian scientists, supported by their British counterparts, worked to convince the recently formed (1901) Commonwealth government of Australia, a federation of the states and territories,¹ of the value of anthropology. They argued that it had value as an academic discipline for two reasons: first, it sought to ascertain the laws of human sociality and origins, and second, it would be useful in training colonial field officials (Kuper 1996; Kuklick 1991; Stocking 1995). To this end they argued for the establishment of a chair of anthropology in an Australian university. It was a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Saga of the L. H. Morgan Archive, or How an American Marxist Helped Make a Bourgeois Anthropologist the Cornerstone of Soviet Ethnography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KAN</surname>
                           <given-names>SERGEI A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ARZYUTOV</surname>
                           <given-names>DMITRY V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are two reasons why a volume dedicated to the memory of George W. Stocking Jr. is, in our opinion, the most appropriate venue for this chapter. First, its American author studied with George at the University of Chicago and developed a strong interest in the history of anthropology under his influence.¹ It was Stocking who encouraged him to take advantage of his knowledge of Russian and explore the history of the relationship between Boas and his Russian colleagues, such as Vladimir Bogoraz and Lev Shternberg. A paper about Shternberg written in Stocking’s seminar eventually grew into a monograph on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>“I Wrote All My Notes in Shorthand”:</title>
                     <subtitle>A First Glance into the Treasure Chest of Franz Boas’s Shorthand Field Notes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HATOUM</surname>
                           <given-names>RAINER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no doubt that Franz Boas, the personification of American cultural anthropology and the concept of cultural relativism, eventually succeeded in making his urge come true, which he expressed in the line from a letter to his sister Toni quoted above. More importantly for this essay, though, is the fact that this urge led Boas to build for himself a lasting and monumental legacy in writing that, to this day, influences research by countless scholars both directly and indirectly. Among them are those scholars who are still trying to cope with the enormous amount of raw material left behind</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Genealogies of Knowledge in the Alberni Valley:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflecting on Ethnographic Practice in the Archive of Dr. Susan Golla</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GREEN</surname>
                           <given-names>DENISE NICOLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Asking for help is important. I learned this over the five years I spent in Nuu-chah-nulth First Nations’<italic>haahuulthii</italic>(traditional territory) as an anthropology PhD student: I witnessed networks of relatives work together to celebrate important moments in their interwoven lives through<italic>n’uushitl</italic>(potlatching) and<italic>tl’itscuu</italic>(feasting).¹ Asking for help demonstrates an understanding that most cultural “business” is larger than the individual.² One must reach out to find the appropriate resource. This is how I eventually found myself, in the fall of 2013, immersed in the archive of Dr. Susan Golla. Someone asked me for help.</p>
                     <p>In May 2012 Tseshaa-aqsup</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The File Hills Farm Colony Legacy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DESNOMIE</surname>
                           <given-names>CHEYANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>First Nations people in Canada have experienced and continue to experience a multitude of hardships at the hand of the government through various colonial and assimilation policies. The aim of this chapter is to provide a unique perspective about a little-known facet of Canadian history, the File Hills Farm Colony, and to engage in an accurate ethnographic representation of contemporary indigenous peoples that avoids the hazards of stereotyping, idealizing, and freezing in time and space.</p>
                     <p>A social experiment grounded in British colonial expansionist ideology, the File Hills Farm Colony was created by the Canadian government in southern Saskatchewan in 1897.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7dv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
