<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27h1m</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3238 .W4 2018</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Whitman &amp; Dickinson</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Colloquy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Athenot</surname>
               <given-names>Éric</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Miller</surname>
               <given-names>Cristanne</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781609385316</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781609385323</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Iowa Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>IOWA CITY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Iowa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1z27hqz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Whitman &amp; Dickinson</italic>is the first collection to bring together original essays by European and North American scholars directly linking the poetry and ideas of Walt Whitman and Emily Dickinson. The essays present intersections between these great figures across several fields of study, rehearsing well-established topics from new perspectives, opening entirely new areas of investigation, and providing new information about Whitman's and Dickinson's lives, work, and reception.Essays included in this book cover the topics of mentoring influence on each poet, religion, the Civil War, phenomenology, the environment, humor, poetic structures of language, and Whitman's and Dickinson's twentieth- and twenty-first-century reception-including prolonged engagement with Adrienne Rich's response to this "strange uncoupled couple" of poets who stand at the beginning of an American national poetic.Contributors Include:Marina Camboni Andrew Dorkin Vincent DussolBetsy Erkkilä Ed FolsomChristine GerhardtJay GrossmanJennifer LeaderMarianne NobleCécile RoudeauShira Wolosky</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="276"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments and Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Transatlantic Convergences and New Directions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ATHENOT</surname>
                           <given-names>ÉRIC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MILLER</surname>
                           <given-names>CRISTANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2015 it had been 150 years since both walt whitman and Emily Dickinson had produced the better part of their poetic output. This collection of essays stems from a “colloquy” that brought scholars together to discuss these poets explicitly in relation to each other for the first time in all those 150 years. As any bibliographical search will confirm, Whitman and Dickinson have frequently inspired fruitful and exciting scholarship when analyzed comparatively—as they have been in several essays, especially from the 1960s on. Naturally, they also have figured alongside each other in nineteenth-century U.S. literature survey courses around</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rethinking the (Non)Convergence of Dickinson and Whitman:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Origins of American Poetry as We Know It</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FOLSOM</surname>
                           <given-names>ED</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are now at the end of a full century, in the case of Walt Whitman, and well over a half century, in the case of Emily Dickinson, of serious critical investigation of the two poets that virtually everyone now agrees mark the beginnings of a unique American poetic tradition—a dynamic, two-pronged tradition of radical innovation. American poetry, as we conceive of it today, truly is the product of an unbelievable convergence—two contemporaneous poets, one female, one male, one a New Englander to the core, one a New Yorker through and through, both working to name an intense</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Sickly Abstractions” and the Poetic Concrete:</title>
                     <subtitle>Whitman’s and Dickinson’s Battlefields of War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROUDEAU</surname>
                           <given-names>CÉCILE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What good are poets in a time of crisis? more than 150 years after the conflict’s ending, Hölderlin’s query continues to haunt the battlefields of the U.S. Civil War.² While Walt Whitman visited the wounded in the hospitals of Washington and stained his notebooks with more than blood, Emily Dickinson saw her life unexpectedly enmeshed in the ongoing bloodshed, and “s[ang] off charnel steps” (<italic>L</italic>298) as the death tolls of the battlegrounds repeatedly reached the gates of her Amherst family home. “War feels to me an oblique place,” she wrote in February 1863 to Thomas Wentworth Higginson (<italic>L</italic>280).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dickinson|Whitman:</title>
                     <subtitle>Figural Mirrors in Biblical Traditions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WOLOSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>SHIRA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite their pronounced differences, dickinson and Whitman are looking-glass reflections of each other and of America; although, as in facing mirrors, each one’s work is also the inverse of the other. One crux of this mutual reflection is their shared figural traditions of American culture. These originate in the biblical typologies that promised to align not only spiritual and mundane worlds, but the extensions of these into self, community, history, and God. Each practices and also tests this habit of figural alignment. The poetry of each is figurally complex, in ways often overlooked in Whitman (who can seem like the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“No Man Saw Awe” / “In the Talk of … God … He Is Silent”:</title>
                     <subtitle>(Not) Seeing and (Not) Saying the Numinous in Dickinson and Whitman</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEADER</surname>
                           <given-names>JENNIFER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One might imagine that for all her admiration of ralph Waldo Emerson, Emily Dickinson would secretly have agreed with Walt Whitman’s sideswipe at that oracle on the occasion of Emerson’s birthday; in an 1880 essay in the<italic>Boston Literary World</italic>, Whitman wrote: “At times it has been doubtful to me if Emerson really knows or feels what Poetry is at its highest, as in the Bible, for instance, or Homer or Shakspere…. Of<italic>power</italic>he seems to have a gentleman’s admiration—but in his inmost heart the grandest attribute of God and Poets is always subordinate to the octaves, conceits,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Phenomenological Approaches to Human Contact in Whitman and Dickinson</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NOBLE</surname>
                           <given-names>MARIANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Antebellum american literature is permeated by a yearning for human contact. Ralph Waldo Emerson, for example, despairs that relationships are superficial, indeed that all of our experiences are superficial. Our encounters with people and the things of life never satisfy our hunger for the real. In his 1844 essay “Experience,” he writes:</p>
                     <p>There are moods in which we court suffering, in the hope that here, at least, we shall find reality, sharp peaks and edges of truth. But it turns out to be scene-painting and counterfeit. The only thing grief has taught me, is to know how shallow it is.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“We Must Travel Abreast with Nature, if We Want to Understand Her”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Place and Mobility in Dickinson’s and Whitman’s Environmental Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GERHARDT</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past decade, ecocritical approaches have profoundly changed the way we read Dickinson and Whitman. In particular, ecocritical analyses have stressed that for all the symbolic and transcendental orientation of Dickinson’s and Whitman’s poetry, an abiding interest in physical places and people’s relationships to specific geographies constitutes a defining feature of their art that has important ecological implications. However, most of these green rereadings have put special emphasis on Dickinson’s and Whitman’s rendition of local areas and people’s steady ties to their environs. In the case of Dickinson, ecocritics have argued that she challenged patriarchal paradigms through a “located”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Hyperbole and Humor in Whitman and Dickinson</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DORKIN</surname>
                           <given-names>ANDREW</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MILLER</surname>
                           <given-names>CRISTANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a long, if somewhat sporadic, history of scholarship acknowledging both Whitman and Dickinson as humorists.¹ Still, these poets’ exaggerated or hyperbolic claims are often read seriously, making Whitman seem egotistical and Dickinson depressed or without self-esteem. In this essay, we argue that the figure of hyperbole is both intrinsically linked with humor and a key element in what makes both poets’ work at once colloquially familiar and radically disorienting. For Whitman and Dickinson the use of hyperbole extends other features of their work that defamiliarize and disorient readers’ values, perceptions, and cognitive processes, while simultaneously creating the effect</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Radical Imaginaries:</title>
                     <subtitle>Crossing Over with Whitman and Dickinson</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ERKKILA</surname>
                           <given-names>BETSY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A decade ago, among american scholars, those who worked on Walt Whitman and those who worked on Emily Dickinson tended to divide into two distinct groups. Those who worked on Whitman, almost exclusively men, rarely ventured into Dickinson studies, which was dominated mostly by women, and those who worked on Dickinson had little to say about Whitman, except to negate his spread-eagle poetics and politics in comparison with the serious experimental art of Emily Dickinson. In recent years, as this collection and the historic conference it embodies make clear, this appears to have changed. But as someone who began my</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Queer Contingencies of Canonicity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dickinson, Whitman, Jewett, Matthiessen</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GROSSMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JAY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For many readers since its publication in 1941, the omission of Emily Dickinson from F. O. Matthiessen’s landmark<italic>American Renaissance: Art and Expression in the Age of Emerson and Whitman</italic>is among its most egregious and often-noted shortcomings.¹ So imagine my surprise to have found a letter from 1931 in which Matthiessen insists upon Dickinson’s necessary place in the following year’s survey of American literature for Harvard undergraduates. Matthiessen writes to his partner, Russell Cheney, about a meeting with his Harvard colleague Kenneth Murdock regarding the syllabus for their co-taught American literature course:</p>
                     <p>The actual scheme of the course, between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Whitman, Dickinson, and Their Legacy of Lists and “It”s</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DUSSOL</surname>
                           <given-names>VINCENT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Indirection—Dickinson’s “Angled Road” (Fr 899)—sometimes works best: a fragment in French author Georges Perros’s<italic>Papiers collés II</italic>suggests the special relationship that seems to link lists to indefinites in Walt Whitman’s and Emily Dickinson’s poetry:</p>
                     <p>There is something that the language we use … is very far from approaching, be it at the acme of communication, something which does not belong to us but concerns us, something like the Christians’ god, and Christ’s “Do not touch me.”</p>
                     <p>There is something which resists such communication, which will not hear of<italic>it</italic>but which keeps worrying us day and night</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Beginners”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rereading Whitman and Dickinson through Rich’s Lens</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAMBONI</surname>
                           <given-names>MARINA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Beginners” is the theoretical location in Adrienne Rich’s critical work where, taking as her starting point the eponymous poem Walt Whitman first published in the 1860–61 edition of<italic>Leaves of Grass</italic>, she develops a complex vision of American poetry while also building the genealogical line that would ultimately include her own work.² That location maps the plural logic of the poet who is not only committed to the truth of a “language intensified, intensifying our sense of possible reality,” but whose “poetic imagination” is “radical, meaning root-tangled in the grit of human arrangements and relationships:<italic>how we are with</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1z27hqz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
