<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hj9w7s</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Seamus Heaney as Aesthetic Thinker</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Study of the Prose</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>O’Brien</surname>
               <given-names>Eugene</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MacKillop</surname>
               <given-names>James</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>Series Editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780815653721</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0815653727</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Syracuse University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Syracuse, New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Syracuse University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j1nw0t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Seamus Heaney’s unexpected death in August 2013 brought to completion his body of work, and scholars are only now coming to understand the full scale and importance of this extraordinary career. The Nobel Prize–winning poet, translator, and playwright from the North of Ireland is considered the most important Irish poet after Yeats and, at the time of his death, arguably the most famous living poet. For this reason, much of the scholarship to date on Heaney has understandably focused on his poetry. O’Brien’s new work, however, focuses on Heaney’s essays, book chapters, and lectures as it seeks to understand how Heaney explored the poet’s role in the world. By examining Heaney’s prose, O’Brien teases out a clearer understanding of Heaney’s sense of the function of poetry as an act of public intellectual and ethical inquiry. In doing so, O’Brien reads Heaney as an aesthetic thinker in the European tradition, considering him alongside Heidegger, Derrida, Lacan, and Adorno. Studying Heaney within this theoretical and philosophical tradition sheds new and useful light on one of the greatest creative minds of the twentieth century.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Structure of Poetic Thinking</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an ever-growing list of studies on the work of Seamus Heaney, this book will attempt something different. His poetry will not be the focus of analysis, except where it is relevant to the main theme, which is an outline of Heaney as an aesthetic thinker in the European intellectual tradition. This tradition, generally located in the sphere of Continental philosophy and cultural theory, sees the aesthetic as a valid epistemological mode of thinking. From Plato through Immanuel Kant and Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel to contemporary philosophical and theoretical writers such as Martin Heidegger, Theodor Adorno, Jacques Lacan, Jacques Derrida,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Poet as Thinker—the Thinker as Poet</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That this is only the second sustained study of Heaney’s prose is surprising, but it is an issue that needs to be addressed at this stage. Generally, he is seen as a poet who gives occasional lectures, writes occasional pieces, and gives interviews; he is not generally seen as an aesthetic thinker, but this point is what I will be arguing, and I think some basics facts about Heaney’s academic career will underline the relevance of my position. Seamus Heaney’s intellectual career began not so much as a poet per se, but as someone who thinks, writes, and teaches about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Space:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Final Frontier</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I will offer readings of essays that demonstrate how Heaney expands the borders and the limits of texts and ideas and how, as an aesthetic thinker, he offers genuinely new perspectives and new ways of looking at paradigms of identity that have traditionally been seen as running on regular tramlines. He looks at the political context of different aspects of literature and also allows the cultural sphere to complicate the political binarism of British-Irish and colonizer-colonized. His engagement with the signifieds of postcolonial theory is framed by his very specific views on the role and force of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Epistemology of Poetry:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fields of Force</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter, we looked at representations of the frontier or border and at poetry both as an epistemological crossing of that border and also as a way of engaging with, and connecting, both sides of that border, whether these sides are self and other, Irish and English identities, or conscious thought and unconscious. This sense of poetry as a genre wherein the necessity of “either/or” choices can be replaced with the more encompassing “both/and” alternative further rhizomatically connects Heaney’s thought with Derrida’s, and with other contemporary European thinking, where meaning and signification are viewed as relational as opposed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Poetics and Politics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Surviving Amphibiously</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has become a truism to say that politics and poetry should not be conflated. This suspicion of the role of poetry in the public sphere has existed as far back as Plato, but became something of an orthodoxy in the period that saw the rise of fascism in Europe. Fascism in Germany, Italy, and Spain merged the divisions between the rational and the emotional and between the constative and the performative, as the public sphere became a dramatic space where the concept of the people, the<italic>Volk</italic>, was embodied and dramatized through massive sociocultural performative theater. Walter Benjamin was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Place of Writing—the Writing of Place</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter will look at the ambiguous relationship between place and writing in the thinking of Seamus Heaney. In the last chapter, we looked at how the aesthetic can be used to validate a monological, monofocal, and motivated connection between a people, a language, and a place. In this chapter, we will examine the careful and nuanced manner in which Heaney treats the connections between place and people in his work. Heaney is well aware of the attenuating influence of the “appetites of gravity” as he describes them (Heaney 1975, 43), which fuse a people to a place, and he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Translations:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Voice of the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In keeping with his view of poetry as encouraging complex and dialectical transformations of the actual, this chapter will discuss how Heaney grants both the effectiveness and the plurality of identifications of Irishness through a further structure, translation. Heaney has spoken a lot about complex structures of meaning and identity, and he has stressed the importance of plurality and influence in his thinking, and in his writing. We have seen his political amphibiousness as well as his displacement and dislocation of foundational attachments to place. We have also seen that he is keen to use the aesthetic as a tool</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aesthetic Responsibilities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Seamus Heaney’s fame derives primarily from his poetry, and this book does not attempt to gainsay that reputation. Heaney’s poetry is a resonant enunciation of the aesthetic in the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries and will be a lasting legacy in times to come. What this book has attempted to do is to demonstrate that, as well as being a practitioner, Heaney is a philosophical thinker on the aesthetic and on its value in defining knowledge and influencing critique, both internally in terms of individual self-knowledge and also in terms of issues in the broader public sphere. I see</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j1nw0t.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
