<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS29.M55P76 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Miller, J. Hillis (Joseph Hillis), 1928–</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism.</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Provocations to Reading: J. Hillis Miller and the Democracy to Come</book-title>
         <subtitle>J. Hillis Miller and the Democracy to Come</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cohen</surname>
               <given-names>Barbara L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kujundžić</surname>
               <given-names>Dragan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823224319</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823275090</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c999h9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book is a marker of the state of theorytoday. Its rich array of wideranging essays explores the dimensions and implications of the work of J. Hillis Miller, one of the most eminent literary scholars in America. For nearly half a century, Miller has been known for his close and imaginative engagement with the implications of European philosophical thought and for his passionate advocacy of close reading.Building on this intellectual legacy, the contributors instantiate and extend the practice and ethics of sustained close reading that is Miller's hallmark. The book culminates in a moving piece by Jacques Derrida, Miller's close friend of forty years, who engages Miller's readings of Gerard Manley Hopkins in a historic encounter between French philosophy and American reading practices.A provocation to reading for new generations of students and teachers, these essays offer important resources for grasping the question of language in historical perspective and in contemporary life-a task essential for any democratic future. Barbara Cohen is Director of HumaniTech at the University of California, Irvine. She is co-editor of Material Events: Paul de Man and the Afterlife of Theory. Dragan Kujunzic is Professor of Russian and Comparative Literature and Director of Russian Studies at the University of California, Irvine. Among his publications is The Returns of History: Russian Nietzscheans after Modernity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Barbara L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kujundžić</surname>
                           <given-names>Dragan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume is inspired by the work of J. Hillis Miller (b. 1928). Miller’s career and work span more than five decades, some fifty edited volumes and monographs (not counting translations and frequent reprints and editions of his works), and honorary doctorates and teaching positions in dozens of universities in the United States and abroad. Miller’s students and colleagues are numerous and form an ever-growing group of outstanding scholars of every generation, as this volume and several others currently in progress amply testify.¹</p>
                     <p>The keynote presentations by J. Hillis Miller and Jacques Derrida at the “J” conference mentioned in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>“J” Is for Jouissance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MacCannell</surname>
                           <given-names>Juliet Flower</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For me, the most valuable aspect of J. Hillis Miller’s work is his persistent questioning of literary language in the context of a widely ranging philosophical inquiry into the human (and lately the inhuman) conditions in which literature emerges. From his first to his most recent books, we find Miller courageously confronting whatever the mind has thought unfathomable. Indeed, Hillis Miller is one of the few great critics of our time to underscore precisely the<italic>provocative</italic>element in literature as he unfailingly highlights how literature stirs the mental labor necessary to face whatever threatens to flood the mind and ruin</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Broadening the Horizon:</title>
                     <subtitle>On J. Hillis Miller’s Ananarratology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shen</surname>
                           <given-names>Dan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of the influential deconstructive theorists and critics, J. Hillis Miller distinguishes himself by his serious engagement with structuralist narratology. About two decades ago, Miller carried out an influential dialogue with the narratologist Shlomith Rimmon-Kenan in<italic>Poetics Today</italic>,¹ and quite recently, in his<italic>Reading Narrative</italic>, which he calls “a work of ananarratology,”² Miller gives a forceful challenge to structuralist narratology in terms of both plot structure and discourse presentation. The present essay argues that ananarratology and narratology, although holding opposite and irreconcilable views on narrative, are to a certain extent complementary to each other. Miller’s ananarratology functions to broaden the horizon</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Finding the Zumbah:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Analysis of Infelicity in Speech Acts in Literature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Odom</surname>
                           <given-names>Glenn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>J. Hillis Miller begins<italic>Speech Acts in Literature</italic>with a promise to show the problematic nature of speech acts in and as literature.¹ Miller’s promise has the authorization that comes, as he says “by being ‘appointed,’ by being given ‘tenure,’ by having [his] seminar description approved beforehand” (4). My critique of his work carries with it none of Miller’s authority. I am perhaps, to cite Miller’s citation of J. L. Austin, “Some Low Type” (or perhaps I should say “‘some low type,’” since this is my citation of Miller’s citation of Austin, a graduate student attempting to claim authority (ibid.).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Between “the Cup and the Lip”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Retroactive Constructions of Inheritance in Our Mutual Friend</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Castillo</surname>
                           <given-names>Larisa Tokmakoff</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Charles Dickens’s<italic>Our Mutual Friend</italic>is a retroactively oriented text, a text that works to undo the events that actuate it. The text begins with an ending, a corpse being drawn from the Thames, and withholds the circumstances surrounding this central event until half of the plot has transpired. While we learn the victim’s history much sooner than we do the events leading to his death, his history, nonetheless, is represented inconsecutively—after his demise. We are never to meet the victim himself; we are never to hear his story from his lips; we are never to receive a linear</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Hillis’s Charity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Williams</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>J. Hillis Miller has loved well as a writer, critic, and theorist. For Hillis, one cannot read well without love—reading is a matter of love because one must submit oneself to an uncontrollable performative force that arises when one attends to a radical recognition of difference in the text. Miller’s long career teaches us that love is the primary obligation that binds the critic to his or her work because instead of covering over a multitude of sins and acting as a blinding or obfuscating force, love requires the critic to respond to the absolute differences and particularities of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>“J”; or, Hillis le mal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cohen</surname>
                           <given-names>Tom</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No one reads letters anymore. E-mail perhaps, but not letters in the manner of the passage cited above. And one can see why. It is not a matter of “fashion”—as if close reading, whatever “close” meant, has had its moment. It could simply be that one cannot bear to. One cannot bear to get near to that space, connected to letteration as sheer form, only not because of the usual alibi—that it does not provide historical reference and so on.<italic>Au contraire</italic>: perhaps it is because of the suspense. It brings us too close to the virtuality of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>The Afterlife of Judaism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Zohar, Benjamin, Miller</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sussman</surname>
                           <given-names>Henry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Judaism, so the common myth runs, is the Abrahamic¹ religion devoid of an afterlife. Where first Christianity and then Islam are quite explicit regarding the determination of the life hereafter by the quality of the life lived in this world, picturesque almost to the degree of luridness in representing the conditions, qualities, and experience of Heaven and Hell (and Purgatory, where applicable), Judaism hedges its bets and is far more reticent in the sphere of eschatology.² The liturgy of the Days of Awe, the New Year’s festivals that stage the collective public acknowledgment of mortal human vices, breeches in morality,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>On the Line</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gelley</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Ariadne’s Thread: Story Lines</italic>,¹ J. Hillis Miller begins with a fable of reading, a fable in which the reader, although presumably following a (straight) line, is continually sidetracked, led off course, and thus forced into labyrinthine byways. How did the reader get into this trap? He thought he was reading a story, but he finds he is that story and can’t get out: “These blind alleys in the analysis of narrative may not by any means be avoided. They may only be veiled by some credulity making a standing place where there is an abyss” (23).</p>
                     <p>What drew me</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>War on Terror</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Redfield</surname>
                           <given-names>Marc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Who speaks, and in what mode, when war is declared on terror? What are the conditions of possibility for this speech act; what clumps of historical context cling to it? To what performative felicity could it aspire? Has such a declaration of war indeed occurred? Could it occur or, for that matter, not occur? Both in what the United States government is now calling the “homeland” and in those generally more distant places where the fighting and killing is going on, the world is now enduring the consequences of what the Western media proclaims, over and over, to be a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>American Literary Studies and American Cultural Studies in the Times of the National Emergency:</title>
                     <subtitle>J’s Paradoxes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pease</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unlike many of the other contributors to this volume, I regret to say that I never had the occasion to study under Hillis Miller in graduate school. And until October of 2002 , I had never enjoyed the benefits of J. Hillis Miller’s prodigious gift for collegiality.¹ When I undertook a course of graduate study in the field of American literature nearly three decades ago at the University of Chicago, I did so under the tutelage of James Edwin Miller, Jr., in the methodology of the myth-symbol school of literary interpretation whose dominance of the field of American literary studies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>“J” Is for Just a Minute:</title>
                     <subtitle>It’s Miller Time When It Shimmers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kamuf</surname>
                           <given-names>Peggy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I heard the beginning of a phrase repeated a propos of this gathering, “J is for . . . ,” it was inevitable, even fatal that I would complete it first in a certain way: “J is for just a minute.” In the idiom of my family, that is something one said—above all my father used to say it—to force a pause, a little more patience when he was being pressed for answers or decisions. By itself, it’s a bit of nonsense, a kind of useless mnemonic device, which is why it could usually effect the pause</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Three Literary Theorists in Search of 0</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Hillis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a quite remarkable recent essay, “Auktorialität: Die Nullstelle des Diskurses” (Authoritality: The zero point of discourse), Wolfgang Iser uses the mathematical zero as a figure for what he calls “the authorial instance [<italic>der auktorialen Instanz</italic>].”¹ The authorial instance is the generative source of a literary or philosophical text. I want first to juxtapose Iser’s essay to two brief essays by Maurice Blanchot that also explicitly use “zero” as a figure for a starting point or origin. I will then turn to Paul de Man’s Pascal essay.² The juxtaposition of Iser and Blanchot brings to the fore what is seemingly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 13</label>
                     <title>Justices</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Derrida</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacques</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>J’aurais dû commencer</italic>, I should have begun, even before an exergue, by wishing my translator, Peggy Kamuf, “good luck,” while thanking her from the bottom of my heart.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Je me dis d’abord</italic>, I say to myself first, that my French<italic>J</italic>will have been lost from the first letter of the first word. I’m not talking here about my first name, but about my<italic>je</italic>, my I and my<italic>jeu</italic>with<italic>je</italic>, my play with I.<italic>Je</italic>(I) will have withdrawn, effaced itself from the first letter of the first word.<italic>Je est un autre</italic>. I is another one.</p>
                     <p>Nevertheless,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999h9.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
