<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX8611 .M77 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mormon Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Book of Mormon</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Race</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Mormon Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Race relations</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Mormon Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mormon Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Membership</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mormons</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">West (U.S.)</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Race and the Making of the Mormon People</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MUELLER</surname>
               <given-names>MAX PERRY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781469633770</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1469633779</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The University of North Carolina Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Chapel Hill</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The University of North Carolina Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5149/9781469633763_mueller"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The nineteenth-century history of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, Max Perry Mueller argues, illuminates the role that religion played in forming the notion of three "original" American races-red, black, and white-for Mormons and others in the early American Republic. Recovering the voices of a handful of black and Native American Mormons who resolutely wrote themselves into the Mormon archive, Mueller threads together historical experience and Mormon scriptural interpretations. He finds that the Book of Mormon is key to understanding how early followers reflected but also departed from antebellum conceptions of race as biblically and biologically predetermined. Mormon theology and policy both challenged and reaffirmed the essentialist nature of the racialized American experience.The Book of Mormon presented its believers with a radical worldview, proclaiming that all schisms within the human family were anathematic to God's design. That said, church founders were not racial egalitarians. They promoted whiteness as an aspirational racial identity that nonwhites could achieve through conversion to Mormonism. Mueller also shows how, on a broader level, scripture and history may become mutually constituted. For the Mormons, that process shaped a religious movement in perpetual tension between its racialist and universalist impulses during an era before the concept of race was secularized.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PROLOGUE.</title>
                     <subtitle>Visions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joseph Smith Jr. was seventeen years old in 1823 when the Angel Moroni first appeared to him in the bedroom that he shared with his five brothers in their western New York log home. The tall, flaxen-haired, blue-eyed, semiliterate farm boy had just finished his nightly prayers. Suddenly a personage “glorious beyond description” appeared before him, Smith recalled years later. Moroni, the historian-prophet and last member of a white-skinned race of pre-Columbian Native Americans resurrected as an angel, hovered above the floorboards. Moroni’s gleaming white robes emitted such bright light that the dark room seemed to be filled with noonday</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>Race on the Page, Race on the Body</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a study of race and how Americans write about it. In America, writing about race with ink and paper has shaped the race that people see on the flesh and bone bodies of others and of themselves. Words that describe degrees of distinction—shade of skin, curl of hair, shape of lips and eyes—get read onto bodies as distinctions of kind. That is, in American history, writing about race has done the cultural work of defining racial sameness as well as racial difference. Yet in America, writing about race does not end with racial description and classification.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE BOOK OF MORMON:</title>
                     <subtitle>A (White) Universal Gospel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Joseph Smith Jr. and his earliest followers, the Book of Mormon was more than a book. It was an Indian treasure of ancient golden plates unearthed from a hill called Cumorah located just south of an Upstate New York canal town. It was the last material remnant of a once great pre-Columbian American civilization. It was a history of the origins of America’s native inhabitants. It was a record of Christ’s first mission to the New World as well as a prophetic account of Christ’s imminent return (fig. 1.1).</p>
                     <p>And yet for those who accepted the Book of Mormon</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>MARKETING THE BOOK OF MORMON TO NOAH’S THREE SONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was March 1830. Broadsheets hung from the rafters and the sweet, metallic smell of drying ink filled the air of E. B. Grandin’s third floor printing office located on Main Street of Palmyra, New York, a bustling Erie Canal town of some five thousand residents. As he set type for the March 26 edition of the<italic>Wayne Sentinel</italic>, the twenty-four-year-old newspaperman was racked with anxiety and doubt.</p>
                     <p>In the previous week’s edition, Grandin printed the bloodless announcement, “<italic>We are requested</italic>to announce that the ‘Book of Mormon’ will be ready for sale in the course of next week.”¹ Grandin’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>FROM GENTILE TO ISRAELITE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By the summer of 1833, the initial wariness that the old settlers of Jackson County, Missouri, felt toward the county’s new residents turned to outrage. Days after the publication of “Free People of Color,” the county’s political leaders met at the Independence courthouse, just across the street from W. W. Phelps’s printing office. There they penned their anti-Mormon manifesto. The Mormons had shown “their true colors” with the July issue of the<italic>Evening and the Morning Star</italic>. They sought to build their New Jerusalem—populated by Indian, Gentile, and “free negroes and mulattos”—in the Missourians’ backyard. The old settlers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>“AUNT JANE” OR JOSEPH’S ADOPTED DAUGHTER?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In late 1843, Joseph Smith’s wife Emma Hale Smith greeted Jane Manning and nine of her family members at the front door of the Mansion House in Nauvoo, Illinois.¹ The two-story Greek Revival building served as the Smiths’ private home and guesthouse for visiting dignitaries to the Latter-day Saints’ booming city-state built on the banks of the Mississippi in western Illinois. The travelers were exhausted. To join their new spiritual brethren, the Mannings had trekked from their home in Connecticut, where the black converts first heard and accepted the Mormon gospel. Yet before he sent them to bed, Joseph Smith</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>PEOPLE BUILDING, ON BODIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the first week of May 1854, the daguerreotypist and portrait artist for John C. Frémont’s final Rocky Mountain expedition, Solomon Nunes Carvalho, traveled south from the Salt Lake Valley with Brigham Young, the president and prophet of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, Utah’s territorial governor, and its ex-officio superintendent of Indian affairs. Young had invited Carvalho, a Sephardic Jew from South Carolina, to join his Mormon cavalcade. The large party, which was making a late spring swing through the growing communities south of the Mormon capital, included Young’s first counselor Heber C. Kimball, apostle Parley P.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>PEOPLE BUILDING, ON PAPER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On January 23, 1852, Brigham Young took to the podium in the central chamber of the Council House built at the southwest corner of what would become Salt Lake City’s Temple Square. Utah’s newly constituted territorial representatives had gathered in the stately two-story, granite and adobe edifice. There they listened to the Mormon prophet and territorial governor call for the passage of laws that would sanction slavery in Utah. Young urged his brethren and fellow lawmakers to legalize the enslavement of “Africans” whom wealthy southern converts, including a few territorial legislators, had brought as slaves into their Zion of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EPILOGUE.</title>
                     <subtitle>Performing Red, Black, and White American</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jane Manning James is dressed in her Sunday best. She wears a dark silk dress. It is cinched at her neck and adorned with a white collar—the preferred fashion of many late nineteenth-century Mormon women. The dress bundles at her waist, then flows down to her feet. She is seated, leaning slightly on her left arm, which is bent at a ninety-degree angle and placed on the drape-covered table next to her. Clutching a white handkerchief, her right hand is positioned in her lap. Her hair is parted in the middle and pulled back to a bun. Her ears</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">9781469633763_mueller.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
