<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Tastes of the Divine: Hindu and Christian Theologies of Emotion</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROBERTS</surname>
               <given-names>MICHELLE VOSS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823257386</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823257409</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13wzvhj"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The intensity and meaningfulness of aesthetic experience have often been described in theological terms. By designating basic human emotions as rasa, a word that connotes taste, flavor, or essence, Indian aesthetic theory conceptualizes emotional states as something to be savored. At their core, emotions can be tastes of the divine. In this book, the methods of the emerging discipline of comparative theology enable the author's appreciation of Hindu texts and practices to illuminate her Christian reflections on aesthetics and emotion. Three emotions vie for prominence in the religious sphere: peace, love, and fury. Whereas Indian theorists following Abhinavagupta claim that the aesthetic emotion of peace best approximates the goal of religious experience, devotees of Krishna and medieval Christian readings of the Song of Songs argue that love communicates most powerfully with divinity. In response to the transcendence emphasized in both approaches, the book turns to fury at injustice to attend to emotion's foundations in the material realm. The implications of this constructive theology of emotion for Christian liturgy, pastoral care, and social engagement are manifold.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SANSKRIT PRONUNCIATION GUIDE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>RASA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Prior to its use as a term for aesthetic delight,<italic>rasa</italic>had basic meanings of taste, relishing, or the essence of a thing.<italic>Rasa</italic>denotes juice or sap, as well as a special concoction of various ingredients that yields a unique flavor distinct from any one of the ingredients. The word<italic>rasa</italic>also applies to each of the six flavors—sweet, bitter, sour, salty, pungent, and astringent—which impart unique gustatory experiences.¹<italic>Rasa</italic>’s use as a technical aesthetic term derives from the Indian tradition of dance-drama in Bharata’s<italic>Nāṭya Śāstra</italic>, where it denotes emotional states savored by spectators of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Bliss of Peace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The peaceful feeling of transcendence palpable in the NBCLC chapel is<italic>śānta</italic>, the<italic>rasa</italic>of peace.<italic>Śānta</italic>won a place as the ninth<italic>rasa</italic>, in addition to the eight enumerated by Bharata, after long debate. Abhinavagupta (tenth century), possibly India’s greatest literary theorist, champions<italic>śānta</italic>as the ninth and most important<italic>rasa</italic>, the one into which all other aesthetic emotions eventually resolve. We shall consider Abhinavagupta’s notion of<italic>śānta</italic>as it evolves in his works of literary criticism: the<italic>Locana</italic>(<italic>Loc</italic>), a commentary on Ānandavardhana’s<italic>Dhvanyāloka</italic>(<italic>DhĀ</italic>);² and the<italic>Abhinavabhāratī</italic>(<italic>ABh</italic>), a commentary on the<italic>Nāṭya Śāstra</italic>.³ As not only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Suffering and Peace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the work of Jyoti Sahi, a contemporary Indian Christian artist who resides near Bangalore, the peaceful sentiment has a special place among the<italic>rasas</italic>. Much of Sahi’s work explores the interplay of opposites in relation to Indian culture and religion. His book<italic>The Child and the Serpent</italic>, for example, looks for symbols of unconscious structures (the serpent) and their birth into consciousness (the child). His use of Jungian psychology grounds his keen interest in Hindu art and mythology in pre-Aryan themes and rituals, so that he draws inspiration both from high Sanskritic culture and from Dalit and Tribal folk</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Rasa of Love Incarnate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The followers of the medieval<italic>bhakti</italic>saint Caitanya, known as the Gauḍīya Vaiṣṇavas, cultivate love for Kṛṣṇa by contemplating scenes from his life. Among the favorite scenes for contemplation are the five chapters of the Bhāgavata Purāṇa that narrate the story of the<italic>rāsa līlā</italic>, the dance Kṛṣṇa performs with his beloved<italic>gopīs</italic>. In this celebrated passage, Kṛṣṇa calls the cowmaidens to him with the sound of his flute. They abruptly leave home in the middle of their activities (getting dressed, applying makeup, milking cows, nursing babies) to go to him. After enjoying themselves with him for a while, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Dilemma of Feeling</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like Rūpa Gosvāmin, the medieval Christian theologian Bernard of Clairvaux (1090–1153) elevates love over all other emotions in the devotional life. He finds ample material for the devotional sentiment of love in the biblical Song of Songs. He writes no fewer than eighty-six sermons on the first chapters of this short book of Hebrew wisdom literature, which consists of a series of poetic exchanges between two lovers. Bernard ranks “reverence” and its attendant emotions of “horror or stupor or fear or wonder” (characteristic of<italic>śānta</italic>in Rūpa’s system) far below the intimacy of love (Serm. 83.3).¹ For him, nuptial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Love, Bodies, and Others</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The four distancing strategies discussed in the last chapter set fences around appropriate devotional feeling, but they also set the devotional community apart from persons suspected of inappropriate love for God. This dynamic is most clear with regard to rival religious groups. Bernard of Clairvaux projects perverse practices upon heretical groups, and later church officials view with profound suspicion unauthorized women who claim Christ as their lover. These moves anticipate the Fourth Lateran Council’s careful circumscription of the real presence and body of Christ to the institutional Church and its sacraments.¹ The rivalry of Gauḍīya Vaiṣṇavas with other sects around</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eight women take the stage against a backdrop depicting a rural Indian village. Each holds a<italic>parai</italic>, the round, flat hand drum with which their “untouchable” ancestors announced the deaths of members of the wider community. They step, kick, and stomp their feet in identical choreography, ankle bells jangling, punctuating their dance with calls of “Hey! Hey!” as a wake-up call to their audience. As they weave among one another in two lines, they beat complex rhythms on their drums, posture erect, smiling broadly.</p>
                     <p>After an extended period of vigorous, exuberant dancing and drumming, a middle man, who arranges labor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Dalit Arts and the Failure of Aesthetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Rural Education for Development Society (REDS) in Karnataka, South India, produces the piece of street theatre just described. The organization works for the promotion of Dalits, the current preferred name for the group formerly known as Untouchables or Harijans. REDS works in over one thousand villages, with pro-Dalit projects ranging from the organization of democratic community councils (Panchayats) to the construction and distribution of solar-powered lamps to families without electricity. There are seventy-seven Dalit groups in the South Indian state of Tamilnadu alone, and these groups include a variety of professions, religions, and ideological approaches to Dalit liberation. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Fury as a Religious Sentiment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The REDS dancers drum up a cauldron of emotions: joy in communal celebration, fear and confusion in the face of violence, courage and defiance toward oppressors, and pride in their victory. The beat of the drum communicates the impetus of these emotions, as do the force of the physical actions of pushing, kicking, and stomping. One of the important emotions that fuels their efforts is anger, which, when distilled into its pure form, can be savored as the<italic>rasa</italic>of fury (<italic>raudra</italic>).¹ Fury is integral to the composition, performance, and reception of Dalit arts for liberation. In the REDS street</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Toward a Holistic Theology of the Emotions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no inherent reason that European philosophical traditions must govern Christian theology across the globe. The cultures of Asia, Africa, and South America, where the majority of Christians now live, offer categories for imagining the life of faith, not only for local or indigenous theologies but for the theological “mainstream” as well. As an aesthetic perspective that relates contextual and bodily aspects of emotion to religious experience,<italic>rasa</italic>sheds light on human flourishing and has much to offer a holistic theology of the emotions.</p>
                     <p>This venture into the realm of emotion and the arts has opened a discursive space</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Wonder</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sight of celestial beings evokes wonder. So does the expression of religious devotion in monuments of paint and stone. Mary trembles before the appearance of the angel. Arjuna gasps in astonishment when Kṛṣṇa, his charioteer, is revealed in his true divine form. The tourist pauses, awestruck, as she enters the halls of the Meenakshi Temple, just as she does when she sets foot in a great cathedral. She cannot take it all in.</p>
                     <p>Faced with eruptions of the wondrous across the world’s religious traditions, we seek manageable strategies for making them comprehensible. Interreligious dialogue often takes its point of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>GLOSSARY OF SANSKRIT TERMS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13wzvhj.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
