<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN5259.L453N687 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Nouvelles extraordinaires de divers endroits</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Press and politics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">18th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Politics and government</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">18th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>News and Politics in the Age of Revolution</book-title>
         <subtitle>Jean Luzac's "Gazette de Leyde"</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Popkin</surname>
               <given-names>Jeremy D.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780801423017</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781501701511</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ithaca; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1989</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cornell University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7591/j.ctt15hvrs3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Jeremy D. Popkin's book is the first comprehensive examination of the European news industry during the era of the American and French Revolutions. He focuses on the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>, the period's newspaper of record, and constructs a detailed picture of the "media market" of which it was a part.</p>
         <p>"<italic>News and Politics in the Age of Revolution</italic>is a first-class study of the crucially important periodical<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>and of its extraordinary editor Jean Luzac, who provided through its pages some of the best, most astutely analytical political journalism of the late eighteenth century. Jeremy D. Popkin argues persuasively that the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>maintained a special kind of superiority even after the revolution brought freedom of the press and hence a huge proliferation of papers onto the French market. Although the paper made no claims to represent public opinion, it certainly did its share to shape it and thus to guide events."-<italic>American Historical Review</italic>
         </p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Popkin</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeremy D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[1]</label>
                     <title>News and European Culture in the Eighteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Newspapers. I set this word down with a feeling of deep respect. Newspapers are one of the great instruments of culture through which we Europeans have become what we are.”¹ So wrote the German journalist August Ludwig von Schlözer, one of the founders of modern social science, in 1804. He had just lived through the period of the French Revolution, when the newspaper press had become a political force impossible to ignore, but there is no doubt that Schlözer meant his comment to apply as well to the prerevolutionary era, when he himself had been one of the continent’s leading</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[2]</label>
                     <title>The Environments of an Eighteenth-Century Newspaper</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Newspapers are bound to be conditioned by the society surrounding them. But in the case of the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>, the elucidation of the links between press and society is unusually complicated. This paper was enmeshed in two quite different societies: the Dutch world in which its editor lived and in which the paper was produced, and the wider European world from which its information came and to which it was addressed. The Dutch world was one of small, self-contained city-republics, of a certain intellectual stagnation, of a rather rigid bourgeois oligarchy, but also one in which a certain amount</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[3]</label>
                     <title>The Eighteenth-Century European Press</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The nature of Dutch society and the characteristics of the European state system made the appearance of such newspapers as Jean Luzac’s<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>possible, but they did not guarantee the success of his particular publication. To assure its survival and prosperity, Jean Luzac had to find a special place for his journal in the highly competitive international commercial market for political news. In 1772, the prospectus for a new French-language newspaper promised readers that the editors would digest information from more than 200 other European periodicals.¹ Clearly, late-eighteenth-century readers had a wide choice of newspapers and journals; they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[4]</label>
                     <title>Making News in the Eighteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An eighteenth-century Italian engraving shows the offices of a Florentine gazette contemporary with the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>, the<italic>Notizie del mondo</italic>. Dressed in wigs and knee-breeches, going over their copy with quill pens, the editors seem to have little in common with their twentieth-century journalistic descendants. But the excitement with which the two men on the left are perusing the bulletins that have just come in and the evident haste with which the seated editors are marking up copy for the printers in the background indicate that some aspects of the news business have not changed. Twice a week, for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[5]</label>
                     <title>Producing a Newspaper in the Eighteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once he had selected the news and documents destined for each issue of the paper, Jean Luzac’s personal role in the production of the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>was at an end. Unlike Benjamin Franklin in Philadelphia in the 1730s, most of the European newspaper editors of the eighteenth century were incapable of setting type or operating a printing press. Nor did they usually have much to do with the distribution of the printed copies or the management of their enterprise’s business affairs. Yet all these aspects of newspaper production vitally affected the content of newspapers and their impact. Jean Luzac</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[6]</label>
                     <title>The Gazette de Leyde’s Readership</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Copies of the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>left Leiden to circle the world: from the Netherlands to Philadelphia, and via Vienna and Aleppo, Syria, to India. Subscribers were of course thinly and unevenly spread across the globe, and they made up a minority of the reading public even in those countries where the paper was most popular, but the steady flow of subscription orders, reflected in the paper’s substantial profits, assured Luzac that there were eager recipients for his product.</p>
                     <p>The<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>’s total press run varied from year to year, depending on the public’s interest in the paper’s news</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[7]</label>
                     <title>The Gazette de Leyde and the Crises of the 1770s</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The year 1772, in which the elder Etienne Luzac summoned his nephew Jean to take over the editorship of the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>, was a year during which the paper had many crises to report to its widely dispersed readers. In four states—France, Sweden, Denmark, and Poland—fundamental principles of Europe’s long-standing order seemed threatened by governments grasping for unrestrained power. According to historian Franco Venturi, the “republican forms of government and those that protected freedom seemed increasingly unable to resist the thrust of absolutism, of standing armies, of bureaucracy, of the diplomacy of countries where power was the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[8]</label>
                     <title>Engagement and Disillusionment:</title>
                     <subtitle>Jean Luzac and the Gazette de Leyde from 1782 to 1787</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even as Jean Luzac was accepting the praise of his fellow townsmen for his role in promoting the cause of American independence, affairs in Europe were moving in directions that posed new problems for him and for the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>. During the 1770s and early 1780s, movements for constitutional liberty in Europe and the New World had been gaining strength, and the paper had not hesitated to support the reaction against Maupeou’s reforms in France and the American Revolution. By 1782, however, the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>found itself questioning movements in Europe that seemed superficially similar to the American</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[9]</label>
                     <title>The Challenge of the French Revolution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the ironies of the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>’s situation during the last years of the Patriot struggle in the Netherlands was that the paper, despite the bitter quarrels in which its publisher was involved, was prospering as never before. The 90 percent of his news space that Jean Luzac did not devote to Dutch politics went to coverage of increasingly dramatic events elsewhere, and although the final collapse of the Patriots in September 1787 was a tragedy for Luzae himself, it freed his newspaper to concentrate even more heavily on other stories. Some of these events in the larger</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[10]</label>
                     <title>An Old Regime Gazette in the Revolutionary Maelstrom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>’s French news coverage from 1789 to 1791 was thorough and generally critical of the French Revolution, although the paper’s opposition was not as extreme as that voiced by the royalist press in Paris or by Edmund Burke in London. Readers in the Netherlands and northern Europe continued to regard Luzac’s paper as a dependable source of information about France. But the emergence of an unfettered press in France itself meant that the paper largely lost its relevance for readers there. The paper’s location outside of France, which before the Revolution had served as an implicit guarantee</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>[11]</label>
                     <title>The Gazette de Leyde, Politics, and Journalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Both Jean Luzac and the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>expired as the European news industry was standing on the threshold of a great period of expansion. The events of the French Revolution, which had finally overwhelmed the<italic>Gazette de Leyde</italic>, had given a lasting stimulus to public interest in political affairs; the innovations of the Industrial Revolution soon provided the means to satisfy the growing demand for news in ways Jean Luzac had never dreamed of. In 1814, as the Napoleonic wars were coming to an end, the London<italic>Times</italic>put into operation the first power-driven newspaper printing press: its use</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sources and Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15hvrs3.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
