<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6t9j1g</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ3940.M863 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Haitian literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Haiti</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">In literature</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Apocalypse in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Apocalypse in motion pictures</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Haiti</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social conditions</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Haiti</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychic trauma</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Caribbean Area</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and history</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Caribbean Area</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Tropical Apocalypse</book-title>
         <subtitle>Haiti and the Caribbean End Times</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Munro</surname>
               <given-names>Martin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813938219</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">081393821X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Charlottesville; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt15r3x8s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In<italic>Tropical Apocalypse,</italic>Martin Munro argues that since the earliest days of European colonization, Caribbean-and especially Haitian-history has been shaped by apocalyptic events so that the region has, in effect, been living for centuries in an end time without end. By engaging with the contemporary apocalyptic turn in Caribbean studies and lived reality, he not only provides important historical contextualization for a general understanding of apocalypse in the region but also offers an account of the state of Haitian society and culture in the decades before the 2010 earthquake. Inherently interdisciplinary, his work ranges widely through Caribbean and Haitian thought, historiography, political discourse, literature, film, religion, and ecocriticism in its exploration of whether culture in these various forms can shape the future of a country.</p>
         <p>The author begins by situating the question of the Caribbean apocalypse in relation to broader, global narratives of the apocalyptic present, notably Slavoj Žižek's<italic>Living in the End Times.</italic>Tracing the evolution of apocalyptic thought in Caribbean literature from Negritude up to the present, he notes the changes from the early work of Aimé Césaire; through an anti-apocalyptic period in which writers such as Frantz Fanon, Antonio Benítez-Rojo, Édouard Glissant, and Michael Dash have placed more emphasis on lived experience and the interrelatedness of cultures and societies; to a contemporary stage in which versions of the apocalyptic reappear in the work of David Scott and Mark Anderson.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the earthquake struck Haiti on January 12, 2010, amid the chaos of fallen buildings, dead bodies, and general panic, citizens of Port-au-Prince were heard to cry that it was the “fin du monde,” the end of the world. To many, it was an apocalyptic moment, a cataclysmic end, but without the promise contained in biblical versions of the apocalypse of a new and better beginning. This was therefore a very particular apocalypse, one that had been prepared for, indeed prophesied to some degree in religious and political discourse, the arts, and culture more generally for decades, perhaps centuries. For</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Duvaliers and Apocalyptic Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Noirisme was a form of political and cultural ideology that grew out of indigenism, which in turn was a reaction to the American occupation of 1915–34.¹ During the occupation, Haitian intellectual culture was reenergized in diverse and often contradictory ways, constructing a discourse of resistance that would finally imprison the nation in a rigid idea of cultural and racial authenticity that served also as the ideological justification for the worst excesses of the Duvalier regime.</p>
                     <p>In 1919, Jean Price-Mars’s<italic>La Vocation de l’élite</italic>had evoked the concept of the “national spirit” (<italic>l’âme nationale</italic>) and had warned of the dangers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Utopian Ends:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aristide and the Apocalypse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is in Haiti and elsewhere a curious relationship between utopian discourse and apocalyptic outcomes. One might argue that many of the apocalyptic wars of the twentieth century were driven and justified by utopian discourses—Marxism, fascism, religions, and various forms of nationalism. The fall of the Berlin Wall seemed to announce the start of the “happy ’90s,” and gave rise to Francis Fukuyama’s utopian idea of the “end of history,” the belief that “liberal democracy had, in principle, won out, that the advent of a global liberal community was hovering around the corner, and that the obstacles to this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Chimères and the Haitian Antihero</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Maximilien Laroche writes of an archetypal antihero figure in Haitian writing, whose function is to transform “an individual decline into a collective deliverance.” In Haitian literature, Laroche writes, “the hero makes himself a zombie amongst zombies in order to free the community. And it is by accepting his victimhood, by acknowledging it, that he denounces it, and thereby attacks the victimization to which he and his people are subject” (n.p.). Laroche’s theory of the Haitian antihero addresses patterns of victimization and self-sacrifice in Haitian literature—notably in classic works of fiction by Roumain, Alexis, and others. His idea however seems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Religion, Nature, and the Apocalypse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Failles,</italic>Yanick Lahens’s first book published after the earthquake of 2010, the author writes of seeing her husband after he returns from town on the evening of January 12, announcing that he has seen the apocalypse. This statement makes Lahens think immediately of her use of the same word in her last novel,<italic>La couleur de l’aube</italic>. She had hesitated, she says, before using the word, striking it out three times before finally writing: “The Apocalypse has already taken place many times on this island” (27). The word had remained with her well after the publication of the novel,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Caribbean is a space defined by and conceptually inscribed in time: pre- and post-Columbian; colonial and postcolonial; pre- and post-emancipation; pre- and postrevolutionary; pre- and post-independence; and in Haiti’s case, pre- and post-occupation, pre- and post-Duvalier, and now perhaps, pre- and post-earthquake. In each case there is a radical and violent irruption in time that is not erased by the apparent movement into the “post-” period, but which instead continues to define time like an inescapable shadow so that any sense of a future truly liberated from the past (however that may be conceived of) remains hanging, suspended, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15r3x8s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
