<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">ML3877.B75 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sublime, The, in music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Muscially Sublime: Indeterminacy, Infinity, Irresolvability</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wurth</surname>
               <given-names>Kiene Brillenburg</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823230631</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823246472</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt14brzjk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Musically Sublime rewrites musically the history and philosophy of the sublime. Music enables us to reconsider the traditional course of sublime feeling on a track from pain to pleasure. Resisting the notion that there is a single format for sublime feeling, Wurth shows how, from the mid eighteenth century onward, sublime feeling is, instead, constantly rearticulated in a complex interaction with musicality. Wurth takes as her point of departure Immanuel Kant's Critique of Judgment and Jean-Francois Lyotard's aesthetic writings of the 1980s and 1990s. Kant framed the sublime narratively as an epic of self-transcendence. By contrast, Lyotard sought to substitute open immanence for Kantian transcendence, yet he failed to deconstruct the Kantian epic. The book performs this deconstruction by juxtaposing eighteenth- and nineteenth-century conceptions of the infinite, Sehnsucht, the divided self, and unconscious drives with contemporary readings of instrumental music. Critically assessing Edmund Burke, James Usher, E.T.A. Hoffmann, Novalis, Friedrich Holderlin, Arthur Schopenhauer, Richard Wagner, and Friedrich Nietzsche, this book re-presents the sublime as a feeling that defers resolution and hangs suspended between pain and pleasure. Musically Sublime rewrites the mathematical sublime as differance, while it redresses the dynamical sublime as trauma: unending, undetermined, unresolved. Whereas most musicological studies in this area have focused on traces of the Kantian sublime in Handel, Haydn, and Beethoven, this book calls on the nineteenth-century theorist Arthur Seidl to analyze the sublime of, rather than in, music. It does so by invoking Seidl's concept of formwidrigkeit ("form-contrariness") in juxtaposition with Romantic piano music, (post)modernist musical minimalisms, and Lyotard's postmodern sublime. It presents a sublime of matter, rather than form-performative rather than representational. In doing so, Musically Sublime shows that the binary distinction Lyotard posits between the postmodern and romantic sublime is finally untenable.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations (in Order of Appearance)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Imagine the wide lawn of the Champs de Mars during the Reign of Terror in late eighteenth-century France.¹ Thousands of people are packed together to participate “universally” in one of the many festivals celebrating the cause of freedom. They sing, they shout, they merge into a massive voice. The sound of this voice alone is staggering and uncannily irresistible. It grows louder as more join in, caught by the thrill of the moment or scared to openly disengage from an agitation that seems to enforce the participation of all. This voice then takes on a life of its own. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Empty Signs and the Burkean Sublime</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The empty sign would have to be the sign of a paradox: a sign that is not quite a sign, yet<italic>as such</italic>marking the process of signifying itself. It is not quite a sign (at least in the Saussurean sense), because it constantly suspends a signified. Empty signs are “pure” signifiers resisting the Saussurean logic that signifiers and signifieds invoke each other and thus cannot function without each other: wherever there is a signifier, a signified is presupposed. Yet what if the associative bond between the two is all too slippery; what if cultural conventions do not (yet) allow</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Sehnsucht, Music, and the Sublime</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his<italic>Allgemeine theorie der schönen Künste</italic>, Johann Georg Sulzer does not confine the experience of the sublime to feelings of wonder, terror, respect, or elevation. The sublime is “the highest in art, and must be employed when the mind is to be attacked with powerful strokes, when admiration, awe, powerful longing, high courage, or also fear or terror are to be aroused.”¹ Powerful longing, excessive and aimless—this recalls James Usher’s mighty unknown want as a modality of the sublime feeling. Filtered by our readings of the pseudo-Longinus, Burke, and Kant, today’s outlook has obstructed this modality from view,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Ruins and (Un)forgetfulness:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Genealogy of the Musically Sublime</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In “Nietzsche, Genealogy, History,” Michel Foucault (re)introduced a concept in philosophy and the writing of history that he had derived from Friedrich Nietzsche: genealogy.¹ Foucault presented this concept as a history-writing against the grain insofar as it no longer starts from timeless values and realities lying in wait behind the stories of the past. Genealogy, for Foucault, was no longer naïve, in that it no longer searched for the pure origin of things but rather showed how such origins were constituted out of incoherent fragments, accidents, errors, and failings. Insofar as genealogy had to do with<italic>descent</italic>, this was a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Sounds Like Now:</title>
                     <subtitle>Form-Contrariness, Romanticism, and the Postmodern Sublime</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Inhuman</italic>, Jean-François Lyotard invents a string of associations with the German<italic>gehorsam sein</italic>: to be obedient, or, literally translated, to be able or tending to hear. “To obey,” Lyotard suggests, “is<italic>gehorchen. Gehoören</italic>is not far, to pertain to, to depend on an agency, to fall into a domain, under an authority, a<italic>dominus</italic>. And<italic>zuhören</italic>, to lend one’s ear.” There is, Lyotard continues, “an inexhaustible network linking listening to belonging, to the sense of obligation, a passivity I would like to translate as<italic>passibility</italic>” (<italic>TI</italic>178). As a concept, passibility nicely merges “pssibility” (<italic>TI</italic>178). As a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Anxiety:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Sublime as Trauma and Repetition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sublime is not only duplicitous in its paradox of pleasure and pain, but also in its “double mode” of a quieter and a more violent sublime: what John Baillie called the sedate sublime and the sublime mixed with pathos—and what Kant, of course, called the mathematical and the dynamical sublime.¹ Usually, critics interpret these two varieties of the Kantian sublime experience as pertaining to theoretical or speculative and practical reason respectively. They can, however, also be elucidated by pointing to the eighteenth-century cult of the sublime as being a cult of empty and vast but also of wild</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coda:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Sublime, Intermedially Speaking</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Years ago, I was hitching with a friend on a Buginese fishing boat from Sulawesi to the island of Lembata in eastern Indonesia. One late afternoon, when the sun was at its lowest, we had spotted a whale rising up from the waters within yards before us—so close and unexpected as to almost become unreal. Dolphins regularly accompanied our boat, and the sea stretched out with nothing in sight save some deserted islands scattered here and there. It was exactly one year before the great flood devastated eastern Flores, wiping away several islands in the Flores Sea. Now, however,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14brzjk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
