<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4vbx</collection-id>
      <volume>13</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Reparative in Narratives</book-title>
         <subtitle>Works of Mourning in Progress</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROSELLO</surname>
               <given-names>MIREILLE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781846312205</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781846315916</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Mireille Rosello</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vj9bm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The authors studied in this book can be visualized as the islands that constitute an unknown, fragile and trembling literary and cultural Francophone archipelago. The archipelago does not appear on any map, in the middle of an ocean whose name we already know. No Francophone anthology would put these authors together as a matter of course because what connects them is a narrative grammar rather than a national origin or even a language. Yet, their writing techniques and their apprehension of the real (the ways in which they know and name the world) both reflect and actively participate in our evolving perception of what Gayatri Spivak calls the “planet”. The Reparative in Narratives argues that argue that they repair trauma through writing. One description of these awe-inspiring, tender and sometimes horrifying tales is that their narrators are survivors who have experienced and sometimes inflicted unspeakable acts of violence. And yet, ultimately, despair, nihilism, cynicism or silence are never the consequences of their encounter with what some quickly call evil. The traumatic event has not killed them and has not killed their desire to write or perform, although the decidedly altered life that they live in the aftermath of the disaster forces them to become different types of storytellers. They are the first-person narrators of their story, and their narration reinvents them as speaking subjects. In turn, this requires that we accept new reading pacts. That pact is a temporal and geographical signature: the reparative narrative needs readers prepared to accept that healing belongs to the realm of possibilities and that exposure and denunciation do not exhaust the victim’s range of possibilities. Rosello contends that this context-specific yet repeating pattern constitutes a response to the contemporary figuration of both globalized and extremely localized types of traumatic memories.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>From the Debate on ‘Repentance’ to the Reparative in Memorial Narratives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘Narratives’ and ‘reparative’: these two words will be used throughout this book, and the nature of their relationship will remain unstable. Originally, I was looking for a working definition of what a ‘reparative narrative’ would be, might be. And positing that reparative narratives could be found was of the order of a theoretical hypothesis. I was not sure that they existed but it was clear that if they did, I needed them, and needed them badly. I wanted to learn at the same time how to identify them and to understand how they worked in order to recognize them and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER I</label>
                     <title>Algerian Humour:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘Jay Translating’ Words and Silences</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The hero of this chapter is Fellag, a famous Algerian humorist, a ‘comic, clown, mime, and performance artist’ as Ruth Weiner calls him in her review of one of his shows (Weiner, 1999, 470). Fellag is a public speaker and a published author. He believes in the power of words and stories and in the inextricability of autobiography and politics. Fellag is originally from Kabylia and grew up during the war of independence. He started his career as a performer in Algiers, where his parents moved when he was a child (a first cultural and linguistic displacement), but he had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>René-Nicolas Ehni:</title>
                     <subtitle>Matricide and Deicide as Figures of Unforgivable Violence and Redemption during the Algerian War of Independence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>René-Nicolas Ehni is not Algerian. He was neither a<italic>harki</italic>nor a<italic>moudjahid</italic>. He was never a<italic>pied noir</italic>. He was not one of the French ‘porteurs de valises’, who helped the NLF in Europe. And he is not a child of Algerian immigrants. As a result, his novels and plays may well have remained invisible to critics interested in the way in which France remembers the war that led to Algeria’s independence. Yet, at the beginning of the twenty-first century, two reasons may be invoked to justify Ehni’s inclusion into a reconfigured postcolonial canon. And interestingly, they may well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Truth of False Testimonies:</title>
                     <subtitle>False Brothers in Michael Haneke’s Caché</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study of Michael Haneke’s<italic>Caché</italic>tests some of the hypotheses formulated in the introduction about the different ways of instrumentalizing history. Is it possible to detect connections between moments of historiographical revision and the emergence of desirable ethical or political occurrences? Is the space between fictional historical rewritings and historical progress not always the site of an ethical dispute? Even if we decide to refuse, as paranoid, a definition of history as that which always sides with the powerful and the dominant, with the masculine or even the West, it would certainly be naive to assume that when discursive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Gisèle Halimi’s Autobiographical and Legal Narratives:</title>
                     <subtitle>Doing to Trees what They Did to Me</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Halimi grew up in the 1930s in Tunisia, in the midst of a Jewish community that she describes as poor, in a family whose members were not particularly receptive to her ambitions and feminist sense of justice. She spent her formative years in a country marked by colonialism, at a time when the party of future president Habib Bourguiba was beginning to organize against the French protectorate (Perkins, 2004, 95–105). The Second World War was about to engulf Europe and France’s North African colonial territories would be involved as a reservoir of military forces, as the theatre of operations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Repentance and Detective Fiction: Legal Powerlessness and the Power of Narratives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In January 2008, after the evening national news, France 2 network showed an episode of the popular<italic>P.J. Saint Martin</italic>detective series called ‘Erreurs de jeunesse’ [Mistakes of Youth].¹ I remember following the plot with a growing sense of astonishment as it slowly became apparent that the puzzle the investigators were slowly putting back together was telling a story about France’s colonial past or more importantly about its impact on the immediate present. The episode made three assumptions that I thought were remarkably revealing about the recent thematic and generic norms that govern memorial narratives (even if they remain invisible).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vj9bm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
