<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS8187.R33 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canadian fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poets, Canadian (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Novelists, Canadian (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literary form</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Narration (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>From Cohen to Carson</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Poet's Novel in Canada</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RAE</surname>
               <given-names>IAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773532762</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773574922</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt801qh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Detailed case studies of novels by Leonard Cohen, Michael Ondaatje, George Bowering, Daphne Marlatt, and Anne Carson, as well as sections on A.M. Klein and Anne Michaels, reveal how these authors framed their early novels according to formal precedents established in their poetry. In tracking the authors’ shift from lyric to long poem to novel, Rae also investigates their experiments with non-literary art forms - photography, painting, film. The authors discussed combine disparate genres and media to alter notions of narrative coherence in the novel and engage the diverse but fragmented cultural histories of Canadian society.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="400"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Framing the Poet’s Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“One unanswered question of Canadian literature,” according to the critic Fraser Sutherland, “is why so many celebrated fiction writers begin and continue as poets.”¹ There are many possible responses to Sutherland’s question, not the least of which is that the designation “novel” holds the promise of greater book revenues and a broader audience. Indeed, Canadian authors have written sequences of prose poems, such as Daphne Marlatt’s<italic>How Hug a Stone</italic>(1983), only to discover that their publishers insist, for marketing purposes, that their poems are novels.² Yet sales figures alone do not explain the shift from poet to novelist,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>(Un)framing Genres</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In choosing to work with the lyric, the long poem, and the novel, I have invoked three of the most established – but also the vaguest – terms in literary criticism. The formal innovation that critics identify as a key aspect of the lyric also characterizes the long poem and the novel. Paul Ricoeur remarks that the novel “has, since its creation, presented itself as the protean genre par excellence ... Indeed, it has constituted for at least three centuries now a prodigious workshop for experiments in the domains of composition.”² My aim here is not to wrestle these shape-shifting genres into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Leonard Cohen:</title>
                     <subtitle>(Un)framing Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before Leonard Cohen achieved international acclaim with “Suzanne” on<italic>The Songs of Leonard Cohen</italic>(1967 ), before he shocked the Canadian literary establishment with the pornographic novel<italic>Beautiful Losers</italic>(1966 ), even before he seduced poetry fans with his popular collection of lyrics,<italic>The Spice-Box of Earth</italic>(1961), he was interested in the visual arts.² His most meticulous biographer, Ira Nadel, observes that in “the 1951 Westmount High School Yearbook, Cohen lists photography as his hobby,” and for a short period of time Cohen operated The Four Penny Art Gallery in Montreal in cooperation with the painter Mort Rosengarten (the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Michael Ondaatje:</title>
                     <subtitle>(Un)framing the Series</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this 1984 interview with Sam Solecki, Ondaatje does not clarify what he means by the “great change” in the structure of poems and novels. Although book reviewers frequently refer to his “Booker-winning novel-poems,” it remains unclear what Ondaatje considers the relation of poetry to the novel to be.² In the Solecki interview, Ondaatje refuses to slot his novels into one category and asserts that “if you’re writing a novel then you’re writing against what you know the novel is.”³ However, he does state that he thinks of the “architecture” of a novel “in terms of repeating and building images</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>George Bowering:</title>
                     <subtitle>(Un)framing the Serial Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bowering redefined the term “serial novel” in his trilogy,<italic>Autobiology</italic>(1972),<italic>Curious</italic>(1973), and<italic>A Short Sad Book</italic>(1977). While a wide variety of genres were serialized in the Victorian era, Bowering chose to define his conception of the serial against the nineteenth-century realist novel and its promise of a window onto a parallel world. Bowering was suspicious of what he perceived as an instrumental use of language in realism, as well as the causal momentum of the kind of plot produced by publication in installments. Instead of the plot-driven realist serial, Bowering developed a prose form based on the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Daphne Marlatt:</title>
                     <subtitle>(Un)framing the Quest Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the ongoing cinerama of Marlatt’s poetry and prose, her first book, the long poem<italic>Frames of a Story</italic>(1968), establishes a narrative framework that reappears in her novella<italic>Zócalo</italic>(1977) and her novel<italic>Ana Historic</italic>(1988). These works perform variations on the heterosexual quest narrative that Marlatt finds in the source text for<italic>Frames of a Story,</italic>Hans Christian Andersen’s<italic>The Snow Queen</italic>(1884). Taken together, the erotic plots of<italic>Frames of a Story, Zócalo,</italic>and<italic>Ana Historic</italic>map a lesbian quest narrative, departing from a scene of heterosexual dissatisfaction and moving towards one of lesbian fulfillment. Although not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Anne Carson:</title>
                     <subtitle>(Un)framing Myth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As in this interview with Mary di Michele, Anne Carson repeatedly tells interviewers that she defies genre conventions because her favourite means of stimulating her imagination “is to break rules or change categories or go outside where they say the line is.”² The subtitle of Carson’s<italic>Autobiography of Red: A Novel in Verse</italic>only hints at the variety of genres that the Montreal poet employs.³ In<italic>Autobiography of Red</italic>Carson brings together a preface on the Greek poet Stesichoros, translated fragments of Stesichoros’s long poem<italic>Geryoneis</italic>, three appendices on the blinding of Stesichoros by Helen, a romance in verse recasting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The English Patient, Fugitive Pieces, and the Poet’s Novel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I began this study by suggesting one response to the question of why so many of Canada’s acclaimed novelists begin and continue as poets. For Cohen, Ondaatje, Bowering, Marlatt, and Carson, the long poem facilitated the transition from the lyric to the novel by allowing them to develop serial forms of narrative that can convey a sense of duration without sacrificing the intensity and concision of the lyric. The authors apply these serial techniques differently in their novels and address particular regional, political, and aesthetic concerns, which has garnered them acclaim in diverse quarters.</p>
                     <p>The poet’s novel is the subject</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Permissions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt801qh.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
