<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BJ1406.E96 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Good and evil</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Good and evil</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Africa</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Evil in Africa</book-title>
         <subtitle>Encounters with the Everyday</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>OLSEN</surname>
               <given-names>WILLIAM C.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>VAN BEEK</surname>
               <given-names>WALTER E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib3">
            <role>FOREWORD BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PARKIN</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253017437</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253017505</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253017505</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt17t75bk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>William C. Olsen, Walter E. A. van Beek, and the contributors to this volume seek to understand how Africans have confronted evil around them. Grouped around notions of evil as a cognitive or experiential problem, evil as malevolent process, and evil as an inversion of justice, these essays investigate what can be accepted and what must be condemned in order to evaluate being and morality in African cultural and social contexts. These studies of evil entanglements take local and national histories and identities into account, including state politics and civil war, religious practices, Islam, gender, and modernity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="404"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PARKIN</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The comparative study of moral systems is fundamental to anthropological thinking. This collection of nineteen chapters and the editors’ introduction present rich ethnographic cases from sub-Saharan Africa on a topic bearing on the definition of morality that has been at the forefront of anthropological findings drawn from research in the continent. Yet, as the editors point out, anthropologists have been hesitant to use a concept of “evil” to refer to acts and beliefs indigenously regarded as moral inversions or perversions of humanity. The term,<italic>evil</italic>, is indeed an ethnographic imposition drawn from the English and cognate languages and therefore part</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>AFRICAN NOTIONS OF EVIL: The Chimera of Justice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VAN BEEK</surname>
                           <given-names>WALTER E. A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>WILLIAM C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his ethnographic account of the Muslim precept of knowledge in Mayotte, Lambek provides thick descriptive detail regarding the cultural and moral system of behavior, including the imagination of evil. In Mayotte, evil is often personified by a figure that circulates after sunset, dancing on graves in blatant contempt for the memory and space of the departed. Rogue characters of the night go unclothed, walk backward, feast on human waste, disrespect the elderly, mock the living, and are particularly harmful toward children. They disregard human morality, social custom, and relations of kin and society. Such actions form the substance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>POLITICAL EVIL:</title>
                     <subtitle>Witchcraft from the Perspective of the Bewitched</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SILVA</surname>
                           <given-names>SÓNIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Evil<italic>is</italic>not any<italic>thing</italic>,” David Parkin asserts in his introduction to<italic>Anthropology of Evil</italic>(1985b). Evil is an odd-job word, a word with a lot of baggage, but evil is also a word whose analytical value in anthropology is to push researchers beyond conventional categories. Instead of asking what evil is, let us explore where evil takes us.</p>
                     <p>Depending on route, the concept of evil can take us in two different directions: morality or ontology. In the first direction, evil is part of morality, being oftentimes interchangeable with bad. In Martin Southwold’s words (1985, 131), this is evil in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>UNTYING WRONGS IN NORTHERN UGANDA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WHYTE</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN REYNOLDS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MEINERT</surname>
                           <given-names>LOTTE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OBIKA</surname>
                           <given-names>JULAINA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evil in northern Uganda is notorious. The film<italic>Kony 2012</italic>, depicting the Lord’s Resistance Army (lra) rebel leader Joseph Kony as the incarnation of brutality, went viral in social media soon after it appeared. More than 120 million people, mostly young Americans, have clicked in to watch a video about a war and a part of Africa about which they had known very little. It described Kony’s guerrilla tactics of abducting children for the lra. In the video, we meet Jacob, from Acholiland, who was seized and made to watch his brother being killed by the rebels. The American narrator</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE EVIL OF INSECURITY IN SOUTH SUDAN:</title>
                     <subtitle>Violence and Impunity in Africa’s Newest State</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JOK</surname>
                           <given-names>JOK MADUT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When South Sudan finally gained independence in July 2011, after long and bitter wars with North Sudan, the event came to mark such a hopeful moment for the millions of its citizens who expected the advent of new era of peace, security, and prosperity. But while it has only been a year since independence and all of these aspirations might still be realized in the future, the new country has now quickly found itself confronted with really daunting challenges, which have since began to dampen the popular celebrated sense of freedom. The most critical of these challenges was insecurity, especially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>GENOCIDE, EVIL, AND HUMAN AGENCY:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Concept of Evil in Rwandan Explanations of the 1994 Genocide</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BURNET</surname>
                           <given-names>JENNIE E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While few cultural anthropologists practicing today would be willing to label culturally bound human behaviors as “evil,” many apply this label to the gruesome individual and collective acts that constituted the 1994 genocide of Tutsis, politically moderate Hutus, and others defined as an “enemy of the state.” Because evil, conceived of as the opposite of good, is defined by a moral system, its application in a particular context involves moral judgment and violates the principle of cultural relativism, which lies at the heart of anthropology. Furthermore, on the continent of Africa, the concept of evil is inextricably tied up in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>POLITICS AND COSMOGRAPHIC ANXIETY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Kongo and Dagbon Compared</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MACGAFFEY</surname>
                           <given-names>WYATT</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay explores the possibility that there may be an inverse causal relationship, in a given historical period, between political stability and the degree of definition of worldview. Evil is not only a moral and ethical problem, but also a political one, in that evildoers real or imaginary must be legitimately dealt with.¹ Because political institutions and activities are intrinsically historical, ideas about evil and the means to deal with it can be expected to change. Indeed, “dealing with” evil by consulting a diviner, healer, or shrine; following through on the recommendations; and mustering economic and social support for remedial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>AMBIVALENCE AND THE WORK OF THE NEGATIVE AMONG THE YAKA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DEVISCH</surname>
                           <given-names>RENÉ</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Intercorporeality and the ethic of desire and evildoing, stripped of their Western modernist thought patterns and view of the person, are among the foci of anthropological and psychoanalytical efforts¹ that I have been undertaking for the last decade.² These were led by the following research questions: How may desire, which unknowingly takes hold of interrelated subjects, make someone either compassionate or madly envious and even maleficent? How much does desire inhabit intercorporeality and inspire close family members to either intensely share life and a communal mode of inhabiting the life world or deflate and undermine the physical and communal life</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>AZE AND THE INCOMMENSURABLE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EKOUÉ</surname>
                           <given-names>LÉOCADIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>WITH</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSENTHAL</surname>
                           <given-names>JUDY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rosenthal</surname>
                           <given-names>Judy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Aze</italic>(usually translated as “witchcraft” in English) was a subject of great concern in Goldcoast (Ghana), Togoland (Togo), and Dahomey (Benin) during the colonial period and is perhaps of even more urgent concern today. Recent research by Douglas Falen (unpublished manuscript 2013) in Benin impresses on us just how thoroughly modern (if not postmodern) preoccupations about<italic>aze</italic>continue to be, not only in rural areas and isolated villages, but also for urbanites, the university-educated, and the middle class.</p>
                     <p>During my own research on Gorovodu in Togo and Ghana, I heard the word<italic>aze</italic>pronounced daily, and I also found it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>EVIL AND THE ART OF REVENGE IN THE MANDARA MOUNTAINS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VAN BEEK</surname>
                           <given-names>WALTER E. A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is always a dramatic moment during a funeral dance, when the corpse is lifted over the wall and placed on the shoulders of the smith. At the funeral dance of Zra Wuvè, the crowd had been warming up for the dance as usual, the mourning kinsmen brandishing their spears, the women ululating and scraping calabashes over their iron skirts, while inside, the deceased was being clothed and decorated for the dance. When the corpse of Zra Wuvè came in sight and a smith climbed over the wall in order to carry the body, the crowd followed the drummers toward</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>DISTINCTIONS IN THE IMAGINATION OF HARM IN CONTEMPORARY MIJIKENDA THOUGHT:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Existential Challenge of Majini</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CIEKAWY</surname>
                           <given-names>DIANE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In discussions about spirit aggression and human agents of harm, Mijikenda,¹ whose lifeworld is centered in the coastal hinterland of Kenya, assert particular views about the importance of moral action. Their claims are imbedded in a complex of thought and practice that has been described by various works on Mijikenda religion, most notably by David Parkin in<italic>Sacred Void: Spatial Images of Work and Ritual among the Giriama of Kenya</italic>(1991). His comprehensive volume details central dimensions of Mijikenda thought and practice and offers conceptual schemes that provide a foundation for contemporary scholarship.</p>
                     <p>This essay examines what Parkin broadly refers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>HAUNTED BY ABSENT OTHERS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Movements of Evil in a Nigerian City</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TROVALLA</surname>
                           <given-names>ULRIKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In comparison with other cities in Nigeria, Jos has often been depicted as relatively peaceful, a place where all of the country’s different religious and ethnic groups live together in harmony. In this vein, the violence that broke out in the city of Jos on Friday, September 7, 2001, and which came to be known as “the crisis,” threw a once-familiar city into disarray and confusion. It came to be viewed as a turning point—a start of a cycle of escalating violence that to date has brought with it repeatedly renewed violent hostilities. On that Friday, a cleansing from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>ATTRIBUTIONS OF EVIL AMONG HAALPULAAREN, SENEGAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DILLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>ROY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The linguistic root<italic>bon</italic>in Pulaar, the main language spoken in northern Senegal, is usually translated in English by words related to the concept of evil. Thus the noun<italic>bone</italic>means “evil,” and as an adjectival root it denotes the “evil eye,” as in<italic>yiitere bonde</italic>, or “malicious or evil speech,”<italic>konngol bonngol</italic>, or “evil gait,”<italic>yaadu bondu</italic>. However, the semantic field marked out by terms that share the same linguistic root is broad, and it encompasses terms that English speakers would denote by the two separate words<italic>evil</italic>and<italic>bad</italic>. So<italic>bonde</italic>is the verb “to be bad or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>REFLECTIONS REGARDING GOOD AND EVIL:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Complexity of Words in Zanzibar</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LARSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>KJERSTI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay addresses the moral category of evil from an anthropological perspective. For that reason I shall explore “evil” from a particular ontology rather than as a universal concept. This is the only approach that could disclose understandings that may challenge the dominant emic Judeo-Christian theological or philosophical framework. Investigating the manner in which evil is embedded in cosmologies of the everyday, I shall pay attention to practice including discourse as, within this domain, it would only rarely be elaborated in any abstract mode. Furthermore, being attentive to how evil is perceived and identified through its practice renders possible a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>CONSTRUCTING MORAL PERSONHOOD:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Moral Test in Tuareg Sociability as a Commentary on Honor and Dishonor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RASMUSSSSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evil often induces human suffering; it may, for example, result in illness. In many African societies, it is often synonymous with witchcraft, possession, and other malevolent practices elaborated in ritual (Comaroff and Comaroff 1993; Ferme 2001; Rasmussen 1998, 2001; West 2005, 2007), and it is often combated through formal religious and political means. I contend that, in addition to these manifestations, evil may also be addressed more informally, in moral testing during deceptively trivial ordinary everyday sociability, not solely in public formal ritual or large-scale political contexts. Preoccupations in such tests include combating literal physical harm, tangible material theft, and/or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>THE GENDER OF EVIL:</title>
                     <subtitle>Maasai Experiences and Expressions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HODGSON</surname>
                           <given-names>DOROTHY L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although there is an emerging scholarship in anthropology on evil (e.g., Parkin 1985a)—its symbolism, manifestations, associations, and changes over time—few scholars have explored whether gender shapes experiences and expressions of evil, and if so how. Women and men appear as agents or victims of evil acts or forces, whether as intentionally negligent mothers (Parkin 1985c) or witches (van Beek 1994), but there has been little systematic effort to analyze what evil acts, beings or forces may tell us about gender relations, or, conversely, how a gender analysis may complicate our understandings of evil. But if, as David Parkin</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>NEOCANNIBALISM, MILITARY BIOPOLITICS, AND THE PROBLEM OF HUMAN EVIL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHEPER-HUGHES</surname>
                           <given-names>NANCY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I address a controversial topic in contemporary biopolitics/necropolitics (Mbembe 2003): the biomedical abuse and plunder of dead bodies, among these, the bodies of enemies, with the complicity and collaboration of militarized states. Although biopiracy of human biomaterials is not new, the technological capacity to harvest and to distribute these anonymously worldwide through “cannibal markets” in blood, skin, bones, organs, bodies and body parts, dna, and reproductive material to feed the desires of these new commodities for transplant medicine, for science and research, for commercial pharmacology, and for recreation and display is a late-twentieth-century innovation.</p>
                     <p>The emergence of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>THEFT AND EVIL IN ASANTE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>WILLIAM C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>302</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In July 2002, I rode a taxi east from the town of Mampong toward a diviner’s village to interview him and his staff. The drive is along a dirt and clay road through two small towns before reaching Apiakrom, where the road then narrows off into the bush. The trip generally lasts about twenty-five minutes. On that day, I saw something unlike anything I have ever seen before. It was both strange and horrible. A young man around the age of twenty was running in the opposite direction of our taxi. He was completely naked and dripping with sweat; on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>SORCERY AFTER SOCIALISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>Liberalization and Antiwitchcraft Practices in Southern Tanzania</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GREEN</surname>
                           <given-names>MAIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>324</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his introduction to the<italic>Anthropology of Evil</italic>, published some thirty years ago, David Parkin calls for an approach to the social manifestation of evil that extends beyond a narrow focus on witchcraft. If evil is perceived more broadly, as a range of actions that are associated with causing human harm, the categorization can include diverse instantiations of the phenomenon. Moreover, as a classification that is inherently relational, involving the imputation of responsibility to someone or something, the analysis of evil takes us into concerns with wider issues of cosmology and ontology. What is the universe of human and extra</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>TRANSATLANTIC PENTECOSTAL DEMONS IN MAPUTO</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VAN DE KAMP</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>344</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Regularly, Pentecostals summoned me to pray when we were on the street in Maputo, the capital of Mozambique.¹ They stressed that we needed to be aware of and protect ourselves against negative spiritual influences that were hiding everywhere. We had to keep our distance from what was happening around us as we first had to judge the intentions of people who approached us. Pentecostals could often tell me the exact moment when someone had approached them on the street or in a building and how afterward they had lost their job or their partner had disappeared because the person they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>THE MEANING OF “APARTHEID” AND THE EPISTEMOLOGY OF EVIL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ASHFORTH</surname>
                           <given-names>ADAM</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>364</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In May 2012, the former president of South Africa was interviewed on cnn by Christiane Amanpour and asked to repudiate apartheid as “morally indefensible.” Despite having played the central role in dismantling apartheid, he could only do this, he replied, in a “qualified” way: “I don’t apologize for saying that what drove me as a young man, before I decided we need to embrace a new vision, was a quest to bring justice for black South Africans in a way which would not—that’s what I believed then—destroy the justice to which my people were entitled,” de Klerk said</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS AND AFFILIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17t75bk.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
