<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>From Faith to Faith</book-title>
         <subtitle>John Wesley’s Covenant Theology and the Way of Salvation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rodes</surname>
               <given-names>Stanley J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Noble</surname>
               <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174289</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902202</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Stanley J. Rodes</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf6d5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The very title of this volume makes a claim and extends an invitation. Simply put, the claim is this: John Wesley was an adherent of covenant theology. Consequently, a proper understanding of his theological thought - and of his soteriology in particular - is impossible apart from accounting for the influence of covenant theology on him. The invitation then, is to investigate Wesley's thought in light of this claim. Having started his research simply as an investigation into a rather curious distinction Wesley made among those to whom he gave spiritual counsel (some people, he said, have "the faith of a servant"; others have "the faith of a son"), Rodes soon realised that covenant theology was an immensely powerful influence on Wesley's thought, and that he was even able to significantly and creatively adapted it to the template of his evangelical Arminianism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="258"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Noble</surname>
                           <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The early years of the twenty-first century have seen belated recognition of a global revolution in world Christianity. Although many secular commentators were blinded by the decline of the Christian church in Europe and the rise of a fairly militant secular opposition to the church in North America, the Christian church as a whole is in a period of enormous growth, particularly in the southern hemisphere and in some parts of Asia. Historians from Latourette to Walls tell us that this global expansion of the church is a consequence of the sowing of the seed during “great century” of missionary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The very title of this volume makes a claim and extends an invitation. Simply put, the claim is this: John Wesley was an adherent of covenant theology. The invitation is to investigate Wesley’s thought in light of this claim. Accepting this invitation is not without risk, as well-established conclusions regarding Wesley’s thought may need to be revised and their implications for praxis reconsidered. But neither is it without reward: namely, a new and deeper appreciation of the substantial theological underpinnings of his pastoral convictions and counsel.</p>
                     <p>As a leading figure of the Evangelical Revival in eighteenth-century England, John Wesley labored</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>John Wesley’s Imaging of Covenant Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When John Wesley compiled and published<italic>A Collection of Hymns, for the Use of the People Called Methodists</italic>in 1780, he saw to it that the hymns were “not carelessly jumbled together, but carefully ranged under proper heads, according to the experience of real Christians.”¹ A glance at the table of contents is revealing. Wesley traces “the experience of real Christians” from start to finish—from before their first setting foot on the way of salvation to mourning under conviction of sin to groaning for and experiencing “full Redemption.”² Paul Ricouer describes such a portrayal as emplotment: “the capacity to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Ancestry of John Wesley’s Covenant Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most direct introductions to the ancestry of Wesley’s covenant theology appears in his sermon “The Righteousness of Faith” published in 1746. His text was Romans 10:5–8, a text from which he had preached at least as early as 1740 and from which he would preach as late as 1789: “For Moses describeth the righteousness which is by the law, The man who doth these things shall live by them. But the righteousness which is by faith speaketh thus, . . . The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth, and in thy heart; that is,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>John Wesley’s Amendment of Covenant Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What we know of John Wesley’s covenant theology comes by way of the minutes of Conferences, the letters borne of controversy, counsel, and reflection, and the sermons, extracts, and journal entries comprising the Wesley corpus. These chronicle his encounter with the covenant theology instilled in the theological understanding of his companions, converts, and antagonists. One indicator of its status as the common currency of theological discourse is Wesley’s confidence that his use of its technical terminology would be understood by his audience. And yet, as the opening paragraph of his sermon “The Righteousness of Faith” clearly demonstrates, he recognized that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>John Wesley’s Covenant Theology and Holy Scripture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the evidence of Wesley’s thoughtful distillation of the covenant theology mediated to him, we might yet be tempted to conclude that he appreciated its theological value only as a craftsman prizes and uses each tool in his toolbox. But suppose covenant theology was not just a tool in Wesley’s hands? Suppose it was a core feature of the infrastructure of his theological thought and consequently influenced the way he used each tool in his toolbox?</p>
                     <p>There may be no clearer testimony to the veracity of these suppositions than Wesley’s approach to the interpretation of Holy Scripture. And the reason</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>John Wesley’s Covenant Theology in Context:</title>
                     <subtitle>I. The Evangelical Revival and the Conversation on Good Works</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the relationship of the servant-son metaphor to covenant theology comes more into view, its value to Wesley as a definitive narrative of his vision of the way of salvation is more clearly apparent. After all, the biblical foundation of the metaphor was indisputable and its capacity for imaging “the two grand manifestations of God, the legal and the evangelical” had established it from pulpit to pew as a familiar and theologically trustworthy summary of God’s saving activity. And yet, the soteriological content of the metaphor is more extensive than its overt relationship to the superstructure of the covenant of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>John Wesley’s Covenant Theology in Context:</title>
                     <subtitle>II. The Conversation on Divine Favor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is increasingly apparent that while there was a strong consensus on many aspects of the theological core of covenant theology and general agreement among Calvinists and Arminians alike on the shape of its superstructure (the covenants of works and of grace), the details were subject to nuancing. And the nuancing was soteriologically critical, as evidenced in the long-running conversations Wesley joined in progress as he sought to stake out the theological foundations of a Methodist morphology of conversion. His regard for the authority of Scripture, his commitment to preserve the Reformation doctrine of justification by faith along with his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>The Salvific Sufficiency of the Covenant of Grace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The attention given thus far to the context of John Wesley’s use of the servant-son metaphor has been compelled in part by the need to lay the groundwork for understanding the soteriological affirmations he expected it to convey. But it has also been compelled by the need to account for his apparent confidence that the theological repertoire of his audience was such that he could draw upon the metaphor with little or no introduction. This judgment on Wesley’s part suggests that neither the metaphor nor the primary elements of its supporting theology were original to him. Yet, it is hardly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>The Holy Spirit and the Salvific Perfection of the Covenant of Grace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The salvific sufficiency of the various dispensations of the covenant of grace, though variously conceived, is one of the primary soteriological affirmations of covenant theology. The sufficiency of each dispensation rests on the promise of Genesis 3:15, a promise for which the warranty is “the lamb slain from the foundation of the world.” Wesley’s vision of the way of salvation is profoundly shaped by his understanding that this promise and warranty are extended to all of fallen humanity rather than to the elect only, and by his conceiving the salvific sufficiency of the covenant of grace to be concurrent and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>“From Faith to Faith”:</title>
                     <subtitle>John Wesley’s Pastoral Application of Covenant Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Wesley spoke of “the whole process of a man reasoning, groaning, striving, and escaping from the legal to the evangelical state,”¹ he was bearing witness that there is “a definite teleology to divine grace.”² The centerpiece of this testimony was that the revelation of Christ was (and is) the salvation-historical event that demarcates the legal from the evangelical (gospel, Christian) dispensation of the covenant of grace. This was more than a theological affirmation, for even as the revelation of Christ in the course of the history of God’s saving deeds ushered all of humanity into the Christian dispensation (historically</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a sermon written just three years before his death, Wesley spoke about a distinction between what he called “species of faith.” He emphasized that this was “a point of no small importance” and was worthy of his ongoing effort to make the distinction and its implications “a little plainer.”¹ The distinction he was highlighting was that between “the faith of a servant” and “the faith of a son.” It is significant not only that Wesley viewed the distinction as important but that he was convinced that the biblical contrast between servant and son most adequately conveyed the<italic>dynamic</italic>of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf6d5.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
