<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN83.R4</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Reading</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Addresses, essays, lectures</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Reader in the Text</book-title>
         <subtitle>Essays on Audience and Interpretation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Suleiman</surname>
               <given-names>Susan R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Crosman</surname>
               <given-names>Inge</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400857111</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400857112</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1980</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zv3jc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A reader may be in" a text as a character is in a novel, but also as one is in a train of thought--both possessing and being possessed by it. This paradox suggests the ambiguities inherent in the concept of audience. In these original essays, a group of international scholars raises fundamental questions about the status--be it rhetorical, semiotic and structuralist, phenomenological, subjective and psychoanalytic, sociological and historical, or hermeneutic--of the audience in relation to a literary or artistic text.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1980.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="456"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>S.R.S.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>I.C.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Varieties of Audience-Oriented Criticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Suleiman</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some revolutions occur quietly: no manifestoes, no marching and singing, no tumult in the streets; simply a shift in perspective, a new way of seeing what had always been there. New words enter the vocabulary, old words suddenly take on new meaning: proletariat, ego, structure. Or they retain their meaning but their<italic>position</italic>changes: the peripheral becomes central, the walk-on becomes the hero of the play.</p>
                     <p>For the past few years, we have been witnessing just such a change in the field of literary theory and criticism. The words<italic>reader</italic>and<italic>audience,</italic>once relegated to the status of the unproblematic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prolegomena to a Theory of Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Culler</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fact that people engaged in the study of literature are willing to read works of criticism or articles like this one tells us something important about the nature of our discipline. Few people, one imagines, open these pages in the belief that this is the most relaxing and entertaining way to spend an hour. We attend to criticism and discussions of criticism because we hope to hear worthwhile proposals, arguments, and discussions. We believe, it would seem, that what is said about literature can matter; that it can affect our own and other’s dealings with literature and thus help</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reading as Construction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Todorov</surname>
                           <given-names>Tzvetan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated from the French by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>August</surname>
                           <given-names>Marilyn A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is omnipresent is imperceptible. Nothing is more commonplace than the reading experience, and yet nothing is more unknown. Reading is such a matter of course that, at first glance, it seems there is nothing to say about it.</p>
                     <p>In literary studies, the problem of reading has been posed from two opposite perspectives. The first concerns itself with readers, their social, historical, collective, or individual variability. The second deals with the image of the reader as it is represented in certain texts: the reader as character or as “narratee.” There is, however, an unexplored area situated between the two: the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Reading of Fictional Texts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stierle</surname>
                           <given-names>Karlheinz</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <role content-type="translator">Translated by</role>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crosman</surname>
                           <given-names>Inge</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zachrau</surname>
                           <given-names>Thekla</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To understand how readers deal with fictional texts we must first consider the status of fiction as such.¹ Despite all potential references to reality, a fictional text is characterized by being a nonreferential composition. Thus references to reality in fiction have their function in a poetics of fiction that might aim at reality and the collective experience of reality to a greater or lesser degree. While a pragmatic referential text can be corrected by our knowledge of reality, a fictional text—in its potential deviation from facts—cannot be corrected but only interpreted or criticized.² However, this license, which distinguishes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interaction between Text and Reader</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Iser</surname>
                           <given-names>Wolfgang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Central to the reading of every literary work is the interaction between its structure and its recipient. This is why the phenomenological theory of art has emphatically drawn attention to the fact that the study of a literary work should concern not only the actual text but also, and in equal measure, the actions involved in responding to that text. The text itself simply offers “schematized aspects”¹ through which the aesthetic object of the work can be produced.</p>
                     <p>From this we may conclude that the literary work has two poles, which we might call the artistic and the aesthetic: the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Readerhood of Man</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brooke-Rose</surname>
                           <given-names>Christine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After a long period when the Real (I prefer Actual) Author had been enthroned by criticism, his every “laundry-list” (as Pound called biography) scrutinized, he was, in true carnivalesque fashion, unthroned, the wild and happy crowd of Actual Readers taking over—but, as is the way with carnival, only for a time. Extremes bring natural reactions, and the two polarities, called at the time the Intentional and the Affective Fallacies, seem to have compromised on a safe buffer state called The Text as Object, an apparently autonomous unit that encodes both its author (implied), or addresser, and its reader (implied),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Do Readers Make Meaning?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crosman</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question is itself annoyingly vague and ambiguous, yet it is as close as I can get to expressing what seems to me the central issue of literary theory today. When Jonathan Culler calls for a “theory of reading,” when Stanley Fish speaks of “reading communities” and “reading strategies,” when Jacques Derrida announces that “the reader writes the text,” they are all, in varying degrees, answering in the affirmative. And when other theorists—Wayne Booth, E. D. Hirsch, and a host of others—see solipsism and moral chaos in such an answer, they too are testifying to the importance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fiction as Interpretation / Interpretation as Fiction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schor</surname>
                           <given-names>Naomi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her 1964 essay, “Against Interpretation,” Susan Son tag sounded the keynote of a neoformalism, a new wave of French criticism that was about to sweep over modern language departments, wreaking havoc with the traditional interpretive positions standing in its path. In order to assess the current state and status of interpretation, that is of hermeneutics in the wake of structuralism, I should like to recall very briefly the main points of Sontag’s essay, for they retain even today their polemical freshness. What must first be noted is Sontag's definition of interpretation, for her assault on hermeneutics is grounded in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Dialectic of Metaphor:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Anthropological Essay on Hermeneutics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maranda</surname>
                           <given-names>Pierre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In nonliterate societies, there are no “texts.” Yet anthropologists “read” those societies the way their compatriots read books. And in our monographs we write up peoples, events, cultures that have never felt the need for an alphabet: we reduce to<italic>linearity</italic>(imposed by written descriptions) the nonlinear (because illiterate) societies we describe. We phrase our accounts of the “others” so as to make them understandable to other “selves”; we interpret what we see and experience in so-called exotic societies in the light of the ideologies that mold us, as we try to bear witness to the diversity as well as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Toward a Sociology of Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leenhardt</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacques</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <role content-type="translator">Translated from the French by</role>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Navelet</surname>
                           <given-names>Brigitte</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Suleiman</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When raising the question of the reader’s status in the text, we may have in mind two sets of problems. According to one approach, the reader is thought of as an end conceived by the writer, whose work, accordingly, may be read in reference to the idea we have of that reader. A certain number of studies have enriched the history of literary criticism in this way, showing that the expectations of a particular public aimed at by the writer were determinative down to the most secret strata of the text (Jauss’s<italic>Erwartungshorizont</italic>for example).</p>
                     <p>In this perspective, one tends</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Text as Reader</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Prince</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reading is an activity that presupposes a text (a set of visually presented linguistic symbols from which meaning can be extracted), a reader (an agent capable of extracting meaning from that text), and an interaction between the text and the reader such that the latter is able to answer correctly at least some questions about the meaning of the former. A text like</p>
                     <p>(1) “The two suites on the second floor were taken, one by an old gentleman named Poiret; the other by a man of forty, who wore a black wig, dyed his whiskers, said he was in business,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“What’s Hecuba to Us?”</title>
                     <subtitle>The Audience’s Experience of Literary Borrowing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rabinowitz</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In choosing the title “Phorion” (“Stolen Goods”) for his hallucinatory fantasy on a Bach prelude, Lukas Foss wittily summed up not only a swelling subgenre of contemporary music, but a major trend in literature and film as well. We live in an age of artistic recycling: Alain Robbe-Grillet’s<italic>Les Gommes</italic>borrows from<italic>Oedipus;</italic>Tom Stoppard’s<italic>Rosencrantz and Guildenstern Are Dead</italic>incorporates passages from<italic>Hamlet,</italic>while his<italic>Travesties</italic>takes Joyce’s<italic>Ulysses</italic>(itself built on Homer) and Wilde’s<italic>The Importance of Being Earnest</italic>as basic material. Peter Maxwell Davies, Hugh Hartwell, George Rochberg, and Karlheinz Stockhausen have in their diverse ways “recomposed”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Montaigne’s Conception of Reading in the Context of Renaissance Poetics and Modern Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>M. Bauschatz</surname>
                           <given-names>Cathleen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In “De l’ expérience,” Montaigne describes the process of verbal communication with an intriguing parallel from tennis: the listener (or person receiving the ball) must be as actively involved as the speaker (or person serving) if the message (or ball) is to be transmitted, and more importantly, to be returned:</p>
                     <p>La parole est moitié à celuy qui parle; moitié à celuy qui l’escoute. Cettuy-cy se doibt preparer a la recevoir selon Ie branle qu’elle prend. Comme entre ceux qui jouent a la paume, celuy qui soustient se desmarche et s’apreste selon qu’il voit remuer celuy qui luy jette Ie coup</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Toward A Theory of Reading in the Visual Arts:</title>
                     <subtitle>Poussin’s The Arcadian Shepherds</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marin</surname>
                           <given-names>Louis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper is an attempt at reading a single painting—Poussin’s<italic>The Arcadian Shepherds</italic>(Louvre)¹—but such a tentative reading cannot be truly accomplished without being aware of the operations involved in the contemplative process, their implications on theoretical and practical levels, and the hypotheses which guide that process. My essay can thus be considered as an approach to a partial history of reading in the field of visual art. To put my undertaking in more general terms, I wish to test some notions and procedures elaborated in contemporary semiotic and semantic theories by using a specific painting as an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Exemplary Pornography:</title>
                     <subtitle>Barrès, Loyola, and the Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beaujour</surname>
                           <given-names>Michel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to avoid the kind of frivolity that holds ethical concerns to be irrelevant in a discussion of the reader in (of) texts, it may be wise to revisit briefly the Russian critical tradition. This tradition has entertained with high seriousness the notion—somewhat disreputable in the West—that literature, and particularly fiction, must be held accountable, since it encodes messages which affect not only the subjective world view of readers, but their attitudes and actions. Novels are presumed capable of endangering (or reinforcing) the structure of society and the legal order.¹ Rufus Mathewson’s analysis of Russian radical poetics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Re-Covering “The Purloined Letter”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading as a Personal Transaction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Holland</surname>
                           <given-names>Norman N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Begin with the text, they say. For me, one central fact about the text is that I am reading this story in Pocketbook No. 39, the copy of Poe I had as a boy—one of the first paperbacks in America. “Kind to your Pocket and your Pocketbook.” Hardly a distinguished edition, yet I find myself agreeing with what the man I call Marcel says in the library of the Guermantes: “If I had been tempted to be a book collector, as the Prince de Guermantes was, I would have been one of a very peculiar sort. . . .</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Theory and Practice of Reading Nouveaux Romans:</title>
                     <subtitle>Robbe-Grillet’s Topologie d’une cité fantôme</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mistacco</surname>
                           <given-names>Vicki</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A critic interested in how we read nouveaux romans might very well be allergic to terms like<italic>convention, naturalhation,</italic>and<italic>literary competence.</italic>Being institutional, conventions rest upon a foundation that smacks uncomfortably of the “dominant ideology” so often decried by Ricardou and his disciples. Naturalization involves constructing “communicative circuits”¹ into which we can fit a literary text; the nouveau roman officially rejects the idea of literature as communication.² And although the reader’s intertext has been invoked as an important factor in processing a given text,³ the model of literary competence has been challenged by that of performance, presumably less</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Annotated Bibliography of Audience-Oriented Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crosman</surname>
                           <given-names>Inge</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>435</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv3jc.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>442</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
