<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Algerian New Novel</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Poetics of a Modern Nation, 1950-1979</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ORLANDO</surname>
               <given-names>VALÉRIE K.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813939636</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813939631</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Charlottesville; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kk66x9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Disputing the claim that Algerian writing during the struggle against French colonial rule dealt almost exclusively with revolutionary themes,<italic>The Algerian New Novel</italic>shows how Algerian authors writing in French actively contributed to the experimental forms of the period, expressing a new age literarily as well as politically and culturally. Looking at canonical Algerian literature as part of the larger literary production in French during decolonization, Valérie K. Orlando considers how novels by Rachid Boudjedra, Mohammed Dib, Assia Djebar, Nabile Farès, Yamina Mechakra, and Kateb Yacine both influenced and were reflectors of the sociopolitical and cultural transformation that took place during this period in Algeria. Although their themes were rooted in Algeria, the avant-garde writing styles of these authors were influenced by early twentieth-century American modernists, the New Novelists of 1940s-50s France, and African American authors of the 1950s-60s. This complex mix of influences led Algerian writers to develop a unique modern literary aesthetic to express their world, a tradition of experimentation and fragmentation that still characterizes the work of contemporary Algerian francophone writers.</p>
         <p>This book considers Algerian writing from 1950-1979 in the context of the French New Novel and proposes that many of the works of this era need to be considered as avant-garde and exemplary of literary experimentation, expressing a new age literarily as well as politically and culturally.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="360"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTE ON TRANSLATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The modern Algerian novel, blending styles, languages, and ways of looking at and being in the world, demonstrates that Algerian writing of French expression has indeed always been cosmopolitan and global, exuding the Maghreb<italic>pluriel</italic>(multiple) ethic that Moroccan philosopher Abdelkébir Khatibi maintains privileges “une pensée autre” (an-Other way of thinking), which he first articulated in the 1980s. The philosopher’s concept explores the inherent hybridity of the Maghrebi subject, particularly the author writing in French, as a celebration of his/her bilingualism, which, according to Khatibi, always displays “two languages in a heterogeneous position, one working on the other, crisscrossing over,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>MIDNIGHT NOVELISTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the 1973 edition of his<italic>Le Nouveau roman,</italic>Jean Ricardou lists leading novelists of the New Novel genre from the early 1950s to 1971. The latter date marked the first colloquium dedicated to the New Novel, “Nouveau roman: Hier, aujourd’hui” (The New Novel: Yesterday, today), held in Cerisy-la-Salle, France. The colloquium contextualized the waning concept of the New Novel as its leading authors were changing their styles and thematic focus. Ricardou’s list more or less reflects the earlier 1958 grouping of authors by the French revue Esprit, as well as a special 1959 edition of<italic>Yale French Studies</italic>entitled</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>FRENCH INTELLECTUALS, VIOLENCE, AND THE ALGERIAN WAR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From 1830 forward, French philosophers, intellectuals, and politicians debated, questioned, and condemned France’s colonial mission immediately following General Bugeaud’s conquest of Algeria.¹ As early as 1833, Xavier de Sade, the liberal deputy of l’Aine, warned against French expansion into Algeria on the grounds that economically and militarily it would weaken France. His outspoken views were echoed by others such as Hippolyte Passy and Théobald Piscatory, both parliamentarians who were adamantly against colonial expansion. Piscatory noted in 1841 that “Africa ruins us during peacetime and weakens us during war. Africa is a disaster, it is madness, and if no end is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>ASSIA DJEBAR’S LA SOIF AND NATHALIE SARRAUTE’S PORTRAIT D’UN INCONNU:</title>
                     <subtitle>Defining the Authentic Self in the Exploration of a Possible World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the previous chapter explained, by the mid-1950s New Novelists began contributing to conversations that became increasingly sociopolitical and intertwined with the Algerian Revolution raging on the other side of the Mediterranean. How to explain and explore the evolving new era as it hurtled toward decolonization, overturning the long-standing colonizer-colonized dynamic, fostered questions about identity in the burgeoning freed nation that would become postcolonial Algeria in the early 1960s. Through their novels of the 1950s, Algerian authors sought to articulate what forms of subjectivity would define men and women of a nascent nation. As discussed in the last chapter, writers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>CLAUDE OLLIER’S LE MAINTIEN DE L’ORDRE AND KATEB YACINE’S LE POLYGONE ÉTOILÉ:</title>
                     <subtitle>Writing the Modern Stories That Cannot Be Told on the Blank Pages of Algeria</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Through labyrinths of eternal returns, flashbacks and flash-forwards, anonymous characters, and places with no designations, Claude Ollier and Kateb Yacine stand on either side of a narrative abyss that is fragile and dark, offering few answers to the unsettling questions that were associated with Algeria during the revolutionary period. Claude Ollier’s novel<italic>Le Maintien de l’ordre</italic>(<italic>Law and Order</italic>), published in 1961, and Kateb Yacine’s final novel in what he vaguely described as the concluding work to the<italic>Nedjma</italic>trilogy,<italic>Le Polygone étoilé</italic>(The starred polygon, 1966), are the bookends to a chapter in Algerian his tory that is as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>MOHAMMED DIB’S HABEL AND THE EXPERIMENTAL ALGERIAN NOVEL:</title>
                     <subtitle>Third World Movements and the Ideological and Literary “New Man”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By the mid-1960s when Kateb published<italic>Le Polygone étoilé,</italic>Algerian authors of French expression had already become disillusioned with the reality in which they were living. While this chapter further considers authors’ disillusionment and alienation in the postcolonial climate, it also studies to what degree the sociopolitical turbulence of the late 1960s continued to shape their works well into the 1970s. Third World movements across Africa and Latin America propelled forward by Algeria’s independence, the nascent U. S.-Vietnam war, the U. S. civil rights movement, and the social movements in France culminating into May ’ 68, all contributed to Algerian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>RACHID BOUDJEDRA’S TOPOGRAPHIE IDÉALE POUR UNE AGRESSION CARACTÉRISÉE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Labyrinths of Algerian Modernity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a 1994 interview, Rachid Boudjedra overtly proclaimed his allegiance to the New Novel: “J’ai été très influencé par le roman français, surtout le nouveau roman et le grand écrivain Claude Simon” (I’ve been very influenced by the French novel, most certainly the<italic>nouveau roman</italic>and the great writer Claude Simon).¹ However, Boudjedra, like most of the Maghrebi authors of his generation, was interested in actively contributing not so much to the oeuvre of writers included in the genre, but rather to “the renewal of the novel . . . through the appropriation of modern techniques of composition.” These techniques</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>NABILE FARÈS’S YAHIA, PAS DE CHANCE, AND OTHER EXPERIMENTAL NOVELS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Out of the Ruins Emerges a New Man and a New World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much of what has been written about Algerian Nabile Farès’s work focuses on exile, his use of multiple languages (Berber, Arabic, and French), linguistic registers, and the historical events depicted in his first three novels covering the period 1954–62 of the Algerian Revolution. His fictional works from 1971 to his death in 2016 express the desire to keep his native Kabylian culture present and alive, to use the Berber language, which he spoke before he knew French, and to break apart the codified structures of all languages. In his novels Farès, like Boudjedra and Kateb, reflects on his disappointment</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>YAMINA MECHAKRA’S LA GROTTE ÉCLATÉE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reclaiming Algeria through the Poetics of Postcolonial Space</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study of the influence of the French New Novel on Algerian writers concludes with the 1979 publication of Yasmina Mechakra’s novel,<italic>La Grotte éclatée</italic>(The shattered cave). Like Nabile Farès, Mechakra, writing in the postcolonial era, attempts to make sense of a country that, at the time of the publication of her novel, was not living up to the promises made to particularly women during the revolution. From the ruins of war and these failed promises, at the age of nineteen when she began writing the novel while attending high school in Algiers, Mechakra constructs a text that resurrects</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contemporary Modes of Being an Algerian Author</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The authors of the 1950s, ’60s, and ’70s, writing in the avant-garde of the French New Novel, set Algerian writers on a path that has inspired them to continue to explore inventive writing styles and themes up to the present day. From the past to the present, these authors have viewed the role of literature, specifically the novel, much in the same way the French-Czech writer and literary theorist Milan Kundera conceptualizes literature’s function in society in his work<italic>L’Art du roman</italic>(<italic>The Art of the Novel</italic>, 1986): “The novel does not examine reality, but existence. And existence is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kk66x9.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
