<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7p9ck</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Secret Police Files from the Eastern Bloc</book-title>
         <subtitle>Between Surveillance and Life Writing</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Glajar</surname>
               <given-names>Valentina</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lewis</surname>
               <given-names>Alison</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Petrescu</surname>
               <given-names>Corina L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781571139269</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782048695</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Rochester, NY; Woodbridge, Suffolk</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Editors and Contributors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt1kzccdr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The communist secret police services of Central and Eastern Europe kept detailed records not only of their victims but also of the vast networks of informants and collaborators upon whom their totalitarian systems depended. These records, now open to the public in many former Eastern Bloc countries, reflect a textually mediated reality that has defined and shaped the lives of former victims and informers, creating a tension between official records and personal memories. Exploring this tension between a textually and technically mediated past and the subject/victim's reclaiming and retrospective interpretation of that past in biography is the goal of this volume. While victims' secret police files have often been examined as a type of unauthorized archival life writing, the contributors to this volume are among the first to analyze the fragmentary and sometimes remedial nature of these biographies and to examine the subject/victims' rewriting and remediation of them in various creative forms. Essays focus, variously, on the files of the East German Stasi, the Romanian Securitate (in relation to Transylvanian Germans in Romania), and the Hungarian State Security Agency. Contributors: Carol Anne Costabile-Heming, Ulrike Garde, Valentina Glajar, Yuliya Komska, Alison Lewis, Corina L. Petrescu, Annie Ring, Aniko Szucs. Valentina Glajar is Professor of German at Texas State University, San Marcos. Alison Lewis is Professor of German in the School of Languages and Linguistics, The University of Melbourne, Australia. Corina L. Petrescu is Associate Professor of German at the University of Mississippi.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="252"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lewis</surname>
                           <given-names>Alison</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Glajar</surname>
                           <given-names>Valentina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Petrescu</surname>
                           <given-names>Corina L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the secret police services of the former Eastern bloc were dismantled at the end of the Cold War, they left an ambivalent legacy for successor governments. The extensive historical archives that were salvaged during the transition—the copious quantities of paper documents either left behind in the confusion of shifting relations of power or rescued by farsighted reformers—are damning evidence of the activities of the disproportionately large political police forces that mushroomed in Central and Eastern European countries under communist rule. Unlike many physical remains of these regimes that have been consigned to the dustbin of history, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1:</label>
                     <title>The Secret Lives and Files of Stasi Collaborators:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Secret Police Files for Identity and Habitus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lewis</surname>
                           <given-names>Alison</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before they were declassified under lustration legislation in the early nineties, the secret police files of Stasi informers (or<italic>Inoffizielle Mitarbeiter</italic>) employed by the domestic branch of the East German secret police in the Ministry for State Security (Ministerium für Staatssicherheit) represented top-secret narratives that were never intended to become public documents. Once unmoored from these original contexts, the files have become a public good, used to tell stories about the communist past and individuals’ entanglement with authority. Security files are a rich archive about power and the secret life of power. And because Cold War surveillance needed humans, rather</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2:</label>
                     <title>“You’ll Never Make a Spy Out of Me”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The File Story of “Fink Susanne”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Glajar</surname>
                           <given-names>Valentina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like secret police files from other Eastern bloc countries, files of the Romanian secret police (or Securitate) present fragments of individual lives that consist of a collection of informers’ notes, officers’ reports and analyses, letters, photographs, and transcripts of interrogations and wiretapped private conversations. While these notes and reports resemble particular snapshots of a person’s life, often taken from different angles and through various lenses, confirmed and reconfirmed by numerous Securitate sources, they typically resist attempts to assemble them into a coherent plot. Yet they do offer relevant insights into the organization of the Securitate and its tactics. The selectively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3:</label>
                     <title>Witness for the Prosecution:</title>
                     <subtitle>Eginald Schlattner in the Files of the Securitate</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Petrescu</surname>
                           <given-names>Corina L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his introduction to Dorin Tudoran’s published Securitate file, historian Radu Ioanid pertinently observes that “the Securitate file is not a postcommunist title of nobility, but the deformed mirror of the persecution set up by a communist regime through its political police,” and that thus “it reflects first and foremost suffering and tragedies lived by the victims during the time of their persecution.”¹ As such, as Mãdãlin Hodor shows, “the documentary value of [a Securitate] file must be constantly seen in relation to [the file’s] origin. One must not forget that it is the creation of a political police and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4:</label>
                     <title>Collaboration as Collapse in the Life Writing and Stasi Shadow-Documents of Monika Maron and Christa Wolf</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ring</surname>
                           <given-names>Annie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the Stasi files were opened in 1992, commentators expressed concern that the resulting revelations would turn the Stasi’s former collaborators into the scapegoats of the newly unified Germany.¹ However, suggestions that the archive should be buried or burned to prevent the hounding of former<italic>Inoffizielle Mitarbeiter</italic>(unofficial collaborators, or IMs) by the press were met with an outcry against the impossibility of doing justice for victims if the files were simply destroyed. Archival access was firmly supported by a collective of poets and authors who had been victims of the Stasi, and who in 1992 together published the volume</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5:</label>
                     <title>Perpetrator as Victim in Jana Döhring’s Stasiratte</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Costabile-Heming</surname>
                           <given-names>Carol Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This introductory comment in the foreword to Jana Döhring’s<italic>Stasiratte</italic>(Stasi Rat, 2012) underscores the Janus-faced nature of memory. Nowhere has this been more evident than in the confrontations that East Germans have had with their secret police (Stasi) files. More than twenty-five years after the dissolution of the oppressive regime that ruled the German Democratic Republic for forty years, the legacy of the Stasi files continues to impact personal biographies in myriad ways. The peculiarity of the Stasi remains a source of fascination, and the Academy Award–winning film<italic>Das Leben der Anderen</italic>(The Lives of Others, 2006) made</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6:</label>
                     <title>Before “It Gets All Wiped Out”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Document-Affect and History-Effect in the Hungarian Performance Apaches on the Danube</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Szucs</surname>
                           <given-names>Aniko</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Agrandmother is projecting a filmstrip for her grandchild on the small stage of a studio theater in Budapest. She is telling a tale of an Indian tribe, seemingly of distant America, from the world of Karl May’s<italic>Winnetou</italic>, about the friendship of the tribe’s Chief Gray Eagle and its medicine man, Black Moon, who together led the Apaches. The audience soon learns, however, that this tale is not about some imaginary tribe in May’s books but about a real group of “Hungarian Indians,” young men and women who spent their free time “playing Indians” in the late 1950s and early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7:</label>
                     <title>The Stasi Files on Center Stage:</title>
                     <subtitle>Life Writing, Witnessing, and Memory in Recent Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garde</surname>
                           <given-names>Ulrike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Approximately two decades after the fall of the Berlin Wall, a number of theater practitioners began to work with documents related to the German Democratic Republic’s Ministerium für Staatssicherheit (Ministry for State Security), the so-called Stasi files, in which the secret police service had gathered information on the lives of its fellow citizens. This chapter focuses on artistic engagements with this specific type of life writing in theater productions which encouraged individual performers who had been directly affected by the surveillance to engage, along with their audiences, with fragments of Stasi files in public performance spaces in and around Germany’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8:</label>
                     <title>Surveillance and the Senses in a Documentary Portrait of Radio Free Europe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Komska</surname>
                           <given-names>Yuliya</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of Radio Free Europe (RFE; since 1976, Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, or RFE/RL), the West’s key Cold War–era broadcaster into five Eastern European countries in six languages, is laced with tales of mystery, murder, and espionage.¹ Founded in 1950 and covertly financed by the CIA until 1967, based in divided Germany’s western half, amplified along fascist Portugal’s coast, and jammed east of the Iron Curtain, the station remained for decades in the spotlight of more than one country’s secret police. In addition to the CIA and its Western European counterparts, “[a] ll of the intelligence services of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kzccdr.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
