<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2n76t0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BX1795.S48S25 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Sex</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious aspects</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Doctrines</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Sexual Person</book-title>
         <subtitle>Toward a Renewed Catholic Anthropology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Salzman</surname>
               <given-names>Todd A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lawler</surname>
               <given-names>Michael G.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>21</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781589012080</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1589012089</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781589017269</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1589017269</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Georgetown University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2tt69p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Two principles capture the essence of the official Catholic position on the morality of sexuality: first, that any human genital act must occur within the framework of heterosexual marriage; second, each and every marriage act must remain open to the transmission of life. In this comprehensive overview of Catholicism and sexuality, theologians Todd A. Salzman and Michael G. Lawler examine and challenge these principles. Remaining firmly within the Catholic tradition, they contend that the church is being inconsistent in its teaching by adopting a dynamic, historically conscious anthropology and worldview on social ethics and the interpretation of scripture while adopting a static, classicist anthropology and worldview on sexual ethics. While some documents from Vatican II, like<italic>Gaudium et spes</italic>("the marital act promotes self-giving by which spouses enrich each other"), gave hope for a renewed understanding of sexuality, the church has not carried out the full implications of this approach. In short, say Salzman and Lawler: emphasize relationships, not acts, and recognize Christianity's historically and culturally conditioned understanding of human sexuality.<italic>The Sexual Person</italic>draws historically, methodologically, and anthropologically from the best of Catholic tradition and provides a context for current theological debates between traditionalists and revisionists regarding marriage, cohabitation, homosexuality, reproductive technologies, and what it means to be human. This daring and potentially revolutionary book will be sure to provoke constructive dialogue among theologians, and between theologians and the Magisterium.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Curran</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The authors of this book, Todd A. Salzman and Michael G. Lawler, write as Catholic theologians who both are married and are very familiar with the Catholic tradition. The book accepts the classical understanding of faith and reason, recognizing especially the importance of human reason in developing sexual marital morality. The authors ground their understanding of sexuality in a more personalistic and relational understanding of natural law theory. They enter into a dialogue almost exclusively with other Catholic authors who have been dealing with these issues. On the basis of their natural law theory, they propose a renewed Catholic anthropology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Two magisterial principles capture the essence of the Catholic moral, sexual tradition. The first principle comes from the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith: “Any human genital act whatsoever may be placed only within the framework of marriage.”¹ The second received its modern articulation in Pope Paul VI’s <italic>Humanae vitae:</italic> “Each and every marriage act must remain open to the transmission of life.”² In the Catholic tradition sexual activity is institutionalized within the confines of marriage and procreation, and sexual morality is marital morality.</p>
                     <p>These two principles that capture the essence of the Catholic tradition do not have the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Sexual Morality in the Catholic Tradition:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Brief History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>6</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Human sexual activity and the sexual ethics that seeks to order it are both sociohistorical realities and are, therefore, subject to historicity, the quality of the human animal that follows inevitably from his and her situation in real time and space and “provides him with a [human] world that he must accept in freedom.”¹ Before we embark on a presentation of contemporary Catholic sexual anthropology and ethics, therefore, it behooves us to look at their past history. In this chapter we do that in two stages. First, and briefly because it is already well known and well documented, we consider</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>Natural Law and Sexual Anthropology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Catholic Traditionalists</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>“Traditionalist” is the general label given to moral theologians who support and defend absolute magisterial norms prohibiting certain types of sexual acts such as premarital sex, artificial birth control, artificial reproductive technologies, masturbation, and homosexual acts. The traditionalist school is contrasted with the revisionist school. “Revisionist” is the general label given to moral theologians who question many of these absolute norms. These two groups disagree on many specific sexual norms because they disagree, more fundamentally, on method and the sexual anthropology that either supports these norms or questions their legitimacy and credibility. After defining the complex term “nature,” which is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Natural Law and Sexual Anthropology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Catholic Revisionists</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Catholic traditionalist sexual anthropology emphasizes classicism, the universality of basic goods and human “nature,” absolute norms, and an act-centered morality. Catholic revisionist sexual anthropology emphasizes historical consciousness, the particularity of basic goods and the human person, norms that reflect this particularity, and a relational-centered morality. In this chapter, we present a revisionist critique of traditionalist sexual anthropology. We then explore various dimensions of revisionist, including feminist, sexual anthropologies.</p>
                     <p>Revisionist critiques of traditionalist sexual anthropologies have parallels with the critique of the implicit moral method and anthropology used in the manuals of moral theology. The defining aspect of these manuals, which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Unitive Sexual Morality:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Revised Foundational Principle and Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Theologians who espouse the <italic>Gaudium et spes</italic> tradition find in the document a foundational principle for judging all human activity, including human sexual activity, namely, the criterion of the human person adequately considered. A reasonable question immediately arises: What does it mean to consider the human sexual person adequately in order to respond to complex moral issues surrounding human sexuality? In response to this question we first formulate a foundational principle of human sexuality; we then expand on the morally significant dimensions of that principle; and finally we draw insight from these dimensions in our reconstructed definition of complementarity, a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Marital Morality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the previous chapter we advanced a theoretical foundational principle for making judgments about the morality of sexual actions. This principle was articulated as follows: Sexual actions within marriage by which a couple is united intimately and chastely are noble and worthy. If expressed in a manner that is truly human and justly loving, these actions signify and promote that mutual self-giving whereby spouses enrich each other, their family, and their community with a joyful and thankful will. We also introduced into the discussion of complementarity, initiated by Pope John Paul II, a definition, the notion of orientation complementarity and,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>Cohabitation and the Process of Marrying</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Emmanuel ntakarutimana expresses the Central African experience of marrying in the following words. “Where Western tradition presents marriage as a point in time at which consent is exchanged between the couple in front of witnesses approved by law, followed by consummation, the tradition here recognizes the consummation of a marriage with the birth of the first child. To that point the marriage was only being <italic>progressively realized</italic>.”¹ Four years of field experience in East Africa taught us the same thing. We offer three points of clarification. First, the Western tradition to which Ntakarutimana refers is the Western tradition of only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>Homosexuality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>One sexual issue is today causing anguish to some Christians and confusion and anger to others and is tearing the churches apart as never before. It is the issue of homosexuality. In this chapter we consider this issue in the context of scripture and the Catholic moral tradition interpreted in the contemporary sociohistorical context. Our approach is that mapped out by Pope Benedict XVI when he was Professor Joseph Ratzinger: “Not everything that exists in the Church must for that reason be also a legitimate tradition; in other words, not every tradition that arises in the Church is a true</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>Artificial Reproductive Technologies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>236</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the 1950s the marketing of effective oral contraceptives made it possible to have sexual intercourse without reproduction; in the 1980s the marketing of artificial reproductive technologies (ARTs) made it possible to reproduce without having sexual intercourse. The Catholic Magisterium argues against the morality of both oral contraceptives and ARTs on the basis of its principle of the inseparability of the unitive and procreative meanings of sexual intercourse. We have already dealt at length with the teaching on contraception. In this chapter, we deal with the teaching on ARTs. The Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith’s (CDF’s) <italic>Instruction</italic>, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Throughout this book we have argued that Catholic sexual morality is institutionalized within the confines of marriage and procreation, and we have examined the foundations of two principles that articulate the essence of that Catholic morality. The first principle states that “any human genital act whatsoever may be placed only within the confines of marriage”;¹ the second states that “each and every marriage act must remain open to the transmission of life.”² In contemporary Catholic moral theology, two approaches to understanding these principles demarcate two schools of Catholic moral theology. First, the classicist approach holds the principles as universal, permanent,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt69p.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
