<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Gift and the Unity of Being</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>López</surname>
               <given-names>Antonio</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Milbank</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227174272</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227902196</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Antonio López</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf9tt"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Starting from both our originary experience of being given to ourselves and Jesus Christ’s archetypal self-donation, 'Gift and the Unity of Being' elucidates the sense in which gift is the form of being’s unity, while unity itself constitutes the permanence of the gift of being. In dialogue with ancient and modern philosophers and theologians, López offers a synthetic, rather than systematic, account of the unity proper to being, the human person, God, and the relations among them. The book shows how contemplation of the triune God of love through Jesus Christ in the Holy Spirit allows us to discover the eternal communion that being is and to which finite being is called. It also illustrates the sense in which God’s gratuitousness unexpectedly offers the human person the possibility to recognize and embrace his origin and destiny, and thus he is given to see and taste in God’s light the ever-fruitful, dramatic, and mysterious positivity of being.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="368"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Milbank</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Today it would be difficult for any one theologian to write a complete, new<italic>Summa</italic>. Yet in this wonderful book, Antonio López offers us no less than a short, indicative<italic>Summa theologiae</italic>for our times, which points the way to a new theological and philosophical synthesis.</p>
                     <p>This synthesis pivots round the concept of “gift.” This is no arbitrary, idiosyncratic choice on Fr. López’s part, because today, to a remarkable degree, much academic and practical thinking is converging round this theme. Ever since Marcel Mauss, anthropologists, sociologists, and historians have come more and more to realize that human society as such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The mystery of birth fills our existence with joy, hope, and wonder, but it does more than this as well:it calls us to ponder the mystery of the positivity of being. There are several layers of meaning to the mystery of being born, and these layers, though intrinsically and circularly related, are distinct but not independent. The first meaning, perhaps the most obvious but not the least important, is the biological. Life, the fruit of the loving union between a father and a mother, is given to us with and through a corporeal, organic existence. Our very body continually refers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>I.</label>
                     <title>Gift’s Originary Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Originary experience opens up a seldom pursued but uniquely fruitful path for pondering the form of the unity of being. In part because of the troubled history of the concept, and partly because of the contemporary use of the term “experience,” originary experience may seem a doubtful starting point. “Experience,” in fact, has been described as the “most deceitful” and “most obscure” of terms.¹ Nevertheless, if by originary experience we mean the engagement of the whole of our being with the whole of reality and with God, who is their innermost and transcendent center, originary experience, despite its difficulties, can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>II. Concrete Singularity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The engagement of the whole of ourselves with the whole of reality, and with the center of both, who is God, calls us to recognize the positivity of all that is. With all its dramatic tensions, originary experience reveals that being itself is good<italic>qua</italic>given, that it is good to exist with others, and that the task for life is given with our destiny. It also reveals how every concrete singular is thus bound together in a complex, manifold unity in which each is fully itself.¹ The preceding chapter’s anthropological reflection now opens up into a path to see</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>III.</label>
                     <title>Reception and Reciprocity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The response of wonder before God’s communication of esse deepens when we become aware that God gives the human person, along with the capacity to stand on his own, the capacity to act out of his own being (<italic>autexousia</italic>).¹ When God gives, he gives because he wants to share his giving. In fact, it would not be a real giving if God did not allow the concrete singular being to participate in his capacity to give, in his own freedom. The divine creating act goes so far that Aquinas claims that the human person is the cause of himself.² Gregory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IV.</label>
                     <title>The Son’s Gift of Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The mystery of the unity of being finds its archetypal expression in the eventful form of Jesus Christ. His person renders in flesh and in history the nature of the one God as an ineffable communion of love that radically responds to man’s rejection. Translating his divine filiation into human existence, Christ’s gift of himself to the utmost redeems humankind; that is, he corrects man’s distorted perception of himself, God, and the world and offers to man the possibility of sharing divine life.¹ Thus, the Logos’s kenotic descent, lived out as a constant, loving obedience to the Father in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>V.</label>
                     <title>The Unpreceded Giver</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ultimate, eternal origin of the gift, God the Father, offers the path for understanding the meaning of gift and the unity it posits: eternal communion. Mindful that the Father always remains an evergreater mystery and that even the eyes of faith cannot bear his eternal light (“You cannot bear it now,” John 16: 12; “It has not appeared as yet what we will be,” 1 John 3: 2), this chapter sets out to consider divine fatherhood by reflecting on the meaning of begetting, the constitutive personal property of the first hypostasis of the Trinity. In what sense is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VI.</label>
                     <title>Gift’s Unifying Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our attempt to understand the unity of being in terms of gift so far has brought to light the primal character of gift. Gift is a primal, a principle, inasmuch as it is a permanent source. The positivity of concrete singular beings suggested by originary experience rests on the permanent, personal principle of originating and ordering, a Father whose face we are invited to see in his beloved, Incarnate Son. Gift is also a primal because it indicates “first-ness.” According to this second sense of “primal,” being’s primordial unity is an ever-new beginning. Each concrete singular being is created; it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VII.</label>
                     <title>The Unexpected Gift</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have approached the circularity of being and gift by saying that whereas gift indicates the unity of being, unity points to the permanence of the gift. The inseparability of the gifted unity of being from the question of time arose through the examination of the gratuity of the gift: the entryway to the meaning of being’s time and eternity.Pondering God’s own gratuity revealed that the tri-hypostatic being is one precisely because God is eternal, ever-fruitful beginning. Eternity is the tri-hypostatic gift that is simple, perfect, self-subsistent, and ever-fruitful beginning. We also arrived at the relation between being and time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Envoi</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>304</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemplating the mystery of birth and our own originary experience invited us to acknowledge that the nature and unity of the singular being is gift, given to itself in order to recognize and adhere to the mystery of God, the<italic>agapic</italic>giver. The existence of the concrete singular reflects at every level— from the dual unity of its being to its action— its constitutive being-gift. Failing to heed the call to affirm himself and the world as gift by gratuitously recognizing that God is everything, the created singular human being attempted to grasp at a greater delight by conceiving himself</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9tt.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Backmatter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
