<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Fueling Culture</book-title>
         <subtitle>101 Words for Energy and Environment</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Szeman</surname>
               <given-names>Imre</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wenzel</surname>
               <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Yaeger</surname>
               <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">Editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823273904</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823273942</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1hfr0s3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How has our relation to energy changed over time? What differences do particular energy sources make to human values, politics, and imagination? How have transitions from one energy source to another—from wood to coal, or from oil to solar to whatever comes next—transformed culture and society? What are the implications of uneven access to energy in the past, present, and future? Which concepts and theories clarify our relation to energy, and which just get in the way? Fueling Culture offers a compendium of keywords written by scholars and practitioners from around the world and across the humanities and social sciences. These keywords offer new ways of thinking about energy as both the source and the limit of how we inhabit culture, with the aim of opening up new ways of understanding the seemingly irresolvable contradictions of dependence upon unsustainable energy forms. Fueling Culture brings together writing that is risk-taking and interdisciplinary, drawing on insights from literary and cultural studies, environmental history and ecocriticism, political economy and political ecology, postcolonial and globalization studies, and materialisms old and new. Keywords in this volume include: Aboriginal, Accumulation, Addiction, Affect, America, Animal, Anthropocene, Architecture, Arctic, Automobile, Boom, Canada, Catastrophe, Change, Charcoal, China, Coal, Community, Corporation, Crisis, Dams, Demand, Detritus, Disaster, Ecology, Electricity, Embodiment, Ethics, Evolution, Exhaust, Fallout, Fiction, Fracking, Future, Gender, Green, Grids, Guilt, Identity, Image, Infrastructure, Innervation, Kerosene, Lebenskraft, Limits, Media, Metabolism, Middle East, Nature, Necessity, Networks, Nigeria, Nuclear, Petroviolence, Photography, Pipelines, Plastics, Renewable, Resilience, Risk, Roads, Rubber, Rural, Russia, Servers, Shame, Solar, Spill, Spiritual, Statistics, Surveillance, Sustainability, Tallow, Texas, Textiles, Utopia, Venezuela, Whaling, Wood, Work For a full list of keywords in and contributors to this volume, please go to: http://ow.ly/4mZZxV</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="400"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HOW TO USE THIS BOOK</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Infinite”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="illustrator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Image by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Logar</surname>
                           <given-names>Ernst</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wenzel</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the first acts of armed struggle undertaken by Umkhonto we Sizwe (MK), the military wing of the African National Congress (ANC) that launched on December 16, 1961, was the dynamiting of an electrical pylon in Durban and a power station near Port Elizabeth.¹ Launched with a series of coordinated attacks, the sabotage campaign of 1961–63—whose targets included major infrastructure as well as pass offices and other government buildings—resulted in the arrest of Nelson Mandela and other ANC leaders, who were charged with sabotage and treason and sentenced to life in prison. When the anti-apartheid struggle</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aboriginal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cariou</surname>
                           <given-names>Warren</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we think of Aboriginal people in the context of fuel, one common image is of Aboriginal protestors voicing resistance to energy projects like PIPELINES, DAMS, and uranium mines. One reason for the prevalence and the visibility of such protests is that Aboriginal people are disproportionately affected by energy megaprojects—in fact, it is difficult to find a megaproject that has<italic>not</italic>displaced indigenous people or in some way threatened their cultural and physical survival. This situation can hardly be accidental. Low population densities, ongoing histories of colonial disempowerment, and the existence of alternate (noncapitalist) value systems within Aboriginal communities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Accumulation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel Gustav</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For those of us who wish to carry on living—as bodies and as “us,” a totality of lived relations—ENERGY is needed. How do we get enough calories to get up and do it again or to create something? Collaboration is necessary, but on what terms? For now, the terms by which people must engage with one another to meet their needs for energy are capitalist ones. “The capitalist production process,” our best theorist on the matter explains, is “a process of accumulation” (K. Marx 1991, 324). Accumulation of what, by whom, and with what consequences? These questions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Addiction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Canavan</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A July 16, 2010, segment on<italic>The Daily Show</italic>, three months after the catastrophic Deep water Horizon oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico, offers an amusing supercut of every president since 1970 promising to eliminate US oil dependence. Barack Obama in 2010 announces that “now is the moment” to “seize control of our own destiny” back from the oil on which we depend; George W. Bush in 2006 promises to “make our dependence on Middle Eastern oil a thing of the past”; his father in 1992 asserts “there is no security for the United States in further dependence on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Affect</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schneider-Mayerson</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We must internalize the externalities. By this I mean not that we must reform neoliberal capitalism so that global markets account for pesky “externalities” like a functional biosphere but that we must internalize and embody the consequences of our heretofore disastrous ENERGY choices. Not as theater or exercise but as a step toward action.</p>
                     <p>Reading Elizabeth Kolbert’s (2014) recent book on mass extinctions, I was reminded that upon the detonation of the first atomic bomb in New Mexico in 1945, J. Robert Oppen heimer claimed that a line from the<italic>Bhagavad Gita</italic>sprung to mind: “Now I am become death,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>America</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pease</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The discovery of oil did not create American capitalist society, but the form of capitalism responsible for the United States’ rise to global dominance can trace its origins to the day in 1859 that Colonel Edwin Drake struck rock oil near Titusville, Pennsylvania. The “American way of life” would be unimaginable without an oil economy marked by surplus production, militarism, AUTOMOBILITY, unregulated markets, and mass consumption.</p>
                     <p>Oil capitalism shaped significant turns in US national history. President Monroe imagined the Americas as a national protectorate, but Big Oil installed the transportation, commercial, military, and geopolitical networks that guaranteed US seigniorage over</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Animal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haynes</surname>
                           <given-names>Melissa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why are animals absent from so many histories of ENERGY development? Given the significance of animal energy to the growth of human civilization, the oversight is puzzling. Perhaps the animal is too close to us to be recognized: animals may be “good to think” (Levi-Strauss 1991, 89), but the immediacy of their energy seems to make them difficult to think<italic>about</italic>. Reading animals into the history of energy might require us to begin at a distance, asking first when and how we have used animal energy, before we can see what it is and what it means to us.</p>
                     <p>Humans</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anthropocene 1</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chakrabarty</surname>
                           <given-names>Dipesh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The International Union of Geological Sciences (IUGS) names the current epoch the Holocene (“entirely recent”), which began about 11,700 years ago, after the last major ice age (Stromberg 2013). Many students of the Earth’s climate argue that, in view of human effects on the biosphere, this name is no longer adequate. They suggest that we may have entered a new geological epoch when humanity acts on the planet as a geophysical force: the Anthropocene. The first statement in this regard was made jointly by Paul J. Crutzen, a Nobel Prize–winning chemist from the Max Planck Institute, and Eugene F.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anthropocene 2</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nixon</surname>
                           <given-names>Rob</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a growing chorus of scientists, the Holocene is history. Through our collective actions we have jolted the planet into a new, unprecedented epoch, the Anthropocene, which, according to one influential view, dates back to the late-eighteenth-century beginnings of the Industrial Revolution. The ecologist Eugene Stoermer coined the term<italic>Anthropocene</italic>(age of humans) in 2000, and the Nobel Prize–winning atmospheric chemist Paul Crutzen quickly popularized its core assertion that for the first time in Earth’s history, a sentient species,<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>, has become not just a biomorphic but a geomorphic force. The grand species narrative that drives the Anthropocene</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Architecture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barber</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1957 the office of Charles and Ray Eames, one of the best known mid-century architecture firms, produced what they called a Solar Do-Nothing Machine. Developed as part of a marketing campaign for the Aluminum Company of America, it consisted of a 24-inch elliptical aluminum platform supporting moving pinwheels and star shapes, all made of brightly colored anodized aluminum. On the side, a freestanding reflector screen of polished aluminum strips captured and reflected sunlight into photovoltaic cells that converted it into ELECTRICITY (Neuhart et al. 1989, 178). As<italic>LIFE</italic>magazine noted in 1958, “the toy has no use and is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Arctic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ruiz</surname>
                           <given-names>Rafico</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Arctic” is a cultural figuration that does a lot of work. It marks a nebulous geographic region, an atmospheric condition, and, increasingly, perhaps<italic>the</italic>common place where environmental CHANGE is made manifest. With the proliferation of time-lapse satellite images showing the shrinking polar ice cap, documentary PHOTOGRAPHY and film following the pace of glacial melt, and the prominence of the Northwest Passage as a maritime transportation corridor, the Arctic has a recurring cultural visuality and instrumentality all its own and utterly of the present. Part of the Arctic’s figurative work depends on its being perceived as a mappable territory—a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Automobile</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sayre</surname>
                           <given-names>Gordon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The current worldwide dominance of gasoline-powered automobiles with internal combustion engines constitutes a “transportation monoculture” (Sperling and Gordon 2009, 15) with deleterious consequences too familiar and numerous to list. But from 1890 to about 1905, newly-invented automobiles were fueled by steam, electric batteries, alcohol, diesel, and biodiesel fuels, as well as gasoline, and it was not obvious which fuel would come to dominate the market. Rough, unpaved roads, short trips, and low speeds were the norm, which negated the advantages in power and range that hydrocarbon fuels later offered. The 1894 Paris-Rouen horseless carriage competition, often called the first automobile</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Automobility</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Green-Simms</surname>
                           <given-names>Lindsey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Life of the Automobile</italic>, Soviet critic Ilya Ehrenburg writes, “Cars don’t have a homeland. Like oil stocks or like classic love, they can easily cross borders . . . . The automobile has come to show even the slowest minds that the earth is truly round” (1929, 167). Ehrenburg’s semi-fictional chronicle of the rise of the AUTOMOBILE can help us understand the specific, paradoxical ways that different subjects experience automobility in a world that is increasingly linked through technologies yet profoundly uneven. His interwar tour de force addresses the combined pleasure and violence of the system of automobility</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Boom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marshall</surname>
                           <given-names>Brenda K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first boom was wheat.</p>
                     <p>In 1873 the Northern Pacific Railroad (NPRR), the recipient of a federal land grant to build a line from Duluth to Puget Sound, ran out of money at Bismarck, Dakota Territory. With newspapers in the east deriding this “wild scheme to build a railroad from Nowhere, through No-Man’s-Land to No Place,” the NPRR came up with a strategy to advertise the fertility of this No-Man’s-Land: “bonanza” farms owned and operated mostly by eastern industrialists who exchanged increasingly worthless NPRR stock for huge parcels of land abutting the railroad.</p>
                     <p>Stories of the productivity of the bonanza</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Canada</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dobson</surname>
                           <given-names>Kit</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Canada offers a case study in what it means to quite literally fuel culture. Since its colonization by European settlers, Canada has built an economy around the extraction of resources destined to feed colonial capitals. In its early days, Canada simply exported whatever was wanted in Europe (furs, mostly). Economist and historian Harold Innis’s now-classic articulation of the staples thesis holds that Canada developed as it did because of its grounding in the export of staple goods like fur, fish, and other raw materials. Innis maintains in<italic>The Fur Trade in Canada</italic>(1930) that “energy in the colony” of early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Catastrophe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aradau</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Invocations of fear, attacks, and adversaries have long been characterized as security imaginaries. More recently, the prospect of catastrophic disruption has led security professionals across the Western world to draw up new scenarios of the worst still to come and to prepare exercises for inhabiting the catastrophic futures they have imagined. More established threats insidiously morph into unexpected, unknowable, and unpredictable catastrophic events that can erupt anytime, anywhere. Over the past few decades, security has come to be appended to almost everything: human security, food security, water security, energy security, climate security, GENDER security, cyber security, data security, and so</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Change</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buchanan</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is simple, really. Our dependency on carbon fuels is jeopardizing our only planet home. To avert DISASTER, we must either switch to a more sustainable fuel source or find technological solutions to the environmental problems we have created. But who is this “we” and how can “they” effect the necessary changes? It cannot be done alone; no individual can pull off this miracle herself. It cannot even be done one country at a time. It will require a coordinated global effort, one that changes our very conception of change. Political science has three main theories of how change of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Charcoal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Irr</surname>
                           <given-names>Caren</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While grilling outdoors is a nostalgic leisure activity pursued by many Westerners, WOOD is the primary fuel of the poor throughout the developing world—especially in sub-Saharan Africa where it is mainly used for cooking. The World Future Council estimates that 80 percent of Africans rely on biomass (wood and charcoal) for their energy needs. The bulk of biomass energy involves combustion of unprocessed fuelwood, but a significant and growing percentage results from charcoal burning in urban settings. Producing charcoal requires burning several times as much per unit of energy as one uses when burning fuelwood directly; charcoal is inefficient</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>China 1</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dirlik</surname>
                           <given-names>Arif</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These headlines date from a short period of no particular eventfulness in late 2013. They are typical of reports that are increasingly streaming out of the People’s Republic of China (PRC). Attention to the social and environmental toll of development in China now claims nearly equal time to celebrations of development and its yet-to-be fulfilled promises. Such gloomy prospects are of deep concern among the leadership and the population at large, especially the latter, who have to live with the negative consequences of development even as they benefit from it.</p>
                     <p>Headlines are intended to lure the reader. Even so, these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>China 2</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zhang</surname>
                           <given-names>Amy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Demand for ENERGY requires a constant search for new territories of extraction. China’s ever-expanding economy has turned to refuse and debris as energy sources. Waste-toenergy (WTE) incineration, which burns garbage to generate energy, carries the promise of transforming trash, previously a constant reminder of the crisis of consumption, into a new power source. What WTE has produced, however, is less an alternative ENERGY RE GIME than a new rationale for current consumptive practices.</p>
                     <p>In spite of a long history of burning waste, modern incinerators now function as an emblem of progress through technological engineering as they transform and reorient matter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dawson</surname>
                           <given-names>Ashley</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Coal is the big dirty secret of our time. Although coal-fired power plants generate more than 50 percent of ELECTRICITY in the United States, few Americans think about coal when they stop to reflect on where their power comes from (Bob Johnson 2010). The tense geopolitics of oil attracts many more headlines than coal, yet 35 percent of the world’s electricity is currently generated by coal power, and developing nations such as CHINA and India bring hundreds of pollution-belching, coal-fired power plants online each year. When we turn on our sleek iPads and MacBooks, we seldom consider that the ENERGY</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Coal Ash</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hatmaker</surname>
                           <given-names>Susie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To live in a coal-fueled culture is to live in the time of ash: a time of irrationality, unpredictability, and unanticipated events that reveal not the work of an angry god, but the limits to human progress and scientific planning. Power generation and electrification emerged in the twentieth century as core elements of modernization and development on a global scale. The failure to account for the corresponding production of waste is neither mistake nor oversight, but inherent to this logic.</p>
                     <p>To fuel culture, COAL must burn. We convert prehistoric organic sediment into an invisible, world-shaping force of ELECTRICITY. Coal powers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Community</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dorow</surname>
                           <given-names>Sara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Oil’s binding of production–social reproduction–consumption binds us, in turn, to it. One shape that such a collective truth takes is “community.” As it has underwritten new arrangements of global capitalist ACCUMULATION over the last century, oil has offered up community by reconstituting the possible forms and imaginaries of collective social life. Petroleum products have promised public and private spaces of leisure, freedom, and urbanized modernity; oil value chains have produced transnational and cosmopolitan NET WORKS of IDENTITY ; flows of oil have invited us into affective spectacles of consumption; and oil has extended and/or compressed the time-space experiences</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Corporation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pendakis</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An ambiguity has clouded our understanding of the corporation ever since Stewart Kyd’s 1793 treatise distinguished between the corporation as a stable juridico-material entity and the process (of incorporation) by which the corporation gains its unique legal prerogative. Incorporation, however, is never mechanically anterior to the corporate form, per se, but instead its very essence: a dynamic, precarious activity characterized by a desire for what Kyd called “perpetual succession,” an existence projected aggressively onto a temporal horizon limited only by the criterion of profit (Kyd 1793, 6). The corporation is a “living being” that combines Spinoza’s<italic>conatus</italic>—the impulse to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Crisis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Jason W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A funny thing happened on the road to a theory of environmental crisis and environmental degradation in capitalist development. It never happened.</p>
                     <p>I do not mean to suggest that questions about the role of ecology in crises of ACCU MULATION have not been posed. But strikingly little movement has occurred in socioecological thinking about capital accumulation and its crises, a quarter-century after James O’Connor’s groundbreaking theory of the second contradiction (1998), which finds in the expanded accumulation of capital an exhaustion of the relations and conditions of (re) production. Radical thought today has settled on a language of crisis that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Dams</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hitchcock</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To understand the dialectical relationship between human species being and NATURE, consider water. Water is so implicated in our substance and our needs as to be axiomatic both in our forms of socialization and their contestation and in how we articulate material being. Yet its apparent ubiquity masks contradictions involved in its measure. Hegel, for example, invokes water in his discussion of measure to explain the leaps between quantity and quality (2015, 288–93). Marx subjects this Hegelian antinomy to a materialist injunction: in the<italic>German Ideology</italic>, he writes that “the ‘essence’ of the fish is its ‘being,’ water” (Marx</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Demand</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shove</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walker</surname>
                           <given-names>Gordon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For physicists, ENERGY is the ability to do WORK. The demand for energy depends on the type of work to be done and how that work is organized. This simple observation opens the way for some less than obvious lines of thought.</p>
                     <p>In borrowing the physicists’ definition in order to understand the historic and ongoing dynamics of energy demand, we need a broad interpretation of<italic>work</italic>—one that includes practices of sociability, having fun, growing up and growing old, and eating and sleeping, along with work in the more conventional sense of production, employment, and labor. Most social practices generate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Detritus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chari</surname>
                           <given-names>Sharad</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Oil is literally rot. As biomass decomposing over millions of years, oil is the rot of ages, and yet it has become the fuel we cannot yet do without. This dialectic of protracted ruination and fatal promise crystallizes the ethos of our time. If the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth-century moment that inaugurated the age of oil was also, at least in some places, a time of modernist hope for human liberation against the specter of annihilation, the present appears more obviously marked by proliferating decay, desperate walling-in from inequality, political discourse utterly disengaged from arts of survival, and painful archiving of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Disaster</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Colebrook</surname>
                           <given-names>Claire</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Disaster films frame life and death situations in such a way as to sharpen the meaning of life. In small-scale films such as<italic>The Poseidon Adventure</italic>(1972),<italic>The Towering Inferno</italic>(1974), or even<italic>Jaws</italic>(1975), a local threat drives characters into familial or tribal collectives, all focused on an exit strategy, with key characters playing out both romance and villain plots. In more recent end-of-the-world films like the viral pandemics 28<italic>Days Later</italic>(2002), 28<italic>Weeks Later</italic>(2007), or<italic>Contagion</italic>(2011), the very survival of humanity and civilization is at stake. Today, in a world of widespread CATASTROPHE, disaster provides</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ecology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morton</surname>
                           <given-names>Timothy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we divide the world into the categories<italic>nature</italic>and<italic>culture</italic>, we perform the quintessential gesture of modernity. But modernity is predicated on the ecological emergency that has given rise to a new geological epoch: the A NTHROPOCENE. “Modernity” is how the Anthropocene has appeared to us historically thus far. Dividing the world into NATURE and culture is precisely anti-ecological insofar as it participates in the logistics that enabled humans to act as a geophysical force on a planetary scale. The Anthropocene is the moment when Western philosophy restricted itself to the (human) subject-world correlate (Meillassoux 2008, 5). This self-imposed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Electricity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ackerman</surname>
                           <given-names>Alan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Electrical charges are positive and negative. That polarity is crucial to the physical and figurative power that electricity generates. “It is impossible to read the compositions of the most celebrated writers of the present day,” writes Percy Bysshe Shelley in “A Defence of Poetry,” “without being startled with the electric life which burns within their words” (1973 [1821], 762). Poetry is “a sword of lightning,” a revolutionary force “which consumes the scabbard that would contain it,” while a fascination with “electricity and galvanism” leads Mary Shelley’s Frankenstein to his “utter and terrible destruction” (2002 [1818], 43). Is our ambivalence about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Embodiment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Johnson</surname>
                           <given-names>Bob</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Empty your mind of chatter. Recline into child’s pose. And let the quiet textures of petroleum caress your body. Congratulate yourself for being here. This is your hour. This is your truth.</p>
                     <p>Hot yoga emblematizes who we are as a people—it is both metonym and exaggeration of the modern condition. The wild excess of steam heat, the span of vinyl-wood flooring, the plate glass walls and mirrors, and the textures of spandex, polyester, and PVC mats immerse the modern body in a festival of tactile and visual sensations that trace back to the pleasures of combusted carbon. Here, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Energopolitics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boyer</surname>
                           <given-names>Dominic</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Iceland, in the dead of winter, you can hike across barren fractal plains of volcanic rock, covered with crusts of ice and lashed with snow. But go with a guide. Because beneath these plains churns water-wishing-to-become-steam, containing ENERGY enough to power an entire country, with plenty heat left over to scald an errant traveler. The whole landscape simmers and plumes. A geothermal spring in the wilderness is one of life’s miracles. Lush moss thrives improbably in the space where bubbling water ends and ice begins.</p>
                     <p>That barrens can be more than they seem is the premise of this essay.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Energy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Soni</surname>
                           <given-names>Vivasvan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Aristotle’s unusual and tragic sense of motion, as the “actuality of a potential, as such” (Kosman 1969, 57; see also Sachs n. d.), we are on the way to our own destruction, even if in slow motion beyond a human scale of time. The hope that animates Patricia Yaeger’s urgent injunction to examine our “energy unconscious” (2011, 306) is that, by bringing energy into cultural awareness, we might be able to fashion forms of collective life and patterns of energy consumption that avert this calamity.</p>
                     <p>Still, there is a limit to how thoroughly we can probe our energy unconscious,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Energy Regimes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Niblett</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Energy regimes are difficult to define but easy to recognize in a CRISIS. The crucial role of dominant ENERGY sources in structuring everyday life tends to impress itself most strongly on popular consciousness at moments of potential disruption: think of the “shrill cries” of pamphleteers warning of a timber shortage in seventeenth-century Europe (Williams 2006, 166), the “coal panics” that swept through Britain in the late nineteenth century as commentators prophesized the EXHAUSTION of the resource that powered the country’s ascent to global hegemony (Podobnik 2006, 1), or the social experiments in sustainable living sparked by oil shocks in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Energy Systems</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Buell</surname>
                           <given-names>Frederick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of oil and its cultures cannot be separated from the more sweeping history of energy systems dating back to the earliest human societies. More proximately, the history of oil cultures cannot be separated from the earlier phase of fossil fuel history that began in the mid-eighteenth century, when the energies unlocked from COAL reshaped and replaced the medieval energy system of wind, water, animal, and people power. Over the next century, a qualitatively new energy system materialized, dubbed coal-capitalism by Jean-Claude Debeir, Jean-Paul Deléage, and Daniel Hémery (1991). Like all previous and later ones, this energy system came</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ethics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zylinska</surname>
                           <given-names>Joanna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Life comes to the fore most explicitly when it is under threat. We think about life (instead of just living it) when faced with the prospect of death, whether of individuals; of ethnic or national groups in wars and other forms of conflict; or of entire species, human or nonhuman. My concern here is with the prospect of the impending death of the human species. In the mainstream MEDIA, human extinction is usually presented as something inevitable. In<italic>Ten Billion</italic>, British computational scientist Stephen Emmott remarks, “we are fucked”:</p>
                     <p>Earth is home to millions of species. Just one dominates it.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Evolution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wald</surname>
                           <given-names>Priscilla</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Debates surrounding biological theories of evolution are evident in the multiple meanings of the word itself, with its etymology haunting its subsequent meanings.<italic>The Oxford English Dictionary</italic>offers its etymology in the “action of unrolling a scroll,” a “lapse of time,” and a “tactical manoeuver to effect a change of formation.”¹ Revelation and deliberation survive in its earliest incarnations. Darwin did not use<italic>evolution</italic>in the first edition of<italic>On the Origin of Species</italic>, yet as James T. Costa points out in his introduction, he gave it the last word—literally—when he concluded that edition with a poetic meditation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Exhaust</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sajecki</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The world of British science fiction writer J. G. Ballard is one of motorways and cars; highways and automobiles emblematize changing technological landscapes and emergent postmodern geographies, betokening capitalism and Americanization. At the beginning of the 1970s, when the environmental effects of automobiles came under increasing scrutiny, another aspect of the car garnered attention: exhaust. A UTOMOBILE exhaust is a secondarily produced waste resulting from energetic depletion. Think of the car as a system: gasoline in the form of fuel drives the system and is required for it to function, but this energetic imperative and the burning of fuel transforms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Exhaustion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Berardi</surname>
                           <given-names>Franco</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Modern culture valorizes ENERGY, vitality, and expansive potency. In biopolitical terms, we may say that<italic>energolatria</italic>—the worship of energy—is another name for modernity. The defining characteristic of modern bourgeois economy is the imperative of growth, which shapes aesthetics, ethics, and political strategies. Expansion is the immanent dynamic of modern capitalism. The lack of growth, by contrast, is associated with exhaustion and all of its negative connotations.</p>
                     <p>The rise of capitalism in Europe was fueled by nationalism and its romantic cult of youthfulness and aggression. Nationalism affirms the energetic potency of young populations against senescent static civilizations. In the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fallout</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Masco</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his 1964 film, Red Desert, Michelangelo Antonioni depicts a terrifying conundrum of late modernity: a world of technological marvels, whose price is local culture and the environment. The film is set in an Italian industrial town, where Monica Vitti plays the increasingly distraught wife of a petrochemical executive. The film veers from an examination of Italian industrial design—the beautiful sculptural forms enabled by PLASTICS, steel, and glass that constitute a radical break with local craft traditions grounded in organic materials—to the natural landscape destroyed by industrial production. The characters inhabit spectacular high modernist living spaces but traverse</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fiction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                           <given-names>Graeme</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like the first law of thermodynamics, literary fiction requires momentum. Fiction relies on propulsive devices: basic units of charge that power action, event, and consciousness, calibrated by laws of narrative motion and physical, material impressions of kinetic and potential energy transference. (These need not involve tales of actual motion or much, if any, movement—consider Beckett’s minimalism or the generic predicates for entropy in naturalist writing.) Fiction requires and is measured through potential—what fuels its psychosocial dynamics, the impetus of plot and character development, and its chronotopic ability to traverse multiple times and spaces. Fiction absorbs, exudes, circulates, conserves,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fracking</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Szeman</surname>
                           <given-names>Imre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As conventional sources of oil and gas become depleted, nations have turned increasingly to “unconventional” (i. e., expensive and difficult to access) forms of ENERGY. Shale gas—natural gas trapped in the rock of black shale—has quickly become one of most important of these. The process known as hydraulic fracturing, or “fracking,” combined with an increased capacity to undertake horizontal (as opposed to vertical) drilling, has transformed a handful of countries into surprise energy superpowers in the past decade. It cannot help but appear as a cruel historical irony that these same countries launched the hydrocarbon era: instead of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Future</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dufresne</surname>
                           <given-names>Todd</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>1. The future looms over the present, provoking and haunting us, not as a postdated check, even less as a blank check, but as a reality check.</p>
                     <p>2. Capitalism’s success can be measured by how effectively it has erased the myriad possibilities of the future, how well its a version of the future is accepted as natural, given, inevitable. In extremis, the capitalist narrative blots out all alternative futures. De facto, it must contend with alternative futures proposed by social and political opposition, science fiction, and utopic literature. However, the de facto experiences of toothless alternatives only work to reinforce</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Gender</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilson</surname>
                           <given-names>Sheena</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In January 2014, Tenelle Star—a 13-year-old student from Balcarres, Saskatchewan, and a member of the Star Blanket Cree Nation in Treaty Four territory—made headlines in Canada when school officials ordered her to remove her hoodie and, later, to wear it inside out (Subdhan 2014). On the front, the hoodie read, “Got Land?” and on the back, “Thank an Indian.” That same month, MEDIA controversy also surrounded hearings about the proposed Enbridge Northern Gateway Pipeline, which would carry tar sands oil from Alberta to ports in British Columbia. Tom Isaac, lawyer and Indigenous rights consultant for the Enbridge, declared</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Green</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Toby</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Green</italic>can signify displeasure, even disgust. For example, “he turned green” or “it is indefensible to have green lawns in Los Angeles.” But the term is more complex than that. It is simultaneously serene, beneficial, disturbing, corrupted, radical, and conservative: green consumption, green certification, new (green) deal, and greenwashing. When I typed<italic>green</italic>into a partially coal-fired search engine, the first entry to pop up was Greenpeace’s website.</p>
                     <p>In the late 1960s and early 1970s, the word<italic>pollution</italic>was in vogue to explain environmental hazards. It was everywhere, yet localizable. The problems it described occurred when particular waterways, neighborhoods, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.51</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Grids</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Howe</surname>
                           <given-names>Cymene</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Channeling a million megawatts of current through millions of miles of wire, the electric grid in CANADA and the United States has been called the world’s biggest machine (Achenbach 2010). It enables an abundance of electric life—not just gadgetry but economies, industry, social space, medicine, and perhaps the stabilization of modernity itself. Circulating a force indispensable to daily life in much of the world, grids are conduits for systems of social organization. But grids are frail machines, prone to breakdown and blacking out. Rummaging in the dark, we realize that we know grids best by their failure. Grids disappear</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.52</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Guilt</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Toly</surname>
                           <given-names>Noah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Old Forecast of Famine May Yet Come True” read the headline of a 2014<italic>New York Times</italic>article by Eduardo Porter about the possibility of FUTURE food shortages caused by climate destabilization. The opening question, “Might Thomas Malthus be vindicated in the end?,” invoked Malthus’s<italic>An Essay on the Principle of Population</italic>, a treatise so bleak that it earned economics the nickname “the dismal science” (Porter 2014; Malthus 1993 [1798]; see also T. Carlyle 1889; Groenwegen 2001; Marglin 2010). Malthus’s premise was simple: because population increases exponentially, DEMAND for nourishment would outpace the supply of food, which grows only arithmetically.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.53</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Takach</surname>
                           <given-names>Geo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the industrialized world, petroleum fuels the INFRASTRUCTURE of our societies and the logistics of our lives. Yet its ubiquity and power transcend gas pumps, foodstuffs, and countless other delights of contemporary existence. Sure, oil fills state and private coffers, builds Brobdingnagian beacons like Dubai, and incites the odd bloodbath. But it can also color the soul of its sites of production by defining expressions of local values and representations of that place to the world. Take my home province of Alberta, Canada—to which many ecologically concerned global citizens would hastily add, “please.” Now playing ball with behemoths like Saudi</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.54</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Image</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kashi</surname>
                           <given-names>Ed</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Niger Delta is where Nigeria’s plagues of political gangsterism, corruption, and poverty converge. What is happening in the Niger Delta is nothing short of a militarized insurgent struggle against the violent machinery of state security forces with a terrible reputation. At the same time, there is something distinctive about this violence; the militants’ struggle is a backlash against a long history of exploitation, the presence of transnational oil corporations, a style of politics dependent upon violence, and myriad groups, gangs, and cults with no leadership as such.</p>
                     <p>Under such dynamics, sustainable development for the local environment and population is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.55</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Infrastructure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Diamanti</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The safest place for rich people to dump their money during a recession is usually the one most likely to receive government stimulus—historically, public works projects aimed at shoring up both employment rates and the physical carrying capacity of an economic setting. Whether new, refurbished, or expanded, infrastructure has always functioned as a kickstarter for macroeconomic recovery, leading (so this fantasy goes) to long-term growth. The idea is somewhat paradoxical: the current configuration of a given economy (call it economy A) has either 1) reached a natural limit or 2) never really worked but works so badly now that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.56</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Innervation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ryder</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Innervation is nowadays a predominantly neurophysiological concept, generally used to refer to an anatomical detail: “the route of the nerve on its way to a given organ” (Laplanche and Pontalis 1988, 213). But in the field of psychology, the term has a more turbulent history. Often thought in a tandem with kinesthetics, innervation can be found in early psychological studies of the articular, tendinous, and muscular complexes (Baldwin 1960, 549). Since its inception, innervation has generally been regarded as a mode of energy transfer or conversion—and therefore a process of stimulation, in stark distinction to its current neurophysiological definition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.57</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Kerosene</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Simpson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “Candles” chapter in<italic>Moby-Dick</italic>, which initiates the narrative’s final drive toward CATAS TROPHE, asks us to confront and reckon the metaphysics of fuel.<italic>The Pequod</italic>is battered by a typhoon—a result, thinks Starbuck, of Ahab’s reckless and relentless chase after Moby-Dick—when Saint Elmo’s fire illuminates the lightning rods atop its masts and the “keen steel barb” of Ahab’s harpoon. Where Stubb strives to find in these “‘corpusants . . . a sign of good luck,’” portending a hold filled “‘with sperm-oil,’” Starbuck sees only DISASTER: electric evidence of divine opposition to the ship’s “‘ill voyage.’” For Ahab,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.58</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Lebenskraft</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kuzniar</surname>
                           <given-names>Alice</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In considering contemporary cultural discourse about ENERGY, we should not forget a different discursive usage in late-eighteenth-and early-nineteenth-century Germany, when the concept of<italic>Kraft</italic>(power, energy, force) was current in the life sciences, referring to organic generative and regenerative processes.<italic>Kraft</italic>and<italic>Lebenskraft</italic>—a vital life force—accrued a range of meanings whose ultimate demise coincided with the technologization and instrumentalization of so-called natural resources—COAL and oil—used in powering life. It was as if the formerly inner, organic propulsion of life became exteriorized in the shift to fossil fuels: energy was generated from outside rather than from within</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.59</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Limits</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Soluri</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Chilean Army Captain Arturo Fuentes Rabé arrived in Tierra del Fuego on official business in 1918, he rented a car “a small, old Ford”—for a “rather steep” price (Fuentes Rabé 1923). Within a decade of the first Model T rolling off an assembly line in Detroit, automobiles had reached the southernmost part of the Americas, introducing a defining element of twentieth-century petrocultures to a place that a generation earlier had been the territory of an indigenous foraging/hunting society. Automobiles appear frequently in Fuentes Rabé’s account of his travels in Tierra del Fuego, but unlike other recent studies that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.60</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Media</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gitelman</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>W. J. T. Mitchell and Mark B. N. Hansen’s<italic>Critical Terms for Media Studies</italic>(2010) includes entries for<italic>new media</italic>and<italic>mass media</italic>but not for plain old<italic>media</italic>, while, in an essay published the same year, John Guillory outlines “The Genesis of the Media Concept,” noting the several centuries across which the concept of media was “absent but<italic>wanted</italic>,” until the new communication technologies of the nineteenth century may be said to have arrived to beg the question (Guillory 2010, 321; Durham Peters 2001). Not until the twentieth century did the term<italic>media</italic>emerge fully in what Raymond Williams</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.61</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mediashock</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Grusin</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More than a decade after 9/11, the networked world remains in an acute state of “mediashock.” At the first sign of meteorological turmoil, social unrest, financial turbulence, or natural cataclysm, news media shift into 24–7 crisis mode, generating on-the-ground reports, live updates, multiple commentaries, and breaking news. CNN pioneered this mode in global cable news as far back as the 1980s, but the media’s obsession with remediating disaster and premediating shock has intensified in the twenty-first century, jump-started by the events of 9/11 but escalating since then. With the exception of regularly scheduled events like to the Olympics or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.62</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Metabolism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dickinson</surname>
                           <given-names>Adam</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In all living things, ENERGY is consumed in specific physical and chemical reactions. Respiration, reproduction, digestion, blood circulation, and waste removal are functions of these metabolic processes. One driver of metabolism is the endocrine system, which regulates the flow of hormones through the body. Hormones act as a complex exchange of messages among different states and locations. The thyroid gland secretes instructions that increase the rate at which cells utilize energy from food. Human reproduction is similarly governed by sensitivity to chemical messengers like estrogen and testosterone. But the conventional energy sources that power economies and give rise to myriad</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.63</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Middle East</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cole</surname>
                           <given-names>Juan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Solar power could be a game changer in the Israel-Palestine conflict. Big Carbon is nowhere more problematic than in Israel and Palestine. These areas have little COAL or oil, and their richest natural gas reserves are offshore in the Mediterranean Sea. That location makes gas expensive to extract at a time when the American technique of hydraulic FRACKING is driving down global prices. Ownership of the fields is contested among Israelis, Palestinians, and the Lebanese, promising more conflict.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, carbon dioxide emissions, causing disruptive climate change, have led to increasing water shortages in the region, which are implicated in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.64</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Nature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Green</surname>
                           <given-names>Louise</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emphasizing the social nature of language, Mikhail Bakhtin writes that when we speak, we do not find words in a dictionary but rather take them from other people’s mouths (1994, 77). To use a word is always to reproduce, adapt, or resist the meanings it acquires as it circulates through other people’s conversations. This is true for all words but particularly so for<italic>nature</italic>, which is like a worn, somewhat blurred coin that has passed among speakers for centuries.</p>
                     <p>At some point in the twentieth century a shift occurred in the kinds of conversations in which<italic>nature</italic>circulated. Nature no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.65</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Necessity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kaposy</surname>
                           <given-names>Timothy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>230</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By now the protagonists of the world’s ENERGY economy are widely recognizable. Over the last two centuries, the energy industry has produced iconic figures whose biographies are studied by entrepreneurs, whose opinions about the market shape economies beyond the energy sector, and whose decisions channel a violent flow of petrodollars from extraction sites to private firms. From Standard Oil’s John D. Rockefeller to ExxonMobil’s Lee Raymond and Yukos’s former CEO Mikhail Khodorkovsky, owners of the energy sector have consolidated corporate power to the detriment of an incalculable number of the earth’s inhabitants (human and otherwise).¹ The iconic One versus the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.66</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Networks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parks</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every keyboard button you push, every screen you view, every ringtone you hear requires electrical ENERGY. If you are reading on an e-reader, smartphone, or computer interface right now, consider how these words arrived before your eyes, how packets of data hopped through network nodes to become digitally rendered pages for your perusal. Data, whether text, image, or sound, moves so rapidly and transparently that we rarely consider the energizing of networks, the fueling of cultures. Building on work in environmental media studies (see Cubbit 2005; Maxwell and Miller 2012; Bozak 2012), I offer three energy-media network scenarios involving water,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.67</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Nigeria</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aghoghovwia</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To write about Nigeria in relation to ENERGY and culture is to write about the Niger Delta, the very theater of energy production. Indeed, one cannot write about energy culture in the Nigerian context without engaging the spectacle of violence it elicits, both in the public mind and in the sphere of creative imagination, precisely because the form of sociality that oil energy generates in cultural production is imagined and inscribed in idioms of violence. My concern here with this concept of violence is less with the destructiveness it inflicts (which is considerable) than with the intricacy of its operation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.68</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Nuclear 1</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Flisfeder</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Nuclear</italic>names not only a prominent form of ENERGY but also myriad ways of being in relation to energy, society, and the world.<italic>Nuclear</italic>occupied a significant place in postwar politics and culture, as a source of great energy and great destruction. But recent concerns about the development of nuclear capabilities in Iran and North Korea, as well as the 2011 DISASTER at the Daiichi nuclear power plant in Fukushima, Japan, point to the salience of nuclear technology today. In addition to its political valences, nuclear themes recur throughout postwar and contemporary popular culture. Is “nuclear” still an adequate energy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.69</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Nuclear 2</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hecht</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabrielle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Fukushima</italic>: from the coasts of Tamil Nadu to the halls of the German Bundestag, the word now stands for danger and deception, contamination and vulnerability. Every day brings new distress. Cesium-137 clings tenaciously to the soil and buildings of northeastern Japan. Radioactive fish promenade across the Pacific. Over 40 percent of children examined by the Fukushima Health Management Survey have thyroid abnormalities; no one really knows yet what that means for their health. Contractors hired for cleanup operations rely on yakuza networks for a steady stream of disposable workers and toss contaminated debris into forest glens and mountain streams when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.70</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Off-grid</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Truscello</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Should radical anticapitalists focus their efforts on sabotage and other forms of rupture designed to interrupt the flows of global capitalism, as many insurrectionary anarchists advocate? Or should they focus on sifting the debris from “the dead labours which crowd the earth’s crust in a world no longer dominated by value,” as Alberto Toscano argues (2011, 40)? Mike Davis describes the challenge for revolutionaries in a dying world dominated by capitalism: “Since most of history’s giant trees have already been cut down, a new Ark will have to be constructed out of the materials that a desperate humanity finds at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.71</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Offshore Rig</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite being linked to the same global circuits of power as the land-based oil and gas industry, the offshore rig poses its own problems of conceptualization. These difficulties are largely attributable to the longstanding figurative history of the sea as “protean” (Raban 1992, 2). In its association with the ocean, the technologically sophisticated rig becomes embroiled in centuries-old discourses.</p>
                     <p>The sea “has long functioned as Western capitalism’s primary myth element,” according to Christopher Connery (2010, 686). Indeed, contemporary discussion of offshore oil and gas invokes the ideal of mastering the ocean for economic gain. In their use of the overdetermined</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.72</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Petro-violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Watts</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is something unsettling about the world of Big Oil, not least the overwhelming intellectual vertigo it produces. Secrecy, guardedness, defensiveness, and corporate ventriloquism are hallmarks of the industry. Despite its technical expertise and scientific sophistication—drilling in deep water is like putting someone on the moon, oil mavens like to say—there is a startling degree of inexactitude, empirical disagreement, and lack of (or lack of confidence in) basic data. Why are the simplest facts of the oil world so vague, opaque, and elastic? Epistemological murkiness greets seemingly mundane, banal questions of how much oil there actually is and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.73</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Petrorealism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bellamy</surname>
                           <given-names>Brent Ryan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In ecological thought, thinking big is back in a big way. And why not? The twin problems of global warming and global pollution are intensified by an energy-reliant system of ACCUMULATION and dispossession that operates at a global scale. Thinking big seems to match the scale of solution-seeking to the size of the problem. Announcing the emergence of an interdisciplinary field they call “energy humanities,” Dominic Boyer and Imre Szeman frame this problem as an ecology-energy impasse: “It is not an exaggeration to ask whether human civilization has a future. Neither technology nor policy can offer a silverbullet solution to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.74</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Photography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Banita</surname>
                           <given-names>Georgiana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Photography and thermodynamics are linked by their simultaneous rise to cultural prominence in the 1820s and by the reliance of the photographic apparatus on SOLAR energy. In 1824, Joseph Nicéphore Niépce placed lithographic stones coated with bitumen at the back of a camera obscura and produced a fixed image of a landscape. Heliography, the name for this method, emphasizes long exposure to natural light, although the process also consumes fossil fuels. In his 1844<italic>The Pencil of Nature</italic>, William Henry Fox Talbot describes his calotype prints as “impressed by the agency of light alone,” as “sun-pictures themselves” (1968, 3). With</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.75</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Pipelines</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barney</surname>
                           <given-names>Darin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When thinking about pipelines, the temptation to revert to one’s native Heideggerianism is almost too great to resist. In a 1955 address, when Heidegger tried to concretize his view of the essence of modern technology as<italic>Gestell</italic>, or “enframing,” he turned to petrochemicals rather than his stock example of hydroelectric DAMS. Under the regime of technology as Gestell, Heidegger says, “Nature becomes a gigantic<italic>gasoline</italic>station, an energy source for modern technology and industry” (1969, 50). Energy was central to Heidegger’s conception of technology as enframing, in which the world is set upon as standing-reserve, a mode of being “which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.76</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Plastics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hawkins</surname>
                           <given-names>Gay</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is difficult to consider plastic as fuel when you confront its ubiquity as urban litter or ocean waste. It seems so passive and inert, the dead stuff of disposability denied even the biological momentum of decay. The eternal persistence of plastic seems to fuel only apocalyptic visions of ecological DISASTER: petrochemical cultures buried in their own DETRITUS.</p>
                     <p>From a different angle, however, plastic represents not the end of NATURE but rather movement or process. This understanding of plastic recognizes what Manuel DeLanda calls “the expressivity of materials,” or their morphogenetic potential (1995). For DeLanda, materials lack inherent fixed qualities,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.77</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Plastiglomerate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jazvac</surname>
                           <given-names>Kelly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corcoran</surname>
                           <given-names>Patricia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What if the material evidence from a scientific finding were also presented as art? What could be gained from such re-presentation?</p>
                     <p>For one, it puts the evidence firmly in the category of<italic>made by human</italic>as well as<italic>observed by human</italic>. When you are making something, as an artist or fabricator does, you are as close to inside it as you can possibly be. A sculptor making an armature for a sculpture figures out the inside support so the exterior can stand on its own. Conversely, studying a phenomenon, instead of making a phenomenon, implies being outside, carefully and objectively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.78</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Renewable</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hofer</surname>
                           <given-names>Werner</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two news items in 2013 should have alerted every CEO or senior manager of an energy utility company, every politician with responsibility for the economy of a country, and every leader of a large manufacturer to recent changes in how the public imagines ENERGY, specifically the place of renewable energy in the mix of fuels we burn through on a daily basis.</p>
                     <p>The first reported the result of a popular vote in Hamburg, where citizens decided, against the wish of their local government, to buy back the energy grids of their city, mostly from large European utility companies (“Initiative” 2013).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.79</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Resilience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Brien</surname>
                           <given-names>Susie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“In our current (and long overdue) efforts to drastically cut carbon emissions, we must also give equal importance to the building . . . of resilience” (Hopkins 2010). This is the premise of Rob Hopkins’s<italic>The Transition Handbook: From Oil Dependency to Local Resilience</italic>(2010), which outlines the process by which communities can work toward local autonomy, reducing their dependence on fossil fuels.¹ Environmentalists hailed the publication, with one review proclaiming: “At last, here is a book about our common future that we don’t have to be afraid to read” (L. Wallace 2010). In a 2011 speech titled “Resilience and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.80</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Resource Curse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stewart</surname>
                           <given-names>Janet</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We might expect that countries where significant oil reserves are discovered would experience unfettered socioeconomic progress. Yet in many parts of the world, oil wealth is no guarantor of prosperity. Instead, as is documented, for example, in Michael Watts and Ed Kashi’s photo-essay book<italic>Curse of the Black Gold</italic>(2008), oil wealth often seems to herald political instability and economic CRISIS. The title of Watts and Kashi’s book on oil extraction in the Niger Delta alludes to a phenomenon described by some economists as the “resource curse,” a key analytic tool in numerous studies of countries rich in natural resources.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.81</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Risk</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pinkus</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Risk</italic>, as I have written elsewhere, is a risky term.¹ We do not know exactly where or when the term originated—in early maritime law, perhaps. More significantly, we do not know quite how to use it properly.<italic>Risk</italic>in its most general sense (<italic>Webster’s</italic>: “the chance of injury, damage or loss”) contrasts significantly with its meaning in the context of investment: price volatility. In common speech,<italic>risk</italic>has a primarily negative connotation, as something to be avoided. But in the market,<italic>risk</italic>has a positive, aspirational sense so long as prices move upward, even if in fits and starts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.82</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Roads</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rymhs</surname>
                           <given-names>Deena</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>292</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On May 31, 2012, Musqueam¹ residents and supporters blocked traffic to Vancouver’s Arthur Laing Bridge to protest further development in the vicinity of an ancestral village and burial site. Earlier that year, human remains from the four-thousand-year-old village, CƏsna?Əm, had been unearthed during construction of a condo development near the bridge’s on-ramp. While construction was ordered to halt, debates ensued over title, compensation, and jurisdictional authority. For motorists traveling that morning, the protest offered a salient reminder that the bridge connecting Vancouver to its international airport runs through one of the most significant ancient sites in the Pacific Northwest. Just</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.83</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rubber</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Loman</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>296</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The petroleum industry emerged alongside the late-Victorian imperial romance, a genre of FICTION in which white men have violent adventures at the Empire’s periphery before returning, usually enriched, to its core. Because petroleum exploration was global, it would not be surprising to see cross-pollination between the romance and discourses on petroleum, in the form, for instance, of adventure novels about oil explorers.¹ Yet no such subgenre of Victorian petro-romance exists.² Still, even if the major imperial romances do not make oil an explicit subject, certain well-known works are demonstrably interested in petromodernity. Edgar Rice Burroughs’s<italic>Tarzan of the Apes</italic>and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.84</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rural</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morton</surname>
                           <given-names>Erin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>300</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The postwar modernization project rendered “the rural” as a space of technological backwardness oriented toward subsistence (Mardsen 2008; Samson 1994). Even the linguistic root of its concomitant category, “the country” (in French as<italic>contrée</italic>and in Latin as<italic>contrara</italic>), points to the idea of rurality existing in opposition to something, which, more often than not, means modern progress (Muecke 2005). Connected to this historical understanding of rural places is the more recent idea that opposes rurality with the global city, the former typically understood as a terrain of perpetual struggle and the latter as a site of what Saskia Sassen</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.85</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Russia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Penzin</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexei</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“I Love Oil” was an ambitious and provocative song released in 2013 by a well-known Russian comic team. An accompanying music video released in 2014 made the song so popular that it could be heard everywhere in Russia.¹ As it spread across the country, “I Love Oil” transformed a blunt comic parody into something sharper and more profound—an index of the place of oil in Russian social and political life today.</p>
                     <p>The video for “I Love Oil” begins with a shot of a petroleum worker, dressed in a blue uniform and wearing a yellow helmet. He presents a metallic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.86</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Servers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hogan</surname>
                           <given-names>Mél</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2011, Greenpeace released the first report on the energy choices made by Big Tech companies, calling attention to “dirty data” and the ENERGY that powers cloud computing. They found that if the Internet were a country, it would be the fifth largest consumer of energy and is projected to use an estimated 1.9 billion kilowatt hours of ELECTRICITY by 2020, an amount that exceeds the current consumption of Canada, France, Germany, and Brazil combined (Ladurantaye 2011). In 2012, Greenpeace reported once again that Big Tech was rapidly expanding without adequate regard to source of electricity and relied “heavily on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.87</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shame</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jacquet</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the late nineteenth century, John D. Rockefeller established Standard Oil, the first multi national CORPORATION to get rich off fossil fuels—so rich that his grandsons started a large charitable trust with some of the money. In the early twenty-first century that same charity—the Rockefeller Brothers Fund—announced that it would divest in the very origins of its endowment: fossil fuels.</p>
                     <p>What happened in the intervening century? Fossil fuels powered the Industrial Revolution and globalization, among other things, but most of society (with some important exceptions) also realized their use was leading to dangerous global climate change. Yet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.88</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Solar</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boetzkes</surname>
                           <given-names>Amanda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>314</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of solar power invites us to consider the difference between a form of ENERGY that shapes cultural exchange and a resource that merely fuels production. In the past century, solar power has been touted as a clean alternative to oil and COAL. It has also inspired visions of new social, ecological, and economic systems it might generate. Solar energy is imagined as fundamentally heterogeneous, characterized by how it precipitates complex transactions and conversions that nonetheless preserve homeostatic LIMITS. Indeed, this aspect of solar energy is often touted by critics of the industrial capitalist model that seeks to accumulate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.89</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Spill</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Juhasz</surname>
                           <given-names>Antonia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>318</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On November 8, 2013, I received an e-mail inviting me to contribute to this book, with a list of potential topics.<italic>Spill</italic>was the obvious choice, given the years I have spent trekking across the United States and much of the world following a trail of dirty, smelly, deadly crude oil unleashed through the mass negligence, greed, and hubris of men (the vast majority of the industry is male).</p>
                     <p>That same day, I received another e-mail, this one with a photograph of a massive black cloud billowing above red flames shooting out of nearly one hundred blackened train cars lying</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.90</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Spills</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LeMenager</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a noun,<italic>spill</italic>denotes a downpour of liquid, with early usages tending toward blood and rain, while the term<italic>oil spill</italic>dates from the era of industrial modernity, after the gushers of the 1890s and the manufacture of the Ford Model T. The Lumière Brothers’ short film<italic>Oil Wells of Baku: Close View</italic>(1896) documents an Azerbaijani oil field fire that could be euphemistically described as a spill. Gushers have been described as spills insofar as they involve uncontained spillage of oil that blankets miles of surrounding land, destroying plants, crops, and soils. The Cerro Azul No. 4 gusher</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.91</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Spiritual</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sideris</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2013, when the Williams and Boardwalk Pipeline Partners announced plans to snake a pipeline of natural gas liquids through a large swath of Kentucky, they set themselves against two bulwarks of Southern culture: religion and bourbon.</p>
                     <p>The Bluegrass Pipeline would connect FRACKING operations in the northeast United States with chemical processing plants in the Gulf of Mexico. Natural gas liquids (NGLs) are hydrocarbons like ethane, propane, and butane that are removed from natural gas and used for a variety of purposes, often as petrochemical feedstock. NGLs may end up as plastic bags or antifreeze, tire RUBBER or lighter fluid.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.92</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Statistics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Morrison</surname>
                           <given-names>Spencer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Edward Burtynsky’s photograph<italic>Shipbreaking #20</italic>, an IMAGE in his collection<italic>Oil</italic>, depicts a ship demolition yard in Chittagong, Bangladesh, strewn with oil barrels and scrap metal from abandoned ships (see Figure 12). Atop one barrel crouches the photo’s sole human figure, a young Bangladeshi ship-breaker splotched with oil; before him lies oil-soaked terrain that descends into a stagnant black pond from which pipes, ladders, and wires haphazardly jut. It might seem counterintuitive to use Burtynsky’s photo to discuss statistical reasoning’s role in shaping discursive relationships between human subjects and ENERGY REGIMES, since no numbers appear in the photo. Yet by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.93</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Superhero Comics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beaty</surname>
                           <given-names>Bart</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fans of superhero comic books divide the history of the genre into at least three periods: the Golden Age, from the first appearance of Superman in<italic>Action Comics</italic>#1 (June 1938) to the Comics Code in autumn 1954; the Silver Age, from the reintroduction of the Flash in<italic>Showcase</italic>#4 (October 1956) to the revision of the Comics Code in 1972; and the Bronze Age, from the mid-1970s to the 1990s. In terms of energy and its relation to this periodization, the most important concern is the distinction between the Golden and Silver Ages. Superheroes created during the Golden Age</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.94</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Surveillance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Badia</surname>
                           <given-names>Lynn</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>338</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Figure 15, produced by the International Energy Agency, maps the flow of the world’s total production and consumption of ENERGY (in various states and materials) between myriad origins and destinations. Although the diagram represents sources ranging from water to COAL, they are all converted into a single unit of measurement—the Mtoe, or millions of tons of oil equivalent. This visualization of global energy flows is just one example of how energy topologies (or energyscapes) are mapped and analyzed (Strauss, Rupp, and Love 2012; Appadurai 1990). Energy is analyzed in terms of type, source, capacity, conversion, distribution, etc., across various</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.95</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sustainability</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Medovoi</surname>
                           <given-names>Leerom</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>342</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent decades, the vision of a genuinely ecological economics has focused on the principle of sustainability. Capitalism, we are told, should be refashioned as a “sustainable economy” whose growth, in the words of the United Nation’s Brundtland Commission Report, “meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of FUTURE generations to meet their own needs” (Brundtland 1987). Like other liberal political ideals (e.g., democracy, freedom, tolerance), the ideological work performed by sustainability is complex and multivalent. As Joan Martinez-Alier (2009) notes, ecological economics understands the economy not as a system of exchange but rather as a metabolic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.96</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tallow</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shannon</surname>
                           <given-names>Laurie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>346</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hamlet, performing his self-styled madman’s script, forces his auditors to remember a disturbing truth that is normally repressed: “A man may fish with the worm that hath eat of a king, and eat of the fish that hath fed of that worm” (<italic>Hamlet</italic>, 4.3.27–28).¹ This logic of circulation recalls the Pythagorean doctrine of the transmigration of souls, a view often mocked in early modernity as equivalent to insanity. But Hamlet’s line traces no flight by the soul from one body to another. Instead, it joins a traditional Christian perspective on worldly vanities (a fortune’s wheel argument) to an insistence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.97</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Texas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Worden</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Texas looms large in contemporary oil culture. The state’s first major oil well, Spindletop, came in in 1901 and led to the formation of Gulf Oil and Texaco. Since then, Texas has figured in oil culture as a site of extraction and refining, a center for the multinational corporate oil industry, and an anchor for the oil industry’s ideological construction as an innately heroic, individualistic, and deeply American enterprise. This prominence is somewhat odd, considering that Pennsylvania was the site of the modern oil industry’s origin in the United States. Alaska, California, Louisiana, and Oklahoma, not to mention the Dakotas,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.98</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Textiles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robertson</surname>
                           <given-names>Kirsty</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every day we dress in oil. At each stage in the process of making, purchasing, and discarding clothing and other textiles, oil is present as a secret companion. Petrochemicals douse the cotton fields; oil powers the complex farm machinery that has replaced hand labor in the fields; it powers the vast looms that weave cotton into fabric. Oil polymers subtend the many synthetic and natural-synthetic hybrid fabrics that make possible a waterproof, stainresistant, hard-wearing, easily replaced material existence. Underlying the vast transport systems that carry textiles and apparel across the globe is oil. At the end of their lives, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.99</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Unobtainium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bartolovich</surname>
                           <given-names>Crystal</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the Wiki for James Cameron’s 2009 blockbuster<italic>Avatar</italic>, unobtanium “is a highly valuable mineral found on the moon Pandora” that “humans mine . . . to save the Earth from its energy crisis” (“Unobtainium” 2016). Against this narrowly humaninterested “one thing needful” approach to saving a planet, the film insists—reassuringly—that “Nature” can do the saving: Eywa—the local Nature goddess—sends forth battalions of conveniently powerful creatures to drive the imperialistic humans out. More interesting than either of these dubious salvation narratives is a moment in the film that implicitly calls both into question. Disgusted with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.100</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Urban Ecology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stoekl</surname>
                           <given-names>Allan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What does urban ecology have to do with ENERGY, specifically with the fuels that power our lives?</p>
                     <p>Urban ecology proposes the study of<italic>all</italic>life in cities, considered not as supremely autonomous human artifacts but rather as ecologies: sites of the interdependence of living things, flora and fauna of all types (Douglas et al. 2011). Urban life is the aggregate lives of all beings and their modes of survival and flourishing. Human life is certainly a function of urban ecology, but so is rodent life, bird life, earthworm life, canine life, and bedbug life.</p>
                     <p>As David Owen points out in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.101</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Utopia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lehmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Philipp</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>365</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whether as optimally employed labor or an infinite supply of power, ENERGY is often central to utopian designs for FUTURE societies. Conversely, utopian impulses have been particularly strong during times of actual or predicted energy transitions, inspiring designs for reorganizing socioeconomic, political, and environmental conditions with the help of new sources and unprecedented quantities of energy.</p>
                     <p>The advent of NUCLEAR power after the Second World War presents the classic example in this story of utopian ideas about energy. Just a few years after atomic energy’s destructive force was demonstrated in Hiroshima and Nagasaki, nuclear power inspired numerous utopian visions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.102</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Venezuela</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kingsbury</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The absolute centrality of oil in Venezuela has produced profound anxieties about vulnerability, dependency, and modernity. Here the “RESOURCE CURSE ”—in which abundance of a highly valued commodity like oil is said to doom a country to inequality and maldevelopment—is not merely an academic concept but the topic of street corner debate. The symbolic and material substance of daily life, oil forms the “transcendent and unifying agent of the nation,” in Fernando Coronil’s account: “Venezuela was seen as having two bodies, a political body made up of its citizens and a natural body made up of its rich</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.103</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Whaling</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burnett</surname>
                           <given-names>D. Graham</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Animal fats have served human beings as sources of ENERGY ever since humans merited the name. Crammed in the gullet, a little marbling or caul afforded early hominids the same kilocalories that such comestibles afforded any other creature equipped to function as a carnivore. And we can assume that whenever those restless hominids mastered the runaway oxidation reaction known as fire, they likely noticed that the white bits of their roasted meat flamed up impressively. Control over these little grease fires presumably followed, in the form of TALLOW lamps and candles.</p>
                     <p>There is no ANIMAL on Earth, and never has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.104</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Wood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nardizzi</surname>
                           <given-names>Vin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>376</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“There’s wood enough within”: projected from offstage, this response to Prospero’s summoning in<italic>The Tempest</italic>launches Caliban into literary history (Shakespeare 1999, 1.2.315). Its emphasis on adequacy indicates that the slave has completed his work. Stemming from this sense of closure, its disgruntled tone suggests an insubordination later elaborated in Caliban’s plan to murder Prospero and burn his books. Such acts of defiance have made Caliban, as Jonathan Goldberg says, “a byword for anticolonial riposte” (2004, ix). But what of the wood? This question may seem slight when weighed against empire and resistance to it, but Caliban uncovers the indispensability</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.105</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Work 1</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Turcot</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can one make sense of a place as vast and inaccessible as Canada’s tar sands?</p>
                     <p>I enter an oil company HQ. It has taken a year to find a way through the fortress wall to access a shift worker live-in camp. Having learned portraiture as a way to spend time with shift workers, I’m aware that a portrait artist gains access to workers in a way that a researcher or journalist might not.</p>
                     <p>Most of the twenty-four people I drew needed to talk, to articulate their pasts, presents, or futures, sometimes with great intensity. Observing is about recognizing subtlety,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.106</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Work 2</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shukaitis</surname>
                           <given-names>Stevphen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“One of the problems,” my friend and comrade Ben said, “is that while we’ve been quite good at celebrating the refusal of work, we never had anything like zerowork training.” This statement struck me as strange, and not merely because of the context—a meeting of the editorial collective for Autonomedia, a long-running Brooklyn-based autonomist publisher. After a decade of involvement with the project, Ben was moving on. In the autonomist equivalent of an exit meeting, Ben declared his exit from a collective whose stated goal was to exit from work itself, to “substruct the planetary work machine,” in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.107</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Oil/Lie”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="illustrator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Image by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reyes</surname>
                           <given-names>Pedro</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.108</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Szeman</surname>
                           <given-names>Imre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The contributions to<italic>Fueling Culture</italic>offer ample evidence of the multiple and varied ways in which energy has figured and transfigured human life. By highlighting the key role of fossil fuels in shaping the experience and reality of the modern, these essays provide an important and much-needed corrective to our understanding of the forces that shape societies, organize geopolitics, and, perhaps most surprisingly, animate cultural and intellectual life. Unprecedented access to massive and ever-increasing amounts of cheap energy from fossil fuels—first coal, later oil and gas—is rarely identified as a constitutive element in the narrative of modernity, which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.109</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.110</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hfr0s3.111</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>435</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
