<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt35b7wp</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Modernism and Magic</book-title>
         <subtitle>Experiments with Spiritualism, Theosophy and the Occult</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wilson</surname>
               <given-names>Leigh</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748627691</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748631650</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748631658</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Leigh Wilson</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt3fgs1g"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While modernism’s engagement with the occult has been approached by critics as the result of a loss of faith in representation, an attempt to draw on science as the primary discourse of modernity, or as a hidden history of ideas, Leigh Wilson argues that these discourses have at their heart a magical practice which remakes the relationship between world and representation. As Wilson demonstrates, the courses of the occult are based on a magical mimesis which transforms the nature of the copy, from inert to vital, from dead to alive, from static to animated, from powerless to powerful. Wilson explores the aesthetic and political implications of this relationship in the work of those writers, artists and filmmakers who were most self-consciously experimental, including James Joyce, Ezra Pound, Dziga Vertov and Sergei M. Eisenstein.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SERIES EDITORS’ PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book argues that the aesthetic experiments of the first half of the twentieth century that we call modernism drew on the discourses of the occult dominant during the period – in particular on spiritualism and theosophy – because in them it saw the possibilities for a reconceptualisation of the mimetic. While these discourses have been much investigated in critical works of the last few decades, what neither recent scholars nor many practitioners, or indeed critics, at the time have admitted is the extent to which they have magic at their heart. Yet these occult discourses provided possibilities for experiment for writers,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>‘BUT THE FACTS OF LIFE PERSIST’:</title>
                     <subtitle>MAGIC, EXPERIMENT AND THE PROBLEM OF REPRESENTING THE WORLD OTHERWISE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The engagement of experimental artistic practices with the contemporary occult in the first half of the twentieth century was not so much the result of personal credulity, or of a search for new forms per se, or a straightforward mimesis of the failure of language, but was instead an attempt to represent the world other than the way it was through a magical mimesis. As I have suggested in the Introduction, this is already to move away from some current accounts of what modernism does with the world. In other accounts, the varieties of modernist experiment are often formed into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>‘AND WHAT HAS ALL THIS TO DO WITH EXPERIMENTAL WRITING?’:</title>
                     <subtitle>WORDS AND GHOSTS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If magic is error for modernity, then the most scandalous of its errors is its collapsing into identity of words and objects. As Randall Styers argues, one of the central themes running through scholarly work on magic from the second half of the nineteenth century is the claim that magic is fixated on the power of words (Styers 2004: 219ff.). Certainly magic is often defined as that which attempts to animate matter, but again and again writers on magic assert a particular attitude to language as central to this animation. For James Frazer, if magic originates in the human fear</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A ‘SUBTLE METAMORPHOSIS’:</title>
                     <subtitle>SOUND, MIMESIS AND TRANSFORMATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the experiment of<italic>Finnegans Wake</italic>is the harnessing of a magical understanding of transformation through a renewed relation between word and world, one of the central mechanisms for this transformation is sound. The importance of sound in<italic>Finnegans Wake</italic>is well known, and has been insisted on from Beckett’s famous assertion in ‘Dante . . . Bruno. Vico . . . Joyce’ (1929) that Joyce’s novel is not to be read, or rather is not only to be read; it ‘is to be looked at and listened to’ (Beckett 1983: 27). Another early admirer, Sergei Eisenstein, went further, suggesting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>‘HERE IS WHERE THE MAGIC IS’:</title>
                     <subtitle>TELEPATHY AND EXPERIMENT IN FILM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The cultural history of film has often been rooted in the shifting conceptions of and metaphorical uses of light. Film produces life, movement and action from light, making it seem organic (as light produces life and growth in the natural world), but also uncanny (the creation of life and movement from nothing). That the world is reproduced through the effects of light in photography and film has led numerous critics recently to reassert the uncanny and occult status of the media (Gunning 1995). Indeed light has many occult resonances, from Emanuel Swedenborg, through theories of vitalism, to the metaphorical uses</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>‘DISNEY AGAINST THE METAPHYSICALS’:</title>
                     <subtitle>EISENSTEIN, POUND, ECTOPLASM AND THE POLITICS OF ANIMATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen in Chapter 4, the work of both Dziga Vertov and Sergei Eisenstein shows a tension between realism as faithfulness to the truth of the world on one hand and realism as reproducing the myths of bourgeois capitalism on the other. For Vertov, facts were central in overcoming this problematic of representation, as expressed in his rejection of actors, filmscripts, created scenarios, and so on. For Eisenstein, however, the relation between the facts of world and their reproduction on the screen was in some ways more complex. He criticised Vertov and kino-eye in general for misunderstanding this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fgs1g.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
