<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DS35.65.A96 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Islamic Empire</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Islam</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Historiography</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization, Islamic</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Times of History</book-title>
         <subtitle>Universal Topics in Islamic Historiography</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Al-Azmeh</surname>
               <given-names>Aziz</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789637326738</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9786155211409</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Central European University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Budapest; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Aziz Al-Azmeh</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7829/j.ctt1cgf93z"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This is a collection of essays on current questions of historiography, illustrated with reference to Islamic historiography. The main concerns are conceptions of time and temporality, the uses of the past, historical periodisation, historical categorisation, and the constitution of historical objects, not least those called "civilisation" and "Islam". One of the aims of the book is to apply to Islamic materials the standard conceptual equipment used in historical study, and to exercise a large-scale comparativist outlook.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="328"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hayden White: Beyond Orientalism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am pleased to be asked to present Professor Aziz Al-Azmeh’s collection of essays on the historiography of the Near East, Muslim religiosity, and the problems raised by the effort to specify the nature of “Islam.” I found them illuminating, full of learning, and intimately relevant to the understanding of current conflicts throughout the Arab world. I hasten to add that I am anything but an expert in these matters, but I recognize expertise when I see it. Al-Azmeh is a subtle guide for anyone wishing to pierce through the fog of prejudice, false learning, and ideology about both the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Al-Azmeh</surname>
                           <given-names>Aziz</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Tropes and Temporalities of Historiographic Romanticism, Modern and Islamic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Below are two texts which will put forth the substance of what is to follow far more eloquently and completely than I could ever hope to do:</p>
                     <p>It is not that there is any difference in God’s knowledge according as it is produced by things not yet in existence, by things now or by things that are no more. Unlike us, He does not look ahead to the future, see the present before him, and look back to the past … Hence all events in time, events that will be and are not yet and those that are now, being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Islam and the History of Civilizations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is appropriate to start by warning against the fascination of Islam in historical studies, and to suggest that interpretations of classical and contemporary Muslim political phenomena be undertaken in terms of their times and places rather than in terms of abiding cultural patterns.</p>
                     <p>Fascination with the exotic, including the Muslim exotic, the distantly attractive or repellent, the self-enclosed and self-explanatory, ensnares the imagination and inhibits reason and the faculty of judgment; for fascination, sympathetic or hostile, is none other than beholding an object as if it were a marvel, and the spectacle of marvels suspends the normal operations of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Chronophagous Discourse:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Study of the Clerico-Legal Appropriation of the World in an Islamic Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Amongst all religious traditions, Islamic civilization has produced what is perhaps the most deliberately sustained concern with, and profuse body of writing on, history. The concern with the past is manifest in all genres of Arabic<italic>Schrifttum</italic>: poetry was classicized with the establishment of anterior texts and modes; pietistic and legal works established a knowledge of early Muslim practice as<italic>Fürstenspiegel</italic>and valorized salutary and deleterious acts of kings and sages from many histories; Koranic exegesis required monumental knowledge of Muslim precedents and linguistic usages of yore; dynasties, times, and biographies were meticulously chronicled and recorded; universal histories were composed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>The Muslim Canon from Late Antiquity to the Era of Modernism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By referring to the Muslim Canon in Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages, it is my intention to underline the specific character of the perspective I wish to cast in this essay upon the Koran and the canonical texts that complement it. It is primarily an historical perspective, insensitive to the mythological accounts one normally encounters with respect to the histories of significant events and times—historical events, often construed as born virtually complete and pristine.</p>
                     <p>The historical accounts subsequent to these events—for example, the “Greek Miracle” on the Event of the Koran—are perceived as being either developments</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>God’s Chronography and Dissipative Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Apocalypses are of interest not only to antiquarians or religious ideologues. They subtend and rest upon a rich and ubiquitous conception of time which is, as we shall see, of salience to fields far broader than eschatology or of salvation history, and this judgement I believe applies to all apocalypses including those of Islam, all of which treat temporality in a manner that is conceptually isomorphous. This is a conception of time that brings out with particular sharpness of relief and of definition, almost as an ideal-type, notions of history that are of an ubiquity far greater than is generally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Rhetoric for the Senses:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Consideration of Muslim Paradise Narratives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That sensual pleasure in this world is praised and, indeed, enjoined in Muslim tradition when it occurs within the bounds of legitimate union, requires no demonstration. Equally evident is the discouragement of serious forms of long-term asceticism and of carnal self-denial, over and above what some Sufis might adopt during periods of initiation and devotional isolation (<italic>khalwa</italic>). The repudiation of pleasure characteristic of Christian traditions in general¹ is almost entirely absent, and monastic life with its various forms of physical self-immolation was frequently the object of derision by Muslim authors, who often regarded it as something contrary to what God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Islamic Political Thought:</title>
                     <subtitle>Current Historiography and the Frame of History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The historical interplay between religion and political functions and conceptions, and with history more generally, has been very much in vogue in recent years, with assertions that the world is being re-enchanted, or that it had never been as disenchanted as had previously been thought in the first place. Yet this new mood sweeping historical scholarship is still conceptually and historically somewhat uncertain in its bearings and conceptual moorings, despite notable exceptions.</p>
                     <p>It is thus perhaps little surprising that conceptions of power and political thought elaborated in the course of Muslim histories, in modern times no less than in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Monotheistic Monarchy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I should like to state at the very beginning my conviction that sacral kingship, in its variety of forms and representations one of which is monotheistic kingship, might in anthropological terms be regarded an Elementary Form of socio-political life: not an autonomous elementary form, but one falling under the category of rulership, of sovereignty in the sense given to the term by Georges Dumézil, without this necessarily entailing the adoption of his trifunctional model which Le Goff saw to be eminently fitting for medieval Europe. Like all other Elementary Forms for the representation of human sociality, this is one of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf93z.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Proper Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
