<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Evil in Contemporary Political Theory</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Haddock</surname>
               <given-names>Bruce</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Roberts</surname>
               <given-names>Peri</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sutch</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748641963</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748654123</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Bruce Haddock</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Peri Roberts</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Peter Sutch</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1r1x42"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Explores the actual and possible roles of evil in contemporary political theory</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON THE CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haddock</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roberts</surname>
                           <given-names>Peri</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sutch</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The concept of ‘evil’ has a long history in the western tradition, extending from early theological debate, through tortured discussion of the relationship between moral and religious issues, to a contemporary context in which moral and political theory have domains of discourse in their own right. The religious roots of the idea of ‘evil’, however, have often made it difficult to accommodate in predominantly secular cultures, especially in multicultural contexts where deeply held beliefs may not be widely shared. Indeed, there has been a tendency in recent decades, especially among political theorists, to set the notion aside as outdated or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>DARKNESS AND SILENCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>EVIL AND THE WESTERN LEGACY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Milbank</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Traditionally, in Greek, Christian and Jewish thought, evil has been denied any positive foothold in being. It has not been seen as a real force, or quality, but as the absence of force and quality, and as the privation of being itself. It has not been regarded as glamorous, but as sterile; never as more, always as less. For many recent philosophers, however (for example, Jacob Rogozinski, Slavoj Zizek, J.-L. Nancy) this view appears inadequate in the face of what they consider to be the unprecedented evil of the twentieth century: the mass organisation of totalitarian control and terror, systematic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>CONSTRUCTIVISM AND EVIL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roberts</surname>
                           <given-names>Peri</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Constructivism in political theory is opposed to both scepticism and foundationalism. Against the sceptic the constructivist hopes to defend the objectivity of at least some political principles. Against the foundationalist the constructivist hopes to show that the defence of objectivity need not appeal to any account of the necessary and unchanging foundations for moral reasoning. Evil has traditionally been seen in foundationalist terms, as a theological concept depending on the existence of God or as depending on some alternative scheme of absolute moral judgement, in order to mark out a special sort of wrongness. When these foundations have been challenged</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>SYSTEMIC EVIL AND THE LIMITS OF PLURALISM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haddock</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Contemporary political theory has never been comfortable with the idea of evil. Indeed, the gradual, sporadic, but nevertheless incomplete secularisation of political discourse since the Renaissance has made the conceptualisation of absolute value deeply problematic. One response, dominant in the liberal tradition, is simply to deny that politics is the realm of absolute value at all. The pragmatic adjustment of competing interests in a scheme of social co-operation invites, at the very least, a moderation of tone. And increasing empirical awareness of the diversity of different schemes of (merely political) co-operation has made us (rightly) guarded in the language we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>UNREASONABLE OR EVIL?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Budde</surname>
                           <given-names>Kerstin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In her book <italic>Evil in Modern Thought</italic>, Susan Neiman argues that the root of the <italic>problem</italic> of evil can be found in the fact that the world is not as it ought to be.¹ Around us, we see needless suffering, callous and thoughtless cruelties, monstrous atrocities, unjust punishments and so much more which makes us cry out: This ought not to have happened! Once we utter this cry, Neiman thinks that we are ‘stepping onto a path that leads straight to the problem of evil’.² That is, once we admit that reality is not as it ought to be, that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>EVIL IN CONTEMPORARY INTERNATIONAL POLITICAL THEORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>ACTS THAT SHOCK THE CONSCIENCE OF MANKIND</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sutch</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>If there is one branch of contemporary political theory that has many concrete examples of ‘evil’ as its subject matter, it is international political theory. Indeed, the word has made a spectacular return to international political discourse since 9/11. In this chapter I suggest a novel approach to theorising ‘evil’ in international political theory. It is an approach that diverges from much of the established (and very useful) commentary that has explored the concept as it emerges in the rhetoric of political leaders on both sides of the war on terror. I think that dealing with evil in that context</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>DOING EVIL JUSTLY?</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MORALITY OF JUSTIFIABLE ABOMINATION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Evans</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>When faced with a choice between courses of action both or all of which have significant attendant costs or drawbacks – a scenario to which politics is, by its nature, especially prone – we are wont to call the choice on which we settle ‘the lesser of two evils’ (or the ‘least evil’ if the options were more numerous). We employ this phrase when we believe our choice has incurred the least cost compared with the alternatives and, to that extent, it is proffered in justification of the choice made. But it is also an acknowledgement that there is a cost which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>EVIL AND THE LEFT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garrard</surname>
                           <given-names>Eve</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Some people on the political Left are very reluctant to deploy the concept of evil, and distrust the use to which others put it. This reluctance and distrust are, I shall argue, unnecessary. What I hope to do here is to outline a case for evil and the Left – that is, a case for saying that the Left can legitimately appeal to the concept of evil, and that it can be of some use to them.</p>
                     <p>I don’t intend to offer a complete theory of evil here: it’s a highly disputed area, and the case for saying that the Left</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>THE GLAMOUR OF EVIL:</title>
                     <subtitle>DOSTOYEVSKY AND THE POLITICS OF TRANSGRESSION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Horton</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Probably the most famous contribution to the discussion of the nature of evil in the modern world over the last half-century, at least in the field of political theory, is that of Hannah Arendt. Her thesis regarding ‘the banality of evil’ set out in the course of her reflections on the Eichmann trial in <italic>Eichmann in Jerusalem</italic>, first published in 1963,¹ is widely celebrated and much invoked, if not always unambiguously favourably. Exactly what she meant by this captivating but misleadingly simple phrase is less easily understood than is sometimes thought and has been the cause of heated debate.² One</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>THE RHETORIC OF MORAL EQUIVALENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shorten</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Evil in contemporary politics has an important rhetorical dimension. Whenever instances of wrongdoing are contested in the public realm, the relevant actors are liable to call upon a familiar store of resources for persuading audiences to respond in particular ways. These resources can be expected to consist in recognisable rhetorical tropes and figures, a predictable range of ‘commonplaces’, and the manipulation of definitions according to recurring patterns of argument. They can be envisaged to entail, too, the arousal of a characteristic series of emotions. The actors themselves, in the relevant sense, might also be variously composed. They may be perpetrators</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 11</label>
                     <title>BANAL BUT NOT BENIGN:</title>
                     <subtitle>ARENDT ON EVIL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boucher</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Hannah Arendt is one of the most revered and reviled philosophers of the twentieth century. Almost sixty years after the publication of <italic>Eichmann in Jerusalem</italic>, her conclusions still have the power to provoke extreme reactions. For example, David Cesarani accuses Arendt of being deeply contemptuous of the Jews of Poland and Russia because of her bourgeois German Jewish background. Barry Gewen, reviewing the book in the <italic>New York Times</italic>, dismisses Cesarani as ‘a writer in control of neither his material nor himself’. Arendt could certainly be dismissive, contemptuous and excessively judgemental of those outside her circle, and yet her flashes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r1x42.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
