<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Redemptive Hope: From the Age of Enlightenment to the Age of Obama</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LERNER</surname>
               <given-names>AKIBA J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Campbell</surname>
               <given-names>Timothy C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>series editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823267910</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823267958</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1657v0t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This is a book about the need for redemptive narratives to ward off despair and the dangers these same narratives create by raising expectations that are seldom fulfilled. The quasi-messianic expectations produced by the election of President Barack Obama in 2008, and their diminution, were stark reminders of an ongoing struggle between ideals and political realities. Redemptive Hope begins by tracing the tension between theistic thinkers, for whom hope is transcendental, and intellectuals, who have striven to link hopes for redemption to our intersubjective interactions with other human beings. Lerner argues that a vibrant democracy must draw on the best of both religious thought and secular liberal political philosophy. By bringing Richard Rorty's pragmatism into conversation with early-twentieth-century Jewish thinkers, including Martin Buber and Ernst Bloch, Lerner begins the work of building bridges, while insisting on holding crucial differences in dialectical tension. Only such a dialogue, he argues, can prepare the foundations for modes of redemptive thought fit for the twenty-first century.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a book about our need for redemptive narratives to ward off despair and the dangers these same narratives create by raising expectations that are seldom fulfilled. The story of the rise of secular redemptive hope narratives from the age of Enlightenment to the early part of the twenty-first century has been a story of the struggle between heightened expectations and postutopian despair.¹ The quasi-messianic expectations produced by the election of President Obama in 2008—followed by the diminution of these expectations—was a stark reminder that redemptive hope is seldom satisfactorily fulfilled. Although what led to the dashing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>REDEMPTIVE HOPE AND THE CUNNING OF HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The notion that the entire world is capable of total transformation begins with the various redemptive narratives introduced by the biblical tradition. Although the explicit expression of these transcendental hopes changed in each period, the common denominator during this first stage is the assumption that transformation is possible. This first stage includes the Hebrew prophets, Christian intellectuals like Saint Augustine and Thomas Aquinas, and the Enlightenment thinker Immanuel Kant. These theocentric groundings of hope all share the claim that individual hopes for happiness are ultimately linked to a transcendental source, for example, God. For all traditional theologians interested in reconciling</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>REVIVAL OF MESSIANIC HOPE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The shock of World War I contributed to a crisis of reason and loss of confidence in the humanist foundations for modern secular utopianism.¹ For some, the ideal of material progress became synonymous with the creation of more efficient weapons of mass destruction. And for many artists, romantic yearnings to express the imagination were channeled toward a growing aestheticization of violence.² One of the consequences of this crisis in European culture was the renewal of interest among Jewish and Christian intellectuals in the history of apocalyptic and messianic hopes.³ According to Gershom Scholem, an interest in the messianic has always</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>THE GOD OF EXODUS AND THE SCHOOL OF HOPE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the history of modern Jewish redemptive narratives, Bloch played a central role in translating what he interpreted as the subversive metahistory within religion into the praxis of horizontal solidarity and revolutionary agitation. Ernst Bloch’s great innovation was to infuse secular Marxist materialism with quasi-Kabbalistic mysticism and a metaphysics of contingency. This chapter is an exposition of those features within Bloch’s writings that contributed to the post–World War II creation of a “school of hope” among theologians and critical theorists. Later theologians—both Jewish and Christian—were drawn to Bloch’s analysis because he also insisted that Marxism had missed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>RICHARD RORTY’S SOCIAL HOPE AND POSTMETAPHYSICAL REDEMPTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the turn of the twenty-first century, Richard Rorty put forward his vision for a new form of social hope, “the hope that life will eventually be freer, less cruel, more leisured, richer in goods and experiences, not just for our descendants but for everybody’s descendants.”¹ The first step toward this neopragmatic future requires a change in priorities in which “everybody thinks that it is human solidarity, rather than knowledge of something not merely human, that really matters.”² This utopian task of “replacing certainty with hope” requires establishing a different kind of solidarity based on increasing individual happiness rather than</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>BETWEEN PRAGMATIC AND MESSIANIC HOPES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theodore Gericault’s Romantic era painting<italic>Le Radeau de la Méduse</italic>(1816) shows a group of castaways desperately clinging to a raft in the midst of chaotic seas. The contrast between some castaways in a state of deep despair and other castaways frantically trying to hail what might be a passing ship in the far distance is a fitting image for the combination of despair and hope within Rorty’s appeal to “human beings clinging together against the dark.”¹</p>
                     <p>For those who yearn for traditional metaphysical foundations, Rorty’s claim that there is “no foundation except shared hope and the trust created by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1657v0t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
