<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn32r9</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Post-beur Cinema</book-title>
         <subtitle>North African Émigré and Maghrebi-French Filmmaking in France since 2000</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Higbee</surname>
               <given-names>Will</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748640041</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0748640045</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748678150</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0748678158</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Will Higbee</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt5hh2vh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Since the early 1980s and the arrival of Beur cinema filmmakers of Maghrebi origin have made a key contribution French cinema's representation of issues such as immigration, integration and national identity. However, they have done so mostly from a position on the margins of the industry. In contrast, since the early 2000s, Maghrebi-French and North African émigré filmmakers have occupied an increasingly prominent position on both sides of the camera, announcing their presence on French screens in a wider range of genres and styles than ever before. This greater visibility and move to the mainstream has not, however, automatically meant that these films have lost any of the social or political relevance. Indeed in the 2000s many of these films have increasingly questioned the boundaries between national, transnational and diasporic cinema, whilst simultaneously demanding, either implicitly or explicitly, a reconsideration of the very difference that has traditionally been seen as a barrier to the successful integration of North African immigrants and their descendants into French society. Through a detailed study of this transformative decade for Maghrebi-French and North African émigré filmmaking in France, this book argues for the emergence of a 'Post-Beur' cinema in the 2000s that is simultaneously global and local in its outlook. Its key features include: A comprehensive overview of the key developments in Maghrebi-French and North African émigré filmmaking in France since the 2000s: counter-heritage cinema and the memorialisation of France’s colonial past; journey narratives and the myth of return; the ‘mainstreaming’ of Maghrebi-French directors and stars; representations of Islam. Detailed case studies of key films from the 2000s that have yet to receive scholarly attention, such as Hors-la-loi, Dernier maquis and Vénus noire. An in-depth analysis of trends in production, distribution and exhibition as they relate to Maghrebi-French and North African émigré filmmakers in the 2000s.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="288"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>FROM IMMIGRANT CINEMA TO NATIONAL CINEMA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In September 2010, Maghrebi-French filmmaker Rachid Bouchareb’s seventh feature film,<italic>Hors-la-loi</italic>, a gangster film set against the backdrop of the Algerian war for independence, was released across cinemas in France. Made for a budget of €20m, released on more than 400 prints and starring Jamel Debbouze – a French-born actor of Moroccan immigrant parents and one of French cinema’s biggest stars –<italic>Hors-la-loi</italic>enjoyed the kind of distribution and marketing conditions reserved for only the most high-profile French mainstream productions. The film aimed to capitalise on the success of Bouchareb’s Second World War epic,<italic>Indigènes</italic>(2006), which attracted over three</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>THE (MAGHREBI-)FRENCH CONNECTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>DIASPORA GOES MAINSTREAM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In many respects, and with few notable exceptions, Maghrebi-French and North African émigré filmmaking in France during the 1980s and 1990s has been characterised in both critical and academic discourse by notions of peripheral and auteur-led modes of production and limited exposure to niche audiences, not to mention struggles relating to funding, distribution and exhibition (Bluher 2001). The films have often been treated by academics and critics as a kind of socio-cultural document, rather than an entertainment ‘product’ aimed at mass audiences: a cinema more of interest to sociologists, journalists and academics as a reflection of contemporary socio-political realities facing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>COLONIAL FRACTURE AND THE COUNTER-HERITAGE FILM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As suggested in the previous chapter, the 2000s have been marked by a qualitative move towards the mainstream for a number of directors and actors of Maghrebi origin, a shift that has led to a greater variety of genres being used by these filmmakers in their work. At the heart of this chapter is an attempt to understand how what will be termed the counter-heritage cinema of Maghrebi-French directors in the 2000s engages with wider public debates around the memorialisation of France’s colonial past (see for example Chevènement 2001; Rousso 1998; Ricoeur 2004; Blanchard<italic>et al</italic>. 2006). Writing in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>OF SPACES AND DIFFERENCE IN THE FILMS OF ABDELLATIF KECHICHE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In previous chapters of this book, it has been argued that Maghrebi-French and North African émigré filmmaking has undergone a transformation in the 2000s that brought certain filmmakers firmly into the mainstream. In the case of actor, writer and director Abdellatif Kechiche, a different (but no less significant) kind of evolution has taken place.</p>
                     <p>Kechiche was born in Tunisia and arrived in France at the age of six. He grew up on a working-class estate on the outskirts of Nice, not far from the city’s famous Victorine studios. During his youth, he indulged a passion for cinema through regular trips</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>HOME, DISPLACEMENT AND THE MYTH OF RETURN:</title>
                     <subtitle>JOURNEY NARRATIVES IN THE 2000s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tony Gatlif’s award-winning feature film<italic>Exils</italic>(2004) begins with darkness, followed by a shot of what initially appears to be the contours of an unidentified, barren landscape. As the camera pulls back, the image is in fact revealed to be the naked back of Zano (Romain Duris), the French son of<italic>pied noir</italic>exiles. The opening scene reaches its chaotic crescendo: Zano surveys the view of the<italic>péripherique</italic>from the window of his high-rise apartment, before sending a glass of beer crashing to the street below; revolutionary slogans, delivered in Spanish and English to a strident rhythm, boom from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>SCREENING ISLAM:</title>
                     <subtitle>CINEMATIC REPRESENTATIONS OF THE MUSLIM COMMUNITY IN FRANCE IN THE 2000s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given the extent to which the integration of France’s North African Muslim population has been foregrounded in public debates over immigration, integration and national identity since the late 1980s, it is perhaps surprising that representations of Islam have remained marginal in Maghrebi-French and North African émigré filmmaking. This is even more so the case when it is considered that films by directors of North African origin have tended to foreground narratives addressing contemporary socio-political realities concerning the Maghrebi immigrant community and their French descendants. In other ways, however, this structuring absence of Islam since the 1980s finds a clear precedence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>POST-BEUR CINEMA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Speaking in 1989, after the initial promise of Beur Cinema appeared to have reached an impasse, Algerian émigré director Abdelkrim Bahloul summarised the situation facing filmmakers of Maghrebi origin in France:</p>
                     <p>The North African was absent from films, or else was shown in a stereotypical way […] because the Maghrebi community didn’t have the means to take hold of its own image […] As filmmakers from this community we don’t want to restrict ourselves to the problems of immigration. Our imagination is far greater than that. It is because we are aware of the limitations and the misrepresentations offered in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>192</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2vh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
