<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">R723.C36513 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Medicine</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Medicine</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Health Sciences</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Writings on Medicine</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Canguilhem</surname>
               <given-names>Georges</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="translator">Translated, with an Introduction, by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Geroulanos</surname>
               <given-names>Stefanos</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Meyers</surname>
               <given-names>Todd</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823234318</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823253654</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c84gs6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>At the time of his death in 1995, Georges Canguilhem was a highly respected historian of science and medicine, whose engagement with questions of normality, the ideologization of scientific thought, and the conceptual history of biology had marked the thought of philosophers such as Michel Foucault, Louis Althusser, Pierre Bourdieu, and Gilles Deleuze. This collection of short, incisive, and highly accessible essays on the major concepts of modern medicine shows Canguilhem at the peak of his use of historical practice for philosophical engagement. In order to elaborate a philosophy of medicine, Canguilhem examines paramount problems such as the definition and uses of health, the decline of the Hippocratic understanding of nature, the experience of disease, the limits of psychology in medicine, myths and realities of therapeutic practices, the difference between cure and healing, the organism's self-regulation, and medical metaphors linking the organism to society. Writings on Medicine is at once an excellent introduction to Canguilhem's work and a forceful, insightful, and accessible engagement with elemental concepts in medicine. The book is certain to leave its imprint on anthropology, history, philosophy, bioethics, and the social studies of medicine.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="116"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Georges Canguilhem’s Critique of Medical Reason</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Geroulanos</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefanos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meyers</surname>
                           <given-names>Todd</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the time of his death in 1995, Georges Canguilhem was a highly respected epistemologist and historian of biology and medicine. He was known for having extended and transformed traditions set by Gaston Bachelard and Henri Bergson, and as an influential figure for generations of scholars, including Michel Foucault, François Dagognet, Louis Althusser, Pierre Bourdieu, Dominique Lecourt, Gilbert Simondon, and Gilles Deleuze. At different stages of his life, he was in conversation with important contemporaries, among them François Jacob, Jean Hyppolite, Maurice Merleau-Ponty, Jean Cavaillès, Kurt Goldstein, and René Leriche. He spearheaded both a radical undermining of scientific positivism and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>The Idea of Nature in Medical Theory and Practice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One may wonder whether the doctor-patient relationship has ever succeeded in being a simple, instrumental relation that could be described in such a way that the cause and the effect, the therapeutic gesture and its result, would be directly related one to the other, on the same plane and at the same level, without being mediated by something foreign to its space of intelligibility. It is certain, in any case, that the centuries-old invocation of a<italic>healing nature</italic>[une nature médicatrice] has been and remains the reference to just such a mediator, who would account, throughout history, for the fact</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Diseases</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the beginning of his<italic>Essays on Painting</italic>, Diderot writes: “Nature does nothing incorrectly. Every form, beautiful or ugly, has its reason; and of all the beings that exist, there is not one that is not as it must be.”¹ One can imagine an<italic>Essays on Medicine</italic>that would begin with: “Nature does nothing arbitrarily. Disease, like health, has its reason, and among all the living beings, there is not one whose state is not as it must be.”² This kind of prologue could not concern all populations at all times. Over centuries and in many places, illness was either</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Health:</title>
                     <subtitle>Popular Concept and Philosophical Question</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Who among us did not speak of what is healthy and what is harmful before the arrival of Hippocrates?” This is how Epictetus, in his<italic>Discourses</italic>, argues for the popular pertinence of an a priori notion of the healthy and of health— a health whose relation to objects or behavior, moreover, he considers to be uncertain.¹ If we were to allow that such a definition of health might be possible without reference to some explicit knowledge, where would we seek its foundation?</p>
                     <p>It would be inappropriate, here in Strasbourg,² to offer you some reflections on health without recalling the definition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Is a Pedagogy of Healing Possible?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Understood as an event in the doctor-patient relationship, healing is at first sight what the patient expects from the doctor, but not what he always obtains from him. There is thus a discrepancy between the patient’s hope regarding the power that he attributes to the doctor on the grounds of the latter’s knowledge and the doctor’s recognition of the limits of his own efficacy. There, without doubt, lies the main reason why, of all the objects specific to medical thought, healing is the one that doctors have considered the least. Yet this is also due to the fact that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Problem of Regulation in the Organism and in Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When my friend Pierre-Maxime Schuhl¹ asked me to lecture at a meeting of the Alliance Israé lite Universelle, I accepted gladly and with great pleasure; it is an honor for me, and I only regret having had to pose this one condition— for which I apologize—which resulted in us meeting at a time so out of the ordinary.</p>
                     <p>I have chosen to treat a problem that, I assure you gentlemen, I have by no means mastered, for it is a question for me, as well. But I have chosen to speak to you of a subject that is not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84gs6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
