<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt184qqbp</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS1182.5 .F68 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. Old Testament</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Socio-rhetorical criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Foundations for Sociorhetorical Exploration</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Rhetoric of Religious Antiquity Reader</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Robbins</surname>
               <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Von Thaden</surname>
               <given-names>Robert H.</given-names>
               <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bruehler</surname>
               <given-names>Bart B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884141693</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884141686</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1f5g5j7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Engaging resources for understanding the importance of bodies and spaces in producing and interpreting persuasive language</p>
         <p>This volume collects essays that represent intellectual milestones that are informing sociorhetorical interpretation during the twenty-first century. The essays are arranged into five parts: (1) Topos; (2) Cultural Geography and Critical Spatiality; (3) Rhetorolects and Conceptual Blending; (4) Rhetography; and (5) Rhetorical Force.</p>
         <p>Features:</p>
         <p>Tools for integrating multiple approaches to biblical interpretationResources that emphasize the importance of language that prompts mental pictures in effective rhetoricEssays from classicists, rhetoricians, and biblical scholars</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="520"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robbins</surname>
                           <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Thaden</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert H.</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bruehler</surname>
                           <given-names>Bart B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sociorhetorical interpretation (SRI) is a heuristic that is properly called an interpretive analytic rather than a method. This means an interpreter can select any series of strategies to analyze and interpret rhetorical, social, and cognitive picturing and reasoning to help interpreters learn how a text prompts and influences thinking, emotion, and behavior. Since it is not a method, it does not prescribe a series of scientific steps or formulae designed to perform and produce predictable results in accord with a particular conceptual framework. Rather, the goal is to produce a programmatic exploration guided by a particular constellation of strategies and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sociorhetorical Criticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mary, Elizabeth, and the Magnificat as a Test Case</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robbins</surname>
                           <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sociorhetorical criticism is a textually based method that uses programmatic strategies to invite social, cultural, historical, psychological, aesthetic, ideological and theological information into a context of minute exegetical activity. In a context where historical criticism has been opening its boundaries to social and cultural data and literary criticism has been opening boundaries to ideology, sociorhetorical criticism practices interdisciplinary exegesis that reinvents the traditional steps of analysis and redraws the traditional boundaries of interpretation. Sociorhetorical criticism, then, is an exegetically oriented approach that gathers current practices of interpretation together in an interdisciplinary paradigm.</p>
                     <p>Both the textual base for the strategies and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reworking Aristotle’s Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kennedy</surname>
                           <given-names>George A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My title, “Reworking Aristotle’s<italic>Rhetoric</italic>,” has several possible meanings. For one thing, all of us who study rhetoric are in some sense engaged in our own reworking, interpretation, and application of it. More specifically, I have recently worked through the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>again in the process of making a new translation of it, with introduction and notes. I would like to discuss some of the things I have noticed, but will only comment occasionally on my own translation. Finally, I will say something about the strengths and weaknesses of the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>and how it, as a general rhetoric, may need to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Aristotelian Topos:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hunting for Novelty</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Carolyn R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the topoi have routinely been thought of as instruments of decorum serving a managerial function in rhetoric, Richard McKeon noted that they can also be understood as sources of novelty, as having a generative function.¹ To establish what the Aristotelian topos can contribute to contemporary interests in generative rhetoric, this essay examines the conceptual contexts from which Aristotle drew his use of the term and the framework from which he drew his thinking about invention. Sources examined include his earlier works, the<italic>Physics</italic>and<italic>On Coming-to-Be and Passing-Away</italic>, as well as aspects of prephilosophical Greek thought that constitutes what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Paul’s Inclusive Language:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ideological Texture of Romans 1</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bloomquist</surname>
                           <given-names>L. Gregory</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no doubt in my mind that sociorhetorical analysis, as envisioned by Vernon K. Robbins, represents one of the most significant and healthy approaches to the analysis of sacred texts to have appeared in many years. It is significant in that it welcomes already-existing forms of analysis to the table for inclusion in an interpretive analytics that asks interpreters to carry forth a programmatic analysis, but to do so in light of a hermeneutical sensitivity to the questions being asked of the text. It is healthy for two reasons: (1) it welcomes all voices to the table, without deciding</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Theories of Space and Construction of the Ancient World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Berquist</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By widely held custom, academic papers on theoretical topics should begin with a history of the terms to be discussed. The pervasiveness of this custom tempts me to start this paper in that time-honored tradition, but I have found myself resistant, for two reasons.</p>
                     <p>First,<italic>space</italic>is an odd term about which to write a history. Throughout most of the history of Western thought, few persons have recognized that space is historical; that is, space has generally been understood as a given, not as a category about which there could be variation. History existed within space (and time); there was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Storied Space, or, Ben Sira “Tells” a Temple</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Camp</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of many debts of gratitude that biblical scholars owe Jim Flanagan is for the time and energy he has spent organizing us to think seriously about space in the same critical way we have become accustomed to thinking about history and society. My own interests are less systematically theoretical than Flanagan’s. Not only do I like my theory heavily applied; I do not even mind if an application skews someone’s theoretical system a bit. In the end, for me, heuristic possibility counts for more than theoretical purity. I have no doubt that some impurity will taint my neophyte venture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>From This Place:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Theoretical Framework for the Social-Spatial Analysis of Luke</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bruehler</surname>
                           <given-names>Bart B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Given the complex nature of what is public, political, and private combined with the relative lack of careful attention to these social-spatial categories in New Testament scholarship, this study will establish a critical and contextual classification of space for Luke’s gospel. This requires three things: an informed theoretical perspective, an adequate system of classification, and broad and specific comparative material. The first third of this chapter will describe several scholars and works that contribute to the eclectic theoretical perspective of this study. However, this study does not delve into unplowed ground. Unfortunately, most previous studies of the public and private</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>KNOWING IS SEEING:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theories of Metaphor Ancient, Medieval, and Modern</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Huber</surname>
                           <given-names>Lynn R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we saw in chapter 1,¹ since the earliest centuries of the church, interpreters have acknowledged the imagistic or metaphorical nature of the book of Revelation, although they disagree about what this characterization means. This suggests that bringing the insights of metaphor theory to bear on Revelation would be an appropriate and fruitful endeavor, especially contemporary theories of metaphor that emphasize the cognitive nature of this phenomenon. This is not to suggest that scholars have ignored discussions about metaphor in their work on Revelation; rather, there has been little systematic analysis of the metaphorical language in the text. Scholars who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Cognitive Turn:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conceptual Blending within a Sociorhetorical Framework</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Thaden</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert H.</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is an exciting time to be engaged in religious studies in general and biblical studies in particular. Developments in the cross-disciplinary endeavor known as cognitive science, a “blanket term for a set of disciplines … concerned with the empirical investigation of the human mind,” have opened up new avenues of inquiry in the study of religion.² The development of the cognitive science of religion promises to reorient the way some scholars of religion study and analyze this particular human phenomenon.³ Cognitive science brings to the table an interdisciplinary array of tools that can, in principle, allow us to rethink</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conceptual Blending and Early Christian Imagination</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robbins</surname>
                           <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The emergence of early Christianity during the first century CE is a truly remarkable phenomenon. The literature this movement produced during its first seventy years of existence exhibits profound creativity in the context of traditional cultures, which are known for their conservative nature. Years ago, scholars such as Amos Wilder observed that there were amazingly “new” formulations of phrases and words in New Testament literature.¹ There has, however, been only limited progress in our understanding of how this “newness” emerged. Many scholars have exhibited and discussed the wide reaching diversity in traditions, concepts, and practices among different groups of early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rhetography:</title>
                     <subtitle>A New Way of Seeing the Familiar Text</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robbins</surname>
                           <given-names>Vernon K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The process of writing this essay has reminded me that “there is nothing new under the sun” (Eccl 1:9).¹ It also has renewed my conviction that all things humans perceive to be new are reconfigurations of that which is old and commonplace. The topic of this essay is<italic>rhetography</italic>, a term of importance for scholars investigating the rhetoric of religious antiquity.² Rhetography refers to the graphic images people create in their minds as a result of the visual texture of a text.³ Rhetography communicates a context of meaning to a hearer or reader. A speaker or writer composes, intentionally or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Clothes Make the (Wo)Man</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jeal</surname>
                           <given-names>Roy R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thinking about perceptions of body as they are used in the Bible leads, inevitably, to reflecting on clothing and the idea of clothing. Clothing is a powerful image throughout biblical literature and in human society generally.¹ At the most obvious level, clothing covers and conceals the body, protecting it from exposure to the elements and the view of other persons. But the significance of clothing extends much further since garments not only cover and conceal, but also function to display the body in particular ways and with many meanings. The ways in which bodies are clothed have far-reaching and sometimes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>415</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>459</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Modern Authors Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>471</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f5g5j7.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>477</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
