<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Education</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Secret Life of Stories</book-title>
         <subtitle>From Don Quixote to Harry Potter, How Understanding Intellectual Disability Transforms the Way We Read</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bérubé</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781479823611</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781479874859</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">147987485X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>NYU Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>New York University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt15zc6mw"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Narrative informs everything we think, do, plan, remember, and imagine. We tell stories and we listen to stories, gauging their "well-formedness" within a couple of years of learning to walk and talk. Some argue that the capacity to understand narrative is innate to our species; others claim that while that might be so, the invention of writing then re-wired our brains.</p>
         <p>In<italic>The Secret Life of Stories</italic>, Michael Bérubé tells a dramatically different tale, in a compelling account of how an understanding of intellectual disability can transform our understanding of narrative. Instead of focusing on characters with disabilities, he shows how ideas about intellectual disability inform an astonishingly wide array of narrative strategies, providing a new and startling way of thinking through questions of time, self-reflexivity, and motive in the experience of reading. Interweaving his own stories with readings of such texts as Faulkner's<italic>The Sound and the Fury</italic>, Haddon's<italic>The Curious Incident of the Dog in the Night-Time</italic>, Kingston's<italic>The Woman Warrior</italic>, and Philip K. Dick's<italic>Martian Time-Slip</italic>, Bérubé puts his theory into practice, stretching the purview of the study of literature and the role of disability studies within it. Armed only with the tools of close reading, Bérubé demonstrates the immensely generative possibilities in the ways disability is deployed within fiction, finding in them powerful meditations on what it means to be a social being, a sentient creature with an awareness of mortality and causality-and sentience itself. Persuasive and witty, Michael Bérubé engages Harry Potter fans and scholars of literature alike. For all readers,<italic>The Secret Life of Stories</italic>will fundamentally change the way we think about the way we read.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Representations of disability are ubiquitous, far more prevalent and pervasive than (almost) anybody realizes. Not because of the truism that we all become disabled in one way or another if we live long enough, but because disability has a funny way of popping up everywhere without announcing itself<italic>as</italic>disability. Everyone knows Dumbo as the plucky little elephant who can fly; few people think of Dumbo as a child with a disability, even though his ridiculously large ears are, for most of the film, a source of stigma and shame—so much so that the other circus elephants torment Dumbo’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Motive</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At a critical moment in the eerie “King’s Cross” chapter of<italic>Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows</italic>, which takes place in a limbo after Voldemort has zapped Harry with the “avada kadavra” killing curse, Albus Dumbledore—who was killed at the end of the previous installment,<italic>Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince</italic>—tells Harry about the youthful indiscretion that constituted his early (and long-unacknowledged) fascist phase, when he teamed up with the evil genius Gellert Grindelwald to propose a plan for world domination in which Muggles around the globe would be subject to rule by an elite cabal of wizards</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first section of<italic>The Sound and the Fury</italic>is not hard to read. No, really. I invite you, dear reader, as I once invited my son Nick, to take a crack at it:</p>
                     <p>Through the fence, between the curling flower spaces, I could see them hitting. They were coming toward where the flag was and I went along the fence. Luster was hunting in the grass by the flower tree. They took the flag out, and they were hitting. Then they put the flag back and they went to the table, and he hit and the other hit. Then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Self-Awareness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literary texts have any number of ways of marking their awareness of themselves as literary texts. Some are cloying; some are trivial; some are merely cute. Some involve explicitly metafictional engagements with the fictionality of fiction, as in the closing passage of Beckett’s<italic>Molloy</italic>, echoing and complicating the opening passage of the novella’s second section: “Then I went back into the house and wrote, It is midnight. The rain is beating on the windows. It was not midnight. It was not raining” (176). Some involve more subtle, implicit meditations on the degree of readerly self-consciousness necessary for reading, as in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Minds</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the spring of 2013, in the middle of a graduate seminar in which my students and I were working out many of the questions I have tried to pose here, suddenly a curious incident happened.</p>
                     <p>I was discussing chapters 2 and 3 of Lisa Zunshine’s<italic>Why We Read Fiction</italic>. I was doing so for two reasons: one, to establish her unfortunate reliance on Simon Baron-Cohen, right down to her acceptance of his description of autism as the “most severe of all childhood<italic>psychiatric conditions</italic>” (qtd. at 7; emphasis added), a phrase that would not have looked at all out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt15zc6mw.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABOUT THE AUTHOR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
