<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gx2w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Small Places, Large Issues</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Introduction to Social and Cultural Anthropology (Fourth Edition)</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Eriksen</surname>
               <given-names>Thomas Hylland</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745335933</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781783715176</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>4</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Thomas Hylland Eriksen</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183p184"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This concise introduction to social and cultural anthropology has become a modern classic, revealing the rich global variation in social life and culture. The text provides a clear overview of anthropology, focusing on central topics such as kinship, ethnicity, ritual and political systems, offering a wealth of examples that demonstrate the enormous scope of anthropology and the importance of a comparative perspective. Unlike other texts on the subject, Small Places, Large Issues incorporates the anthropology of complex modern societies. Using reviews of key monographs to illustrate his argument, Eriksen's lucid and accessible text remains an established introductory text in anthropology. This new, fourth edition is updated throughout and increases the emphasis on the interdependence of human worlds. There is a new discussion of the new influence cultural studies and natural science on anthropology. Effortless bridging the perceived gap between "classic" and "contemporary" anthropology, Small Places, Large Issues is as essential to anthropology undergraduates as ever.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garsten</surname>
                           <given-names>Christina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Fourth Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Anthropology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Comparison and Context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Studying anthropology is like embarking on a journey which turns out to be much longer than you had initially planned, possibly because the plans were somewhat open-ended to begin with and the terrain turned out to be bumpier and more diverse than the map suggested. Fortunately, like many journeys which take an unexpected turn, this one also has numerous unexpected rewards in store (as well as, it is only fair to concede, a few frustrations en route). This journey brings the traveller from the damp rainforests of the Amazon to the cold semi-desert of the Arctic; from the streets of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A Brief History of Anthropology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like the other social sciences, anthropology has fairly recent origins. It developed as an academic discipline during the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, but it has important forerunners in earlier historiography, geography, travel writing, philosophy, comparative linguistics and jurisprudence. There are many ways of writing the history of anthropology, just as there may exist, in any given society, competing versions of national history or origin myths, promoted by groups or individuals with diverging interests. History is not primarily a product of the past itself, but is rather shaped by the concerns of the present. As these concerns change, past</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Fieldwork and Ethnography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anthropology distinguishes itself from the other social sciences through the strong emphasis placed on ethnographic fieldwork as the most important source of new knowledge about society and culture. A field study may last for a few months, a year, or even two years or more, and it aims to develop as intimate an understanding as possible of the phenomena investigated. Many anthropologists return to the same field throughout their career, to deepen their understanding further or to record change. Although there are differences in field methods between different anthropological schools, it is generally agreed that the anthropologist ought to stay</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Social Person</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The press occasionally brings stories about ‘feral children’ who are discovered after allegedly having spent many years in a forest or similar wilderness, isolated from culture and human society. According to such stories – Kipling’s novel about Mowgli,<italic>The Jungle Book</italic>, is the most famous one (and one which does not, incidentally, claim authenticity) – these children have been raised by animals, usually monkeys, and are therefore unable to communicate with humans. Normally, ‘feral children’ are said to reveal a pattern of acting similar to animal behaviour; they growl, they are terrified of humans and they lack human language, table</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Local Organisation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much of the empirical material necessary for anthropological thinking and research is still obtained through studies of local communities. Most classic anthropological analyses are based on detailed descriptions of culture and social organisation in a delineated system, which could be a village or an urban environment. Anthropology has diversified in recent decades into a variety of new, specialised directions and, given the complexity (and often non-localised nature) of many contemporary fields of study, it has become clear that it may be necessary to consult sources which cannot be obtained through fieldwork (such as historical sources, statistics, mass and social media,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Person and Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The person is a social product, but society is at the same time created by acting persons. In the previous chapters, this apparent paradox has been illustrated in several ways. It has also been made clear that there will always be some aspects of society which change and some aspects which remain the same, if we look at the entire system over an extended period. Put differently, one might say that different parts of a society change at different speeds. In this chapter, we draw some theoretical lessons from these themes, and also propose a model of the relationship between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Kinship as Descent</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Generations of anthropologists have been flabbergasted at the intricate kinship systems existing in many allegedly ‘primitive’ societies. Several famous examples of such complicated systems are to be found in the Australian aboriginal population, whose kinship systems were studied systematically already in the 1870s by the self-taught ethnographers Lorimer Fison and William Howitt (1991 [1880]). These peoples, traditionally hunters and gatherers, have the simplest technology in the world. They lack metals, domesticated animals and writing, and in most cases they do not even have the rudiments of agriculture. Nonetheless, many of these nomadic groups have kinship systems so complex that it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Marriage and Relatedness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Seen from a male point of view, women are a scarce resource. No matter how male-dominated a society is, men need women to ensure its survival. In matrilineal systems, the men’s sisters carry out this work; in patrilineal societies, their wives do it; and in cognatic or bilateral societies, sisters and wives each do part of the job, seen from a male perspective. A man can have a nearly unlimited number of children – in theory, he can beget several children every day – while a woman’s capacity is limited to one child per year under optimal conditions and, moreover,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Gender and Age</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In all societies, there are differences in power between persons. There is not a single society where all adults have exactly the same influence over every decision, where everyone has exactly the same rights and duties. Social differentiation and inequality are, in other words, universal phenomena. The European ideas of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries about the ‘original primitive society’, where all humans supposedly had the same rank and were political equals, was completely devastated when the first professional ethnographers returned from the field. Even among very small groups, and even among peoples with very simple technology, differences in rank</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Caste and Class</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like gender and age, caste in the Indian subcontinent refers to ostensibly inborn, ascribed characteristics. In theory, changing your caste membership is as difficult as changing your gender.</p>
                     <p>The concept of social classes is different, and not only because classes exist in many different kinds of societies, while caste is usually associated with Hinduism and India. Although many social scientists have demonstrated that most people in class societies take over their parents’ class membership (if one is a working-class child, it is likely that one remains in the working class), there is a great deal of mobility between the social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Politics and Power</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Politics is linked with power; both the power that people exert over each other, and the ways in which society wields power over people by imposing institutionalised constraints on their agency – constraints ranging from property taxes and traffic rules to torture and genocide. However, politics also has to do with the prevention of lawlessness and insecurity; that is, it concerns law and order, the implementation of the rights of persons, conflict resolution and social integration.</p>
                     <p>Politics can be identified analytically in all societies, but by no means all societies that anthropologists have studied have political institutions distinct from otherx</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Exchange and Consumption</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Just as the anthropological study of politics is markedly different from the discipline of political science, economic anthropology distinguishes itself in important ways from the economic sciences. Anthropologists have always – at least since Boas and Malinowski – wished to call attention to the ways in which the economy is an integrated part of a social and cultural totality, and to reveal that economic systems and actions can only be fully understood if we look into their interrelationships with other aspects of culture and society. Just as politics ought to be seen as part of a wider system which includes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Production, Nature and Technology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idea that there is an interrelationship between ecological conditions and ways of life can be traced back to the ancient Greeks, and it was also prevalent in Enlightenment thought in the mid eighteenth century (for instance in Montesquieu and in the Marquis de Sade’s non-pornographic writings). Montesquieu, like many others, held that the main cause of Europe’s technological and scientific advances was the harsh climate, which required the inhabitants to be inventive and sharp-witted to survive. Two centuries later, the human geographer Ellsworth Huntington (1945) argued for climatic determinism in an original study where he shows, among other things,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Religion and Ritual</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a study of the Basseri pastoralists of southern Iran, Barth (1961) expresses some surprise regarding their lack of religious interest (they describe themselves as ‘slack Muslims’). His surprise is caused by the fact that religion seems to loom large in the lives of most of the peoples described in classic anthropological studies. This may be a major reason why religion has always been a central field of inquiry in anthropology, even if, as Evans-Pritchard (1962) once pointed out, social scientists have themselves often been indifferent or even hostile to religion.</p>
                     <p>In attempting to propose non-ethnocentric, comparatively useful definitions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Language and Cognition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Benjamin Lee Whorf was a fire prevention engineer, working for an insurance company in the US in the 1920s. A recurrent problem in his job concerned the interpretation of words; their precise meaning was often rather significant with regard to indemnity payments. What did it mean, for example, that a fire was ‘self-inflicted’? And what did it mean that a drum of petrol was ‘empty’? In some cases, it could be empty of petrol, but full of petrol gas and thus highly explosive. A fire that was caused by an empty petrol drum exploding could not, however, be defined as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Complexity and Change</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Some of the previous chapters have examined different forms of political organisation, world-views and systems of economic production and distribution. It has been noted for decades that the ethnographic present, the tense conventionally used when anthropologists talk about different societies, is increasingly, and more and more rapidly, becoming a past tense. In Australia, 250 languages were spoken in the late eighteenth century. At the outset of the twenty-first century, there were about 30 still regularly spoken, and few of them seemed likely to survive for another generation in Australia. Virtually all inhabitants of the world live in states which define</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Ethnicity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A well-known musician from Finnmark, the Sami-dominated county in northern Norway, was once asked the following question by a journalist: ‘Are you mostly a Sami or mostly a musician?’ She tried to be accommodating and accordingly answered the meaningless question; if she had been an anthropologist, she would probably have discarded it as being absurd. This chapter, which outlines basic dimensions of ethnicity, explains why.</p>
                     <p>A systematic search through major anthropological journals and monographs from, say, 1950 to 2015, will quickly reveal a change in the language of the subject. The terminology has generally become more influenced by hermeneutics and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Nationalism and Minorities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scarcely anyone who has used the methods of ethnography to identify and describe ideologies anywhere in the world since the 1960s can have avoided encountering expressions of nationalist ideology. The growth of nationalism and nation-building has been, and still is, an important, spectacular and highly consequential dimension of the worldwide processes of change connected with colonialism and decolonisation. Nationalism is a kind of ideology which exists almost everywhere in the world, although it assumes very different forms and varies in significance. This does not mean that all the citizens of any state know about, or for that matter support, nationalist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Anthropology and the Paradoxes of Globalisation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An anecdote is told about a tribe of transhumant camel nomads in North Africa, whose annual migration had taken place in March since the dawn of time. Recently their migration was several months delayed. The reason was that they did not want to miss the final episodes of<italic>Dallas</italic>.</p>
                     <p>The point is not whether or not this tale is true. What it may tell us is that the world is no longer what it used to be – or rather, perhaps, what anthropologists and many others used to imagine it to be. For it is easy to find evidence that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>Public Anthropology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To the extent that anthropological texts and lectures have an audience, all anthropology could be considered to be public. However, public anthropology, as the term is generally used, refers to a specific set of practices and positions within the discipline that aim to reach out beyond the confines of the academy. This can be accomplished through writing for different audiences, engaging in advocacy-oriented work in local communities, or by taking part in the transnational conversation about the ills and spoils of the contemporary world and what it means to be human.</p>
                     <p>The common denominator of these practices is the conviction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Making Anthropology Matter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What is the ultimate point of social anthropology? One may, obviously, use the subject to collect academic distinctions and eventually get a job in research or teaching. On the other hand, in most cases there are faster and more rewarding methods, at least in a pecuniary sense, of acquiring a livelihood. Fortunately, there are also other reasons for becoming involved in the subject.</p>
                     <p>The single most important human insight to be gained from this way of studying and comparing societies is perhaps the realisation that everything could have been different in our own society – that the way we live</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>404</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p184.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>435</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
