<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13kh4md</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>History of Science &amp; Technology</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Man and His World/Terres des hommes</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Noranda Lectures, Expo 67/Les Conferences Noranda/L'Expo 67</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib1">
            <role>Introduction by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hogg</surname>
               <given-names>Helen S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Préface de</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hogg</surname>
               <given-names>Helen S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>1968</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781487591755</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781487599560</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1968</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/j.ctt1vxmbvr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The fruits of a unique cultural exchange are brought together in this unusual book. Twenty-eight of the most eminent men and women of our generation – philosophers, historians, and scientists from nineteen countries – here discuss what they consider the most vital issues of our day.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="452"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                     <subtitle>Avant-propos</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bradfield</surname>
                           <given-names>John R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Expo 67 (Man and his World) was the outstanding event of Canada’s Centennial Year of Confederation. Some fifty million people had an opportunity to see at close range what is being achieved in the fields of science, art, the humanities, and industry in the principal countries of the world.</p>
                     <p>The Noranda Lectures, delivered in the Du Pont of Canada Auditorium by worldrenowned scientists and scholars, constituted an outstanding feature of this great exhibition. Noranda Mines is proud to have been associated with this undertaking and we hope that the benefits deriving from the Lectures have made some contribution to mankind’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hogg</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FOR THE CONTRIBUTION of Noranda Mines to Expo 67, the Board of Directors decided to metamorphose some of the native copper and gold from the Canadian shield into jewels for the mind. These jewels include the thoughts of renowned philosophers and historians, and the penetrating insights of scientists into the details of man’s world.</p>
                     <p>The task of carrying out this plan was placed in the hands of the Canadian Corporation for the World Exhibition, and the outcome was a series of twenty-eight lectures, delivered at weekly intervals. This volume is the complete collection of these lectures, and includes also the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Préface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hogg</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The lectures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Foster</surname>
                           <given-names>G. B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>JE SUIS HEUREUX de présider, au nom de la Compagnie Noranda, à la première des vingt-huit conférences présentées par notre société. Nous désirons remercier les responsables de l’Expo de nous avoir fourni l’occasion de commanditer ces conférences. Nous nous devons aussi de remercier les vingt-huit personnalités eminentes qui ont bien voulu accepter de participer à cette série de conférences.</p>
                     <p>Lorsque nous avons étudié les possibilités d’apporter notre contribution aux fêtes marquant le Centenaire de la Confédération, plusieurs projets nous ont été soumis. Après avoir apporté à chacun de ces projets beaucoup de considération, nous en sommes venus à conclure que</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Les conférences</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>JE SUIS TRÈS HONORÉ de me trouver dans cette splendide salle nouvelle, et devant ce distingué auditoire, pour inaugurer les Conférences Noranda, et d’assister à la présentation du premier conférencier de la série, M. Paul-Henri Spaak.</p>
                     <p>Comme on le sait sans doute de par le monde, l’Expo a pour thème Terre des Hommes. Autour de ce thème, on se propose d’envisager l’homme dans son milieu actuel, d’exalter ses réalisations dans les domaines de la culture et de la science, et de montrer comment il doit s’adapter aux idées nouvelles et aux nouveaux modes de vie communautaire, afin de favoriser l’harmonie</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dupuy</surname>
                           <given-names>Pierre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I MET M. PAUL-HENRI SPAAK a few days after he had accepted, for the first time, the office of Foreign Minister of Belgium. It was at the time of the Manchukuo crisis, when the Japanese invaded the northern part of West China. This invasion then appeared to most as a distant struggle, with practically little consequence for the rest of the world. But men like M. Spaak already appreciated the full meaning of events. He knew this was the gong starting a storm that was bound to reach the West sooner or later.</p>
                     <p>Years passed, during which M. Spaak built</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Comment faire régner la paix dans le monde</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spaak</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul-Henri</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>J’AVOUE que j’aborde cette tribune avec un certain complexe d’infériorité, quand je vois la liste des personnalités qui vont me succéder. Homme politique, je me suis toujours senti un peu embarrassé dans le monde des savants et des écrivains. Je sais que nous, hommes politiques, avons « les joies du pouvoir » et que nous sommes quelquefois mieux connus que les plus grands savants. Je suppose que c’est parce que nos erreurs sont plus fatales à l’humanité. Je crains ces géographes, ces chimistes, ces biologistes, qui vont me succéder; je crains leurs preuves, leurs arguments, leurs démonstrations précises, leurs certitudes.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robbins</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DR. GUNNAR MYDRAL of Sweden has been a familiar and respected name among economists of the world for a generation. Indeed his name has been familiar to a very much wider circle of readers than just professional economists. The practical problems of men living together in a free society, in a peaceful world, have been foremost in his mind, and he has expressed himself concerning them in a way that the layman can understand.</p>
                     <p>In the 1920s, Dr. Myrdal was a student at the University of Stockholm, where he received a Doctorate of Jurisprudence in economics. It was a time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>An economist’s vision of a sane world</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Myrdal</surname>
                           <given-names>Gunnar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE ECONOMISTS HAVE always constituted a fighting church with many sects. Our common religion was always rationality. My old teacher, fatherly friend, and predecessor in the chair of political economy at the Stockholm University, Gustav Cassel, gave his memoirs the title:<italic>In the Service of Reason.</italic>Even if most of his colleagues, then as now, would have learned to express themselves with more modesty, this is how they look upon themselves and their profession, and I am no exception. We always have the vision of a more rational organization of society, of a sane world.</p>
                     <p>I say this to explain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bissell</surname>
                           <given-names>Claude</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE NORANDA LECTURES have accepted the full implications of the theme of Expo, “Man and His World,” and have encompassed all of the disciplines that strive to explain man, the natural world at large around him, and the world he has created, either in physical form or in the more potent environment of idea and spirit. Two of the speakers are listed as economists. They are supported by political scientists, historians, philosophers, and by one literary critic and writer. It is not especially elegant to say that the crucial breakthroughs in human understanding must come in these areas. The must</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A new history</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jackson</surname>
                           <given-names>Lady</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I CONFESS I COULD have chosen a better day than June 5, 1967, to speak about “A New History.” As we look at the war that has broken out in the Middle East, we must have the feeling that this is the oldest of all histories, going right back to the hominids dug up in Kenya from forty millennia of dust with their weapons lying beside them. It is easy to conclude, as we confront the crises of the Middle East and Southeast Asia, that, far from seeing a new history, we are re-entering one of those appalling spirals of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Neatby</surname>
                           <given-names>Hilda</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IT IS DIFFICULT to do justice to Mr. Singh’s career and achievements in a short introduction. He was educated in Lahore, and at King’s College and the Inner Temple, London. After some years in legal practice in Lahore, he entered the service of the newly independent nation of India. As a member of the ministry of external affairs, he served as Press Attaché in Canada, and later as Public Relations Officer in Great Britain. Then after another period of service in India as Minister of Information and Broadcasting, he entered the Department of Mass Communications of Unesco.</p>
                     <p>Mr. Singh has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Orient pearl in the world oyster</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Singh</surname>
                           <given-names>Khushwant</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I FIRST CAME TO this country twenty years ago – soon after India had attained independence and had become an equal partner with Canada in the Commonwealth. I was sent here as Press and Cultural Attaché charged with the duty of selling my country’s politics, culture, and way of life to the Canadians. I did this to the best of my very limited ability along channels open to diplomatic missions. I bombarded your newspapers and broadcasting stations with press handouts. Little notice was taken of my handouts by either your press or your radio. I went on extensive tours and addressed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Adams</surname>
                           <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DR. SEYYED HUSSEIN NASR is not only one of the most distinguished young scholars of his own country, but a man who in spite of his youth has won an international reputation for scholarship, forthrightness, and vigour in the advocacy of his opinions, and for his contribution to an important area of research and knowledge. This is Dr. Nasr’s second visit to Canada. His first visit was made in 1962 at the invitation of the Institute of Islamic Studies of McGill University, and he stayed with us then only for one short day. On this occasion he has been with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Who is man? the perennial answer of Islam</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nasr</surname>
                           <given-names>Seyyed Hussein</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN A WORLD EXHIBITION whose theme is Man and His World, La Terre des hommes, and which is devoted to a display of the different aspects of man’s life and activities, it is perhaps not futile to pause for a moment and pose the question who is this man to whom the world is said to belong, the world or the “earth” which he has conquered, yet is on the verge of destroying at the very moment when his conquest seems most complete. Modern man feels at home on earth, or rather would like to feel at home completely in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gaudry</surname>
                           <given-names>Roger</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>M. LEROI-GOURHAN est professeur à la Sorbonne, membre du Comité permanent de la Commission d’ethnologie-anthropologie-préhistoire au Centre national de la recherche scientifique, membre du Conseil national de la recherche archéologique, membre de la Commission des fouilles à l’étranger au Ministère des affaires extérieures et président honoraire de la Société préhistorique française. Parisien, originaire de Bretagne, il est par vocation et profession un anthropologue dans le sens le plus large du mot, c’est-à-dire un citoyen du monde. Son activité débordante, une fructueuse carrière de trente ans toute consacrée à la recherche et à l’enseignement, et toujours d’ailleurs en plein essor, me</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Terre des hommes préhistoriques</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leroi-Gourhan</surname>
                           <given-names>André</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>L’INTÉRÊT DE L’HOMME pour son propre passé remonte aux plus lointaines origines historiques : les généalogies, comme les mythes sur la création du monde, forment une part importante des premiers textes écrits. Pendant de nombreux siècles, les hommes de l’Antiquité et du Moyen Age, pénétrés du respect des auteurs anciens, ont satisfait leur soif de connaissance dans les livres. Leur perspicacité n’était d’ailleurs pas moindre que la nôtre; ils avaient parfaitement reconnu dans certaines pierres découvertes dans le sol les traces d’un travail de façonnage, et la présence de coquilles marines jusqu’au sommet de certaines montagnes ne leur avait pas</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bernier</surname>
                           <given-names>Roger</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>PRÉSENTER LE PROFESSEUR LÔWITH n’est pas une tâche facile, car sa vie intellectuelle a été d’une telle intensité et s’est manifestée par une si importante contribution en publications philosophiques qu’il est difficile dans les quelques instants dont je dispose de vous le présenter adéquatement.</p>
                     <p>En effet, Monsieur le Professor Lôwith, disciple de Martin Heidegger, devenait en 1928 lecteur en philosophie à l’Université de Marbourg, après avoir complété ses études en philosophie et en biologie aux Universités de Munich, Freibourg et Marbourg. Dès cette année, à l’âge de 31 ans, le professeur Lôwith publiait sa première oeuvre en allemand, dont le</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Progress:</title>
                     <subtitle>a fatality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Löwith</surname>
                           <given-names>Karl</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE CONCEPTION OF progress is of ten confused with that of development. We speak of “underdeveloped” countries and mean those which still have to develop by assimilating the advances of Western civilization. We speak of the progress of science and in the same sense of its development. Hegel even asserts that truth itself has the tendency to “develop,” i. e.</p>
                     <p>to unfold in the history of the spirit. Since this explication leads to more and more advanced stages, Hegel calls the principle of history in which reason develops in the world a “progress” in the consciousness of freedom. Both development</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dupuy</surname>
                           <given-names>M. Pierre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>L’AFRIQUE, qui est entrée de plein pied dans la vie mondiale depuis 1960, est représentée par un certain nombre de pays qui jouent un rôle dont l’importance croît d’année en année. Mais parmi ces pays, il en est un qu’il me plaît de signaler tout particulièrement -c’est la Côte d’Ivoire.</p>
                     <p>La Côte d’Ivoire est un pays qui par ses ressources, par l’utilisation de ses ressources, et par l’autorité qui la dirige, fait l’admiration du monde entier. Son Excellence Monsieur le Président de la Côte d’Ivoire, M. Houphouët-Boigny, est l’héritier d’une autorité qui existait dans le pays avant qu’il ne devînt</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Unité et développement</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Houphouët-Boigny</surname>
                           <given-names>Félix</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>PARMI LES NATIONS les plus avancées, nombreux, peut-être, sont les responsables politiques, les chercheurs, les penseurs et les artistes qui se sentent si proches de cet avenir qu’ils éprouvent le besoin de l’organiser dès maintenant. Et les peuples de ces pays sentent que la transition se fera pour eux sans difficulté majeure, de la vie qu’ils connaissent à celle que leur prépare l’incessante activité créatrice de l’humanité.</p>
                     <p>Et pourtant, le monde de demain suscite -dit-on -certaines appréhensions chez les meilleurs esprits du siècle. Vous comprendrez d’autant plus aisément, j’en suis sûr, les appréhensions, les craintes, les angoisses même que peuvent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hicks</surname>
                           <given-names>Henry B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DR. CARL J. FRIEDRICH is now the Eaton Professor of the Science of Government at Harvard; since 1956 he has been a professor in political science at the University of Heidelberg in Germany. Born in Leipzig in 1901, he was educated at the Universities of Marburg, Frankfurt, Vienna, and Heidelberg, and came to the United States when he was only twenty-one years of age. He is now an American citizen.</p>
                     <p>He has taught political science at Harvard since 1926, but has also lectured at other great centres of learning all over the world. He is president of the International Political</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Man and his government</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Friedrich</surname>
                           <given-names>Carl J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MAN AND HIS GOVERNMENT is Surety one of the most important dimensions of the general theme of Man and His World. If I wished to dramatize the subject of my discussion, I would have to say that my ultimate concern is with the present drift toward universal anarchy. This will serve as a warning of the rather pessimistic tone which I am afraid that the student of government must adopt in the year 1967.</p>
                     <p>The problem of the drift toward universal anarchy is as a matter of fact the problem of man and his government today. But if one had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meynaud</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>JE CONNAIS le Professeur William Robson depuis bientôt vingt ans, et j’ai été son collaborateur immédiat à l’époque où il était président de l’Association internationale de science politique (1952-1955). Il serait vain de ma part de présenter une personnalité internationalement aussi connue, mais je voudrais dire ce qu’il représente pour nous, c’està-dire pour les hommes de la collectivité universitaire. D’abord, un savant de classe exceptionnelle qui a su faire progresser son domaine par des recherches nombreuses et puissantes. Toute son oeuvre est centrée sur l’administration publique au sens large du mot, c’est-àdire sur l’ensemble des aspects politiques et administratifs du</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The role and conduct of public enterprise</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robson</surname>
                           <given-names>William A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I WILL BEGIN by explaining what I understand by public enterprise. It comprises all those activities on the part of public authorities which plan, control, initiate and organize economic and social development. It is convenient to divide the functions of the State into three categories. There are the traditional functions such as the maintenance of law and order, foreign affairs, and defence. These have been provided by the governments of all civilized countries for many centuries. There are the social services, such as education, public health, welfare, public housing, social insurance, and public assistance. These are relatively modern hi their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Solandt</surname>
                           <given-names>O. M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>ONE OF THE MOST DISTINCTIVE features of our times has been the rise of the scientistengineer to positions of importance, both in the management of industry and, more importantly, in the shaping of political events throughout the world. Dr. Augustus Braun Kinzel is the epitome of this dynamic and effective group of engineer-scientists who are supplying the technological leadership that has put the United States ahead of the world. He has also helped to supply the sane and friendly outlook that has made the United States such a good neighbour to Canada and to the world.</p>
                     <p>One of the conventional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Industrial research:</title>
                     <subtitle>why, how, and what</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kinzel</surname>
                           <given-names>Augustus B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WE LIVE IN a changing world. This platitude was probably first uttered by Adam as he led Eve out of the Garden of Eden. As with all platitudes, the truth still holds. Research has brought about many of the changes. Organized research, which has itself been made possible by changes and increases in education, communication, and organization, has vastly accelerated the rate of change.</p>
                     <p>Organized research is truly a twentieth-century phenomenon. Before then the individual could cope with an individual project. Today, a whole team effort is required to come up with the answer to problems, many times larger in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bonneau</surname>
                           <given-names>Louis-Philippe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>LORSQUE ON FAIT un séjour quelque peu prolongé dans un pays étranger, on prend l’habitude de lire les journaux avec attention et intérêt. J’ai vécu l’expérience suivante en France durant l’été de 1959. Les journaux du temps étaient pleins de deux sujets. Le premier se rapportait à un crime perpétré dans le bois de Fontainebleau. Ce n’est pas, bien sûr, à ce fait divers que je pense, mais bien plutôt au second qui prenait une allure intéressante pour un étranger. Il s’agissait du projet d’implantation, par la firme américaine Libby’s, d’une usine de conserverie dans le Midi de la France.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>La diffusion de la connaissance technique, impetus de progrès</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Armand</surname>
                           <given-names>Louis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IL EST DEVENU un lieu commun de dire que notre époque est celle de l’accélération des transformations des sociétés humaines, et que les changements survenus dans les domaines les plus divers des activités des hommes -depuis la guerre jusqu’aux spectacles destinés à leur information ou à leur délassement -se sont modifiés en un siècle plus que pendant les dix ou même vingt siècles précédents. Cette constatation impose, cependant, des réflexions de type très différent, embrassant l’ensemble des disciplines intellectuelles.</p>
                     <p>Ces disciplines ne sont pas toutes aussi poussées qu’elles le mériteraient car, si les sciences physiques et naturelles font nécessairement l’objet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Charbonneau</surname>
                           <given-names>Real</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>L’EXPANSION DES COMMUNICATIONS, le problème de la faim, les progrès des sciences et des techniques, le développement de la création artistique, les activités cosmiques, l’accès la liberté et à la participation démocratique : autant de réalités auxquelles auront à faire face les générations futures, et dans lesquelles nous sommes déjà engagés. A ce moment de l’histoire humaine, l’éducation est d’une importance critique.</p>
                     <p>M. K. Helveg Petersen vient d’un pays, le Danemark, bien connu pour ses initiatives dans les secteurs de la coopération et de l’éducation des adultes. Durant une carrière bien remplie, M. Petersen a occupé les postes-clés dans les</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>New trends in education</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Petersen</surname>
                           <given-names>K. Helveg</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE 1960s can be called the decade of education, because a great number of changes and reforms have taken place and are taking place all over the world, in order to meet the increasing demands from a society which itself is changing rapidly. This growing awareness of the role of education meets with increasing demands for well educated and specialized people. Governments realize that they have an obligation to provide the means for an efficient educational system. It is characteristic that parliaments and governments really begin to listen when shown that expansion in education provides for economic growth. Generally speaking,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Affleck</surname>
                           <given-names>R. T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>PEOPLE IN MONTREAL feel that the enormous impact and enormous success of Expo in many ways transcends architecture as such. Professor Bruno Zevi in his life and his work is an example of an architect who transcends architecture. This one can see in a moment when one examines his activities as a historian, a scholar, a professor, a writer, a journalist, and a practising architect, planner, and consultant. He has been involved in Expo as a consultant to the Italian pavilion. He has been involved in direct education in a very meaningful way at the University of Rome as professor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Architecture 1967:</title>
                     <subtitle>progress or regression?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zevi</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruno</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IT is QUITE EVIDENT that I would not be discussing such a controversial subject as “Architecture 1967: Progress or Regression?” were it not for a fortuitous but significant coincidence. The year 1967 is not only the Canadian Centennial, a very happy event, but also the third centenary of a tragic episode in architectural history. In 1667 Francesco Borromini, perhaps the greatest architect of the Baroque period, committed suicide. Why? we ask ourselves. Was he neurotic, sexually frustrated, unhappily married? Actually he killed himself because he felt and knew that everything he had been struggling to accomplish during his life was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gauvin</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>LINUS PAULING was born in Oregon and was educated at Oregon State College where he obtained a Bachelor’s degree in Chemical Engineering in 1922. The following year he married Ava Helen Miller. In addition to being a constant source of inspiration during the next forty-five years, Mrs. Pauling has, in recent times, become a collaborator in her husband’s work for world peace.</p>
                     <p>In 1922 Dr. Pauling went to the California Institute of Technology where he obtained a PH. D. degree in 1925. He was to remain on the teaching staff of this institution continuously for almost forty years (until 1963),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Science and the world of the future</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pauling</surname>
                           <given-names>Linus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I SHALL DISCUSS the subject “Science and the World of the Future” in several ways. I shall first talk about some aspects of the progress of science during recent years, especially during the last fifty years, while I have been watching what has been going on and have also been taking part in it. I shall then attempt to make some efforts at a forecast about the progress of science in the future, what the impact of science on the world has been during recent decades, and, finally, what the impact of science might be on the world of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marion</surname>
                           <given-names>Léo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>ACADEMICIAN FRANTIŠEK ŠORM Was born in Prague in 1913, and studied chemistry at the Higher School of Chemistry and Technology of that city, where he obtained a Doctor’s degree in 1936.</p>
                     <p>Professor Šorm began his career in industry, first as a research chemist in the Skoda Works at Pilsen, and later in the same capacity at the former Society of Chemical and Metallurgical Products. After the war he taught habilitation at the Polytechnical School of Prague in the field of organic chemistry and organic technology, and was given the rank of professor in 1946. In 1950 he was appointed professor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>How to fool the cell (antimetabolites and analogues)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Šorm</surname>
                           <given-names>František</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MAN AND HIS WORLD – the theme of this world exposition – must appeal to the mind and heart of every scientist. It is the very essence of science, and its historic mission, to explore the laws of the world which surrounds man, to learn to use these laws and through their use to govern the world for the benefit of man. Science frees humanity from blind dependence on the play of natural and social forces and opens the road to a happier future for coming generations. It is for this reason that the series of science lectures at this world exposition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Krotkov</surname>
                           <given-names>G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>PROTEINS HAVE BEEN attracting the attention of biologists for many years. Being extremely varied, complex, and unstable, these substances could be studied from many different points of view and using different techniques. However, a Chinese proverb says : “There are many paths to the top of the mountain, but the view is always the same.”</p>
                     <p>One of the paths that has been followed extensively by Professor Katchalski involves the use of synthetic polypeptides, made up of polyamino acids of known structure and composition. Assuming that such polypeptides are similar to very primitive and simple proteins, it is possible, therefore, to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The role of proteins and nucleic acids in determining life processes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Katchalski</surname>
                           <given-names>Ephraim</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>WHEN I WAS A STUDENT of botany at the Hebrew University, I had many occasions to observe the beauty of flowers, plants, and trees while roaming in the Jerusalem hills and the Judean desert. I was fascinated by the complexity of living organisms and the intricate ways in which they perform so many functions. I tried to understand these functions in a somewhat deeper way than is required of a student, but I soon realized that I would first have to study chemistry, physics, and mathematics before trying to grapple with these complicated processes. I thus spent many years in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Penfield</surname>
                           <given-names>Wilder</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FRANK MACFARLANE BURNET Was born in 1899 at Traralgon, Victoria, Australia, the son of the manager of the Colonial Bank there. He entered Geelong College and in 1922 graduated in medicine from the University of Melbourne. He secured his doctorate in medicine in 1923 and became resident pathologist at the Melbourne Hospital. At that time Charles Kellaway, the director of the Walter and Eliza Hall Institute, recognized the remarkable ability of the young pathologist.</p>
                     <p>In 1926 Burnet studied bacteriophage at the Lister Institute in London under Charles Martin, and thus began his investigations in the field of virology, which were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Immunological tolerance:</title>
                     <subtitle>its bearing on organ transplantation and autoimmune disease</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burnet</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank Macfarlane</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>EVERYONE, doctor and layman alike, is aware of the current interest in the transplantation of organs from one human being to another. For reasons which are fairly obvious, the kidney is of special importance in this respect. I can well remember a patient I had when I was an interne in the Melboure Hospital forty-four years ago. She was a married woman in her early thirties with two young children – a very attractive, intelligent person. The previous year she had had a kidney removed for multiple stones and now it was evident from the X-ray that the same process was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robertson</surname>
                           <given-names>H. Rocke</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MOST OF us are aware that bacteria are very small and very numerous. We know that they are to be found everywhere. Some idea of their size may be gained if one considers that the number of bacteria that would normally be found in a colony the size of a typewritten full stop is approximately equal to the number of people that attend Expo on a good day. People, by and large, are aware that bacteria are both useful and harmful; harmful insofar as they can produce a host of diseases – in earlier days the most dreaded diseases and nowadays</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Report to Metchnikoff</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wood</surname>
                           <given-names>William Barry</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MAN’S WORLD teems with potentially lethal bacteria. It is not inappropriate, therefore, to consider on this occasion how phagocytic cells defend man, and other animals, against bacterial diseases. Evidence that phagocytes might serve as protective cells was first provided by an experiment on starfish larvae performed in 1882 by the Russian zoologist Elie Metchnikoff (Fig. 1). Here is his own account of the experiment:¹ One day when the whole family had gone to a circus to see some extraordinary performing apes, I remained alone with my microscope, observing the life in the mobile cells of a transparent starfish larva, when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blain</surname>
                           <given-names>Emile</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DEPUIS 1935, le professeur Stanislas de Sèze oriente ses travaux, ses recherches et son enseignement hospitalier vers l’étude des affections rhumatologiques. En 1946, il devient professeur agrégé. En 1953, il prend la direction du Centre rhumatologique Viggo Petersen de l’hôpital Lariboisière. Après avoir été pendant quelques années professeur d’histoire de la médecine, il est maintenant professeur de clinique rhumatologique à la Faculté de médecine de Paris. Auteur d’une vingtaine de volumes et de huit cents publications dans sa discipline médicale, il participe activement au mouvement rhumatologique dans le monde contemporain. Il fait partie de l’Académie nationale de médecine, et il</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Un siècle de rhumatologie:</title>
                     <subtitle>progrès des connaissances sur les problèmes du rhumatisme de 1867 à 1967</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Sèze</surname>
                           <given-names>Stanislas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>EN CHOISISSANT CE THÈME, nous dous sommes proposés de montrer quels étonnants progrès marquèrent l’évolution de la médecine pendant les cent années qui vont de 1867 à 1967, date de l’Exposition de Montréal. Cherchant des exemples dans la spécialité qui est la nôtre, la rhumatologie, nous avons choisi de retracer, entre ces deux dates, l’évolution des idées sur la goutte, la sciatique, le rhumatisme articulaire aigu, les rhumatismes articulaires chroniques.</p>
                     <p>En 1867, la goutte est une maladie bien connue des médecins. Guillaume de Baillou en 1647 l’a distinguée du rhumatisme. Sydenham en 1683 en a donné une description clinique restée</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Coutu</surname>
                           <given-names>Lucien</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CERTAINS PARMI NOUS se rappelleront qu’entre les deux guerres, le professeur Emile Sergent, grand spécialiste français des maladies pulmonaires, avait, avec la collaboration de quelques amis canadiens comme les professeurs Dubé, Albert Lesage et Télesphore Parizeau, crée un comité dont le but était de faciliter l’accès des médecins canadiens aux hôpitaux universitaires français pour y poursuivre des études à titre de résidents dans les divers services médicaux et chirurgicaux. A la mort du professeur Sergent, Monsieur le Professeur Kourilsky, qui était alors l’élève de ce maître eminent, décida de prendre la relève et chercha par tous les moyens à intensifier</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>La médecine est une science de régulation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kourilsky</surname>
                           <given-names>Raoul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>LE TITRE DE CETTE CONFÉRENCE a de quoi surprendre -peut-être même est-il choquant pour certains d’entre vous ? La médecine est-elle donc une science ? N’est-elle plus cet art, qui selon la définition classique, a pour but la conservation de la santé et la guérison des maladies ? C’est sur ce point qu’il nous faut d’abord réfléchir. «L’esprit -dit Claude Bernard dans son<italic>Introduction à l’étude de la médecine expérimentale</italic>¹ – a naturellement des tendances systématiques, et c’est pour cela que l’on cherche plutôt à s’accorder sur les mots que sur les choses. » (p. 249) C’est ce que je prendrai</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leduc</surname>
                           <given-names>André</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>LE PROFESSEUR ERIC MARTIN, à qui je demandais récemment de me fournir quelques notes bibliographiques, me faisait remarquer qu’il est toujours désagréable de parler de soimême lorsqu’on est très conscient du peu d’importance de la personne humaine. En réplique à cette observation, je n’ai pu trouver plus approprié que cette phrase d’Antoine de St-Exupéry, phrase qui est maintenant presque devenue lieu commun tellement elle fut citée : « Etre un homme c’est sentir qu’en posant sa pierre, on contribue à bâtir l’Univers.</p>
                     <p>» Cette citation, à mon point de vue, ne peut définer plus exactement le rôle joué par chacune</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.51</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Le progrès et la santé de l’homme</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Le Progrès (avec un P majuscule), dit le Robert « c’est l’évolution de l’humanité, de la civilisation, considérée dans son ensemble, comme se rapprochant d’un idéal. » C’est une définition plus restrictive que formule Paul Valéry quand il dit : « Je me suis essayé autrefois à me faire une idée positive de ce que l’on nomme le progrès. Eliminant donc toute considération d’ordre moral, politique, esthétique, le progrès me parut se réduire à l’accroissement très rapide et très sensible de la puissance (mécanique) utilisable par les hommes ou à celui de la précision qu’ils peuvent atteindre dans leurs prévisions.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.52</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Volkoff</surname>
                           <given-names>George M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>PROFESSOR HIDEKI YUKAWA was born in Tokyo sixty years ago. He received his education in Kyoto, obtaining his Master’s degree at the age of 22. He then was a lecturer and assistant professor at the Universities of Osaka and Kyoto. At the early age of 27 he conceived and published a piece of work which later led to his being awarded the Nobel Prize in physics. He then proceeded to complete his Doctorate degree, and was appointed full professor at the University of Kyoto in 1939. In 1948 he came to the United States, where he visited the Institute for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.53</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Creative thinking in science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yukawa</surname>
                           <given-names>Hideki</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MAN AND HIS WORLD is a theme which has many and immensely diverse aspects. Nobody can take up this theme in all its aspects. In this lecture I will confine myself to Man and His Science. Even this is too broad to be dealt with in a limited time. I shall further narrow the subject later on, but for awhile let us dwell on the role played by science in shaping the world as the environment of man.</p>
                     <p>What we call environment today is not simply the part of nature which happens to surround man. Man builds houses, manufactures clothing,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.54</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Whitehead</surname>
                           <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>ACADEMICIAN NIKOLAI GENNADIEVICH BASOV was born in Usman, near Voronezh, the son of a professor of forestry. His schooling was interrupted by the war and it was not until 1945 that he entered university. He graduated in 1950 in theoretical and experimental physics from the Moscow Institute of Physical Engineers. During his last two undergraduate years and in the three postgraduate years which followed, Academician Basov established his association with the P. N. Lebedev Physical Institute of the Academy of Sciences and with Professor A. M. Prokhorov with whom he was to do the research for which he is internationally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.55</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Quantum electronics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Basov</surname>
                           <given-names>N. G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IT WOULD BE INTERESTING to know the prospects for the development of quantum electronics, but I do not think they can yet be foretold. In spite of its rapid development and large practical contribution, quantum electronics is not yet a formed scientific trend. In most cases, where the action of quantum devices depends on certain physical limits, these limits are not yet fixed. We cannot yet distinctly answer the simplest questions: are there any limits to the monochromaticity and coherence of radiation, and how do they depend on energy and radiation frequency? How far can we go into the high-frequency</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.56</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Herzberg</surname>
                           <given-names>G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>PROFESSOR H. B. G. CASIMIR is known throughout the world for his fundamental contributions to theoretical physics. He was a student of the late Professor Ehrenfest at Leyden University in Holland. Ehrenfest was an extraordinary teacher who saw to it that his outstanding students had an opportunity to visit other centres of physics and meet the foremost workers in the field. I happened to be at Gottingen University thirty-eight years ago, at the time when Ehrenfest had come there for several weeks bringing along two young students, Casimir and Uhlenbeck. It was here that I had the first opportunity to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.57</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Low temperatures and their applications</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Casimir</surname>
                           <given-names>H. B. G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>HEAT IS A MODE OF MOTION. Even in its most simple form this idea helps us to understand the influence of temperature on the properties of matter. If we heat a solid the motion of atoms becomes more and more violent until they break up their fixed arrangement: the solid melts. If we heat the liquid still further, the atoms will escape still further from their mutual ties: the liquid evaporates. Conversely, if we cool down a gas at constant pressure it will first become a liquid, then a solid. Low temperature physics in its early days was concerned with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.58</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Uffen</surname>
                           <given-names>R. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>365</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DR. J. TUZO WILSON, Professor of Geophysics and Director of the Institute of Earth Sciences in the University of Toronto, is an unusual and energetic man. The only Canadian to be included in this lecture series, he has earned the right not only by virtue of his international reputation as a prolific and original writer, but also because of the part he played as president of the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics during the International Geophysical Year of 1957-58. Many will recall the excitement in the fall of 1957 during the meetings of the IUGG which were held in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.59</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Terre des hommes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilson</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Tuzo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE GREATEST ENTERPRISE in the field of research and development today is the attempt to land on the moon. Naturally astronomers, geologists, and geophysicists have been consulted about what to expect there, but unfortunately planetary science has not been developed and has proved an uncertain guide. Before the first landings of mechanical devices and cameras on the moon, no one knew whether the moon was thick with dust or not. Before close photographs were taken of Mars, it was widely supposed to be covered with canals, although some astronomers had speculated that these might be optical illusions. Photographs show that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.60</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harrison</surname>
                           <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MME VALERIE TROITSKAYA has a doc torate in physical and mathematical sciences, and is chief of the department of the electromagnetic field in the Institute of Physics of the Earth in Moscow. This group co-ordinates the investigations of rapid variations of the earth’s magnetic field. To see Mme Troitskaya in her Moscow laboratory, as I did recently, takes a bit of luck, because she is responsible for overseeing a network of magnetic observatories extending over the whole of the Soviet Union and Mongolia. Moreover, she has helped out in various African countries as well as making studies in the French</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.61</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>We and the sun</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Troitskaya</surname>
                           <given-names>Valerie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I SHALL DISCUSS some of the main scientific concepts of the problems of solar terrestrial relationships (STR), which originated with the first man-made satellites, and have been studied by the united and co-ordinated efforts of nations in several international enterprises during the last decade. I shall also mention some of the newborn practices in the organization of research in geophysics. Then I shall stress that for the future use of cosmic space it is most important to combine a wealth of continuous geophysical surface observations with direct measurements in cosmic space carried out by space probes. In connection with geophysical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.62</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hogg</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>411</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AN EARLIER SPEAKER in this Noranda Series, Professor Carl Friedrich, noted that it was a constitutional right in Bavaria to enjoy the beauties of nature. Astronomers certainly agree with this idea. I think they would almost like to make it stronger, even compulsory. But the points of light issuing from the heavens need to be interpreted with knowledge. Today we are fortunate to have Professor Hermann Bondi to interpret them for us.</p>
                     <p>When Professor Bondi, who is one of the foremost investigators in the field of cosmology, accepted the invitation of Expo to participate in the Noranda Lecture Series, he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxmbvr.63</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Cosmology, enduring and changing features</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bondi</surname>
                           <given-names>Hermann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>413</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MY SUBJECT in this lecture is perhaps more concerned with the human reaction to cosmology rather than with cosmology itself, since I have become more and more fascinated with the way the human muid responds to changes and advances in science. Cosmology excites particularly strong, varied and interesting responses, for the subject matter is the structure and history of the universe as a whole. It is therefore not in the least surprising that people have been fascinated by it for thousands of years. Nor is it surprising that it belongs among the most speculative and rapidly varying subjects in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
