<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg7fc</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">ML410.B25W5 1992</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bartók, Béla, 1881–1945</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Music of Béla Bartók</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WILSON</surname>
               <given-names>PAUL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>1992</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300051117</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300237955</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1992</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xp3tqk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this book, Paul Wilson presents a new theoretical and analytical approach to the music of Béla Bartók, Hungary's most famous composer and a key figure in twentieth-century music. Wilson explains his theory and the applies it to five important pieces: the Sonata for Piano, the Third Quartet, and movements from the Fifth Quartet, the Sonata for Two Pianos and Percussion, and the Concerto for Orchestra.</p>
         <p>According to Wilson, earlier critics of Bartók's music have often sought to discover an unvarying precompositional system that accounted for individual musical events. Wilson's approach is different in that he develops a way to explore each work within the musical contexts that the work itself creates and sustains. Wilson begins by discussing a number of fundamental musical materials that Bartók employed throughout his oeuvre. Using these materials as foundations, he then describes a series of flexible, behaviorally defined harmonic functions and a model of pitch hierarchy based on the functions and on several connective designs. Wilson shows how these hierarchical structures provide meaningful forces for coherence and for dynamism and progressional drive in the music. After analyzing the five works from Bartók's oeuvre, he concludes by explaining the philosophical similarities between his theory and the work of David Lewin and Charles Taylor in the related fields of perception and hermeneutics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="222"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>First Steps toward a Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book presents a theoretical account of the music of Béla Bartok. Constantly implicit in such an account is the tension between two conflicting demands: that the account be theoretical, that is, composed of (among other things) broadly applicable general statements directed to certain kinds of musical understanding; and that it be firmly situated within the detailed context formed by Bartok’s works and life, as that context has grown in our knowledge over the past fifty years and more. Where it is necessary to choose between these demands, generality must give way to context. But the book attempts to avoid</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>FUNDAMENTALS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Source Sets, Harmonic Function, Privileged Pattern, and Context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter discusses four elements fundamental to the book’s approach to Bartok’s music. That these elements are fundamental does not imply that, once described, they are to be forgotten or necessarily subsumed in some higher theoretical synthesis. Although this part of the theory is foundational for the part that follows in chapter 2, there are works by Bartok for which these fundamental concepts are the only ones that an analysis using the theory can successfully employ. In any case the topics discussed in this chapter are a constant presence in every analysis undertaken in Part 11.</p>
                     <p>If one thinks of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>A MODEL OF HIERARCHICAL STRUCTURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The mention of hierarchical pitch structure immediately and appropriately calls forth the imposing figure of Heinrich Schenker. His immensely important (if not universally accepted) theories of the structure of tonal music are the inescapable source for any subsequent inquiry into this general area. Unfortunately for those who wish to apply his ideas to newer music, the prolongational model does not seem to travel well outside the common-practice literature for which it was designed. The introduction alluded to efforts by Felix Salzer and Roy Travis to employ that model in Bartok’s music and in other music of the twentieth century.</p>
                     <p>As</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>THE SONATA FOR PIANO</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The series of analyses begins with the Sonata for Piano (1926).¹ This work has special significance on several grounds. Though Bartok had written important music for the piano prior to 1926, this is his first and only work for solo piano entitled “Sonata.” It stands as the first in a series of three important works for the piano written in 1926, the others being the suite<italic>Out of Doors</italic>and the First Piano Concerto. The first movement is also, as mentioned in the introduction, his first major work after World War 1 to exhibit a strong emphasis on tonal centers.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>THE THIRD STRING QUARTET</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bartok completed the Third String Quartet in September 1927. Shortly thereafter he entered the score in a competition for new chamber music sponsored by the Musical Fund Society of Philadelphia, and the work is dedicated to that Society. He received half of the $3000 first prize, the other half going to Alfredo Casella. In London on February 19, 1929, the Waldbauer-Kerpely Quartet gave the piece its premiere. Among Bartok’s previous works the clearest precursor of the Quartet in form and treatment of material is the Second Sonata for Violin and Piano of 1922. The Quartet is in my view one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>THE FIFTH STRING QUARTET, II AND IV</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus in this chapter is again on two movements that share thematic or harmonic material, but in this case the two are linked within a broader, carefully planned formal design. The design is Bartok’s famous “bridge” or “arch” plan, and the Fifth Quartet is one of three works that Bartok names as employing the general plan (the others being the Fourth Quartet and the Second Piano Concerto). He has also provided an analysis of the Fifth Quartet which describes in some detail the plan for the work and the place of these two movements in it.¹ As is well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>THE SONATA FOR TWO PIANOS AND PERCUSSION, I AND II</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Sonata for Two Pianos and Percussion was the product of a commission to compose a chamber work for the tenth anniversary of the Basel chapter of the International Society for Contemporary Music. Bartok wrote the Sonata in Budapest during July and August of 1937. It has long held a central place in his oeuvre and in the contemporary two-piano literature.</p>
                     <p>The most important issues for the analysis are three: the explicit presence and use of octatonic sets and subsets to provide harmonic structures in several different ways; the interaction, especially in movement 11, of these sets with the chromatic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>THE CONCERTO FOR ORCHESTRA, I</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The final analysis in the book returns to a work on a very large scale. In the Concerto for Orchestra we find an obvious increase in the stability and clarity of tonal function at several levels of structure. Some functions appear in almost traditional common-practice form. Whether the clarity of function supports an equally increased clarity of structural overlay remains to be seen.</p>
                     <p>Bartok composed the Concerto for Orchestra in the late summer and fall of 1943, in response to a commission from Serge Koussevitzky. The work received its premiere performance on December 1, 1943, with Koussevitzky conducting the Boston</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The analyses completed, this final chapter carries out four tasks by way of conclusion. First, it surveys the analytical findings in a comprehensive way, stepping back from the details of each piece. Second, it places the theory of part I within a larger model of musical understanding. Next comes a brief exploration of the logical and conceptual connections among the theory’s separate parts. Finally, the chapter takes a quick look at a still larger view of certain kinds of investigation connected with this one.</p>
                     <p>The last three of these tasks may seem like parts of an outline for an epistemological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX:</title>
                     <subtitle>ERNŐ LENDVAI AND THE AXIS SYSTEM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3tqk.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
