<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xs3b</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>World Christianity as Public Religion</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Editors</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BARRETO</surname>
               <given-names>RAIMUNDO C.</given-names>
               <suffix>JR.</suffix>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CAVALCANTE</surname>
               <given-names>RONALDO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DA ROSA</surname>
               <given-names>WANDERLEY P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506433714</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506433721</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>MINNEAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tm7hn1"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This volume stresses world Christianity as a form of public religion, identifying areas for intercultural engagement. Divided into five sections, each formed by two chapters, this volume covers themes such as the reimagination of theology, doctrine, and ecumenical dialogue in the context of world Christianity; Global South perspectives on pluralism and intercultural communication; how epistemological shifts promoted by liberation theology and its dialogue with cultural critical studies have impacted discourses on religion, ethics, and politics; conversations on gender and church from Brazilian and German perspectives; and intercultural proposals for a migratory epistemology that recenters the experience of migration as a primary location for meaning.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="230"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kay</surname>
                           <given-names>James F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Princeton Theological Seminary is honored to join with the Faculdade Unida de Vitoria in supporting the launch of this first volume in the Fortress Press series World Christianity and Global Religion. Historically speaking, it is difficult to imagine either the phenomenon or the emerging academic field of world Christianity without the nineteenth-century missionary movement fueled by such student fervor at the colleges, universities, and seminaries of the early American republic, including Princeton. Out of this movement, ecumenical partnerships across Protestant denominations were forged, and the study of world religions arose in order to translate the Christian message into the idioms</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                     <subtitle>The World Christianity and Public Religion Series</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="other" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARRETO</surname>
                           <given-names>RAIMUNDO C.</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                        <role>SERIES EDITOR</role>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>World Christianity as Public Religion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARRETO</surname>
                           <given-names>RAIMUNDO C.</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a book about the public nature of religion in world perspective. It is not confined to the emerging field of public theology. Instead, it assumes that there is a public reality where public theology emerges. In an important study of Latin American liberation theology, Brazilian-French scholar Michael Lowy distinguished between liberation theology as a body of literature and the milieu in which it was formed, i.e., the broad network of social movements whose praxis gave birth to liberation theology. He called that broader movement “liberationist Christianity.”¹ According to him, liberationist Christianity preexists liberation theology. The latter is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>An Essay on Theology, Doctrine, and Ecumenical Dialogue</title>
                     <subtitle>Protestant Christian Perspectives in Latin America</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAVALCANTE</surname>
                           <given-names>RONALDO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the accomplishments of modernity was the openness to a democratic dialogue between social classes and strata previously unmindful of each other. Otherness was neglected because of deeply ingrained prejudices. A dialogue implies a wish for mutual regard between concerned parties. Such accomplishment has finally come into religious culture, theology, and religious studies through an emphasis on knowledge of the other and the other’s perspective. Despite its limitations and even some backward steps, Protestantism played an important role in the early moments of this dialogue by fostering the study of comparative religion, thus breaking down Christianity’s self-imposed hegemony and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Limits and Possibilities for the Ecumenical Movement Today</title>
                     <subtitle>A Latin American View</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DO NASCIMENTO CUNHA</surname>
                           <given-names>MAGALI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The marks left on the contemporary history of Christianity by the international ecumenical movement of the twentieth century are undeniable. Among the marks deserving to be remembered and celebrated are, first, the search for an answer to the demands of unity in the missionary movement, striving “so that the world may believe”; second, the articulations around “practical Christianity” that would overcome historical doctrinal divides; third, the doctrinal dialogue in efforts to produce “faith and order”; and fourth, the joint actions of Christian youth and educators from different churches, confessions, and regional Christian associations.</p>
                     <p>As history unfolds in the wake of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Pluralism, Ecumenism, and Intercultural Communication</title>
                     <subtitle>South African Experiences</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MÜLLER</surname>
                           <given-names>RETIEF</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Twentieth-century Christian ecumenism was a form of globalization with universalistic ideals. It would be safe to suggest, of course, that it was a benign form of globalization, but it was certainly an attempt to find common ground and unify global Christianity to an extent hitherto unknown in the world of religions. In this process of Christian globalization, the World Council of Churches (WCC) reigned supreme.</p>
                     <p>In the contexts of the Cold War, neocolonialism, and colonialism of a special type (as apartheid in South Africa had been described),¹ the WCC made important and decisive statements and contributions to actively promote the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Christianity as a Public Religion</title>
                     <subtitle>Pluralism and Dialogue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SUNG</surname>
                           <given-names>JUNG MO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Faced with situations of injustice and human suffering, people with genuine faith cannot remain indifferent. They must take a stand and engage in movements or struggles for justice and for overcoming oppressive situations and suffering. Such engagement breaks away from the divide established by the modern world between public and private spheres, the latter being the one where religion should play its role. That is why Christian groups engaging in those struggles feel the need for theologies that are not restrained by the modern relegation of religion to the private sphere and eternal life; they search for reasons for their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Theology, Ethics, and Society</title>
                     <subtitle>Latin American Liberation Theologies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RIVERA-PAGÁN</surname>
                           <given-names>LUIS N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Latin American liberation theology was the unforeseen enfant terrible in the academic and ecclesial realms of theological production during the last decades of the twentieth century. It brought to the conversation not only a new theme—liberation—but also a new perspective on doing theology and a novel way of referring to God’s being and action in history. Its project to reconfigure the interplay between religious studies, ethics, and politics became a meaningful topic of analysis and dialogue in the general theological discourse. Many scholars perceive in its emergence a drastic epistemological rupture, a radical change in paradigm, a significant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Beyond Contextualization</title>
                     <subtitle>Gospel, Culture, and the Rise of a Latin American Christianity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BARRETO</surname>
                           <given-names>RAIMUNDO C.</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Religion played a crucial role in European expansionism. Toward the end of the Middle Ages, the rise of the Spanish Empire, fostered by the myth of the Reconquista, blended nationalist and religious motives. According to that myth, “Spain was born as a nation convinced that God had entrusted it with the defense of the Catholic faith against all Muslims, Jews, heretics, and other unbelievers.”¹ Under that banner, the Spaniards invaded and explored the “New World … convinced that this was a sacred trust so that they could bring their religion to the benighted people in these lands.”²</p>
                     <p>Accordingly, modern colonialism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Church and Gender in Germany</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ANDRÉE</surname>
                           <given-names>UTA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was invited to reflect about church and gender as a contribution from the Global North, I immediately thought about the unequal presence and role of women and men within German Protestant churches. Because of this focus, this will not be a representative reflection of the Global North—which is, in my opinion, a highly questionable term—but an attempt to describe the situation of a very specific reality of a powerful church in a secularized country. As I begin my reflection, I want to note that I find it interesting, as an individual from the Global North, to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Women and Academic Theological Education</title>
                     <subtitle>A Reflection on the Experience of Female Students from the Faculdade Unida de Vitória-ES (Brazil)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ULRICH</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAUDETE BEISE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay, I aim to offer a reflection on women and academic theological education based on the experience of female students from the Faculdade Unida de Vitória, in the state of Espírito Santo, Brazil. Academic theological education is an important step for women to achieve ecclesial agency. My reflection is based on narrative interviews conducted with female students concerning the impact of theological studies in their own life experiences. Academic theological training enhances the self-esteem of women, empowers them, and provides them with tools for reflection-action-reflection in their Christian communities or in other organizational spaces, and it is fundamental</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>A New Frontier</title>
                     <subtitle>Intercultural Communication and the Urgency of a Migratory Epistemology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HARRIS-SMITH</surname>
                           <given-names>YVETTE JOY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Christianity, we move through cultural contexts often. Whenever we recite scripture or sing hymns penned long ago, listen to sermons or read the Bible privately or aloud, we are moving through cultural contexts. The study of World Christianity is interested in the myriad of expressions of the Christian faith as seen across several continents. It is interested in the cultural contexts through which people express their belief in God.¹ Similarly, the field of public religion is interested in the expressions of religious beliefs through behaviors that “have a direct bearing on public order.”² The common thread that connects these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>“Who You Are Does Not Matter in Europe!”</title>
                     <subtitle>African Diaspora Christianities and the Ethical Politics of Wasting Bodies and Unwanted Immigration in Fortress Europe</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ADOGAME</surname>
                           <given-names>AFE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On May 20, 2015, Nicolas Haque anchored the story of sixteen-year-old Senegalese Abdou as he prepared his perilous journey to Europe.¹ This was part of a prolonged Al Jazeera TV documentary<italic>Desperate Journeys</italic>, chronicling a series of woes, misery, and catastrophe in which hundreds of thousands of African and other immigrants, hopeless but with sanguine expectations, are fleeing economic hardship, poverty, natural disasters, ethnic clashes, political oppression, and unwarranted civil strife partly orchestrated by failing governments. By raising a loan of over $3,000 to facilitate the journey organized by individuals in the migration industry, including people smugglers or human traffickers,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7hn1.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
