<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HF1455.A6155 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Foreign economic relations</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Economic policy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Consumption (Economics)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Globalization</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Foreign relations</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization, Modern</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">American influences</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">World politics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Geopolitics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Hegemony</book-title>
         <subtitle>The New Shape Of Global Power</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Agnew</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781592131525</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781592137671</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Temple University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PHILADELPHIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Temple University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt14bsxmk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Hegemony</italic>tells the story of the drive to create consumer capitalism abroad through political pressure and the promise of goods for mass consumption. In contrast to the recent literature on America as empire, it explains that the primary goal of the foreign and economic policies of the United States is a world which increasingly reflects the American way of doing business, not the formation or management of an empire. Contextualizing both the Iraq war and recent plant closings in the U.S., noted author John Agnew shows how American hegemony has created a world in which power is no longer only shaped territorially. He argues in a sobering conclusion that we are consequently entering a new era of global power, one in which the world the US has made no longer works to its singular advantage.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Words matter. Currently, there is much talk and writing about<italic>empire</italic>or<italic>American empire</italic>—words used to describe the dominant force in world politics today.¹ I want to challenge this creeping consensus by proposing a different word to describe the current state of affairs. This word<italic>hegemony</italic>is often confused with empire and frequently appears with such ancillary words as<italic>imperial, imperialist,</italic>and so on, as if they all meant the same thing. Of course, they can be made to mean the same thing. But what if the consensus is fundamentally mistaken about what is actually unique about the current</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Hegemony versus Empire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The United States brought into existence the first fully “market-place society” in history. This is a territorial society in which politics and society operate largely in terms of exchange value rather than use value. A distinction first made by Adam Smith but developed in various ways by later thinkers such as Karl Marx and Karl Polanyi, exchange- versus use-value revolves around the idea that social and political relationships can be based predominantly on either their instrumental value (i.e., as if a price could be placed on them) or their intrinsic/consummatory value (i.e., as if they had unique qualities). Previous societies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>American Hegemony and the New Geography of Power</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In mainstream theories of world politics, the workings of political power are usually seen as a historical constant. They share the view expressed so clearly by Paul Ricoeur that “power does not have much of a history.”¹ At the same time, political power is overwhelmingly associated with “the modern state,” to which all states are supposed to correspond, but which is usually a version of France, England, or the United States regarded as a unitary actor equivalent to an individual person. Political power is envisioned in terms of units of territorial sovereignty (at least for the so-called Great Powers) that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Placing American Hegemony</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The twentieth century was by many accounts the American century. The twenty-first century, however, is not likely to be. Between these two sentences lies the history of American hegemony. In this chapter I show how American hegemony started. It began at home. Only later did it extend outward, and it was the U.S. interventions in the two world wars of the twentieth century that made this possible. After the Second World War in particular, the United States formed NATO and other alliances to contain the former Soviet Union and its allies. This required significant military and political commitments beyond the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>U.S. Constitutionalism or Marketplace Society?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The uniqueness of the United States is often attributed to the structure of its political organization rather than to its political economy. As the first fully modern polity built from scratch, with reference to classical and early modern political theories of republicanism and liberalism, the United States has often been presented as a constitutional model for the world at large. The strand of American political thought associated most closely with President Woodrow Wilson—arguably the founder of modern American political science and the prophet of American global institutionalism—lends itself to world politics not only as a model for emulation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Globalizing American Hegemony</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Globalization” is one of the premier buzz words of the early twenty-first century. In its most general usage it refers to the idea of a world increasingly stretched, shrunk, connected, interwoven, integrated, interdependent, or less territorially divided economically and culturally among national states. It is most frequently seen as an economic-technological process of time-space compression, as a social modernization of increased cultural homogeneity previously national in character scaled up to the world as a whole, or as shorthand for the practices of economic liberalism spontaneously adopted by governments the world over.¹ I do not want to deny the truth in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The New Global Economy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent studies of the world economy invoking the impact of globalization, the idea of “time-space compression” or its equivalents have dominated discussion among geographers and many others.¹ This idea postulates that revolutionary changes in communication and transportation technologies are producing a new global economy. In this chapter I challenge the adequacy of this idea for understanding the course of the contemporary world economy and the new uneven development it is producing. In its place I argue for the importance of the geopolitical role of the United States and the vision of world economic order—<italic>transnational liberalism</italic>—which, post–1970s,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Globalization Comes Home</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The world economy that the United States has created beyond its territorial boundaries is no longer one in which all of America sees a positive reflection. Though the American economy has largely recovered from the worst negative trends of the 1970s and 1980s, there is nevertheless a widespread unease about what the world economy delivers to the United States. As this chapter claims, there is good reason for this. The United States now faces an impasse in its relations with the global economy. This is not to say that the United States uniformly is a victim of its own hegemony.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The terms “globalization” and “imperialism” signify two features of contemporary world politics that are regarded as antagonistic to each other. The former stands for a seemingly autonomous process of globe shrinking or stretching (depending on how you look at it), whereas the latter indicates a self-conscious extraction and movement of profit from some places to others through political domination and coercion more than economic rationality. If advocates of the first tend to have a postmodern, depoliticized view of the world, those of the latter tend to have a profoundly modernist geopolitical view in which dominant states (above all, the United</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt14bsxmk.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
