<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS8147.L6C66 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Love poetry, Canadian (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Women poets, Canadian (English)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canadian poetry (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Canadian poetry (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Women authors</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Writing Lovers</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reading Canadian Love Poetry by Women</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Cook</surname>
               <given-names>Méira</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773527973</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773572270</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen's University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zsk3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In writings by the French post-structuralists, rhetorical tropes such as speechlessness, fragmentation, and deflection testify to the writer's difficulty in broaching the subject of love. Similarly, Cook shows that love poetry proceeds out of a profound failure of language resulting from the opacity of discourse, its lack of neutrality, or the fugitive transparency of reference. Writing Lovers also explores race, ethnicity, age, and sexual identity within the context of the passionate excesses of amatory discourse.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Language of Love:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Oblique Beginning</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his essay “On Love,” Adam Phillips observes that since the language of love borrows its referents from the discourses of theology and epistemology, it is at once relentlessly redemptive and insistently enlightening (40). The lover, like the mystic or the paranoiac, is a reader of signs and wonders: all are terrorized and bewitched by an experience that, in the absence of a transcendental signifier, displaces our contemporary version of the sublime. If this comparison is to provide a useful analogy, then it is possible to concede that we have, in the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries, enshrined literature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Love and Other Unofficial Stories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narrative Prowling in Kristjana Gunnars’ The Prowler</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Prowler</italic>begins at the end of the Second World War on the remote northern island of Iceland. The narrator “prowls” amongst her memories of growing up in a disenfranchised, starving nation that has been successively colonized by a variety of countries: Denmark, the United States, and the Soviet Union. At the same time the reader learns that the murder of an unknown girl has taken place, a murder that is never resolved but that serves as a warning against all unknown “prowlers.” Yet<italic>The Prowler</italic>is also, indeed mostly, about love as what Gunnars’ narrator names that “vulnerable territory”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Possessed by Love:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Metaphoric Production of Desire in Elizabeth Smart’s By Grand Central Station I Sat Down and Wept</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her foreword to<italic>By Grand Central Station I Sat Down and Wept,</italic>Brigid Brophy praises what she names Elizabeth Smart’s “poetic prose” (7), an apt designation since it accounts for both the narrative momentum of the text and its emphasis on metaphor, figurative language, and poetic rhythm.¹ In fact, Smart’s book-length<italic>cri de coeur</italic>conforms to the elements of poetry rather more than to those of prose, since the narrative does not exceed the geometry of a lover’s triangle and much of the so-called plot must be inferred from the narrator’s ecstatic lamentation.² As such, I feel justified in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>In Between:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dionne Brand’s Poetics of Love and Resistance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of creating something nourishing out of nothing much – bread out of stone, revolution out of writing - haunts Brand’s earlier poetry collection<italic>No Language Is Neutral</italic>(1990), much as it does her political manifesto. As a Black¹ lesbian feminist, as a self-proclaimed immigrant (a position she explores<italic>in Winter Epigrams</italic>[1983] and<italic>Land To Light On</italic>[i997]),² as a politically charged writer, Brand is multiply displaced from white patriarchal heterosexual discourse, from what she despises as a “secret and cowardly language of normalcy and affirmation” (<italic>Bread</italic>23). In the same essay she proclaims the need for writing that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Love Letters from an Unmade Bed:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dorothy Livesay’s Poetics of Disquiet</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If absence is the first premise of desire, then the love letter is the perfect motive of its expression because it is the form of writing that transforms the beloved’s absence into what Barthes has named “an ordeal of abandonment” through a fugitive episode of language (<italic>A Lover’s Discourse</italic>13). Intercepted between the two locutions of presence and absence, the lover/writer addresses her beloved, absent to her as object, at the moment that s/he is most available, most impelling as referent.</p>
                     <p>To speak of love is itself a<italic>jouissance,</italic>proclaims Lacan (<italic>Feminine Sexuality</italic>142), and the love letter addresses this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>On the Line:</title>
                     <subtitle>Revenge as Confessional Strategy in Kristjana Gunnars’ Carnival of Longing and Nicole Markotic’s “No Goodbye, Just:”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The narrative of the love story is traditionally structured as an ordeal of abandonment prolonged by the promise of return and resolved through metaphors of seduction, the configurations of language that release the particular from its burden of meaning. Amorous discourse is characterized by the variety of narratives that follow in the wake of this abandonment. As devotees of the genre may observe, the “story” is already over by the time Heloise composes her first passionate epistle to Abelard, or, in a more contemporary example, when the narrator of “The Tennessee Waltz” begins his plaintive hurting song. The romance is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Bone Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Love and Breath in Louise Bernice Halfe’s Blue Marrow</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gunnars’ privileging of breath and voice and Markotic’s preoccupation with acoustics by way of the telephone both gain resonance from a comparison - however dissymetrical, to recall Mieke Bal’s idea -with Louise Bernice Halfe’s long poem<italic>Blue Marrow.</italic>In Halfe’s narrative, storytelling and orality provide the medium in which love breaks through the text, breaks open and into a text, and provides texture to the long story of dispossession and cultural appropriation that punctuates this account. Not an explicitly amorous discourse, Halfe’s narrative begins with her narrator awakening in the crook of her husband’s arm and ends shortly after this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Speaking in Tongues:</title>
                     <subtitle>Daphne Marlatt’s Answering Touch or How To Sign a Love Letter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The nouns “tissue” and “text” originate from the selfsame root, Marlatt reveals in her essay “Self-Representation and Fictionalysis,” in which she at once fictionalizes autobiography and locates self-representation in the context of “a living tissue we live together with / in” (205). Critics have responded to Marlatt’s textual tissue by emphasizing her “intricate networks” and “labyrinthean structures” (Godard, “Body I” 481), by locating her lyrical, locutionary narratives as a “textual field” intersected by various trajectories (Butling 167), by suggesting that the received cultural script frays in Marlatt’s texts into an infinitely more complex web of connections (Nichols 114), and by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Postscript</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I began obliquely and can end no less so. Discourses of desire are always a<italic>tissu de greffes,</italic>¹ a fabric of grafts in which, writes Kauffman, “something is always added on, borrowed from something else, embroidered” (304). Or alternately lost, left behind, eluded, eroded, avoided, evaded, substituted by metaphor, deferred through metonymy. What remains is the event of love, an impossible, inescapable, and absolutely ambiguous event exceeding all categories of expression and signification while, at the same time, attempting ceaselessly - recklessly, repeatedly - to articulate itself.</p>
                     <p>The desire that suffuses these texts is not fulfilled or surfeited, yet neither</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zsk3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
