<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8c5d</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Latin American Philosophy from Identity to Radical Exteriority</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>VALLEGA</surname>
               <given-names>ALEJANDRO A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253012487</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253012654</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253012651</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Alejandro Arturo Vallega</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzkjc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While recognizing its origins and scope, Alejandro A. Vallega offers a new interpretation of Latin American philosophy by looking at its radical and transformative roots. Placing it in dialogue with Western philosophical traditions, Vallega examines developments in gender studies, race theory, postcolonial theory, and the legacy of cultural dependency in light of the Latin American experience. He explores Latin America's engagement with contemporary problems in Western philosophy and describes the transformative impact of this encounter on contemporary thought.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="296"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Only what is difficult can sustain thought. Today in philosophy one of these difficulties comes from the end of a myth that took philosophy as the child of Western rationalism, with its origins in Greek thought. Philosophy today is changing; the field of philosophy is undergoing a new dawn with the formation and inclusion of world philosophies that bear origins, experiences, overlappings, encroachments, and transformations well beyond the modern North American and European traditions. The new world philosophies open possibilities of unfathomable and fecund thinking as one engages and is exposed to unbridled senses of existence, to lineages, configurations of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Question of a Latin American Philosophy and Its Identity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Simón Bolívar and Leopoldo Zea</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophy and Western culture have been synonymous at least since Hegel’s philosophy of history. Even when philosophy has been ignored, degraded, reappropriated, or put into question and even when philosophers have sought to “destroy” it, philosophy has been taken as a given inseparable from Western culture and born of it. Practically speaking, no one from the West or educated under the Western tradition, no matter how critical of it, would put into question the existence of European, French, German, or Italian philosophy. In Latin America the situation is different: The question that animates the very arising into existence and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Existence and Dependency:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ernesto Mayz Vallenilla’s Phenomenological Analysis of Being Latin American and Augusto Salazar Bondy’s Negative Critique of Latin American Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have just seen, at the heart of Leopoldo Zea’s thought appears Western philosophy as a creative force that results in the domination of other peoples and cultures who have not likewise developed their reflexive rationality. Two major Latin American philosophers who engage directly with the kind of existence that results from experiencing such domination are the Venezuelan Ernesto Mayz Vallenilla and the Peruvian Augusto Salazar Bondy. The first offers a deep phenomenological analysis of the abyssal existence Simón Bolívar introduces in his “Jamaica Letter” when he articulates the difficulty of Latin American existence. Salazar Bondy takes on domination</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Latin American Philosophy and Liberation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Enrique Dussel’s Project of a Philosophy of Liberation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapters we found a call for recognizing Latin American philosophy, which may be traced back to the 1940s and 1950s in the work of Leopoldo Zea, along with other Latin American philosophers such as Arturo Ardao in Uruguay and Francisco Romero in Argentina. For these philosophers the fundamental questions were those of the identity, sense, and possibilities of a Latin American philosophy. As discussed in chapter 2, Salazar Bondy responded to these questions in 1968, and Leopoldo Zea engaged with that negative critique in 1969 in<italic>Latin American Philosophy as Philosophy and No More.</italic>¹ Latin American philosophy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Delimitations . . . of Dussel’s Philosophy of Liberation and Beyond</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout our discussions so far one pressing issue becomes evident as the driving concern behind Latin American thought: the concern with engaging concrete, living Latin American existence. As Dussel points out, it is ultimately life that calls for thought’s liberation. In this chapter I discuss some of the main critiques of Dussel’s thought, all of which are driven by this same concern. As we will see, these critical approaches will raise the question of how to engage the concrete and diverse singularities that compose the general fields Dussel has strategically outlined. What is put in question is the way thought</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Beyond the Domination of the “Coloniality of Power and Knowledge”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Latin America’s Living Ana-Chronic Temporality and the Dissemination of Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapters we have seen a constant attentiveness in Latin American thinkers toward thinking in light of their concrete situation. This situated thought finds a profound opening in Enrique Dussel’s insight concerning Latin American thought as arising out of a radical exteriority beyond the possible control, determination, and manipulation of Western European and North American thought and culture. We also saw that such experience is pre-rational, inasmuch as it ultimately refers us to a sensibility found at the heart of the disposition that differentiates us as human, namely the encounter of other humans in a proximity sustained by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Remaining with the Decolonial Turn:</title>
                     <subtitle>Race and the Limits of the Social-Political Historical Critique in Latin American Thought</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I revisit Quijano’s analysis critically, in order to underline some of the difficulties that come with his historical materialist critique of Western modernity, difficulties that I believe ultimately may undermine the very attempt to the decolonization of consciousness and thought that his analysis intends. My aim is to point toward the possibility for another way of thinking that may contribute to the decoloniality of thought and to the unfolding of philosophies today. This way of thinking takes its departure from a Latin American experience that no longer fits the attempts to establish a place for Latin America</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Yucatán:</title>
                     <subtitle>Thought Situated in Radical Exteriority as a Thinking of Concrete Fluid Singularities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapters led us to a difficult place. Latin American thought is not<italic>about</italic>Latin America but figures a yet unthought delimitation of the very system we have come to know as modernity and modern philosophy. The exposure to this situation offers an opening for thinking from beyond the instrumental rationalism of contemporary modernity, from radical exteriority. Latin America is a concrete living and articulate reality that, as the underside of modernity, displaces the Western North American and European claims to a hegemonic, selfsufficient, and autonomous power and causes a fecund opening for understanding anew philosophical thought. In this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Modernity and Rationality Rethought in Light of Latin American Radical Exteriority and Asymmetric Temporality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hybrid Thinking in Santiago Castro-Gómez</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we gathered a series of conclusions and implications that led to the question of how one may engage the simultaneous ana-chronic or the asymmetric or non-simultaneous simultaneity and the disseminating movement of meanings and forms of life figured by Latin American experience.¹ This question is no longer posed over and against modernity; as we saw, Latin America figures a slipping within and beyond modernity, the underside of modernity. This view is possible because of two seemingly contradictory moments. The first is the possibility of a critique of modernity that arises from a sense of total exteriority</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Thinking in Remarkable Distinctness:</title>
                     <subtitle>Decolonial Thought in Some Key Figures in Contemporary Latin American Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These opening words from Walter Mignolo’s essay “Decolonial Thought: Detachment and Opening (A Manifesto)” capture the fluid and disseminating movement from which and toward which the thought of Dussel, Quijano, and Castro-Gómez have led us.¹ In light of the previous chapters, we are faced with the challenge to think in other ways than those sustained by instrumental rationalism and the coloniality of power, knowledge, and time. In this chapter I first reintroduce the idea of hybrid thinking in Castro-Gómez in order to set up and gain access to the relevance and impact of three contemporary Latin American philosophers. These thinkers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Fecund Undercurrents:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Aesthetic Dimension of Latin American and Decolonial Thought</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout this book I have underlined an issue that accompanies the various discourses of liberation and decolonial thought in Latin America, namely, the issue of its aesthetic dimension. As we saw, Dussel’s philosophy of liberation is based on a pre-rational and pre-linguistic sensibility, a sense of radical exteriority, that distinguishes humans. Quijano exposes a pre-rational disposition or sensibility that sustains the coloniality of power and knowledge. Moreover, as he goes on to uncover and engage ana-chronic simultaneity in Latin American existence, Quijano turns to the writers, poets, and artists of Latin America, who articulate senses of existence beyond and otherwise</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkjc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
