<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Rhetoric of Jesus in the Gospel of Mark</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>YOUNG</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>STRICKLAND</surname>
               <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506433356</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506438474</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>MINNEAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tm7j37"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Young and Strickland analyze the four largest discourses of Jesus in Mark in the context of Greco-Roman rhetoric in an attempt to hear them as a first-century audience would have heard them. The authors demonstrate that, contrary to what some historical critics have suggested, first-century audiences of Mark would have found the discourses of Jesus unified, well-integrated, and persuasive. They also show how these speeches of the Markan Jesus contribute to Mark‘s overall narrative accomplishments.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="416"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Young</surname>
                           <given-names>David M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Strickland</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the dawn of the form-critical era of New Testament scholarship, Rudolf Bultmann confidently described how the discourse material in the Gospel of Mark came together. As with other synoptic material, Bultmann argued, the discourses in Mark are composites of various traditions that came to the evangelist only after a complex history of development. Though the core of some of these traditions may go back to the historical Jesus, their final forms are the results of years of hard use by the church that completely reshaped them into the voice of the church. Mark collected these traditional units,¹ which generally</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>The Discourses of Jesus since Form Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout its nineteen centuries of circulation, the Gospel of Mark has been asked numerous questions.¹ Each generation of admirers and critics has looked to the Gospel for information desired in its own era. As groups and individuals in each milieu bring their peculiar questions to the Gospel, they form methodologies appropriate for finding the answers they seek. Thus, all readings of the Gospel are particular to their own cultural and historical contexts, and all methodologies derive from distinct orientations.</p>
                     <p>In general, the questions twentieth-century Western scholars brought to the discourses of Jesus in the Gospel of Mark were dominated by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The Discourses of Jesus as Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goal of this study is to hear the discourses of Jesus in the Gospel of Mark as first-century audiences would have heard them. Though attempting to read the Gospel in terms of its own cultural/literary milieu, we are, of course, nonetheless employing a contemporary reading model that we find compatible with our goals and with the text under consideration.¹ We assume a reading model similar to that generally proposed by the reader-response critics, especially by Wolfgang Iser in his seminal<italic>The Act of Reading</italic>.² In this model, understanding, or as Iser calls it, “actualization” or “meaning effect,” occurs at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Satan Cannot Cast Out Satan (Mark 3:20–35)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>And he comes into a house, and again a crowd gathers, so that they were not even able to eat. And having heard, his family came out to grab him, for they were saying “He is mad!” And the scribes who had come down from Jerusalem were saying “He has Beelzebul!” and “By the prince of demons he casts out demons!”</p>
                     <p>And calling them in comparisons, he says to them,</p>
                     <p>“What power has</p>
                     <p>Satan to cast out?</p>
                     <p>And if a kingdom were against itself divided,</p>
                     <p>No power to stand would that kingdom have.</p>
                     <p>And if a house were against itself</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Whoever Has Ears Had Better Listen!</title>
                     <subtitle>(Mark 4:1–34)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>And again he began to teach beside the sea. And the greatest crowd gathers around him so that he was getting into a boat to sit on the sea, and all the crowd was next to the sea, upon the earth. And he was teaching them many things in comparisons. And he was saying to them in his teaching:</p>
                     <p>“Listen! Look!</p>
                     <p>The sower went out to sow, and this happened while he sowed:</p>
                     <p>One fell on the path, and the birds came and ate it up.</p>
                     <p>And another fell on rocks, which did not have much earth.</p>
                     <p>And immediately it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>What Defiles a Person?</title>
                     <subtitle>(Mark 6:53–7:23)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>And having crossed over to the earth, they came into Gennesaret and moored. And after they came out of the boat immediately the whole region, recognizing him, went running through and began to bring the sick on their mats to the place where he was.</p>
                     <p>And wherever he entered villages, cities, or fields, in the marketplaces they would place the sick and beg him that they might touch the hem of his garment. And whoever he touched was healed.</p>
                     <p>And the Pharisees and certain scribes from Jerusalem gathered around him, and were seeing certain of his disciples, that they eat</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>The Marvel of the Coming Son of Man (Mark 11:27–13:37)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>And they come again into Jerusalem. And while he was walking in the temple the chief priests and the scribes and the elders came to him, and they were saying:</p>
                     <p>“By what authority are you doing these things?</p>
                     <p>And who gave to you this authority to do these things?”</p>
                     <p>And Jesus said to them,</p>
                     <p>“I will ask you a question, and you answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things. The baptism of John, was it from heaven or from humans? Answer me.”</p>
                     <p>And they were discussing among themselves saying, “If we say, ‘from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Gospel of Mark (or, for that matter, any text) may be read from different locations. Our attempt has been to enter imaginatively into the world in which the Gospel was composed and to hear its discourses as a first-century audience might have heard them. Twentieth-century historical critics brought questions to Mark that required that the discourses be fragmented to uncover their pre-Markan sources or traditions. Having fragmented the discourses, historical critics were then unable to read them as coherent speech acts. Our reading has sought to hear the discourses themselves, their distinct patterns and strategies, in terms of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Brief History of Greco-Roman Rhetoric</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary of Select Rhetorical Terms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Modern Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Ancient Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7j37.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>381</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
