<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HQ1190.M3775 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminist theory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Body, Human</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Material Feminisms</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Alaimo</surname>
               <given-names>Stacy</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hekman</surname>
               <given-names>Susan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253349781</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253013606</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253013607</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>BLOOMINGTON; INDIANAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzgqh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Harnessing the energy of provocative theories generated by recent understandings of the human body, the natural world, and the material world, Material Feminisms presents an entirely new way for feminists to conceive of the question of materiality. In lively and timely essays, an international group of feminist thinkers challenges the assumptions and norms that have previously defined studies about the body. These wide-ranging essays grapple with topics such as the material reality of race, the significance of sexual difference, the impact of disability experience, and the complex interaction between nature and culture in traumatic events such as Hurricane Katrina. By insisting on the importance of materiality, this volume breaks new ground in philosophy, feminist theory, cultural studies, science studies, and other fields where the body and nature collide.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="448"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>EMERGING MODELS OF MATERIALITY IN FEMINIST THEORY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alaimo</surname>
                           <given-names>Stacy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hekman</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this anthology is to bring the material, specifically the materiality of the human body and the natural world, into the forefront of feminist theory and practice. This is no small matter indeed, and we expect this collection to spark intense debate. Materiality, particularly that of bodies and natures, has long been an extraordinarily volatile site for feminist theory—so volatile, in fact, that the guiding rule of procedure for most contemporary feminisms requires that one distance oneself as much as possible from the tainted realm of materiality by taking refuge within culture, discourse, and language. Our thesis</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>DARWIN AND FEMINISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>PRELIMINARY INVESTIGATIONS FOR A POSSIBLE ALLIANCE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Grosz</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There has traditionally been a strong resistance on the part of feminists to any recourse to the question of nature. Within feminist scholarship and politics, nature has been regarded primarily as a kind of obstacle against which we need to struggle, as that which remains inert, given, unchanging, and resistant to historical, social, and cultural transformations.¹ The suspicion with which biological accounts of human and social life are treated by feminists, especially feminists not trained in the biological sciences, is to some extent understandable. “Biology” not only designates the<italic>study</italic>of life but also refers to the body, to organic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>ON NOT BECOMING MAN:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MATERIALIST POLITICS OF UNACTUALIZED POTENTIAL</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Colebrook</surname>
                           <given-names>Claire</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why would feminism turn to vitalism, and how could vitalism today become a way of politicizing problems? To feel the force of these questions, we might begin to consider why, until recently, “vitalism” was a pejorative term. Only then can we begin to see how and why the reworkings of the vitalist tradition have been so beneficial—and perilous—for feminist thought.</p>
                     <p>When feminists turn to vitalism today, they do so with a full sense of the exhaustion and limits of the linguistic paradigm. The idea that the world is constructed through language merely repeats a centuriesold privilege of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>CONSTRUCTING THE BALLAST:</title>
                     <subtitle>AN ONTOLOGY FOR FEMINISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hekman</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this essay is to tell a story. It is a story that attempts to explain why feminists in particular and critical theorists in general are facing a theoretical and practical crisis. In order to tell this story we have to understand the origin of the crisis, where we are now, and where we might be going in the future. It is a story that has a beginning, although not an origin. The events of the story have precipitated a crisis that has not yet been resolved, although the parameters of the resolution are emerging. It is a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>POSTHUMANIST PERFORMATIVITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>TOWARD AN UNDERSTANDING OF HOW MATTER COMES TO MATTER</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barad</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Language has been granted too much power. The linguistic turn, the semiotic turn, the interpretative turn, the cultural turn: it seems that at every turn lately every “thing”—even materiality—is turned into a matter of language or some other form of cultural representation. The ubiquitous puns on “matter” do not, alas, mark a rethinking of the key concepts (materiality and signification) and the relationship between them. Rather, it seems to be symptomatic of the extent to which matters of “fact” (so to speak) have been replaced with matters of signification (no scare quotes here). Language matters. Discourse matters. Culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>OTHERWORLDLY CONVERSATIONS, TERRAN TOPICS, LOCAL TERMS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haraway</surname>
                           <given-names>Donna J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nature is for me, and I venture for many of us who are planetary fetuses gestating in the amniotic effluvia of terminal industrialism and militarism, one of those impossible things characterized during a talk in 1989 in California by Gayatri Spivak as that which we cannot not desire. Excruciatingly conscious of nature’s constitution as Other in the histories of colonialism, racism, sexism, and class domination of many kinds, many people who have been both ground to powder and formed in European and Euro-American crucibles nonetheless find in this problematic, ethno-specific, long-lived, and globally mobile concept something we cannot do without</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>VISCOUS POROSITY:</title>
                     <subtitle>WITNESSING KATRINA</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tuana</surname>
                           <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The events of August 29, 2005, have left a lasting impact on the citizens of the United States. Seeing through the eye of a Category Four hurricane has resulted in multiple destabilizations. Levees have been breached, a historic city devastated, climate change rendered not simply believable, but palpable,¹ and the face of suffering given a complexion that revealed to a shocked nation the plight of the poor and the racism that is woven into our economic structures.</p>
                     <p>As I considered the news reports of the various impacts of Katrina and thought about the city of New Orleans, I knew that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>NATURAL CONVERS(AT)IONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>OR, WHAT IF CULTURE WAS REALLY NATURE ALL ALONG?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kirby</surname>
                           <given-names>Vicki</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “linguistic turn” in postmodern and poststructural criticism has had a major impact on the landscape of the humanities and social sciences and the way we conceive and communicate our various concerns. Words such as “text,” “writing,” “inscription,” “discourse,” “language,” “code,” “representation,” and so on are now part of the vernacular in critical discussion. Indeed, over the years the textualizing of objects and methodologies has generated new interdisciplinary formations across the academy and transformed the content, approach, and even the justifications for research. On the political front we have seen similar shifts in the practices, modes of argumentation, and even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>TRANS-CORPOREAL FEMINISMS AND THE ETHICAL SPACE OF NATURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alaimo</surname>
                           <given-names>Stacy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the tremendous outpouring of scholarship on “the body” in feminist theory and cultural studies and the simultaneous outpouring of environmental philosophy, criticism, and cultural studies, these two streams of scholarship rarely intermingle. Although there are notable exceptions, by and large two isolated conversations have evolved—conversations that would be complicated and enriched by collisions and convergences. Most feminist analyses of the body, in particular, sever their topic from the topos of “nature.” Indeed, from an environmentalist-feminist standpoint, one of the most unfortunate legacies of poststructuralist and postmodern feminism has been the accelerated “flight from nature” fueled by rigid commitments</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>LANDSCAPE, MEMORY, AND FORGETTING:</title>
                     <subtitle>THINKING THROUGH (MY MOTHER’S) BODY AND PLACE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mortimer-Sandilands</surname>
                           <given-names>Catriona</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a recent exchange in the journal<italic>Environmental Ethics</italic>, David Abram and Ted Toadvine engage in a spirited debate about questions of sensuousness, perception, reflection, writing, memory, and landscape. Focused on their conflicting interpretations of Abram’s popular book<italic>The Spell of the Sensuous</italic>(1996), and eventually resting on their divergent readings of Merleau-Ponty’s<italic>Phenomenology of Perception</italic>(1962),¹ Toadvine and Abram each attempt to address a set of ontological questions that are, I think, foundational for environmental philosophy: How can we understand the human body as a particular site of perceptions of, and interactions with, the more-than-human world? How can we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>DISABILITY EXPERIENCE ON TRIAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Siebers</surname>
                           <given-names>Tobin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On May 17, 2004, the fiftieth anniversary of<italic>Brown v. Board of Education</italic>, the U.S. Supreme Court delivered, in<italic>Tennessee v. Lane</italic>, another ruling with far-reaching implications for civil rights. The Court ruled unexpectedly and by a narrow margin that states not making courtrooms and legal services physically accessible to people with disabilities could be sued for damages under Title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA). George Lane, the plaintiff and a wheelchair user, told how he was summoned to the Polk County Tennessee Courthouse on a minor traffic charge and had to crawl up two flights of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>HOW REAL IS RACE?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hames-García</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A quick read of Ward Connolly’s Racial Privacy Initiative (which would have eliminated California’s use of race as a means of classification) reveals much about the contradictions in public discourse about race. Among other things, it explicitly provided for the retention of racial profiling on the part of the police while freeing police departments from having to keep track of the race of the people they arrested or detained. The ballot measure, promoted using liberal, antiracist rhetoric, would have frustrated all attempts to demonstrate discriminatory patterns of surveillance, arrest, or harassment by police. Race clearly matters, and yet throughout its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>FROM RACE/SEX/ETC. TO GLUCOSE, FEEDING TUBE, AND MOURNING:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE SHIFTING MATTER OF CHICANA FEMINISM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bost</surname>
                           <given-names>Suzanne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Gloria Anzaldúa and Cherríe Moraga first collaborated on<italic>This Bridge Called My Back: Writings by Radical Women of Color</italic>at the end of the 1970s, their primary concern was addressing the simultaneous oppressions experienced by women of color along the axes of race, class, sex, and sexuality. As they challenged the masculinist subject of Chicano nationalism, these writers turned to coalition building and editorial collaboration to locate themselves at the intersection of multiple sociopolitical identifications. Collections like<italic>Bridge</italic>shifted feminist criticism toward a greater sensitivity to the ways in which feminist identity politics traverse racial and sexual differences. One</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>ORGANIC EMPATHY:</title>
                     <subtitle>FEMINISM, PSYCHOPHARMACEUTICALS, AND THE EMBODIMENT OF DEPRESSION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wilson</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Judith Kegan Gardiner opened her 1995 review of<italic>Listening to Prozac, Talking Back to Prozac</italic>, and<italic>Prozac Nation</italic>for the journal<italic>Feminist Studies</italic>with this anecdote:</p>
                     <p>I recently attended an interdisciplinary feminist meeting that assumed a consensus about social constructionism and criticized scholarly work that was perceived as “essentialist,” because it implied a biological basis for gender attributes. During meals and breaks, however, I heard a different story. Several women were taking Prozac or similar drugs for depression. Some of their children, who had been difficult, “underachieving,” or disruptive in school, were also being medicated. These informal discussions centered on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>CASSIE’S HAIR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bordo</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>400</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first year and a half of Cassie’s life, her hair was basically not an issue because she didn’t have much. Then one day she came home from day care with a dozen tiny braids marking a complex and delicate pattern on her tiny head. I was, first of all, mystified. I had no idea she had enough hair to do anything like this. Where had all that hair come from? How had her teacher gathered it up like that? And how had she gotten her to sit still long enough to do it?</p>
                     <p>When my friend Annice found</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzgqh.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
