<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2h08gn</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B4691.I534M58 1996</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ingarden, Roman, 1893-1970</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ingarden, Roman, 1893-1970</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Contributions in ontology</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Roman Ingarden's Ontology and Aesthetics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MITSCHERLING</surname>
               <given-names>Jeff</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>With a foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KLIBANSKY</surname>
               <given-names>Raymond</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>1997</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780776616889</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0776616889</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Ottawa Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1997</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Ottawa Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cn6sd9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A leading Polish philosopher of the 20th century, Roman Ingarden is principally renowned in Western culture for his work in aesthetics and the theory of literature. Jeff Mitscherling demonstrates, in this extensive work, how Ingarden's thought constitutes a major contribution to the more fundamental fields of ontology and metaphysics. Unparalleled in existing literature, Mitscherling's comprehensive survey of Ingarden's philosophy will give the reader an informed introduction to this major work of phenomenological analysis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="244"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>VII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Klibansky</surname>
                           <given-names>Raymond</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>XI</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dr. Mitscherling provides the first comprehensive monograph on the life and the works of a philosopher who in Germany and in his native Poland has long been known as a thinker of marked originality. Now that several of Roman Ingarden’s writings have become available in English translations and that his distinguished pupil Anna-Teresa Tymieniecka has published some essays on him, his thought is attracting growing interest both in Europe and in North America.</p>
                     <p>From his early student days at the universities of Gottingen and Freiburg, Ingarden was closely associated with Edmund Husserl and the phenomenological movement. Dr. Mitscherling shows how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE AND ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XIII</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The basic claim of this book is twofold: (1) that we are not in a position accurately to interpret and evaluate Ingarden’s studies in aesthetics until we place them within the framework provided by his realist ontological position as a whole, and (2) that, conversely, we cannot fully appreciate the force of Ingarden’s arguments in his ‘non-aesthetic’ epistemological and ontological investigations—such as we find in his magnum opus,<italic>The Controversy Over the Existence of the World</italic>¹—without understanding how Ingarden intended his studies in aesthetics to provide those investigations, and his own position with regard to the idealism/realism debate,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>A SKETCH OF INGARDEN’S LIFE, CAREER, AND WORKS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ingarden’s life and career spanned not only one of the greatest eras of European intellectual and cultural history but also the last chapters of one of the most tragic periods of the turbulent history of Poland, much of which revolved around Krakow, the city of his birth. Throughout the eighteenth century, Krakow had been repeatedly attacked, occupied, and plundered by the armies of Sweden, Russia, Prussia, and Austria, and by the end of the century Poland had formally ceased to exist. The movement of Polish national independence proclaimed in the Market Square of Krakow by Tadeusz Kosciuszko on 24 March</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>INGARDEN’S INTERPRETATION OF HUSSERL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I offer a critical examination of Ingarden’s interpretation of Husserl as a ‘metaphysical idealist’. While the idealist interpretation antedates Ingarden’s first statement of criticism, his ceaseless endeavour to drive home his point for his entire career has resulted in his being designated its chief proponent. The current debate concerning Husserl’s metaphysical position may be said to have been initiated by Richard Holmes’s 1975 paper “Is Transcendental Phenomenology Committed to Idealism?,”¹ which, like most of the recent literature, identifies Ingarden as such. With regard exclusively to Ingarden’s interpretation, the issue as addressed in the recent literature focusses on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>CONTROVERSY OVER THE EXISTENCE OF THE WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While Danuta Gierulanka correctly remarks that Ingarden’s<italic>Controversy</italic>“came about in a spirit of opposition to Husserl’s idealism,” and that Ingarden began the preparatory work for Controversy in 1925,¹ he had, in a sense, begun this work as early as July 1918, when he wrote the ‘idealism letter’ to Husserl (discussed in Chapter 2). Indeed, he writes in that letter that “the problem of Idealism,” which<italic>Controversy</italic>is devoted to treating, had “tormented [him] already several years.”² Ingarden’s relationship to Husserl, like his entire philosophical career, seems to have revolved around that problem:³</p>
                     <p>Aside from my remarks to<italic>Méditations Cartesiennes</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>THE LITERARY WORK OF ART</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preface to the first edition of<italic>The Literary Work of Art</italic>¹ Ingarden states (<italic>LWA</italic>lxxii):</p>
                     <p>Although the main subject of my investigations is the literary work, or the literary work of art, the ultimate motives for my work on this subject are of a general philosophical nature, and they far transcend this particular subject. They are closely connected to the problem of idealism-realism, with which I have been concerning myself for many years.</p>
                     <p>As we saw in the preceding chapters, Ingarden conceived of the problem of idealism/realism in terms of (as he writes a bit further in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>INGARDEN’S ANALYSES OF OTHER SORTS OF ARTWORKS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen, Ingarden’s primary philosophical concern lay not in aesthetics per se but in ontology. He undertook his extensive analyses of art in order not to gather material for the construction of a general ‘theory of art’ but rather to elucidate and, to some extent, ground his position with regard to the idealism/realism debate. Seen in this light, it is not at all surprising that his analyses of the different sorts of art do not yield a single conception of ‘the nature of art’,¹ which had been the goal of most traditional philosophy of art and aesthetic theory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>INGARDEN AND CONTEMPORARY AESTHETICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I shall be explaining in Sections B and C below, Ingarden’s analyses of the ontology of art provide both a strong foundation and a powerful tool that could be employed in current research in aesthetics and theory of art.¹ The operative expression here, however, is ‘could be’, for Ingarden’s work has exerted surprisingly little influence on the contemporary scene.² Zhang Jin-Yan, speaking of the influence of Ingarden’s analyses of the literary work on contemporary literary criticism, accurately sums up the situation regarding his influence in general:</p>
                     <p>Finally, one important weakness in Ingarden’s phenomenological aesthetics of literature is that it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY OF WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF SUBJECTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF PROPER NAMES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cn6sd9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
