<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Crisis of Global Capitalism</book-title>
         <subtitle>Pope Benedict XVI's Social Encyclical and the Future of Political Economy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pabst</surname>
               <given-names>Adrian</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227680162</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227901373</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Wipf &amp; Stock Publishers</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf0cr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The current economic crisis stems from a deeper crisis of cultural imagination and civilisational ethics: here is the starting point of this collection of essays which draw a new political economy facing the crisis of Western civilization. This book gathers together a range of audacious and provocative readings of Caritas in Veritate, the first papal encyclical that addresses issues immediately relevant for politic, economic, and social theory. These readings embody the kind of fruitful dialogue Pope Benedict XVI wanted to generate with his radical discourse for an alternative political economy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="292"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pabst</surname>
                           <given-names>Adrian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>The Future of Political Economy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pabst</surname>
                           <given-names>Adrian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a sense, the global recession of 2007–2010 is just another reminder that capitalist economies suffer periodic crises but that capitalism does not collapse under the weight of its own inner contradictions. Instead, it always reverts to the “normal” cycle of expansion, contraction, and recovery. This reversion is linked to over-accumulation and falling profit rates that prompt capital owners to cut the real wages of laborers in order to generate new surplus value, as both Adam Smith and Karl Marx recognized.¹ But whereas Smith evaded the issue of “primitive accumulation,” Marx followed Sir James Steuart in arguing that this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Real Third Way</title>
                     <subtitle>For a New Metanarrative of Capital and the Associationist Alternative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Milbank</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A common view about Christianity and politics is that Christians divide up over politics in much the same way as other people. But this is only superficially true and only true of Christians who have thought about politics superficially and in disconnection from their faith. For if one examines the writings of Christian thinkers who have thought long, hard, and theologically about politics, then the consistency of their emphases ever since the dawn of the Industrial Age is extremely striking.</p>
                     <p>This is most of all true of Catholic thinkers, but the conclusions of Anglican and Orthodox thinkers have been remarkably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A Tale of a Duck-Billed Platypus Called Benedict and His Gold and Red Crayons</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rowland</surname>
                           <given-names>Tracey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Caritas in Veritate</italic>is the most recent in a long list of papal interventions in the territory of social justice, and for most commentators there was nothing surprising in the document apart from its extraordinary length and the way in which it sought to offer a comprehensive overview of the whole tradition rather than isolating a couple of issues and focusing upon them. It was as if Benedict XVI reviewed the tradition, made an executive summary of what he regards as its most significant elements, and gave his papal stamp of approval to them, at the same time as enriching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“We Communists of the Old School”</title>
                     <subtitle>Benedict’s Encyclical and the Future of Christian Socialism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McCarraher</surname>
                           <given-names>Eugene</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thomas Carlyle once famously dubbed economics “the dismal science,” but Ruskin went his friend one better by denying that economics is a science at all. (That whatever it is, is still dismal, went without saying.) With a fine contempt that we’ve lost in our deference to the clerisy of the business schools, Ruskin declared his utter indifference astrology, witchcraft, and other such popular creeds,” Ruskin mused in Unto This Last, “political economy has a plausible idea at the root of it”: that human beings are motivated by self-interest. True, he conceded, but also trite and misleading, for men and women</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Beyond the Culture of Cutthroat Competition</title>
                     <subtitle>The Pope Takes the World by Surprise</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Mark</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zwick</surname>
                           <given-names>Louise</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pope Benedict XVI’s social encyclical,<italic>Caritas in Veritate</italic>, took the economic world by surprise.¹ While readers on both the right and the left were waiting for more statements about capitalism and socialism, they found instead a challenge to Catholics and other people of good will toward a profoundly new way of understanding business enterprise. The Pope did not approve the status quo, but in what he called the social<italic>magisterium</italic>, addressed the global dimension of the social question understanding of what has been happening in the contemporary international economic scene. Benedict recognizes the disconnect between the Word of the Gospel</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Fraternity, Gift, and Reciprocity in Caritas in Veritate</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zamagni</surname>
                           <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the marks of our time is a constant call for ethics, which has progressively replaced, over the past quarter of a century, the persistent call for politics typical of the 1960s, when it was imagined that “everything was politics.” But this agreement on the primacy of ethics ceases when it comes to tangible moral issues. As Alasdair McIntyre observed in<italic>After Virtue</italic>, the apodictic use of moral principles serves only to put an end to the ethical dialogue itself. In other words, the broad convergence on ethics in public debate almost never translates into ethical consensus.</p>
                     <p>The teaching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Paradoxical Nature of the Good</title>
                     <subtitle>Relationality, Sympathy, and Mutuality in Rival Traditions of Civil Economy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pabst</surname>
                           <given-names>Adrian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A cross different academic disciplines, we are witnessing a fundamental and perhaps paradigmatic shift away from individuality towards relationality. Both natural sciences and humanities are seeing the emergence of different relational models that attempt to theorize the widespread recognition that reality cannot be reduced to self-generating, individual beings and that the outcome of interactions between various entities is more than the sum of parts (whether these be more atomistic or more collectivist). For instance, in particle physics it has been suggested that there are “things” such as quarks (subatomic particles) which cannot be measured individually because they are confined by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Anthropological Unity of Caritas in Veritate</title>
                     <subtitle>Life, Family, and Development</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schindler</surname>
                           <given-names>David L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The truth of development consists in its completeness: if it does not involve the whole man and every man, it is not true development.”¹ This, says Pope Benedict in his new encyclical, is “the central message of [Paul VI’s]<italic>Populorum Progressio</italic>, valid for today and for all time” (<italic>Caritas</italic>,18). “Integral human development on the natural plane, as a response to a vocation from God the Creator, demands self-fulfillment in a ‘transcendent humanism which gives [to man] his greatest possible perfection: this is the highest goal of personal development’” (<italic>Caritas</italic>, 18 ).²</p>
                     <p>According to Benedict, God-centered charity in truth is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Integralism and Gift Exchange in the Anglican Social Tradition, or Avoiding Niebuhr in Ecclesiastical Drag</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hughes</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I would like to begin by asking what, from an Anglican perspective, is particularly interesting about<italic>Caritas in Veritate</italic>, before exploring what resonances its key theological ideas of “integral development” and charity as reciprocal gift exchange have within the Anglican Social Tradition(s). My argument will be that, first, Anglicans have been at the forefront of the recovery of Augustinian notions of charity as reciprocal gift exchange and the associationist application of such ideas to the social and economic sphere; and secondly, that, despite some recent evidence to the contrary, Anglicanism has particular ecclesiologicopolitical reasons to be sympathetic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Common Life</title>
                     <subtitle>Ethics, Class, Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cruddas</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rtherford</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The buildings of Canary Wharf in east London are huge factories of information and communications that have grown out of the old industrial structure of the Docklands. There are no longer any cranes on West India Dock lifting heavy goods from the holds of ships, very few workers engaged in physical toil, and no trade routes from the workshop of the world to the four corners of empire. The hard lives this industrial economy sustained have been made redundant. The new engines of Western capitalism are companies like Credit Suisse, HSBC, Citigroup and Morgan Stanley. The new trade routes are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Equity and Equilibrium</title>
                     <subtitle>Why Distributive Justice Is Necessary for Economic Science</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Médaille</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The premise of this collection is that “there is a ‘middle’ position between an exclusively religious and a strictly secular perspective” on economics. But it seems to me that a “middle position” must, by definition, compromise the truths of both religion and economics. Indeed, such a premise accepts what is one of the primary problems with modern economics, namely, the belief in the so-called “equity/efficiency” trade-off. That is, the belief that an economic system can be equitable or it can be efficient, but it cannot be both.</p>
                     <p>What we should seek, I believe, is not a compromise, but a connection.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf0cr.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
