<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JZ1253.P69 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Collective memory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">International relations</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">World politics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20 th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">World politics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21 st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Power and the Past</book-title>
         <subtitle>Collective Memory and International Relations</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Langenbacher</surname>
               <given-names>Eric</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Shain</surname>
               <given-names>Yossi</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">Editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781589016408</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1589016408</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781589016613</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1589016610</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Georgetown University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2tt597"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Only recently have international relations scholars started to seriously examine the influence of collective memory on foreign policy formation and relations between states and peoples. The ways in which the memories of past events are interpreted, misinterpreted, or even manipulated in public discourse create the context that shapes international relations.<italic>Power and the Past</italic>brings together leading history and international relations scholars to provide a groundbreaking examination of the impact of collective memory. This timely study makes a contribution to developing a theory of memory and international relations and also examines specific cases of collective memory's influence resulting from the legacies of World War II, the Holocaust, and September 11. Addressing concerns shared by world leaders and international institutions as well as scholars of international studies, this volume illustrates clearly how the memory of past events alters the ways countries interact in the present, how memory shapes public debate and policymaking, and how memory may aid or more frequently impede conflict resolution.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Twenty-first-Century Memories</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Langenbacher</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shain</surname>
                           <given-names>Yossi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Collective memories have long influenced domestic politics and especially international affairs—a fact most recently exemplified by the terrorist attacks on the United States on September 11, 2001. The events and the memories resulting from them became powerful motivating forces for Americans almost overnight. At home, an infrastructure of commemoration quickly arose—in films like <italic>United 93</italic> (2006); memorials including one unveiled at the Pentagon in September 2008 and the Tribute World Trade Center Visitor Center opened in 2006; and even in political campaign discourse, as at the 2008 Republican National Convention.¹ Yet, as with other collective memories worldwide, there</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Collective Memory as a Factor in Political Culture and International Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Langenbacher</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>For years, observers have identified a so-called memory boom among scholars and in many societies worldwide—a boom that the September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks have only intensified.¹ In some countries the memory of traumatic events is still raw, and processes of settling accounts linger in the current political agenda. Elsewhere, where the seminal events on which collective memories rest are further in the past, the issues involve debating and institutionalizing an appropriate culture of memory and collective identity for future generations. Sometimes the individual and collective wounds fester, waiting for necessary healing through political and judicial processes. Other times</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Germany’s National Identity, Collective Memory, and Role Abroad</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Warburg</surname>
                           <given-names>Bettina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>During soccer’s 2008 European Cup, many German fans waved their flags jubilantly after the national team’s victories—continuing a new patriotic tradition that was especially pronounced during the 2006 World Cup of soccer hosted in Germany and in which the national team made it to the semifinals. Both times, it was difficult not to recall a much bleaker version of German nationalism that prevailed in the not-so-distant past. National pride and flag-waving have a dark connotation in German history, bringing to mind images of swastika-brazened banners from the 1936 Olympic Games, and recalling the fate of Europe’s Jews and all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Collective Memory and German–Polish Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Langenbacher</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>There are few other countries today whose perceptions of each other, bilateral relations, and foreign policies are as beholden to historical legacies and collective memories as Poland and Germany. As Oliver Schmidtke writes: “It is difficult to imagine finding a similar case in Europe, in which the relationship between two nations is so firmly anchored in memories.”¹ Or as Marcin Zaborowski puts it: “Germanic–Polish relations have been some of the most troublesome in Europe ever since the eighteenth century. . . . Polish–German antagonism has always been of more than bilateral or even regional significance.”² Although the twentieth-century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Building Up a Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Austria, Switzerland, and Europe Face the Holocaust</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beker</surname>
                           <given-names>Avi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>A unique conference took place in Stockholm at the end of January 2000. Forty-three heads of states and foreign ministers, together with world leading historians and educators, gathered for three days to discuss education and commemoration of the Holocaust. The eight hundred journalists who joined U.S. president Bill Clinton, European leaders, and other world leaders provided an additional dimension to the extraordinary awakening of world interest in the events of the Holocaust, more than fifty years later.</p>
                     <p>The choice of Sweden as the conference venue can illustrate how historical consciousness about the Holocaust was developing in the 1990s. In late</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Memory, Tradition, and Revival:</title>
                     <subtitle>Who, Then, Speaks for the Jews?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Soltes</surname>
                           <given-names>Ori Z.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>After the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, as at many other moments in history, a specifically “Jewish” dimension has arisen. Beyond the shockingly persistent rumors of some kind of Israeli–Jewish conspiracy behind the attacks in the first place, the policy aftermath—especially the global war on terror and the invasion of Iraq—was widely perceived as being pushed by “Jewish interests and actors.”¹ These most recent examples once again raise the question of who speaks on behalf of “Jewish political interests”—and once again generates interest in the complex interrelationship among various diasporas and Israel, as well as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>September 11 in the Rearview Mirror:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contemporary Policies and Perceptions of the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bartov</surname>
                           <given-names>Omer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>At the end of the last century several books were published reviewing the past hundred years and making predictions about the future. Historians naturally participated both in the summing up and in the more tentative forecasts. Not surprisingly, historians are much better qualified to analyze the events of yesteryear than to predict what might happen tomorrow. But they—or I should say we—do work under the assumption that by detecting some trends, undercurrents, structures, evolutionary predilections, or revolutionary preconditions, which characterized past events, we might be better prepared for them in the future as well. In other words, we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>The Eventful Dates 12/12 and 9/11:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tales of Power and Tales of Experience in Contemporary History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kazin</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The title of this chapter may puzzle the reader. My purpose is to juxtapose the historical impact of events that took place on two highly significant dates in the recent past. Then I raise what I hope will be a few provocative suggestions about what we might think about what occurred—especially with regard to American identity and foreign affairs.</p>
                     <p>September 11, 2001, is a date we know well—and will probably commemorate for the rest of our lives—as the day of the horrific terrorist attacks on the United States. But the consequences of what occurred late one evening</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>The Use and Abuse of History in Berlin and Washington since 9/11:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Plea for a New Era of Candor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Herf</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffrey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Now that the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, are almost ten years in the past, it may be illuminating to elaborate on three hypotheses concerning the relationship between collective memory and the lessons of the past, on the one hand, and the foreign policies of the United States and the major European powers, especially Germany, on the other. First, despite some difficulties in its application to differing historical settings, the concept of totalitarianism—first applied to fascism, Nazism, and Stalinism—also usefully applies to the secular expression in the Ba’ath regime of Saddam Hussein’s Iraq, along with the religious</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 9</label>
                     <title>Of Shrines and Hooligans:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Structure of the History Problem in East Asia after 9/11</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Berger</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas U.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the early years of the twenty-first century, as the world confronts terrifying new security threats in the shape of international terrorism and the spread of weapons of mass destruction, international relations in East Asia remain mired in disputes over the past. At the soccer final of the Asian games in August 2004, the Chinese government had to deploy six thousand heavily armed riot policemen to quell enraged Chinese soccer hooligans who burned the Japanese flag, pelted innocent Japanese spectators with abuse, and threatened to attack the Japanese embassy. The reason given by the fans for their rampage?—Japan’s failure</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 10</label>
                     <title>Popular Culture and Collective Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering and Forgetting in Chinese–U.S. Relations after 9/11</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gong</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerrit W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>On the morning of September 11, 2001, where in the United States was the ambassador of the People’s Republic of China, Yang Jiezhi? He was in Salt Lake City, previewing, among other things, preparations for the 2002 Winter Olympics. Standing side by side, the ambassador and I watched CNN in disbelief and horror as the World Trade Center towers, struck by two fuelladen hijacked jetliners, burned and collapsed. In the hours and days that followed, I watched as the ambassador (and others) reoriented Chinese–U.S. relations from strategic competition to global war on terrorism cooperation. Those foreign policy changes reflected</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Collective Memory and the Logic of Appropriate Behavior</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shain</surname>
                           <given-names>Yossi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Several common themes and conclusions have emerged from the contributions assembled in this volume. First, and perhaps not surprisingly, collective memories emerge in a variety of cultural and national contexts to greatly influence various foreign policies, bilateral relationships, and international affairs. Nevertheless, the ways in which collective memories become influential factors in decision making are not always as expected. The ways that memories are used as rhetorical weapons are often surprising. Although the emotions that are embedded in these memories-as-weapons are visceral and, as with other more conventional weapons, can be highly divisive and even dangerous.</p>
                     <p>Second, complex interactions between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tt597.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
