<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2tvq1z</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">R723.G6 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Medicine</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Medical ethics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Health planning</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Health care reform</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Health Sciences</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Goals of Medicine</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Forgotten Issues in Health Care Reform</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hanson</surname>
               <given-names>Mark J.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Callahan</surname>
               <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781589014442</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1589014448</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>WASHINGTON, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Georgetown University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1qd8zdh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Debates over health care have focused for so long on economics that the proper goals for medicine seem to be taken for granted; yet problems in health care stem as much from a lack of agreement about the goals and priorities of medicine as from the way systems function. This book asks basic questions about the purposes and ends of medicine and shows that the answers have practical implications for future health care delivery, medical research, and the education of medical students.</p>
         <p>The Hastings Center coordinated teams of physicians, nurses, public health experts, philosophers, theologians, politicians, health care administrators, social workers, and lawyers in fourteen countries to explore these issues. In this volume, they articulate four basic goals of medicine - prevention of disease, relief of suffering, care of the ill, and avoidance of premature death - and examine them in light of the cultural, political, and economic pressures under which medicine functions. In reporting these findings, the contributors touch on a wide range of diverse issues such as genetic technology, Chinese medicine, care of the elderly, and prevention and public health.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>The Goals of Medicine</italic>clearly demonstrates the importance of clarifying the purposes of medicine before attempting to change the economic and organizational systems. It warns that without such examination, any reform efforts may be fruitless.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Callahan</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Callahan</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1993, the Hastings Center initiated a project on the Goals of Medicine. It was conceived out of a sense of frustration and perplexity. Throughout the world, but especially in the United States during that time, vast national debates had erupted over needed reforms in the health care system. The Clinton Administration was pushing for universal health care while other bills before Congress pursued a variety of proposals on that general theme.</p>
                     <p>Both the Congress and the public, however, were dominated by matters of economics, organization, politics, and efficiency. The debate was essentially a technical discussion, one touching here and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Goals of Medicine:</title>
                     <subtitle>Setting New Priorities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a report of a project that examined the goals of medicine in light of its contemporary possibilities and problems. Where has medicine been, where ought it to be going, and what should its future priorities be? These are important and difficult questions. An international group worked on them four years, and this report is the result of its efforts. While there is by no means total agreement among those who developed it on every item in the report, what follows represents a general consensus. We struggled to define the issues, and then to see if we could come</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Goals and Ends of Medicine:</title>
                     <subtitle>How Are They to be Defined?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pellegrino</surname>
                           <given-names>Edmund D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Medicine today is in an unprecedented state of confusion about its identity, about its role and the role of physicians in contemporary society. Philosophers and judicial opinions are disassembling the Hippocratic Oath and ethic; medical care has become a commodity transacted as a business and organized as an industry; insurance companies see in medicine an investment opportunity; scientists and engineers see it as the subject of technical prestidigitation.</p>
                     <p>All of this puts patients and physicians in a quandary. Is the physician still a helper, healer, and caregiver? Or are physicians something else—gatekeepers, guardians of society’s resources and employees, “managed”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Medicine and Other Means of Health Enhancement:</title>
                     <subtitle>Towards a Conceptual Framework</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nordenfelt</surname>
                           <given-names>Lennart</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are many ways to enhance health. At one end we have the paradigm case of medicine, the encounter between the physician and a suffering patient who is seeking help; at the other end we have a piece of legislation issued by a government or other official body forbidding smoking on public premises. Both enterprises have human health as their ultimate goal; both are intentional health-enhancing activities.</p>
                     <p>Between these extremes are various other health-enhancing human activities, some of them situated in an institution of health care such as a clinic, others performed in a public office or in a medium</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What Kind of Values?</title>
                     <subtitle>A Historical Perspective on the Ends of Medicine</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gracia</surname>
                           <given-names>Diego</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Medicine has not been a unique or homogeneous task throughout history. What we call medicine is a diverse set of ideas, methods, procedures, and practices that has been changing continuously from the beginning of human culture until now. The only point in common throughout history has been the goal of helping people overcome disease and promote health. But if we try to analyze the contents proper of those two terms, “health” and “disease,” we realize that over time their meaning has changed; a canonical or paradigmatic concept cannot be found for them. In other words, health and disease are not,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Pain, Suffering, and the Goals of Medicine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cassell</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philoctetes, according to myth, was on his way to Troy with the Greeks when he was bitten by a snake. Because of the stench of his wound he was abandoned by his shipmates on the Island of Lemnos. He is emblematic of the problem of pain and suffering: of pain because of his wound, of suffering because he has been abandoned. His life is organized around o o his awful affliction, and his torment is now the focus of his life. His countrymen return, not because they desire to help, but because they want to steal his charmed bow and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Symptoms or Persons?</title>
                     <subtitle>A Question for Setting the Goals of Medicine</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hellström</surname>
                           <given-names>Olle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sufficiently delivered medical services presuppose well-considered ideas about the goals of the enterprise, knowledge about those who use the services and their needs and expectations as well as knowledge, ability, and resources to reach the goals. To be able to discuss the goals of medicine meaningfully and how to formulate them, who should do what and to what extent, we must first of all reflect upon the context of medical views to which the different concepts refer. Have doctors in general got a well-thought-out picture of the qualities that make a person a patient? What does it really mean to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Idea of Progress and the Goals of Medicine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hanson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In June 1995, the U.S. Institute of Medicine (IOM) held a conference on xenotransplantation. The Institute gathered scientists, patients, and ethicists to hear their perspectives on the issue so that an IOM committee could develop recommendations regarding this emerging form of medical technology. Scientists and transplant surgeons began the conference by presenting their data, prefaced always with comments regarding the current shortages of transplantable organs. The scientists were, as one would expect, optimistic about potential successes. All they asked for was more money and less regulation.</p>
                     <p>Patient perspectives concluded the meeting, providing often dramatic and emotional testimony to how their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Old Age:</title>
                     <subtitle>Something to Look Forward To?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boyd</surname>
                           <given-names>Kenneth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Grandfather was not a problem but a solver of problems.”¹ That may be too optimistic a picture of old age in the past. In preliterate societies, the old were valued as “the libraries of the people.” But once societies became literate and devised more efficient means of information retrieval, the elderly no longer had a secure cultural niche. Individuals who retained control of significant resources—active politicians and intellectuals, for example—might be treated with respect. But the common lot of the elderly, in agricultural and industrial societies, was sometimes closer to the cruel marginalization depicted, for example, in Zola’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Genetic Medicine:</title>
                     <subtitle>A New Copernican Turning Point?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sponholz</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerlinde</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baitsch</surname>
                           <given-names>Helmut</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ahr</surname>
                           <given-names>Willfried</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harr</surname>
                           <given-names>Helmut</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib5" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hölzer</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib6" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keller</surname>
                           <given-names>Frieder</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib7" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Meier-allmendinger</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib8" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Straif</surname>
                           <given-names>Kurt</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib9" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Allert</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerhard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last two decades human genetics has developed into an extensive scientific field of enormous range, a dynamism that previously didn’t exist. New molecular genetic techniques have enabled far-reaching changes to take place in medicine, with new knowledge and new techniques in prevention, diagnosis, and treatment. New models of health and disease are superseding old ones. Scientists predict that these developments will lead to a deeper understanding of disease and health. The individual propensities of each person for mono-and multifactorial diseases and disorders can be recognized and foreseen.</p>
                     <p>These developments are taking place at great speed. New results are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Goals of Medicine and Public Health</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Peng</surname>
                           <given-names>Rui-cong</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goals of medicine have become a focus for debate in the world of medicine today. But thorough reflection on recent developments in health care and medicine is necessary to understand the significance of this discussion. Many changes have taken place in recent years. For example, the demographics of disease have changed markedly with advances in biomedical science and public health. Remarkable progress has been made in medical technology. In developed countries, chronic and degenerative diseases and aging have become major problems threatening people’s health. Consequently, they are experiencing a continuous rise in the cost of health care which results</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rethinking DoctorThink:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reforming Medical Education by Nurturing Neglected Goals</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fox</surname>
                           <given-names>Ellen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On a fundamental level, the goals of medical education are necessarily derivative of the goals of medicine. Although overall, education is certainly a worthy end in its own right, the quintessential purpose of medical education is to provide society with professionals to fill a vital social need. Therefore, medical education’s specific goals depend entirely on a prior question: What sort of medical practitioners should our society aim to produce?</p>
                     <p>The term “medical education” is ordinarily used to denote the professional education of physicians, as opposed to the education of nurses and other health care providers. This terminology reflects the degree</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Traditional Chinese Medicine and the Goals of Medicine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weibo</surname>
                           <given-names>Lu</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) has much in common with other forms of so-called traditional medicine, but it is also unique. It has its own theoretical system and terminology. It can also guide clinical practice effectively. The development of modern science and technology is the primary cause for the evolution from ancient Greco-Roman forms of traditional medicine to modern medicine. Most traditional medicine could not accommodate science and technology, and were largely overcome by it. Only TCM met this challenge, arming itself to prove its efficacy and the validity of its philosophy.¹ Over time, hundreds of modern doctors and professors who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Future of Medicine:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Analytical Framework</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gyarmati</surname>
                           <given-names>Gabriel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The future is unpredictable. But one thing we can do is examine the factors that are likely to steer the development of specific institutions: in this case, medicine. That is what I will do in this essay. To identify those factors, however, it is first necessary to define the situation in which medicine currently finds itself and examine the events that forged that situation. I suggest that the current state of medicine is shaped by three circumstances.</p>
                     <p>First, from the Second World War onward and with the emergence of a new view of society, widening sectors of the population began</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On the Goals of Medicine:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reflections and Distinctions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lolas</surname>
                           <given-names>Fernando</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Defining medicine as a discipline and as a profession, requires a recognition that it comprises theory, and not merely practice.¹ The conceptualization of suffering and disease in secular terms, for example, has been one of the most pervasive theoretical aims of medicine throughout history. In addition, as a proto-paradigmatic discipline, medicine has been influenced by the science of the positivistic era, which may be said to have the inherent goal of reproducing itself and achieving autonomy as a techno-scientific enterprise. Therefore, as a scientific discipline, modern medicine shares with the sciences the goals of innovation and invention, aside from its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Negotiating the Goals of Medicine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fox</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Doctors have complained for centuries when lay persons, especially public officials and most recently the executives of managed care organizations, challenge their authority to set the goals of medicine. There been more controversy about who should determine the goals of medicine and who should monitor their implementation than about what they ought to be. From caring for persons with plague in Italian city states of the late Middle Ages to hospitalizing women after childbirth the United States in the 1990s, disputes about goals have been simultaneously struggles over power. Purpose and politics are as inseparable in medicine as in any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1qd8zdh.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
