<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Sacramental Presence after Heidegger</book-title>
         <subtitle>Onto-theology, Sacraments, and the Mother's Smile</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sweeney</surname>
               <given-names>Conor</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227175354</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227904824</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Conor Sweeney</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf1rx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"Theology after Heidegger must take into account history and language as elements in the pursuit of meaning. Quite often, this prompts a hurried flight from metaphysics to an embrace of an absence at the center of Christian narrativity. Conor Sweeney here explores the “postmodern" critique of presence in the context of sacramental theology, engaging the thought of Louis-Marie Chauvet and Lieven Boeve. Chauvet is an influential postmodern theologian whose critique of the perceived onto-theological constitution of presence in traditional sacramental theology has made big waves, while Boeve is part of a more recent generation of theologians who even more wholeheartedly embrace postmodern consequences for theology. Sweeney considers the extent to which postmodernism à la Heidegger upsets the hermeneutics of sacramentality, asking whether this requires us to renounce the search for a presence that by definition transcends us. Against both the fetishization of presence and absence, Sweeney argues that metaphysics has a properly sacramental basis, and that it is only through this reality that the dialectic of presence and absence can be transcended. The case is made for the full but restless signification of the mother’s smile as the paradigm for genuine sacramental presence."</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="282"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Context, History, Object</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Heideggerean cry to “overcome” metaphysics understood as “onto-theology” continues to reverberate throughout the continental world and beyond. Ever since Martin Heidegger’s resurrection of the<italic>Seinsfrage</italic>and his subsequent turn to time and language as the horizon of Being, philosophers and theologians courageous—or perhaps naïve—enough to grapple with the Heideggerean corpus have been struggling to come to grips with the implications of Heidegger’s claims. According to many commentators, this is a task that in the Catholic world has only just begun.</p>
                     <p>Broadly speaking, this book is about sacramental presence after the kind of postmodern narrative that draws on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Postmodern Soundings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this first chapter is to gain a greater understanding of the “riot of diversity”¹ that has been called postmodernism. The following overview is geared to the particular postmodern problematic facing contemporary discourse on sacramental presence, and in this sense is meant to be a preparation for the question of how postmodern thought is made productive for the Christian tradition by contemporary theology. In this, as we have already seen, Heidegger’s relationship to postmodernism will be accented insofar as his critique of Western thought emerges as an important catalyst for postmodern sacramental theology. At the end of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Sacramental Presence in Louis-Marie Chauvet</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theology of Louis-Marie Chauvet is a sustained example of how Heidegger can be made productive in the theology of sacramental presence, and also theology in general. Chauvet moves his theological statements completely outside of the realm of metaphysics understood as a privileged discursive conceptualism; such statements may only be made via a phenomenology and hermeneutics of the ritual dynamic proper to Christian liturgy. In this symbolic mode, as we will see, theological statements, no longer mediated by traditional metaphysics, will be weighted more towards history than ontology, and therefore more towards absence than presence. Vincent J. Miller asserts that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Sacramental Presence in Lieven Boeve</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While Boeve believes Chauvet’s hermeneutical-theological project “offers a plausible and relevant<italic>relecture</italic>of Christian existence today,” he suggests that the project nevertheless remains a child of the early shift to hermeneutics and linguistics.¹ In this, he draws attention to new questions of particularism, narrativism, relativism, and false universalism that must push the hermeneutical project still further. Concerned that the paths pointed to by these questions will lead many back to the safety and security of an onto-theological approach, Boeve asserts that, notwithstanding the risks, we must follow where this methodology leads. Specifically, in relation to a further<italic>relecture</italic>of Chauvet’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Praxis of Sacramental Presence after Heidegger</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Up to this point in our analysis, we have made our way very broadly through the conceptual scaffolding of the work of Louis-Marie Chauvet and Lieven Boeve, identifying the major postmodern features of their thought and drawing an initial connection between these features and their bearing on the theme of sacramental presence. What has not yet been accomplished is a more detailed consideration of the implications—whether proximate or remote—of these features in regard to the individual sacraments themselves and therefore in relation to the praxis of sacramental presence. To this end, we select two sacraments for study in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Reimagining Metaphysics after Onto-Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean-Luc Marion has remarked that “one must ask forgiveness for every essay in theology.”¹ Just as St. Thomas purportedly reached the conclusion that, when compared to the living glory of God, “all that I have written seems like straw,” so Marion stresses the shortcomings of discourse on God insofar as it is tattooed by the abyss between objective glory and the unworthiness of its interpreter. As a general rule of thumb, these sentiments of Thomas and Marion simply remind us of the enduring and ineliminable<italic>maior dissimilitudo</italic>between God Himself and any attempt to stammer words in His honor. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sacramental Presence and the Mother’s Smile</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The occlusion of the mother’s smile is the death of sacramental presence. The mother’s smile is the kiss of Being, the sign or symbol of all that is gratuitous, all that is gift, and therefore all that is non-calculative, nonmechanical, and non-violent. Its erasure therefore erodes the sacramental foundation of grace. A sacramental “sign,” it is also a phenomenological and metaphysical sign, a “real,” existent form from which breaks forth the splendor of the depths of Being. It signifies the permanence of the truth, goodness, and beauty of the created order. As form, it also refers to infinity, for “it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf1rx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
