<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7p9ck</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PT363.A4P73 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">German literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">18th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">German literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics, German</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">18th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics, German</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romanticism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Germany</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">18th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romanticism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Germany</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Imagery (Psychology) in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Aesthetic Vision and German Romanticism</book-title>
         <subtitle>Writing Images</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Prager</surname>
               <given-names>Brad</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781571133410</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781571136954</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Rochester, NY, USA; Woodbridge, Suffolk, UK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Brad Prager</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt169wdp2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The work of the groundbreaking writers and artists of German Romanticism -- including the writers Tieck, Brentano, and Eichendorff and the artists Caspar David Friedrich and Philipp Otto Runge -- followed from the philosophical arguments of the German Idealists, who placed emphasis on exploring the subjective space of the imagination. The Romantic perspective was a form of engagement with Idealist discourses, especially Kant's Critique of Pure Reason and Fichte's Science of Knowledge. Through an aggressive, speculative reading of Kant, the Romantics abandoned the binary distinction between the palpable outer world and the ungraspable space of the mind's eye and were therefore compelled to develop new terms for understanding the distinction between "internal" and "external." In this light, Brad Prager urges a reassessment of some of Romanticism's major oppositional tropes, contending that binaries such as "self and other," "symbol and allegory," and "light and dark," should be understood as alternatives to Lessing's distinction between interior and exterior worlds. Prager thus crosses the boundaries between philosophy, literature, and art history to explore German Romantic writing about visual experience, examining the interplay of text and image in the formulation of Romantic epistemology. Brad Prager is Associate Professor of German at the University of Missouri, Columbia.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="295"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>B. P.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Vorschule der Ästhetik</italic>(<italic>School for Aesthetics</italic>, 1804), Jean Paul also observes that in the mind of a genius the inner world frequently swallows up the external one. He then adds that there is a higher reflectiveness that divides that inner world into two parts: a self and its realm, or the creator and his world. While such statements are intended to describe the inner lives of Romantic geniuses, they are also indicative of an overall understanding of the life of the mind as it was discussed among the German Romantics. In Romantic literature and thought, the space of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1:</label>
                     <title>Interior and Exterior:</title>
                     <subtitle>G. E. Lessing’s Laocoon as a Prelude to Romanticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although Lessing was not a Romantic, his writings were important precursors to Romantic thought, especially his 1766 essay on the subject of the<italic>Laocoon</italic>, which served as a foundational moment in the Romantic discourse on the perception of art. The following chapter provides background for my general argument in that it explores the philosophical consequences of Lessing’s assertions about vision, art, and the exterior world. His observations concerning the<italic>Laocoon</italic>sculpture argue against the power of works of art as they are found “in the outside world” and instead favor aesthetic experience as it is said to occur in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2:</label>
                     <title>Image and Phantasm:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wackenroder’s Herzensergießungen eines kunstliebenden Klosterbruders, Tieck’s Franz Sternbalds Wanderungen, and the Emergence of the Romantic Paradigm</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the Romantics the canvas and the written page were sites of contestation, spaces on which ephemeral experience was said to be represented in the material world. Art, understood in these terms, became the middle point or stage upon which something absent and intangible was made to appear present and graspable. It was, in other words, a material invocation of a sphere unavailable to the senses. In the following chapter I attempt to reconstruct the model of aesthetic perception in the work of Wackenroder and Tieck in light of the epistemological and perceptual categories laid out by Lessing’s essay on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3:</label>
                     <title>Symbol and Allegory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Clemens Brentano’s Godwi</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although he wrote his novel<italic>Godwi, oder Das steinerne Bild der Mutter</italic>(hereafter<italic>Godwi</italic>) in Jena, Clemens Brentano was not really part of the Jena circle of Romantics. His real fame as a Romantic writer and poet came after he moved to Heidelberg and became associated with a circle of writers that included Achim von Arnim, Josef Görres, and Friedrich Creuzer, among others. Together with von Arnim, Brentano published an anthology of<italic>Volkslieder</italic>(folk songs) called<italic>Des Knaben Wunderhorn: Alte deutsche Lieder</italic>(<italic>The Youth’s Magic Horn</italic>) in three volumes between 1805 and 1808. As a result, they became the leading</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4:</label>
                     <title>Sublimity and Beauty:</title>
                     <subtitle>Caspar David Friedrich and Joseph Anton Koch</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most attempts to place the work of Friedrich in context tend to focus on his Protestantism, his patriotism, his contempt for the French, and the reasons he was confined to his bed after Prussia’s defeat by Napoleon in 1806. Friedrich’s paintings from that period are in turn said to express “a desire for freedom based on a revolutionary return to a better past.¹ While this may indeed be the case, I wish to put the larger European historical context in the background and focus on several formal components of Friedrich’s style. Because analyses of Friedrich’s work tend to involve questions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5:</label>
                     <title>Light and Dark:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Paintings of Philipp Otto Runge</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philipp Otto Runge saw himself as the apostle of a new Romantic religion. He was undisputedly Christian, but his primary object of veneration was less the martyr’s passion than the interconnectedness of man and nature. He was dissatisfied with the contemporary arts — which, in his view, demurred from presenting the unfolding of the natural world — and considered Weimar Classicism a flight into the past. He saw classicism’s failure primarily in its lack of attention to color. Using Jacob Böhme’s theology of light and dark as a basis, Runge developed his own approach to religious painting. For him a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6:</label>
                     <title>Absolution and Contradiction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Confrontations with Art in Heinrich von Kleist’s “Die heilige Cäcilie oder Die Gewalt der Musik” and “Der Findling”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to critique the philosophical concept of the absolute subject — the subject posited by German idealist thought — one need not dismiss wholesale all prior Western metaphysics, as did Heidegger. For his part, Kleist made narratives of such critiques. Casting a critical eye upon contemporary philosophical systems, he relentlessly denied absolution to the characters in his texts. His explorations of the fundamentally fragmentary nature of subjectivity implicated him in the same Romantic philosophical dilemma that I have been describing throughout. If an abyss can be said to have opened around 1800, Kleist fell into it. In this chapter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7:</label>
                     <title>Self and Other:</title>
                     <subtitle>Joseph von Eichendorff’s Das Marmorbild</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Joseph von Eichendorff was born into a Catholic family in Upper Silesia in 1788. The Eichendorffs were landed gentry who had recently taken residence in a castle (Lubowitz). As Eichendorff grew older, however, it became clear that it would not be financially viable for him or his brother, Wilhelm, to continue as “gentleman farmers.” He studied in Halle and Heidelberg at the height of Romanticism, ending up in Vienna when he was twenty-one, where he spent time with the Schlegels and with Adam Müller, among others. Although he passed the civil service exam and served in the military, he was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>226</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preceding chapters I have studied a range of literary and visual works representing a variety of Romantic encounters with art that shed light on the relationship between the real world and the space of the imagination as it was conceived around 1800. These examples have served to paint a fuller picture, so to speak, of what I consider a major turning point in the construction of the modern subject, particularly in relation to aesthetic experience. The critics and artists associated with this period opened a space we still inhabit; the contradictions they confronted have not yet been resolved.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt169wdp2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
