<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN56.M94G6</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Myth in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Mythical Intentions in Modern Literature</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gould</surname>
               <given-names>Eric</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400886258</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400886252</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey; Guildford, Surrey</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1981</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1m3225s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Eric Gould revises some current assumptions in literary myth criticism, especially Jungian notions of the archetype and myth's immanence in literature that have dominated literary studies for so long. Working from structuralist theories of language, myth, and psyche, he defines myth as part of the symbolic order of language which grows out of the duplicity of the sign.</p>
         <p>Originally published in .</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback and hardcover editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="290"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any account of the relation between myth and literature has a responsibility first to define “myth.” And there, with historical stubbornness, lies not merely a problem, but perhaps the entire subject of myth studies. On the one hand, there is a question as to what myths actually refer to, since they have come to mean many things, from primitive and sacred ritual to propaganda and ideological statements. On the other, there is a good deal of confusion and conflicting argument over how to define the significance of myth. Is it primarily a matter of thematics, or form, or function—or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>ON THE ESSENTIAL IN MYTH:</title>
                     <subtitle>INTERPRETING THE ARCHETYPE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The archetypalist position is a very familiar one in literary studies, where it has sanctioned a long history of interpretation as the art of translating symbols into universal archetypes. From this we learn, according to Jung, that the creative process “consists in the unconscious activation of an archetypal image, and in elaborating and shaping this image into the finished work. By giving it shape, the artist translates it into the language of the present, and so makes it possible for us to find our way back to the deepest springs of life.”³ Jung is clearly the most influential figure in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>THE STRUCTURAL MODEL:</title>
                     <subtitle>ANTHROPOLOGY AND SEMIOTICS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is there a genetic model available to us which fulfills the ontological conditions for myth as discourse which I have just been discussing? For obvious reasons, one hesitates to assert that such a model could possibly exist, but it is valuable nonetheless to turn with some skepticism, but a good deal of admiration, to one of the most influential attempts to prove that myth has some kind of discernible structure. This will give us an opportunity to examine in more detail the relationship of the structural model to mythicity. Claude Lévi-Strauss, in lengthy documentation from totemistic myth drawn mainly from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>MYTHIC INVERSION AND ABSTRACTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>JAMES JOYCE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last two chapters, we have seen that there is a progression from the ontological conditions of myth as language to more functional terms for its existence. Mythicity may be revealed in the play of language, but it is also a systematic attempt to grasp the world as fact and metaphor, as a synchronic and diachronic whole. We can see the relevance to a theory of myth of Saussure, Gadamer, and Lacan, on the one hand, and Levi-Strauss and Barthes on the other. The theory of myth and mythicity embodies a necessary link between interpretation theory and Structuralism. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>THE MYTHIC AND THE NUMINOUS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We cannot answer the question of what makes mythology so attractive to writers and readers of modern literature if we remain with structure and semiotics alone and ignore myth’s talent for arguing for the numinous signifier and the validity of the supernatural. But, not surprisingly, that has been a much avoided question in modern literary criticism. The safest way of showing the relationship between the sacred and art, for example, has long been to emphasize art’s reference to or use of religious and mythological (meaning archetypal) motifs. Art becomes the transition between the numinous and the everyday. But as I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>RECOVERING THE NUMINOUS:</title>
                     <subtitle>D. H. LAWRENCE AND T. S. ELIOT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From opposing ideological positions—familiarly translated as vitalist-theosophical on the one hand and orthodox Anglo-Catholic on the other—D. H. Lawrence and T. S. Eliot have been considered important in our modern tradition for their effort to reinstate some connection between religion and art in a literature aggressively shorn of religious thought. If we think of early twentieth-century writing as occasionally turning to some prescription for spiritual health, then we do think of Lawrence and Eliot. But what prescriptiveness there is—and it is perhaps less pronounced than criticism would have it—is not the affinity between these two writers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SELECT BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3225s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>280</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
