<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Christian Ethics as Witness</book-title>
         <subtitle>Barth's Ethics for a World at Risk</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HADDORFF</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173749</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903025</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>David Haddorff</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf9s9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Christian ethics is less a system of principles, rules, or even virtues, and more of a free and open-ended responsible witness to God's gracious action to be with and for others and the world. &lt;CR&gt;&lt;CR&gt; Postmodernity has left us with the risky uncertainty of knowing and doing the good. It also leaves us with the global risks of political violence and terrorism, economic globalization and financial crisis, and environmental destruction and global climate change. How should Christians respond to these problems? Haddorf creatively explores how Christian ethics is best understood as a witness to God's action, bringing together two of his interests, Christian social ethics and social theory, and the theology and ethics of Karl Barth. &lt;CR&gt;&lt;CR&gt; Although demanding and sometimes uncertain after postmodern changes, christian ethics enable humankind to remain God's witnesses of love and care for the future, even in a world at risk.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="494"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haddorff</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book brings together two long-standing interests of mine, namely Christian social ethics and social theory, and the theology and ethics of Karl Barth. Giving serious attention to both of these fields of inquiry is not an easy task, but requires a great deal of thinking about how the methodologies of these two fields fit together. On one hand, this really is not a problem for the social ethicist who occasionally refers to Barth’s theology or ethics, by applying his thought to issues like church and state, war, or politics. On the other hand, it is a different matter when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Theological Ethics in Transition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter looks at the conversation between theology and ethics in its historical transition from modernity to postmodernity. The first part of the chapter discusses how the relationship of theology and ethics leads to an inherent tension within the strategies of theological and Christian ethics. The second part provides a general summary of the characteristics of modernity and its affect on modern theological ethics, with particular references to Rene Descartes, Immanuel Kant, and Friedrich Schleiermacher. Two of the most important characteristics of modern theology and ethics are the emphasis on<italic>poesis</italic>and<italic>praxis</italic>, which leads to two important rami-fications, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Barth’s Early Ethics and the Trinitarian Other</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter looks at the early development of the theological ethics of Karl Barth. Because of his significant wrestling with the problems of modern theology and ethics in the early twentieth century, the early years of Barth’s thinking (1916–31) provides an important point of departure for our study. Barth rejects the anthropocentric “immanent frame” of liberal theology, by shifting theology away from personal religious consciousness toward a genuine search for the divine trinitarian<italic>Other</italic>; his method is deconstructive and critical before it becomes constructive and positivist. With this in mind, two important points must be stated about Barth’s early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Barth’s Social Ethics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Witness in Tumultuous Times</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter, we saw how Barth, in his early writings, responded theologically and practically to the events around him during 1910s and 1920s. Reversing the dominant structure of modern ethics, which attempts to secure human freedom by separating humanity from God, Barth saw clearly that human freedom depends upon God’s freedom to act<italic>in relatio</italic>. Thus, his task, in these early writings, was not to simply contrast God’s action and our action as the way to preserve human autonomy, but instead attempts to demonstrate how divine agency establishes, rather than negates, human agency. This theme more fully emerges</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Social Theory and Postmodernity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The last two chapters have demonstrated the fact that the church, as a witnessing community, cannot rise above and live outside its surrounding society and culture. In his 1924 essay “Church and Culture,” for example, Barth writes that the church cannot give witness without conversing with the “actual political and economic standards of its own age. Throughout its own course, the Church swims along in the stream of culture” (<italic>TC</italic>: 351). This does not imply, of course, that the church ought to accommodate itself to its surrounding culture, only that the church cannot “free itself even partially” from society and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>From Modern to Postmodern Ethics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter shifts our focus from social theory to ethical philosophy, showing how it too has been shaped by the transition from modernity to postmodernity. In chapters 1–2, we introduced this theological transition by looking at the shift from Kant and Schleiermacher to Barth. In the last chapter, we discussed characteristics of postmodernity as understood within current social theory, and concluded that social theory, by itself, cannot provide an answer to the problem of moral epistemology in social ethics. Although social theory makes positive contributions to our understanding of the social world we inhabit, it fails to provide a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Witness and the Word of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last two chapters, we have examined two central responses to the postmodern situation, and concluded that neither theory, as such, can tell us with certainty what the<italic>good</italic>is and how we ought to practice it in the world. The crisis of postmodernity affects both the “supply” and “demand” of ethics, that is of moral knowledge and action, of truth and agency, and embodying and doing the good. Without a coherent moral ontology there is no coherent understanding of moral realism; we cannot have a coherent view of the good because we cannot account for the moral structure</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Witness and Christian Moral Judgment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ethics as Christian witness begins with God’s action to be “with us” and “for us” in Jesus Christ. In this event, God has given Christians the<italic>freedom</italic>to respond, as witnesses, to this objective reality both individually and collectively within the church. This leads to a particular dialectical understanding of ethical judgment and action. That is, Christians give witness by both standing against the various powers that oppress humanity and standing with and for others, the church, and the world. In chapter two, we saw how Barth’s dialectical thought during the<italic>Römerbrief</italic>period often began with the No of transcendent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Witness and the Powers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>268</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter explores further Barth’s ethics of reconciliation as a “responsible witness of the Word of God” serving both “God and men” (<italic>CD IV</italic>/3: 609). The Yes of responsible moral judgment corresponds, in this chapter, to the No of resistance against the powers. This chapter begins with a theological discussion of the powers and its relation to ethics as it pertains to the subjects of evil, eschatology, and reconciliation. Central to this is a discussion of Christ’s victory over the powers, the triumph of<italic>Christus victor</italic>. Following this general discussion is a specific analysis of Barth’s discussion of the “spiritual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Witness and Public Ethics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Options in Christian Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter concludes this section exploring themes in Barth’s theological ethics in the context of contemporary Christian ethics. We have mostly been concerned with theoretical rather than practical issues, thereby looking at issues like moral knowledge, agency, and judgment. These various theoretical issues that Barth began struggling with in the early twentieth century still remain with us a century later. After a period of great liberal optimism and growing internationalism came the crisis of World War I. This horrific event challenged Barth and others of his generation to rethink strategies of Christian ethics, both in method and in practice. Central</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Witness and Christian Responsibility</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>343</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this last section of the book, we carry through in practice what was developed in theory, namely that Christian ethics is “responsible witness of the Word of God” serving both “God and men” (<italic>CD</italic>IV/3: 609). In each movement, there is a corresponding dialectic of God’s initiating action and human response. In chapters 7–8, we saw how the Yes of moral knowledge of the good, human agency, and moral judgment is followed by the No against the nothingness of sin, death, evil, and the powers. We are now able to discuss further how God’s reconciling Yes provides the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Political Witness:</title>
                     <subtitle>For Faith and Peace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>369</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the next three chapters, we carry through in a practical way Christian responsible witness as social ethics in political, economic, and environmental practice. In the last chapter, we focused on responsible witness to the other, the church, and the world. In each case, there is a dialectical movement between synthesis and diastasis, between the homogeneity and heterogeneity of church and world. As demonstrated earlier, the church as the “inner circle” is a witness to the “outer circle” of the civil community demonstrating how it, as secular witness, can affirm social ethical practice that is free and open-ended as it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Economic Witness:</title>
                     <subtitle>For Love and Justice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>394</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter follows the same pattern at the last chapter, but the focus shifts from political to economic witness. In so doing, we look at<italic>CD</italic>IV/2, where Jesus Christ embodies love and overcomes the sin of sloth, leading to “upbuilding” of the Christian community. Although the sins of pride and falsehood could equally apply to the power of mammon, this chapter correlates the sin of sloth with structural power of mammon. So, in dialectical fashion, sloth is juxtaposed with love, and mammon is juxtaposed with justice. Just as political witness leads to the practice of peace in the civil</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Environmental Witness:</title>
                     <subtitle>For Hope and Freedom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>415</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Barth finally visited America, in 1962, he gave what would be his last set of public lectures, published together in the fine book,<italic>Evangelical Theology</italic>. In the introduction, he makes the cryptic remark that what is needed at this time, on both sides of the Atlantic, is not a return to the traditional orthodoxy of Thomism, Lutheranism, or Calvinism or the liberal theology of Harnack and Troeltsch, and most of all not “Barthianism,” but what he calls a “theology of freedom.”¹ A theology of freedom, says Barth, is: “marked by freedom from fear of communism, Russia, inevitable nuclear warfare</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>447</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf9s9.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>459</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
