<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt4z9mq</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>William Faulkner</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Economy of Complex Words</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Godden</surname>
               <given-names>Richard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691130712</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">069113071X</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400827916</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7sb40"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In<italic>William Faulkner</italic>, Richard Godden traces how the novelist's late fiction echoes the economic and racial traumas of the South's delayed modernization in the mid-twentieth century. As the New Deal rapidly accelerated the long-term shift from tenant farming to modern agriculture, many African Americans were driven from the land and forced to migrate north. At the same time, white landowners exchanged dependency on black labor for dependency on northern capital. Combining powerful close readings of<italic>The Hamlet, Go Down, Moses</italic>, and<italic>A Fable</italic>with an examination of southern economic history from the 1930s to the 1950s, Godden shows how the novels' literary complexities--from their narrative structures down to their smallest verbal emphases--reflect and refract the period's economic complexities. By demonstrating the interrelation of literary forms and economic systems, the book describes, in effect, the poetics of an economy.</p>
         <p>Original in the way it brings together close reading and historical context,<italic>William Faulkner</italic>offers innovative interpretations of late Faulkner and makes a unique contribution to the understanding of the relation between literature and history.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MY TITLE intends no metaphor in its linking of language and economy. Words, as social instruments, exemplifying what Marx calls “practical consciousness,”¹ act upon a reality which they make as much as find. If the real is in a real sense made through words, those words needs must tend to complexity, not least because speakers inherit a language always “already occupied”² by prior and unknown users and usage. Since verbal instrumentalists work with a partially known instrument, and in circumstances not of their own design, they, to adapt Marx, are practically unconscious concerning large portions of their practice. Yet that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Earthing The Hamlet</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A PRELUDE: regarding leisured New Yorkers of the 1870s from the perspective of 1920, Edith Wharton is much preoccupied with social transition as registered in mannered artifacts, hence her attention to “Worth dresses,” in<italic>The Age of Innocence</italic>. Whether it is “vulgar” to wear Parisian fashions bought at Worth in the year of their purchase, or whether custom requires that such garments be “put away” for two years prior to display, concerns those gathered at Mrs Archer’s Thanksgiving dinner. One guest, Miss Jackson, blames the banker Beaufort for starting “the new fashion by making his wife clap her new clothes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Comparative Cows:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading The Hamlet for Its Residues</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>AS RATLIFF returns to the Bend, mourning Eula’s departure from it, Mink Snopes awaits his day in court. The point at issue between Mink Snopes and Jack Houston is a fence.¹ Unfenced or open range represented for Mink, and the southern tenantry, access to common use rights. Whereas, the principle, “fence stock, not crop,” served the interests of owners such as Houston. Varner, the magistrate, “fence rail…, thin,”² decides for Houston. His decision can only be read as class-interested. In the late 1880s fencing was the linchpin of the owners’ determination to control labor: a cropper or small renter who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Revenants, Remnants, and Counterrevolution in “The Fire and the Hearth”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE Agricultural Adjustment Act (AAA) of 1933 initiated the transformation of southern labor and its place, prompting a labor revolution, driven by federal funds, and effectively exorcising black from white. To read sociological commentators in the early 1930s, addressing southern agriculture, is to hear black tenants described as “virtual slaves,” held “in thrall,” subjected to “almost complete dependence” and “incapable of ever achieving but a modicum of self direction.”¹ Although the Civil War had freed the slave, it had done so only for southern landowners to bind him again in an alternative form of “dependency”: for chattel slavery read debt</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>“Pantaloon in Black” and “The Old People”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Migration, Mourning, and the Exquisite Corpse of African American Labor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN the plantation South, by 1942 historical conditions existed for the extraction of black from white. For two decades, whiteness had whitened by way of steady out-migration. With the decline of tenantry and the relaxation of the structure enforcing dependency, white, in the last instance, had less reason to be black. The first three stories of<italic>Go Down, Moses</italic>, usefully described by John Matthews as the “plantation trilogy,”¹ feature black movement, much of it away from whites. “Was” (set in 1859) concerns Turl’s annual runaway. Buck and Buddy McCaslin catch their slave, but not before black motion has disrupted two</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Reading the Ledgers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Textual Variants and Labor Variables</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Godden</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Polk</surname>
                           <given-names>Noel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE Old People” opens with Buck and Buddy tangled on the horns of a latently black beast;¹ the story closes with two males in bed, dark hand to white “flank.”² At either end, “The Old People” exhibits associative transformations rendered only slightly less shocking by their not being singular. The first four stories in<italic>Go Down, Moses</italic>, read cumulatively, release a whispered ur-narrative, or more properly an ur-narrative kit, whose constituent parts (bed; woman under erasure; male cross-racial couple; corpse) with each emergence advance toward emergency. The nub of that emergency, or so this argument has run, is to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Find the Jew:</title>
                     <subtitle>Modernity, Seriality, and Armaments in A Fable</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>FAULKNER published<italic>A Fable</italic>in 1954. He wrote it over the ten years between 1943 and 1954, a period during which issues of “hot,” “cold,” and “total” war came to preoccupy American life. A brief list may serve to make the point that<italic>A Fable</italic>, though set during a single week of the Great War, addresses militarization in a more extensive sense. The eleven years of the novel’s writing include: the last years of World War II (1943–45); the explosion of the first atomic bomb (August 1945); the Red Scare, reaching into the State Department and toward the Pentagon</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>“The Bugger’s a Jew”:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Fable as Melancholic Allegory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>MY ACCOUNT of<italic>A Fable</italic>, seeking the Jew and finding him in the potentially Semitic semen of the old general, risks simplifying the complex politics of the supreme commander’s sexuality. In 1918, aged sixty-two, the “old” general apparently approaches what Faulkner elsewhere spoke of as ungendered peace, but the biography of his missing years (1877–circa 1914), fabricated over two meetings by his contemporaries (graduates of the St Cyr military academy) in Paris (1877) and Zermatt (1887–88), suggests a life founded on a systematic negation of sexuality. Since the life is collectively and substantially made up, its findings may</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7sb40.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
