<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4w7x</collection-id>
      <volume>14</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Varieties of World Making</book-title>
         <subtitle>Beyond Globalization</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KARAGIANNIS</surname>
               <given-names>NATHALIE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WAGNER</surname>
               <given-names>PETER</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781846310195</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781781380857</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Liverpool University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt5vjmbn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Globalization has been the topic of heated debate in recent years, with one side asserting that it will produce a better standard of living for people around the world, and a fierce opposition arguing that it will ultimately lead to greater poverty and the destruction of unique human cultures. Varieties of World Making tackles the issue from a different angle, proposing that the contemporary global network of business, politics and culture be viewed from the inter-disciplinary perspective of ‘world making’. Drawn from the ranks of sociology, law, international relations, political philosophy and history, the distinguished contributors cut through polarized rhetoric to examine the current global situation. Their proposed diagnoses draw upon thoughtful analyses of various political dilemmas whose ripple effects are felt around the world, such as the volatile relationship between Islam and Europe, or the legal foundations for a true international order absent in the shadows of imperialism. Varieties of World Making will be an essential resource for all those grappling with the complex consequences of globalization for the future.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Globalization or World-Making?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Karagiannis</surname>
                           <given-names>Nathalie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wagner</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An artist living at the end of the twelfth century in France contributed to the miniature illustration of the<italic>Bible de Souvigny</italic>by painting the creation of the world. Until the sixth day, everything is in order: day after day, God creates light, the firmament, the earth, the animals. The first deviation by the artist from the Biblical text concerns the seventh day when, instead of resting – as he should, according to Genesis – God creates Adam and Eve. Even less predictably, the miniaturist adds an eighth day to the creation of the world: it is the day of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Republic or Empire?</title>
                     <subtitle>On the American End and the European Beginning of Politics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Henningsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Manfred</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When in 2000 Michael Hardt and Antonio Negri published their book,<italic>Empire</italic>, it became an instant best-seller in anti-globalization circles around the world. The major thesis of the authors was that an empire-like regime with no territorial boundaries was presiding over ‘an irresistible and irreversible globalization of economic and cultural exchanges. Along with the global market and global circuits of production has emerged a global order, a new logic and structure of rule – in short, a new form of sovereignty.’ The empire they saw ‘materializing before our eyes’ (Hardt and Negri 2000: ix) reverted to the more familiar imperial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Latin American Varieties of Modernity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Larrain</surname>
                           <given-names>Jorge</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following Castoriadis, I shall understand by ‘modernity’ the conjunction of two key significations: autonomy and control. Autonomy refers to the freedom of a society to make its own laws; control has to do with the expansion of rational mastery over the world of things, including the development of science and technology and their application to production and the control of nature (Castoriadis 1990: 15–17). Peter Wagner has developed this idea more precisely into an ‘interpretative approach’, which focuses on the responses that human beings give to certain basic<italic>problématiques</italic>of social life, responses that change with the onset of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Multiple Modernities or Global Interconnections:</title>
                     <subtitle>Understanding the Global Post the Colonial</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bhambra</surname>
                           <given-names>Gurminder K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The colonial encounter has been a defining moment in the making of the contemporary world. It has<italic>made</italic>a particular world and established cognitive patterns for<italic>knowing</italic>the world, yet the colonial encounter is missing in most sociological accounts of modernity. In recent times, increasing significance has been given to global phenomena. Acknowledging the complexity brought by globalization and interdependence has led theorists to contend that a new approach to modernity is needed. A shift from the singular trajectory of modernity to multiple modernities has been recommended (Arnason 2000; Delanty 2004; Eisenstadt 2000, 2001, 2004; Eisenstadt and Schluchter 1998; Wittrock</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Europe, America, China:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contemporary Wars and their Implications for World Orders</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Davis</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The operative paradigm of the current world order reflected in the UN Charter has proved a troubled one in the post-Cold War era. Differences over principles of sovereignty and military intervention have divided the world, especially the three critical strategic actors addressed in this essay: the United States, China and Europe. I characterize their competing notions of sovereignty as ‘new sovereigntism’, ‘old sovereigntism’ and ‘transnationalism’, respectively.¹ These three views, while clearly colliding with each other, are also in many respects mutually constitutive. In the shrinking world addressed in the Introduction and various chapters of this book, the challenge for international</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Islam Online:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Internet, Religion and Politics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Siapera</surname>
                           <given-names>Eugenia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The historico-political developments following September 11 2001 have raised the profile of Islam and its political relevance. From a secular and liberal perspective, religious/transcendental struggles should be confined to the private domain and should concern individual consciences. However, the forceful entry of Islam as a topic into the public domain post-9/11 represents a questioning of the secular/liberal world. This raises broader questions about the links between religion and politics and the relevance of religious interpretations for our life in common and in the commons, that is, in the public domain. At stake here are the common elements and bonds necessary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>‘In the Name of Politics’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sovereignty, Democracy and the Multitude in India</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chakrabarty</surname>
                           <given-names>Dipesh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>‘To take part in demonstrations and hooliganism<italic>in the name of politics</italic>’ [my emphasis], said Jawaharlal Nehru, the first Prime Minister of India, speaking to a group of college students in the city of Patna in Bihar on August 30 1955, ‘is, apart from the right or wrong of it, not proper for students of any country’ (Nehru 2001b [1955]: 83). A ‘minor’ conflict between the students of the B. N. College, Patna, and the State Transport Employees had led to police firing on the students on August 12 and 13 1955. The Independence Day celebrations on August 15 were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>‘Horizontal’ Connections and Interactions in Global Development</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Halperin</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to consider fully the challenges and possibilities of world-making, it is necessary to understand the socioeconomic space that already exists across national boundaries and how it has been politically constituted and reconstituted over time. Nelson Goodman’s observation, already cited by the editors in the Introduction to this volume, makes the point precisely: ‘Worldmaking as we know it always starts from worlds already at hand; the making is a re-making’ (1978: 6).</p>
                     <p>Discussions of the global era and how to navigate or shape it often fail to give sufficient consideration to the global socioeconomic order that pre-existed, and continuously</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Multiple Solidarities:</title>
                     <subtitle>Autonomy and Resistance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Karagiannis</surname>
                           <given-names>Nathalie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter looks at world-making from the viewpoint of one of its constitutive ingredients: solidarity. Solidarity is the substance of a successful world-making, if world-making is defined as the creation of a common universe. It makes sense to think that in order for this common universe to exist, there must be something that holds it together. Here, I will argue that solidarity should not be conceptualized as the ‘something that holds the common universe together’ but rather as the ‘there must be something that holds the common universe together’. The distinction here lies in a step I think worth taking,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>The Making and the Unmaking of Europe in its Encounter with Islam:</title>
                     <subtitle>Negotiating French Republicanism and European Islam</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Göle</surname>
                           <given-names>Nilüfer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The point of departure for this chapter is that Islam is an active agent in the alteration of European space, necessitating a new frame for thinking about the relationship between the political and the religious bond, and the ways in which this relationship reinforces or transforms the meaning of a polity such as the French Republic or a religious community such as European Islam. Rethinking the relations between Islam and Europe requires a new conceptual space, a new frame that introduces an intercultural perspective to our readings of European modernity. It requires a sensitivity to the duality of certain key</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Democratic Justice in a Globalizing Age:</title>
                     <subtitle>Thematizing the Problem of the Frame</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fraser</surname>
                           <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Globalization is changing the way we argue about justice. Not so long ago, in the heyday of social democracy, disputes about justice presumed what I shall call a ‘Keynesian–Westphalian frame’. Typically played out within modern territorial states, arguments about justice were assumed to concern relations among fellow citizens, to be subject to debate within national publics, and to contemplate redress by national states. This was true for each of two major families of justice claims: claims for socioeconomic redistribution and claims for legal or cultural recognition. At a time when the Bretton Woods system of international capital controls facilitated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Contracting and Founding in Times of Conflict</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Girard</surname>
                           <given-names>Charlotte</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the emergence of a common world out of a diverse set of founding assumptions – and the question of what sort of world it can be – are crucial in the context of pronounced regional varieties of world-making conceptions. Assuming that world-making possibly means that a society must be framed, then this frame entails rules – i.e., rules can be the frame. This call for rules answers Nancy Fraser’s call (in Chapter 10) for a frame. But the frame she suggests should be of a special kind. She argues that framing refers to transformative politics and thus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>Worlds Emerging:</title>
                     <subtitle>Approaches to the Creation and Constitution of the Common</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mouzakitis</surname>
                           <given-names>Angelos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>232</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Implicit in the idea of world-making are the assumptions that human beings are the makers of their own history and that in the incessant shaping of their socio-historical worlds they experience some sort of commonality. This dual presupposition entails the attribution of at least some sort of control to both individuals and emerging collectivities over the status and direction of socio-historical institutions and life-trajectories. The allegedly ‘common’ world, emerging and/or persisting in time, poses a number of theoretical problems, of which this chapter attempts to examine only those relating to its creation and constitution. However, a preliminary task that I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 13</label>
                     <title>Imperial Modernism and European World-Making</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wagner</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the time of writing, it seems that the sceptics have been right. After the referenda on the constitutional treaty of the European Union in France and the Netherlands, the European political project is in disarray. Some of those sceptics will even insist that there never was such a political project anyway. The European Union, in their view, is nothing but an association of states to further their own interests, and the apparent acceleration of political integration over the past fifteen years did not really change its nature. The EU Charter of Fundamental Rights, so they will underline, explicitly does</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 14</label>
                     <title>Global Governance and the Emergence of a ‘World Society’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kratochwil</surname>
                           <given-names>Friedrich</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That nations dwell in eternal anarchy has been one of the defining assumptions that have shaped the socialization of several generations of students of international relations. While political struggle inside the state takes place in the shadow of the law (conceived as the sovereign’s command), this mediation was thought to be absent in the international arena. However, the demise of the Soviet Union and the increase in the volume, scope and speed of transnational interactions challenged this traditional assumption of anarchy and non-co-operation. Departing from the presumption that war was now a less plausible defining characteristic of the international arena,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5vjmbn.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
