<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Martin Luther and Buddhism</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Chung</surname>
               <given-names>Paul S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Moltmann</surname>
               <given-names>Jürgen</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227172940</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903292</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Paul S. Chung</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf98j"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Martin Luther and Buddhism: Aesthetics of Suffering carefully traces the historical and theological context of Luther's breakthrough in terms of articulating justification and justice in connection to the Word of God and divine suffering. Chung critically and constructively engages in dialogue with Luther and with later interpreters of Luther such as Barth and Moltmann, placing the Reformer in dialogue not only with Asian spirituality and religions but also with an emerging global theology of religions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="472"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moltmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Jürgen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A foreword is neither an afterword nor a review. A foreword should open up the door to a text and make one feel so invited that the book gets read. I will confine my introductory remarks to such an invitation. The work of Paul Chung says much more than the title suggests. The title speaks of a comparison between Martin Luther and (Mahayana) Buddhism in regard to the “Aesthetics of Suffering,” but the content provides an extraordinarily rich theology that combines Europe with Asia, the sixteenth century with the twenty-first century, and Christian theology with the history of religion in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Second Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chung</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is designed to bring the great reformer Martin Luther into dialogue with Asian theology and spirituality, especially that of Mahayana Buddhism. A common basis for interreligious dialogue between Luther and Buddhism lies in the interpretation of<italic>dukkha</italic>(suffering), in which an attempt is made to construct a theological aesthetics of divine suffering and human suffering. Therefore, it is of special significance to contextualize Luther’s theological insights and their ecumenical repercussions in an encounter with other traditions. In recent ecumenical conversation, Luther is examined in depth as we see him in his theological struggle and project. In this ecumenical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxiv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Martin Luther in the Context of Poverty and Religious Pluralism</title>
                     <subtitle>Doing Theology in a Pluralistic Context</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It becomes an inevitable reality in Asia that a way of dealing with the gospel/culture question turns into a gospel/religions question without further ado. Consider a story about a missionary and a tribal leader: A young missionary worked with a tribal group for several months and then sent a message to his senior colleague asking him to officiate at a baptism as the sign of recognizing them as Christians. The senior missionary arrived and made a plan for baptism on the following day. During the night the tribal council had a serious discussion, and then sent a message of regret</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Uniqueness of Luther’s Life and Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theology of Martin Luther cannot be fully understood without considering his spiritual and social biography, at the heart of which lies his struggle for and discovery of God’s justification for all. As all the theological structures and ideas of Luther are inspired and extended by his teaching on justification, so his doctrine of justification becomes the driving force of his whole life-struggle and the larger program of the reformation. Martin Luther (1483–1546) is thought to have been born on November 10, 1483, in a middle-class house in Eisleben, and named after the saint of the day, Martin of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Martin Luther and the Doctrine of Justification in Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “Joint Declaration on the Doctrine of Justification” AFFIRMS an epoch-making new ecumenical consensus and reconciliation between the Roman Catholic Church and the Lutheran World Federation concerning the understanding of justification, which has historically been a stumbling block to both sides.¹ This declaration was signed on October 31, 1999, Reformation day. In order fully to understand the importance of this statement on justification, it is necessary to take note of the historical development and debates on this doctrine that have played a major role separating the Catholic Church from Protestant churches. In this chapter I discuss justification in a broader</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Luther and Theology of the Cross in Context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen from Luther’s theological development in relation to scholastic theology (in chapter 3), Luther’s understanding of<italic>theologia crucis</italic>cannot adequately be understood without the background of the late medieval heritage with which Luther struggled. Scholastic thinkers—the “schoolmen” as they were called—are often represented as debating earnestly, if pointlessly, how many angels could dance on the head of a pin, or whether or not God is able to create a stone that God cannot lift up, etc. Scholasticism was regarded by the humanists at the beginning of the sixteenth century as pointless, arid intellectual speculation over</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Luther and Asian Theology of Trinity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I begin with the<italic>filioque</italic>(the Spirit proceeding from the Father and the Son) controversy. Under the influence of Eastern Orthodox theology of the Trinity, Moltmann makes a wholesale attack on Sabellian notes in Western trinitarian theology. Thus, ecumenical challenges to the<italic>filioque</italic>added to the creed of Nicea and Constantinople have a well-known history. The doctrine of the Trinity reaches its climax in God’s plan of salvation in the person and the work of Jesus Christ, his incarnation, crucifixion, resurrection, and ascension through the Spirit (cf. Eph 1:3–14).</p>
                     <p>Although there is no explicit mention of the full doctrine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Luther and Asian Eucharistic Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What shapes and characterizes Luther’s ecclesiology is his theology of Word and Sacraments. In this chapter we meet Luther’s eucharistic theology in relation to Roman Catholic teaching. Luther’s theology of the Lord’s Supper, when seen in a time-related and eschatological dimension, will engage the spirituality of ancestral rites that has been controversial until the present in Asian churches and theologies. Would it be possible to deepen Luther’s theology of the Lord’s Supper in terms of his keen insight into Jesus’ descent into hell? If we perceive a real presence of Jesus Christ in the Eucharist in relation to Christ’s total</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Re-visitation of Martin Luther and Karl Barth in Interreligious Dialogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>337</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Baar Statement of the World Council Churches (1990) encouraged Christian theology to improve concern about other religions and take issue with interreligious dialogue in exploration of the theology of religious pluralism. The theology of religions has become more and more attractive, but also controversial in its encounter with postmodern thought and hermeneutic theory. In the circle of theology of religions, Martin Luther and Karl Barth have undergone intensive criticism for their conservative-evangelical attitude toward world religions. Barth’s understanding of other religions is often criticized as a model advocating the conservative position, the content of which would imply an exclusive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this writing I am interested in articulating a hermeneutical theology of interfaith dialogue in engagement with this issue of suffering by interpreting and actualizing Luther’s theology as it encounters (Mahayana) Buddhist wisdom. According to Hans Urs von Balthasar, a theological aesthetics begins with the expression that God’s glory appears. Thus, God’s beauty leads the beholder out of the previous existence into a participation in God’s mission in Christ in the presence of the Spirit.¹</p>
                     <p>However, when it comes to God’s appearance in Christ’s life and death, a theological discourse on aesthetics is not sufficient without reference to God’s loving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>Afterword The Theologia Crucis and the Aesthetics of Suffering in Postmodern Divinity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>413</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luther’s theological aesthetics of God’s glory in Christ’s suffering love lays a basis for reshaping and redirecting motives of Asian post-confessional theology toward a different understanding and transformation of Luther. When Luther encounters a postmodern context, he can best be understood by challenging and transcending him. His doctrine of justification, theology of the cross, Trinity, law and gospel, eucharistic theology, and two kingdoms theory among others are seen at the point of the death, resurrection and reconciliation of the crucified Christ, the scope and reach of which is of inclusive, universal character allowing and tolerating other ways. If aesthetics are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary of Technical Terms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf98j.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>444</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
