<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">D804.3.C374 2005</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust memorials</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Influence</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Denkmal fèr die ermordeten Juden Europas (Berlin, Germany)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Vâlodrome d’hiver (Paris, France)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Holocaust Monuments and National Memory</book-title>
         <subtitle>France and Germany since 1989</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Carrier</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2005</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781571819048</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782389613</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">178238961X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Peter Carrier</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1x76f8h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Since 1989, two sites of memory with respect to the deportation and persecution of Jews in France and Germany during the Second World War have received intense public attention: the Vélo d'Hiver (Winter Velodrome) in Paris and the Monument for the Murdered Jews of Europe or Holocaust Monument in Berlin. Why is this so? Both monuments, the author argues, are unique in the history of memorial projects. Although they are genuine "sites of memory", neither monument celebrates history, but rather serve as platforms for the deliberation, negotiation and promotion of social consensus over the memorial status of war crimes in France and Germany. The debates over these monuments indicate that it is the communication among members of the public via the mass media, rather than qualities inherent in the sites themselves, which transformed these sites into symbols beyond traditional conceptions of heritage and patriotism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="280"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The impact of monuments and related rituals upon collective memories of the Second World War is a source of recurrent political debate in all former Allied and Axis countries. The spate of fiftieth anniversary commemorations of this event served not only to reappraise national histories in light of the end of the balance of power sustained during the Cold War, but also to symbolically compensate the dwindling number of living witnesses and victims of the war period. In both cases, public representations acquired considerable political authority as means of sustaining social memories of this period. But do representations ensure that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Monuments in History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his famous essay on ‘Monuments’ of 1927, the writer Robert Musil claims that there is nothing more invisible to the human eye than a monument. ‘The remarkable thing about monuments is that one does not notice them. There is nothing in the world so invisible as a monument.’¹ The suggestion that precisely those images, figures and events that people strive to represent in public should go unheeded provokes numerous questions about the relation of individuals and groups to symbols and their impact as focal points of political communication. If familiarity with everyday objects indeed erodes the curiosity of passers-by,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>History in Monuments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Amonument may never lay claim to artistic autonomy from its social and historical context. It is necessarily a product and reflection of its time, derived from the initiative of an individual, group or state. The production and reception of monuments are determined by three diachronic historical moments. First, the moment of the historical event or figure which it represents or denotes. Second, the moment at which the monument was conceived and constructed. Third, the moment(s) of its reception, when subjected to interpretation or debate due to its renewed political relevance, a decision to renovate or demolish the monument, or even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part II Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The national monuments in memory of deportations and genocide carried out during the Second World War, known as the Vél’ d’Hiv’ and Holocaust Monument, arose from distinct political and cultural contexts and did not result from a policy of Franco-German reconciliation. Comparison of these monuments does not reveal direct interaction between the two memory cultures, therefore, but transnational analogies between local commemorative customs and discourses as well as local specificities.¹ It is precisely with such investigations of commemorations on the basis of analogies and specificities that it is possible to establish the degree to which the focal points, narrative structures</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Paris:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Vél’ d’Hiv’ and the Promise of National Reconciliation 1992–97</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Controversial ceremonies on the site of a central monument commemorating the deportation of Jews from Paris in 1942 became the focus of presidents Mitterrand and Chirac’s attempts to secure national reconciliation from 1992. Memories of state persecutions and victims of national policy presented an obstacle to the representation of conventional national identity. The monument and related commemorations of Vichy were nevertheless used to legitimate a cohesive official state memory: by rhetorical appeals to humanist traditions and to nationhood as an ideal, almost religious vocation.</p>
                     <p>The introduction of a parliamentary bill to instigate a ‘National Day of Commemoration of the Racist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Berlin:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Monument for the Murdered Jews of Europe and the Promise of Consensus 1988–2000</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Plans for a ‘Monument for the Murdered Jews of Europe’ or ‘Holocaust Monument’² in Berlin gave rise to one of the most intense and prolonged debates over the memorial legacy and representations of the Second World War in the history of the Federal Republic of Germany. Following the renaming of streets and the removal or modification of monuments in the eastern sector of the city from 1989, and parallel to negotiations over the possible reconstruction of the Hohenzollern Palace, the debate over the planned Holocaust Monument exemplified the problematical cultural and symbolic transformation of this city prior to and following</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Institutionalisation of Memory in Public Art and Rhetoric</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This detailed examination of the evolution of the Vél d’Hiv’ and Holocaust Monument reveals discrepancies, but also analogies and overlaps between memory cultures in France and Germany. Memory cultures are not unique and confined in time and space, but are subject to what the sociologist Ulrich Beck calls ‘polycentric memory, in which non-state, transnational actors (such as social movements) also play a role’¹ – a model which he perceives to be a key to the constitution of a European memory culture. Beck dismisses Christianity, ethnicity or principles of the welfare state as foundations of either national or European heritages. A multinational</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part III Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dramatic increase in the number of historical monuments, commemorations and exhibitions since the 1970s is an international phenomenon, as demonstrated by the sociologist Frank Füredi in his extensive study of memory cultures in the U.K., France, Germany, Japan and the United States.¹ In Europe, debates over historical monuments, museums and commemorations have occurred with such frequency and intensity during this period that the debates themselves have become paradigmatic moments if not intellectual monuments of contemporary public understandings of history. Controversy over the cult of the past following the National Heritage Act of 1983 in the U.K., the Historians’ Dispute</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The National Memorial Paradigm</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The proliferation of monuments and commemorations and the social and political values invested in them since the 1970s are symptomatic of societies that have been actively seeking a symbolic reinforcement of collective memories. Public symbols are neither a cause nor a consequence of the present international preoccupation with memory, however, but the very language with which these societies transmit and negotiate their pasts. What are the historical and political origins and the social consequences of this phenomenon? And how do contemporary societies legitimate their existence on the basis of memory and historical representations? The rise of memory cultures, which is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Postnational Memorial Paradigm</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The monumental historiographical projects on sites of memory in France and Germany,<italic>Les Lieux de mémoire</italic>and<italic>Deutsche Erinnerungsorte</italic>, provide pedagogical models for understanding the historical foundations of contemporary memory cultures in these two countries. Both projects are highly informative, thorough in their treatment of historical facts, and theoretically innovative. The notions that collective symbols are today ‘patrimonial’ instead of partisan foci of collective memory, that we are subjects of ‘archival’ memory, that ‘present time’ is a historiographical category in which societies forge a cohesive self-understanding on the basis of shared symbols of the past, and that the mass media</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Dialogic Monuments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Vél’ d’Hiv’ and Holocaust Monument are examples of a new kind of war memorial. They commemorate neither military victory nor glorious defeat, customary following national campaigns of the nineteenth century and following the First World War, but war crimes. Consequently, there is no all-embracing notion that captures either the style or function of contemporary monuments. Several existent terms, such as ‘ephemeral’ or ‘objectless’ monuments, pinpoint essential formal features of monumental art, but are normative and partial (see Introduction). Other concepts have pinpointed the reactive function of monuments in relation to existing monuments and traditions, including ‘counter-monuments’ and monuments erected</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76f8h.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
