<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS374.S68 S53 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social classes in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social conflict in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Illiberal Imagination</book-title>
         <subtitle>Class and the Rise of the U.S. Novel</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Shapiro</surname>
               <given-names>Joe</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813940526</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813940524</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Charlottesville; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1wx93xr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>The Illiberal Imagination</italic>offers a synthetic, historical formalist account of how-and to what end-U.S. novels from the late eighteenth century to the mid-1850s represented economic inequality and radical forms of economic egalitarianism in the new nation. In conversation with intellectual, social, and labor history, this study tracks the representation of class inequality and conflict across five subgenres of the early U.S. novel: the Bildungsroman, the episodic travel narrative, the sentimental novel, the frontier romance, and the anti-slavery novel.</p>
         <p>Through close readings of the works of foundational U.S. novelists, including Charles Brockden Brown, Hugh Henry Brackenridge, Catharine Maria Sedgwick, James Fenimore Cooper, and Harriet Beecher Stowe, Joe Shapiro demonstrates that while voices of economic egalitarianism and working-class protest find their ways into a variety of early U.S. novels, these novels are anything but radically dialogic; instead, he argues, they push back against emergent forms of class consciousness by working to naturalize class inequality among whites.<italic>The Illiberal Imagination</italic>thus enhances our understanding of both the early U.S. novel and the history of the way that class has been imagined in the United States.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="278"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of this book,<italic>The Illiberal Imagination,</italic>is meant to evoke two much earlier books: Lionel Trilling’s<italic>The Liberal Imagination</italic>(1950) and Louis Hartz’s<italic>The Liberal Tradition in America</italic>(1955). And it is intended to emphasize that this book is in large part an argument with the understanding of U.S. literary history for which these earlier books laid the foundation.</p>
                     <p>In the United States, Trilling famously argued, “the real basis of the novel has never existed—that is, the tension between a middle class and an aristocracy which brings manners into observable relief as the living representation of ideals</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Charles Brockden Brown, Poverty, and the Bildungsroman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Ormond; or, The Secret Witness</italic>(1799) and<italic>Arthur Mervyn; or, Memoirs of the Year 1793</italic>(1799, 1800), Charles Brockden Brown—the late eighteenth-century U.S. novelist most celebrated by early nineteenth-century American writers and most studied by twentieth and twenty-first-century critics—tells the same story twice. At the outset of both novels, Brown’s protagonists—Constantia Dudley and Arthur Mervyn, respectively—fall into “poverty.” Having become “poor,” these protagonists must sell their labor to others in order to acquire “subsistence.” They become, then, members of late eighteenth-century Philadelphia’s “lower sort.” While Constantia and Arthur eventually—and fortuitously—ascend to property at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Modern Chivalry’s Defense of “the Few”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Class, Politics, and the Early U.S. Episodic Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The imagination that has produced much of the best and most characteristic American fiction,” writes Richard Chase at the outset of<italic>The American Novel and Its Tradition</italic>(1957), “has been shaped by the contradictions and not by the unities and harmonies of our culture.”. Though absent from<italic>The American Novel and Its Tradition,</italic>Hugh Henry Brackenridge’s<italic>Modern Chivalry</italic>—a sprawling episodic travel novel published in seven volumes over the course of twenty-three years (1792, 1792, 1793, 1797, 1804, 1805, 1815)—has been described in terms that recall Chase’s account of how the American novel supposedly diverges from the European (and,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Providence of Class:</title>
                     <subtitle>Catharine Maria Sedgwick, Political Economy, and Sentimental Fiction in the 1830s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last two chapters, I have tried to show that unwieldy U.S. novels published in the final decade of the eighteenth century and the first two decades of the nineteenth century work as rejoinders to Enlightenment-era and radical plebeian varieties of economic egalitarianism. This chapter moves to the 1830s, a decade in which socialism as a political perspective begins to edge onto the stage in the United States. More particularly, this chapter argues that two of Catharine Maria Sedgwick’s 1830s sentimental novels,<italic>The Poor Rich Man, and the Rich Poor Man</italic>(1836) and<italic>Live and Let Live</italic>(1837), should</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>No Apologies for the Anti-Renters:</title>
                     <subtitle>Class, James Fenimore Cooper, and Frontier Romance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sedgwick’s<italic>The Poor Rich Man and Live and Let Live,</italic>I argued in the previous chapter, legitimate economic inequality in part by imagining the working class as politically docile: in Sedgwick’s 1830s novels, the working class assents to an economically hierarchical social order, discovering in economic inequality the manifestation of “providence.” Yet, what if U.S. workers do not assent to economic inequality? What if U.S. workers understand economic inequality as a violation of “natural law”? These are questions that animate James Fenimore Cooper’s now (also) largely forgotten 1840s Littlepage novels—<italic>Satanstoe</italic>(1845),<italic>The Chainbearer</italic>(1846), and<italic>The Redskins</italic>(1846). In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Working-Class Abolitionism and Antislavery Fiction:</title>
                     <subtitle>“White Slaves” and Harriet Beecher Stowe’s Dred</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the final chapter of<italic>Love and Theft</italic>:<italic>Blackface Minstrelsy and the American Working Class,</italic>Eric Lott details how 1850s stage adaptations of Harriet Beecher Stowe’s<italic>Uncle Tom’s Cabin</italic>were indebted to blackface minstrelsy, which was one of the primary forms of working-class entertainment in the antebellum North. These adaptations, Lott writes, “could not . . . have avoided making use of blackface devices: minstrelsy was the current material condition of theatrical production in the representation of racial matters.” But while these adaptations thus reproduced the problematic racial politics of blackface minstrelsy, they also refashioned minstrelsy, Lott contends, “for explicit antislavery</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Illiberal Imagination</italic>has ventured three interrelated arguments. They are, in a nutshell: first, the U.S. novel has from its beginning been “about” class; second, early U.S. novels “about” class are to be read as rejoinders to emergent forms of oppositional political economy; and, third, through the 1840s the U.S. novel does not hide class—but, rather, works to naturalize it.</p>
                     <p>In making these arguments, I have been picking a bone with “the liberal tradition”—with an understanding of American literary history wherein class does not, cannot, matter. As I noted in the introduction, I’m not the first to pick</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wx93xr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
