<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B3209.B584 W339 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Benjamin, Walter, 1892–1940</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Walter Benjamin and Theology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DICKINSON</surname>
               <given-names>COLBY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SYMONS</surname>
               <given-names>STÉPHANE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITORS</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823270170</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823270200</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1bmzm39"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In the Arcades Project, Walter Benjamin writes that his work is "related to theology as blotting pad is related to ink. It is saturated with it." For a thinker so decisive to critical literary, cultural, political, and aesthetic writings over the past half-century, Benjamin's relationship to theological matters has been less observed than it should, even despite a variety of attempts over the last four decades to illuminate the theological elements latent within his eclectic and occasional writings. Such attempts, though undeniably crucial to comprehending his thought, remain in need of deepened systematic analysis. In bringing together some of the most renowned experts from both sides of the Atlantic, Walter Benjamin and Theology seeks to establish a new site from which to address both the issue of Benjamin's relationship with theology and all the crucial aspects that Benjamin himself grappled with when addressing the field and operations of theological inquiry.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DICKINSON</surname>
                           <given-names>COLBY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SYMONS</surname>
                           <given-names>STÉPHANE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a famous letter written to Max Horkheimer in March 1937, Walter Benjamin describes his philosophy as “something that forbids us to conceive of history as fundamentally atheological, little as it may be granted to us to try to write it with immediately theological concepts.”¹ In<italic>The Arcades Project</italic>, he writes: “[My work is] related to theology as blotting pad is related to ink. It is saturated with it. Were one to go by the blotter, however, nothing of what is written would remain.”² For a thinker so decisive to critical literary, cultural, political, and aesthetic writings over the past</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Benjamin’s Messianic Metaphysics of Transience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THIEM</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNIKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While religious and theological questions have seen a renewed interest within critical theory, metaphysics still remains under suspicion when it is not, as is so often the case in contemporary critical theory, considered a matter of little consequence. Similarly, Walter Benjamin’s drawing upon theological tropes as the conceptual framework for theorizing history and life is no longer met with criticism but rather is widely embraced and harnessed as a theoretical resource for political and ethical thought. However, as obvious as it is that Benjamin’s work is shot through with theological tropes and concepts, it proves more difficult to reflect systematically</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Completion Instead of Revelation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward the “Theological-Political Fragment”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FENVES</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay is concerned with the act of the Messiah. According to a brief sketch that Walter Benjamin read to Theodor and Gretel Adorno in the winter of 1937–1938 and that has since acquired the title of “Theological-Political Fragment,” there is a single messianic act, the description of which requires three separate terms. Two of these terms can be easily translated into English, for they belong to a long tradition of theological speculation that encompasses a broad group of languages, including German and English. But the word through which Benjamin identifies<italic>the</italic>act of the messiah—namely,<italic>vollenden</italic>—cannot</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fidelity, Love, Eros:</title>
                     <subtitle>Benjamin’s Bireferential Concept of Life as Developed in “Goethe’s Elective Affinities”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEIGEL</surname>
                           <given-names>SIGRID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fidelity certainly does not rank among the central themes of Walter Benjamin’s work.¹ Likewise, it has garnered little attention in critical reception of his work so far—one will mostly look in vain for the term in the indexes of scholarly works on Benjamin.² The word nevertheless occupies a crucial position in Benjamin’s conception of life. It appears to have played an indispensable role in the elaboration of a fundamental facet of Benjamin’s thought: the double determination of human life as both creaturely (or natural) and supernatural, and thus of a concept of life derived from its relationship to these</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Will to Apokatastasis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Media, Experience, and Eschatology in Walter Benjamin’s Late Theological Politics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JENNINGS</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHAEL W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To begin with the ending: Walter Benjamin’s much discussed and little understood allegory of the Turkish puppet in his last known text, “On the Concept of History,” raises one central question for the entirety of his work: exactly<italic>how</italic>might politics take theology into its service, and to what effect?¹ Throughout his career, Benjamin’s use of theological concepts and motifs is invariably bound to the formulation of a politics; but how are we to trace the invisible strings that allow theology to ensure that historical materialism always wins? Benjamin’s deployment of theological motifs and his political commitments are of course</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Walter Benjamin’s Jewishness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EILAND</surname>
                           <given-names>HOWARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Benjamin’s Jewishness was at first no more than an exotic “aroma” in his life. He grew up in a thoroughly assimilated household of the liberal Jewish bourgeoisie in Berlin. His mother’s side of the family felt some allegiance to the Jewish reform community in Berlin, while his father’s side inclined to the orthodox rite, but all during Benjamin’s protected childhood his family celebrated Christmas in high style and organized Easter egg hunts for the children—these occasions are commemorated in his<italic>Berlin Childhood around 1900</italic>—whereas the young Benjamin knew next to nothing about the Jewish holidays.¹ In the vignette</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Benjamin’s Natural Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAYGILL</surname>
                           <given-names>HOWARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>144</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of Benjamin’s more unexpected citations can be found in his letter to his friend Gershom Scholem, dated Paris June 12, 1938. As far as I am aware it is the only time that he cites at length from a Gifford Lecture, the distinguished series founded in 1888 and intended “to promote and diffuse the study of natural philosophy in the widest sense of the term—in other words, the knowledge of God.” I am referring to the citation from Arthur Stanley Eddington’s influential presentation of the revolutionary advances in early twentieth century cosmology (the theory of relativity and subatomic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Walter Benjamin—A Modern Marcionite?</title>
                     <subtitle>Scholem’s Benjamin Interpretation Reexamined</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TAUBES</surname>
                           <given-names>JACOB</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The Devil is in the details.” This<italic>aperçu</italic>of Aby Warburg applies not only to philology and history, but to philosophical and theological reflection as well. Gershom Scholem, a highly speculative mind, invoked Aby Warburg’s words when he made his bold, imposing descent into the deep strata of Jewish history of religion, where he brought dark, dialectically fascinating, albeit profoundly demonic, forms of the Jewish spirit to light. A student once proposed that Scholem’s “historical-rational” apparatus could be the bridge over which searching secular students could enter onto the path to the “nonrational” content of Jewish mysticism and its demonic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Seminar Notes on Walter Benjamin’s “Theses on the Philosophy of History”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TAUBES</surname>
                           <given-names>JACOB</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The following text is the first English translation of seminar notes taken in a seminar on Walter Benjamin’s “Theses on the Philosophy of History” given by Jacob Taubes in 1984 at the Freie Universität Berlin, where Taubes held the Chair for Jewish Studies and Hermeneutics.¹</p>
                     <p>The notes were initially published in the German edition of Elettra Stimilli’s documentation of Taubes’s critical confrontation with Gershom Scholem’s work on the phenomenon of Messianism and its history.² They cover the first seven sessions of Taubes’s course on Benjamin, which took place from October 18 to December 6, 1984, before Taubes had to discontinue</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Benjamin’s Baudelaire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AGAMBEN</surname>
                           <given-names>GIORGIO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Walter Benjamin’s<italic>Charles Baudelaire, A Poet of the Age of Advanced Capitalism</italic>is a special book, not only because of its unusual form, but also because of its somewhat adventurous history, or rather, prehistory, which is inseparable, at least for me, from its existence in the form of a printed document.</p>
                     <p>In 1981, I was in Paris, searching for the traces of the famous manuscript that, according to the testimony of Lisa Fittko—the woman who had guided Benjamin in the attempt to flee from occupied France to Spain that ultimately cost him his life—Benjamin had kept by his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Vanishing and Fulfillment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRIEDLANDER</surname>
                           <given-names>ELI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In various places in Benjamin’s writing the divine is identified in the total passing away and disappearance of the phenomenal. Probably the most famous case for such annihilative characterization of the divine occurs in the essay “Critique of Violence.” Yet, the account of divine violence in that essay, with its intimation of active destruction, tempts one to construe the moment of disappearance in terms of catastrophic effects wrought by God on the physical world, on the model of a force that makes visible changes in reality. This problematic figuration of the catastrophic in Benjamin’s vision of history might hide a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rhythms of the Living, Conditions of Critique:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Judith Butler’s Reading of Walter Benjamin’s “Critique of Violence”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DEUBER-MANKOWSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>ASTRID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her reading of Walter Benjamin’s “Critique of Violence,” Judith Butler provides a persuasive interpretation of the critical resources Benjamin mobilizes. She points out that Benjamin draws on an alternative Jewish tradition of understanding the commandment “Thou shall not kill.” In her analysis, the commandment is opposed to a principle of guilt and hence can become the basis for a critique of legal violence. Moreover, according to Butler, the commandment, as Benjamin conceives of it, constitutes the condition for a theory of responsibility that would be fundamentally concerned with the ongoing struggle with nonviolence. Benjamin’s controversial distinction between fate and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>One Time Traverses Another:</title>
                     <subtitle>Benjamin’s “Theological-Political Fragment”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BUTLER</surname>
                           <given-names>JUDITH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Benjamin’s “Theological-Political Fragment” opens up several questions about the status of religion in Benjamin’s work. Two questions tend to emerge when I teach this short text. One of them is whether Benjamin understands the divine as a purely immanent feature of the world. The second has to do with the notion of the “rhythm of transience” that appears in the text and, simply put, whether the rhythm of transience is itself transient—that is, it comes and goes but not in a regular or law-like way—or whether that transience comes and goes in a rhythmic way, suggesting that the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Walter Benjamin and Christian Critical Ethics—A Comment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAKER</surname>
                           <given-names>HILLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>286</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As enigmatic as it is at times, Walter Benjamin’s retrieval of Jewish theological language has perhaps done more for postwar German Christian theology than it could do for itself after the Holocaust, even though, admittedly, only a few theologians marked the Holocaust as a radical rupture of their tradition.¹ My reading of Benjamin engages specifically with two texts: “Critique of Violence” and “Theological-Political Fragment.”² I will demonstrate how an analysis sensitive to theological concepts may further inform a reading of Benjamin’s essays, before turning to Johann Baptist Metz’s reinterpretation of Christian theology as a new political theology. By linking the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm39.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>331</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
