<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8bdj</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">ML3800.A46 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy and aesthetics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Musical analysis</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Semiotics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music and literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music theory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Theory of Musical Narrative</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ALMÉN</surname>
               <given-names>BYRON</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>23</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253352385</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253030283</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253030285</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Byron Almén</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005szf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Byron Almén proposes an original synthesis of approaches to musical narrative from literary criticism, semiotics, historiography, musicology, and music theory, resulting in a significant critical reorientation of the field. This volume includes an extensive survey of traditional approaches to musical narrative illustrated by a wide variety of musical examples that highlight the range and applicability of the theoretical apparatus. Almén provides a careful delineation of the essential elements and preconditions of musical narrative organization, an eclectic analytical model applicable to a wide range of musical styles and repertoires, a classification scheme of narrative types and subtypes reflecting conceptually distinct narrative strategies, a wide array of interpretive categories, and a sensitivity to the dependence of narrative interpretation on the cultural milieu of the work, its various audiences, and the analyst.<italic>A Theory of Musical Narrative</italic>provides both an excellent introduction to an increasingly important conceptual domain and a complex reassessment of its possibilities and characteristics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>An Introduction to Narrative Analysis:</title>
                     <subtitle>Chopin’s Prelude in G Major, Op. 28, No. 3</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we think of narrative music, certain assumptions come quickly to mind—assumptions that have strongly colored our responses to the topic. First, narrative music is often thought to be in some way problematic or idiosyncratic; that is, we tend to resort to narrative interpretations when traditional formal, harmonic, and generic paradigms do not apply. Anthony Newcomb (1984, 1987), for example, has located a certain type of narrative music within a particularly nineteenth-century mode of expression that attaches plot archetypes to nonstandard or unusual compositional designs. Second, narrative music tends to be associated with programmaticism, dramatic or epic texts, evocative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Perspectives and Critiques</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problematic status of musical narrative as a disciplinary entity today is reflected in a general disagreement about its nature, properties, and range of application. Some scholars have ascribed it primarily to programmatic music (Kivy), while others expand its reach to music that is in some manner formally problematic (Newcomb, Abbate) or to a broader spectrum of works including “absolute” music and instrumental genres (Maus). A further group (Nattiez, Abbate, Kramer) has questioned its applicability to music. Musical narrative has variously denoted a loose analogy between literary and musical patterning, a historically bounded and primarily Romantic compositional impulse (Newcomb), a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>A Theory of Musical Narrative:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conceptual Considerations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Musical narrative resists simple formulation, its complex identity emerging through a confluence of factors. First, the essential characteristics of narrative are partly obscured by the distinct inflections given it by the different media through which it manifests itself. Dramatic narrative is phenomenally immediate, realized by characters and settings both visually and audibly present. Literary narrative is likewise relatively specific with respect to character and setting, but is constructed through verbal description and dialogue. Mythic narrative invokes characters, settings, and/or themes with numinous cultural significance, situating these elements in an idealized, hyper-real manner. Historical narrative ostensibly employs real events and characters</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Theory of Musical Narrative:</title>
                     <subtitle>Analytical Considerations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hierarchical organization is implicated at two levels in narrative analysis. The initial or prevailing cultural units themselves articulate a scale of values, and the interactions between them revaluate the scale, reinforcing the rank relations among the cultural units (assimilation) or undermining them (displacement). As a result, when we turn to the issue of musical analysis, we shall have to account for the distinctive contributions of these two levels, which Liszka terms the<italic>agential</italic>and<italic>actantial</italic>levels respectively (1989: 120).</p>
                     <p>In defining a procedure for the analysis of mythic narrative, Liszka characterizes the agential level as uncovering the “general features of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Narrative and Topic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consider the employment of musical topic in three short examples. In my narrative analysis of Chopin’s Prelude in G major, given in chapter 1, I highlighted the topical qualities of the gently undulating left-hand ostinato figure that both generates and accompanies a slow, meandering melody embellished by sixths and thirds (measures 1–6 of this piece are shown in example 5.1). The pervasive and tonally stable “harmony-within-nature” figure, redolent of murmuring streams and gentle breezes, creates a benign, peaceful background environment that strongly influences how a listener might interpret the piece as narrative. The semantic impact of its musical elements</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[PART TWO: Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The next four chapters of this book—chapters 6–9—feature a shift in emphasis from the theoretical to the analytical, the latter being both explicitly and implicitly informed by the former. These analyses also perform additional functions that, in order to orient the reader, require articulation here. Along with anchoring and instantiating the theory as developed in the first half of this volume, they expand and develop this theory further, exemplify its scope and range of application, and reveal the role of narrative considerations within a larger hermeneutic agenda. The following considerations, then, should be kept in mind when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Romance Narratives and Micznik’s Degrees of Narrativity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The romance archetype occupies uneasy ground within our current interpretive landscape. Twenty-first-century society is the child of a demythologizing and ironic age, an age that gave birth to a Freudian critique of rational behavior, a Marxist critique of capitalist inequality, a deconstructionist critique of the privileged interpretation, and a pluralist critique of Western hegemony. We are expected as scholars to look beyond received wisdom for new insights, beneath the surface for deeper readings, in the cracks of discourse for divergent positions. We are suspicious of monolithic doctrines, airtight systems, and political bias. Equally, however, we are the children of an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Tragic Narratives:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Extended Analysis of Schubert, Piano Sonata in B♭ Major, D. 960, First Movement</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Musical representations of tragedy are sites of potential confusion between narrative and topical signification. This is largely due to the relative ubiquity of tragic<italic>topoi</italic>in music literature, in combination with a degree of familiarity on the part of the scholarly community about what characterizes a tragic<italic>topos</italic>. Certain stylistic and paradigmatic conventions of various historical durations—minor mode, slow tempo, sigh figures, descending gestures, chromaticism, expressive dissonances, funeral march, low register, exact repetition—easily call to our minds pieces that are tragic in a topical sense: the “Crucifixus” in Bach’s Mass in B minor, the first movement of Beethoven’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Ironic Narratives:</title>
                     <subtitle>Subtypes and Phases</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The merging of inductive analytical levels—the agential and actantial—with a quartet of overarching, culturally significant categories—the narrative archetypes—is an important feature of the theory of musical narrative found in this volume. The former ensure that the musical details themselves determine the narrative trajectory, while the latter situates that trajectory within the network of social and personal value. The archetypes, as we have seen, model the distinct outcomes resulting from the interactions between alternative structures of power—interactions that are constantly being played out in our intrapsychic, interpersonal, and communal relationships. Given the pervasiveness and importance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Comic Narratives and Discursive Strategies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The spectrum of narrative phases discussed in the previous chapter is essentially an extension of the narrative level of analysis outlined in chapter 4. As a result, it is—like the narrative level itself—a deductive taxonomy determined by the general principles of musical narrative and superimposed upon the musical domain. Narrative phases thus enable a greater degree of interpretive subtlety: with expansion of the four basic archetypes according to secondary criteria that vary by degree (instead of by kind), more precise comparisons can be made within the larger categorical frames.</p>
                     <p>The same approach can be taken from an inductive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Summary and Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the preceding pages, I have elaborated and illustrated a theory of musical narrative that is both grounded in principles applicable to narrative media in general and organized around discourses that are specifically musical. In place of the subtle and not-so-subtle distortions arising from a literature-based approach to narrative, this book reconstitutes the fundamentals of narrative theory in terms of Liszkian transvaluation, recognizing that the shifting hierarchical organization of our various “cultures”—psychic, interpersonal, social—lies at the heart of our subject.</p>
                     <p>The four narrative archetypes—romance, tragedy, irony, and comedy—are collections of discursive trajectories organized according to broad</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005szf.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
