<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD444. L485 2012</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Death</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mediocrity</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization, Western</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civilization, Western</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Death's Following: Mediocrity, Dirtiness, Adulthood, Literature</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LIMON</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823242795</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823246311</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c5chjz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Almost all twentieth-century philosophy stresses the immanence of death in human life-as drive (Freud), as the context of Being (Heidegger), as the essence of our defining ethics (Levinas), or as language (de Man, Blanchot). In Death's Following, John Limon makes use of literary analysis (of Sebald, Bernhard, and Stoppard), cultural analysis, and autobiography to argue that death is best conceived as always transcendentally beyond ourselves, neither immanent nor imminent. Adapting Kierkegaard's variations on the theme of Abraham's near-sacrifice of Isaac while refocusing the emphasis onto Isaac, Limon argues that death should be imagined as if hiding at the end of an inexplicable journey to Moriah. The point is not to evade or ignore death but to conceive it more truly, repulsively, and pervasively in its camouflage: for example, in jokes, in logical puzzles, in bowdlerized folk songs. The first of Limon's two key concepts is adulthood: the prolonged anti-ritual for experiencing the full distance on the look of death. His second is dirtiness, as theorized in a Jewish joke, a logical exemplum, and T. S. Eliot's "Ash Wednesday": In each case, unseen dirt on foreheads suggests the invisibility of inferred death. Not recognizing death immediately or admitting its immanence and imminence is for Heidegger the defining characteristic of the "they," humanity in its inauthentic social escapism. But Limon vouches throughout for the mediocrity of the "they" in its dirty and ludicrous adulthood. Mediocrity is the privileged position for previewing death, in Limon's opinion: practice for being forgotten. In refusing the call of twentieth-century philosophy to face death courageously, Limon urges the ethical and aesthetic value of mediocre anti-heroism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="212"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Preliminary Expectoration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the crisis of<italic>Catch-22</italic>approaches, just before Yossarian must choose whether to sell out to the Army or flee it, he has a dream while under an anesthetic. The novel, to this point, has been radically antipsychological—what use is the diagnosis of paranoia, for example, if everyone is in fact shooting at you?—and Yossarian, on Heller’s behalf, has delighted in concocting dreams to placate or frustrate psychoanalysts. But he is frightened by his one actual dream, and feels the urgency of plumbing its recesses.</p>
                     <p>A hand with sharp fingers shook him roughly awake [presumably in his dream].</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Alas a Dirty Third:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Logic of Death</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I cannot think how to prove that there is a special difficulty in knowing that we shall die. To an empiricist or existentialist, no hypothesis is more likely. To a skeptic, there is a difficulty in knowing that we shall die but it is not a special one. Yet our foreknowledge of our deaths is, uniquely, certain knowledge that always falls short. In Don DeLillo’s<italic>White Noise</italic>, someone in the cockpit of a jet, for the benefit of investigators of a crash that seems imminent, speaks into the voice recorder: “Now we know what it’s like. It is worse than</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>Thomas Bernhard’s Rant</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thomas Bernhard’s memoirs were published in five volumes; because the memoir of his earliest childhood was written fifth, it was with some suspense that readers arrived at his choice of introductory episode. Eight-year-old Thomas (scamp father absconded, guardian with the German army in Poland) determines to learn to ride a bicycle on his own, succeeds, feels prematurely “like a conquering hero,” and immediately embarks on riding to his Auntie Fanny’s house, twenty-two miles distant across the Austrian border. “I judged this,” he writes, “the most appropriate destination for my first outing and intended, having arrived at my aunt’s house and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Following Sebald</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The friend to whom I am indebted for leading me to W. G. Sebald—I had mentioned that I was musing on the subject of how we know we shall die—told me that he proposed to write an essay on him. When I wondered what the essay would argue, he said that it would not have an argument. I myself was determined to write on Sebald free of the foreknowledge of my topic or point. The most powerful motive of these blind intentions is that one senses, in Sebald’s vicinity, a confirmation of the dignity of writing, even conceivably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Tickling the Corpse:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tom Stoppard’s Memento Mori</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Prove: that<italic>memento mori</italic>games are the essential form of postmodern narratives, or anyway Tom Stoppard’s.</p>
                     <p>1.1<italic>Memento mori</italic>paintings provide two useful paradigms.</p>
                     <p>1.2 The first paradigm is Albrecht Dürer’s<italic>St. Jerome</italic>(1521), in which a ferocious St. Jerome glares down to his left, his vision passing behind and beyond the skull on his desk, which he points to and softly touches with his left index finger. Among the things that Jerome is not looking at is the crucifix behind him and over his right arm. Nevertheless, it would seem to be in his mind’s eye or, more exactly,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Don Rickles’s Rant</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am in Oxford, Mississippi, to address the Yoknapatawpha Society. It is the middle of July, boiling, inescapably the South. My host who, like several of the top Faulknerians at the conference, seems to know every last utterance of the great man, is taking me out to catfish dinner. I have assumed that he is a Southerner.</p>
                     <p>He is talking to me about my book on standup comedy; he wonders why I did not go deeper into the history of Jewish humor, starting in the Bible. I am happy to concede my historical limits, though his estimate of the humor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Too Late, My Brothers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The wrong place to begin this chapter is with an account of daydreaming through a Daniel Barenboim recital at Symphony Hall in Boston. Perhaps because Barenboim’s playing was routine that evening, I found myself recollecting a concert there forty years prior: the Limeliters, a folk group popular at the dispersal of the fifties and the gathering of the sixties, had been performing. I could, at the Barenboim concert, only vaguely recall roly-poly Glenn Yarbrough, an Irish tenor whose lovely voice sounded to me enough like falsetto to be embarrassing at the time. A more vivid memory was Alex Hassilev, somehow</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Re:</title>
                     <subtitle>Barth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On February 29, 1960, when I was exactly, by way of a rare half-birthday, eight-and-a-half, my father, Gerald Limon, was finally killed by an aneurysm, not yet thirty-nine. He had fainted in his car outside his factory, had improved daily for about a week, and died. Family policy, pretty strictly adhered to, was never to discuss him, either his life or death, again. Some time after his death, maybe a month or two, my mother asked me if I had any questions about it. None came to mind. She thought perhaps I had worried that I might die in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5chjz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
