<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GR45 .N49 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fairy tales</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Tales</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fairy tales in motion pictures</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Tales</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Film adaptations</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>New Approaches to Teaching Folk and Fairy Tales</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jones</surname>
               <given-names>Christa C.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schwabe</surname>
               <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781607324805</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781607324812</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Utah State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Boulder, Colorado</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University Press of Colorado</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1f2qr02"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>New Approaches to Teaching Folk and Fairy Tales</italic>provides invaluable hands-on materials and pedagogical tools from an international group of scholars who share their experiences in teaching folk- and fairy-tale texts and films in a wide range of academic settings.This interdisciplinary collection introduces scholarly perspectives on how to teach fairy tales in a variety of courses and academic disciplines, including anthropology, creative writing, children's literature, cultural studies, queer studies, film studies, linguistics, second language acquisition, translation studies, and women and gender studies, and points the way to other intermedial and intertextual approaches. Challenging the fairy-tale canon as represented by the Brothers Grimm, Charles Perrault, Hans Christian Andersen, and Walt Disney, contributors reveal an astonishingly diverse fairy-tale landscape.The book offers instructors a plethora of fresh ideas, teaching materials, and outside-the-box teaching strategies for classroom use as well as new and adaptable pedagogical models that invite students to engage with class materials in intellectually stimulating ways. A cutting-edge volume that acknowledges the continued interest in university courses on fairy tales,<italic>New Approaches to Teaching Folk and Fairy Tales</italic>enables instructors to introduce their students to a new, critical understanding of the fairy tale as well as to a host of new tales, traditions, and adaptations in a range of media.</p>
         <p>Contributors:Anne E. Duggan, Cyrille François, Lisa Gabbert, Pauline Greenhill, Donald Haase, Christa C. Jones, Christine A. Jones, Jeana Jorgensen, Armando Maggi, Doris McGonagill, Jennifer Orme, Christina Phillips Mattson, Claudia Schwabe, Anissa Talahite-Moodley, Maria Tatar, Francisco Vaz da Silva, Juliette Wood</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="264"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haase</surname>
                           <given-names>Donald</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It’s about time. Time , that is, for a collection of essays like this. Time for scholars of folktales and fairy tales to acknowledge the role that teaching plays in their work. The study of folktales and fairy tales has a long history that took a radical turn in the 1970s and ’80s, a turn that reinvented, revitalized, and expanded the field across disciplines. That burgeoning interest generated new university courses on fairy tales that over the last thirty years have introduced countless students to a new, critical understanding of the fairy tale and to a host of new tales,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cross-Disciplinary Perspectives on Teaching Folklore and Fairy Tales in Higher Education</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jones</surname>
                           <given-names>Christa C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schwabe</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the earliest stage of storytelling, oral tales and their mani fold retellings have served not only to mesmerize, entertain, and captivate listeners, but also to educate audiences about valuable life lessons and uni versal truths. Early tales contained examples of human conduct and provided guidelines on how to overcome serious challenges, survival struggles, or master problematic interpersonal relations. As Jack Zipes (2012) states in his recent study<italic>The Irresistible Fairy Tale</italic>, “For once a plethora of stories began to circulate in societies throughout the world, they contained the seeds of fairy tales, ironically tales at first without fairies formed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Fairy Tales, Myth, and Fantasy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mattson</surname>
                           <given-names>Christina Phillips</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tatar</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The course “Fairy Tales, Myth, and Fantasy Literature” takes up the study of foundational stories from the childhood of culture and also from the culture of childhood. It tracks how narratives are recycled as they migrate into new media and old—how the story of Demeter and Persephone, for example, shows up in J. M. Barrie’s play<italic>Peter Pan</italic>or how “Little Red Riding Hood” is refashioned in contemporary films ranging from David Slade’s<italic>Hard Candy</italic>(2005) to Joe Wright’s<italic>Hanna</italic>(2011). It seeks to dismantle the divide between what we read to children and what we read as adult</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Teaching Fairy Tales in Folklore Classes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gabbert</surname>
                           <given-names>Lisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That the Brothers Grimm are among the founding fathers of folk lore is a fact learned early on in most folklore studies. The Grimms, who collected their tales with the interest in promoting German language and culture, produced<italic>Kinder- und Hausmärchen (Children’s and Household Tales</italic>, 1812), a scholarly but also wildly popular publication that served as a kind of handbook for tale-collecting enthusiasts in various European countries during the mid to late nineteenth century (Grimm and Grimm 1974). These enthusiasts included Alexandr Afansef in Russia, Joseph Jacobs in England, and Peter Christen Asbøjrnsen and Jørgen Moe in Norway. Across Europe,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>At the Bottom of a Well:</title>
                     <subtitle>Teaching the Otherworld as a Folktale Environment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wood</surname>
                           <given-names>Juliette</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The numerous tales brought together by the Brothers Grimm and other collectors provide a seemingly endless selection of folk narratives. Although early scholarship sought to situate the folktale within theoretical frameworks that could explain the evolution of culture, it also recognized the characteristically patterned nature of such tales and produced indexes concerned with mapping out the components of oral tales. The most notable and comprehensive indexes were undoubtedly those of Stith Thompson and Antti Aarne, which are still in use today (Aarne and Thompson 1961).</p>
                     <p>Interest in the folktale, especially the<italic>Märchen</italic>, or fairy tale, has under gone something of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Fairy-Tale Forest as Memory Site:</title>
                     <subtitle>Romantic Imagination, Cultural Construction, and a Hybrid Approach to Teaching the Grimms’ Fairy Tales and the Environment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McGonagill</surname>
                           <given-names>Doris</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>TeachIng undergraduate courses In German StudIes I have had the opportunity to prepare several courses and smaller teaching units on the Grimms’ folk and fairy tales, but each time I find myself facing the same question: How should I structure my material? There are some obvious choices—chronological, regional, thematic—each with its own advantages and limitations. Structuring principles based on thematic similarities and related plot elements—the folklorists’ tale types—can provide a basic infrastructure, along with specific character constellations, motifs, and topoi. Thus your groups may include tales about family conflict and gender relationships (“child victims,” “bad dads,”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Grimms’ Fairy Tales in a Political Context:</title>
                     <subtitle>Teaching East German Fairy-Tale Films</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schwabe</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of my German students once stumbled upon several fairy-tale film adaptations by the<italic>Deutsche Film-Aktiengesellschaft</italic>(DEFA), the stateowned film studio of the former German Democratic Republic (GDR), and inquired: “Are these movies very different from the Grimms’ original fairy tales?” This question inspired me to design a German fairy-tale class that ties students’ interest in fairy tales and films to a significant and fascinating part of Germany’s recent history. Although the Grimms’<italic>Märchen</italic>(fairy tales) are firmly embedded in courses and syllabi in German language, literature, folklore, culture, history, narrative theory, and fairy-tale studies, they are rarely discussed in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Teaching Charles Perrault’s Histoires ou contes du temps passé in the Literary and Historical Context of the Sun King’s Reign</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jones</surname>
                           <given-names>Christa C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My undergraduate French literature and civilization class is a communication and writing-intensive class that discusses Charles Perrault’s (1697)<italic>Histoires ou contes du temps passé</italic>, excerpts from other seventeenth-century literary and historical texts, and contemporary fairy-tale adaptations, both onscreen and literary. One of my main goals is to enable students to enjoy studying the original French text, which can be challenging for students who read a seventeenth-century text for the first time. To this end, I encourage an intertextual approach: my hope is to “hook” students on Perrault’s tales by anchoring his tales in the cultural background of his time and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Lessons from Shahrazad:</title>
                     <subtitle>Teaching about Cultural Dialogism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Talahite-Moodley</surname>
                           <given-names>Anissa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the beginning of the eighteenth century, the stories of the<italic>One Thousand and One Nights</italic>—also known as<italic>The Arabian Nights</italic>—have exercised a particular fascination on the Western imagination. Whether it is in the context of the Orientalist construction of an exotic Eastern “Other” or the more recent feminist and postcolonial rereadings of the tales, the<italic>Nights</italic>is a text that has generated numerous critical responses as well as a wealth of literary, musical, artistic, and cinematographic adaptations, some of which are examined in this chapter.¹ In this respect, it constitutes an ideal text for college students to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Significance of Translation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jones</surname>
                           <given-names>Christine A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the opening pages of Voltaire’s (2005) mid-eighteenth-century satire,<italic>Candide</italic>, a sheltered young man finds himself cast out of his comfortable German manor life and into a hostile world. On the only one of his many adventures that does not lead immediately to catastrophe, he and his South American guide, Cacambo, stumble upon the fabled land of Eldorado in Peru. There exist no currency, no courts, and no prisons. In their place the duo finds rivers of gold, a palace of sciences filled with marvels of mathematics and astronomy, and a welcoming royal palace where they are treated to hospitalities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Giambattista Basile’s The Tale of Tales in the Hands of the Brothers Grimm</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Maggi</surname>
                           <given-names>Armando</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Rewriting is a fundamental aspect of the Western tradition of literary fairy tales. A literary fairy tale is a text composed by a writer in a particular cultural context. These tales are “literary” because they result from a specific author’s poetics. Composing fairy tales in the twentieth and twenty-first centuries often means appropriating and retelling a handful of tales that have acquired the status of classics. Alert readers of this literary genre must be able to appreciate and dissect a given tale in the light of its models. The phenomenon of rewriting becomes particularly meaningful when it pertains to key</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Teaching Hans Christian Andersen’s Tales:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Linguistic Approach</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>François</surname>
                           <given-names>Cyrille</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As one of the most famous fairy-tale writers and one of the most translated authors in the world, Andersen should be given a prime place in a teaching unit on fairy tales. At the same time, as he was a Danish writer, both the language and the cultural context make it difficult for non-Danish -speaking instructors to grasp the many dimensions of his work. This chapter gives advice and suggests activities that can be used to work on Andersen’s tales in an academic setting, focusing on a comparative analysis of translations to approach the particular language in which they were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Teaching Symbolism in “Little Red Riding Hood”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Silva</surname>
                           <given-names>Francisco vaz da</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I often teach an optional course on fairy tales to undergraduate social-anthropology students. This is usually the first contact they have with fairy tales in an academic setting, and I mean to make it memorable. Many of my students find themselves fascinated by the topic of symbolism in fairy tales but cannot quite fathom why. This course aims to develop the students’ intuitive grasp of fairy-tale meanings into a level of explicit comprehension. It shows how to make sense of (apparent) nonsense in traditional narratives. This chapter describes the basic contents of four prelimi nary sessions, spanning two weeks, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Binary Outlaws:</title>
                     <subtitle>Queering the Classical Tale in François Ozon’s Criminal Lovers and Catherine Breillat’s The Sleeping Beauty</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Duggan</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within the domain of fairy-tale studies, queer theory has yet to receive the critical attention that it deserves, particularly given the centrality of sexuality in fairy tales.¹ This situation increasingly is changing, evident in the work of Kay Turner and Pauline Greenhill, among others.² Approaching fairy-tale texts and films from the perspective of queer theory can help students understand the ways in which fairy-tale plots can subvert what is often—and problematically—taken for granted in classical tales: the heteronormative plot, upheld by a specific configuration of gender roles. As Turner has argued, “Even if many tales hurtle headlong toward</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Teaching “Gender in Fairy-Tale Film and Cinematic Folklore” Online:</title>
                     <subtitle>Negotiating between Needs and Wants</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Greenhill</surname>
                           <given-names>Pauline</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Orme</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Teaching fully online a third-year undergraduate University of Winnipeg Women’s and Gender Studies (WGS) course called “Gender in Fairy-Tale Film and Cinematic Folklore” (GFFCF) offered significant challenges, but also considerable rewards. Though the course’s final form was strongly influenced by the particular demands of Internet delivery, like any other course, live or online, GFFCF reflected a compromise between pedagogical goals, available materials, and approaches to the content (see, e.g., Garrison 2011; Simpson 2012). Our chapter explores how we worked to balance the latter three issues, particularly in terms of the online medium’s usually positive influence on our teaching. We detail</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Intertextuality, Creativity, and Sexuality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Group Exercises in the Fairy-Tale/Gender Studies Classroom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jorgensen</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many students enter the fairy-tale classroom familiar primarily with the Disney versions of fairy tales, though they are eager to supple ment that awareness with knowledge of “the original” tales that (as everyone knows) are darker, sexier, and more violent. Catherine Tosenberger designates this “recovery story” about fairy tales a “rescue operation” designed to uncover the “real” fairy tale and “rescue it from Disney oppression” (Tosenberger 2010, [5.2]). While Tosenberger acknowledges that this approach to fairy tales is as much a construction as any other authenticitydriven narrative, I want to point out that fairy-tale audiences (including college students) who have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aarne-Thompson-Uther Index Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Authors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1f2qr02.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
