<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">LC5015 .C55 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Working class</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Education (Higher)</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">College students’ writings</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Classroom environment</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English language</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Composition and exercises</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Study and teaching</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Class in the Composition Classroom</book-title>
         <subtitle>Pedagogy and the Working Class</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CARTER</surname>
               <given-names>GENESEA M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>THELIN</surname>
               <given-names>WILLIAM H.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781607326175</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781607326182</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Utah State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Boulder, Colorado</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University Press of Colorado</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1whm918"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Class in the Composition Classroom</italic>considers what college writing instructors should know about their working-class students-their backgrounds, experiences, identities, learning styles, and skills-in order to support them in the classroom, across campus, and beyond. In this volume, contributors explore the nuanced and complex meaning of "working class" and the particular values these college writers bring to the classroom.</p>
         <p>The real college experiences of veterans, rural Midwesterners, and trade unionists show that what it means to be working class is not obvious or easily definable. Resisting outdated characterizations of these students as underprepared and dispensing with a one-size-fits-all pedagogical approach, contributors address how region and education impact students, explore working-class pedagogy and the ways in which it can reify social class in teaching settings, and give voice to students' lived experiences.</p>
         <p>As community colleges and universities seek more effective ways to serve working-class students, and as educators, parents, and politicians continue to emphasize the value of higher education for students of all financial and social backgrounds, conversations must take place among writing instructors and administrators about how best to serve and support working-class college writers.<italic>Class in the Composition Classroom</italic>will help writing instructors inside and outside the classroom prepare all their students for personal, academic, and professional communication.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>Contributors</italic>: Aaron Barlow, ​Cori Brewster, ​Patrick Corbett, ​Harry Denny, Cassandra Dulin, ​Miriam Eisenstein Ebsworth, ​Mike Edwards, ​Rebecca Fraser, ​Brett Griffiths, ​Anna Knutson, ​Liberty Kohn, ​Nancy Mack, ​Holly Middleton, ​Robert Mundy, ​Missy Nieveen Phegley, ​Jacqueline Preston, ​James E. Romesburg, ​Edie-Marie Roper, Aubrey Schiavone, Christie Toth, ​Gail G. Verdi</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="369"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thelin</surname>
                           <given-names>William H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carter</surname>
                           <given-names>Genesea M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Travis, eighteen, had just started his first year at the University of Wisconsin–Stout. An undeclared major at Wisconsin’s only polytechnic, he came to UW–Stout hoping to major in something practical. He chose Stout because it is a few hours’ drive from home, the people were friendly during his campus visit, the college town was small, and his application was accepted. Travis, like many of the students at UW–Stout, is from a small rural farming community and does not know what he wants to do yet. He is pretty sure he wants to stay in Wisconsin and maybe</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>PEDAGOGY AT THE CROSSROADS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Instructor Identity, Social Class Consciousness, and Reflective Teaching Practice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schiavone</surname>
                           <given-names>Aubrey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Knutson</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna V.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While composition instructors are frequently encouraged to recognize the intersectional identities of their students, including social class identity, we assert in this chapter that it is equally critical to recognize the identities of composition<italic>instructors</italic>. Too often we assume instructors of college composition classes are universally middle-and upper-class individuals who must be attentive to the needs of their working-class students. While this, in many cases, may be true, we would like to make two related assertions: (1) socioeconomic diversity exists in the ranks of composition instructors, and by overlooking that, we miss a major puzzle piece central to our understanding</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>NO HOMO!</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward an Intersection of Sexuality and Masculinity for Working-Class Men</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mundy</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Denny</surname>
                           <given-names>Harry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have struggled with the adjectives students, particularly men, assign us in classroom settings. If our identities as white, male, working-class academics seem transparent and privileged, our gender and sexuality work counterintuitively. In public spaces, particularly when with students, Rob is a “guys’ guy” and Harry is the “ambiguously gay” guy. We both have come to embrace our identities, particularly our masculinities and how their performativity enables men who share our background a certain degree of comfort with us, especially for those men who have historically felt out of place in writing classrooms. During classes and conferences, our masculinity provides</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>IMPLICATIONS OF REDEFINING “WORKING CLASS” IN THE URBAN COMPOSITION CLASSROOM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barlow</surname>
                           <given-names>Aaron</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Corbett</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, we explore the disconnect between New York City College of Technology (City Tech) students’ working-class subjectivities and the traditional implementation of first-year composition (FYC) pedagogy. We articulate the relationship between institutional realities, pedagogical tradition, and students’ needs and how these intersections of institutionality and students’ lives do not connect our students’ working-class subjectivities to the educational project of FYC. We raise three questions we believe must be explored as part of the process of creating tangible changes to how teachers and scholars of FYC approach urban working-class students.</p>
                     <p>How do we identify urban working-class students as working</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>CALIFORNIA DREAMS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Working-Class Writers in the California State University System</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dulin</surname>
                           <given-names>Cassandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The US Department of Education has found that forty percent of students who set out to complete a bachelor’s degree from a four-year institution fail to graduate in six years.¹ There are many reasons students leave college before they complete their degrees. A study conducted in 2009 found that working while going to school was the main reason students left before finishing their programs.² Juggling work and school is difficult and stressful. This same study also found that the students who dropped out due to strenuous work schedules admitted it would be too hard to reenroll. These students live with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE WRITING SPACE AS DIALECTICAL SPACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Disrupting the Pedagogical Imperative to Prepare the “Underprepared”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Preston</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacqueline</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In most public and private universities, students are placed in one or another writing course based on scores from the ACT, SAT or another standardized assessment, such as Accuplacer. As it stands, most writing assessments used to place students measure primarily students’ capacity to demonstrate knowledge of middle-class “Standard Written English” of the essayist bent. We know students of low-income families are likely to achieve lower scores on these aptitude tests. Not surprisingly, a high percentage of students of working-class origin fill basic writing (BW) and first-semester first-year writing (FYW) classrooms. At worst, many of these courses, as well as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>CHANGING DEFINITIONS OF WORK AND CLASS IN THE INFORMATION ECONOMY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Roper</surname>
                           <given-names>Edie-Marie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Edwards</surname>
                           <given-names>Mike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Class changes. As coauthors, our own attitudes toward class differ in some ways and overlap in others. Edie-Marie worked as an undergraduate with federally funded TRIO programs for disadvantaged students but does not identify as working class, despite her dad having worked in a factory all her life and having worked in one herself. Mike served for four years as an enlisted soldier driving tractor trailers for the United States Army but does not claim a working-class identity despite that experience. As contributors to this volume, we have both been interested in the differences between our own experiences of class</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>TELLING OUR STORY:</title>
                     <subtitle>College Writing for Trade Unionists</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fraser</surname>
                           <given-names>Rebecca</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A liberal arts college program solely devoted to tradespeople and their interests is a radical idea; after all, why spend money, time, and effort to educate people in the liberal arts who are going to be doing some form of construction for the rest of their lives? When I was nineteen, a professor challenged us with these questions: Should bus drivers go to college? Shouldn’t we leave them well enough alone to drive their buses? Why give them the tools that might make it possible for them to imagine another life when all they are going to do is drive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>EMOTIONAL LABOR AS IMPOSTERS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Working-Class Literacy Narratives and Academic Identities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mack</surname>
                           <given-names>Nancy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By teaching writing I am asking students to buy into an academic identity and to learn to write like a member of what I have sarcastically called the<italic>discourse community country club</italic>. I also know that teaching this prestigious discourse to working-class students places them in a subordinate status to those who have been privileged by the academy.¹ Language is a class marker that can expose inferiority with one error in punctuation, word ending, or pronunciation. Conversely, hearing, speaking, or writing one small turn of phrase from my working-class roots can be ethically satisfying.² Language is so powerful that its</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>WE’RE ALL MIDDLE CLASS?</title>
                     <subtitle>Students’ Interpretation of Childhood Ethnographies to Reflect on Class Difference and Identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kohn</surname>
                           <given-names>Liberty</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lynn Bloom has argued that first-year writing functions not to address social class differences but to instill critical thinking as well as middleclass decorum, efficiency, language use, and related middle-class standards in students.² Linda Adler-Kassner argues the same of the college essay, for in the essay “disjuncture between students’ values and the values implicit in the essay can pose a difficulty for some in the composition classroom.”³ This disjuncture can situate first-year writing as a “dumping ground for the problems of the academy and a fertile site for investigating academic and student literacies.”⁴</p>
                     <p>Composition has responded to social class as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>PEDAGOGIES OF INTERDEPENDENCE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Revising the Alienation Narrative for Cultural Match</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Middleton</surname>
                           <given-names>Holly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2007 I moved to northern New Mexico to teach at New Mexico Highlands University (NMHU), an open-admissions federally designated Hispanic-serving institution. At the time, an anti-DUI public service campaign (PSA) was underway appealing to the cultural values of young Hispanic men. In this series, the effects of DUI are dramatized as a threat to families—not to those of the victims of drunk driving but to the families of those who drink and drive. The one I want to single out is called “Mi Mijito.” It opens on a young Hispanic man leaving the house for a night out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>NEVER AND FOREVER JUST KEEP COMING BACK AGAIN:</title>
                     <subtitle>Class, Access, and Student Writing Performance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Phegley</surname>
                           <given-names>Missy Nieveen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a high-school teacher in the mid-90s, I often integrated technical writing into the curriculum for my<italic>non-college-bound</italic>classes (a label used by the school administrators to differentiate from the<italic>college-prep</italic>classes), which were mainly populated with working-class students who planned to enter the workforce immediately after graduation. Consequently, I frequently asked these students to create documents using a computer. On one particular occasion, after introducing a new assignment, I asked my class whether they had any questions, and I received the usual Are<italic>you gonna make us type this?</italic>As I answered, a tall white student nicknamed “Fro” for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>SOCIAL ECONOMIES OF LITERACY IN RURAL OREGON:</title>
                     <subtitle>Accounting for Diverse Sponsorship Histories of Working-Class Students in and out of School</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brewster</surname>
                           <given-names>Cori</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Drawing on a subset of interviews conducted with fifty-two students from rural Oregon attending eleven public two-and four-year colleges across the state, I focus in this chapter on the diverse sponsorship histories of seven rural, working-class students and the social economies of literacy in which these students participate.¹ I include occasions in which students have been sponsored as well as occasions in which they have served as self-sponsors and actively sponsored the literacies of others. As Kim Donehower, Charlotte Hogg, and Eileen Schell have argued, the “rhetoric of lack” through which rural experience is so often read in public discourse</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>RETHINKING CLASS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Poverty, Pedagogy, and Two-Year College Writing Programs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Griffiths</surname>
                           <given-names>Brett</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Toth</surname>
                           <given-names>Christie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The educational impact of poverty on working-class students often goes unexamined in disciplinary conversations about composition pedagogy and theory. This elision reflects a long-standing national rhetoric that simplifies interactions between social classes and hails a middle-class identity so persuasively that most Americans self-identify as middle class, regardless of their economic bracket, material affordances, or social interests.² As a result, narratives about education and social uplift tend to obscure many of the lived realities of students experiencing poverty.³ In first-year composition courses, where many students first encounter the linguistic and cultural expectations of a middle-class professoriate, examining the relationships between class</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>RETROGRADE MOVEMENTS AND THE EDUCATIONAL ENCOUNTER:</title>
                     <subtitle>Working-Class Adults in First-Year Composition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Romesburg</surname>
                           <given-names>James E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every two years the planet Mars appears to temporarily stall in its direct or prograde motion across the night sky and reverse course, making a loop against the more stable backdrop of distant stars before resuming its long, steady trajectory eastward through the heavens. As seen from Earth, this looping or<italic>retrograde</italic>motion occurs over the course of weeks and months but has long been known to careful observers such as the ancients, who were troubled by the planet’s aberrant behavior. Ptolemy theorized an elaborate system of “epicycles” to explain Mars’s apparent motions within the ancient understanding of a geocentric</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>“BEING PART OF SOMETHING GAVE ME PURPOSE”:</title>
                     <subtitle>How Community Membership Impacts First-Year Students’ Sense of Self</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carter</surname>
                           <given-names>Genesea M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>College instructors who wish to help first-year working-class students transition from high school to college are often tasked with teasing out the array of intentions working-class students have for attending college. Working-class students attend college for a variety of reasons that have been well documented,² and supporting them in the classroom is not necessarily easy. Academia, as a well-oiled discourse community, can be inflexible and unforgiving toward new members who may not be prepared for the expectations therein. Students who are academic insiders already know how to “process, comprehend, and respond to existing knowledge—in short, making it their own</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>LITERACY DEVELOPMENT AS SOCIAL PRACTICE IN THE LIVES OF FOUR WORKING-CLASS WOMEN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Verdi</surname>
                           <given-names>Gail G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ebsworth</surname>
                           <given-names>Miriam Eisenstein</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>298</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literacy, in a traditional sense, is the ability to decode written texts and to encode oral language into writing. Yet many researchers and theorists argue that learning to read and write involves social activities influenced by interactions¹ and mediated by class affiliations.² In addition, gender, race, and ethnicity impact how individuals compose internal narratives driving motivation and academic performance.³ Therefore, the narratives we construct through our exchanges with families, teachers, and peers frame our literate identities. The recent focus on the achievement of academic literacy by all learners has underscored the challenges that must be addressed by individuals from different</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>AN AFTERWORD TO CLASS IN THE COMPOSITION CLASSROOM:</title>
                     <subtitle>First-Year Writing as a Social Class Enterprise</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zebroski</surname>
                           <given-names>James T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>320</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>You have in your hands or on your screens an extraordinary volume,<italic>Class in the Composition Classroom</italic>. This is one of the most important books in the discipline that I have read in years. This book is extraordinary in several ways. At a time when some scholars in rhetoric and composition still argue we must cut our ties to teaching and particularly to the so-called universal requirement, freshman composition, this book focuses primarily on freshman composition.¹ At a time when people in rhetoric and composition still see an untenable dualism, a rigid binary between teaching and research, this book deconstructs</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>336</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABOUT THE AUTHORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt1whm918.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
