<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13kh4md</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>French Existentialism</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Christian Critique</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kingston</surname>
               <given-names>F. Temple</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>1961</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781487592318</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781487589257</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1961</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/j.ctt1vxm95x"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this study the author makes a comparison between the two main types of existentialism: the Christian and the non-Christian. Dr. Kingston handles the issues in a fair and honest way, neither concealing his own position nor dealing unfairly with those of whom he is most critical.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="238"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mascall</surname>
                           <given-names>E. L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A GREAT DEAL has been written about Existentialism in recent years, but this work of Dr. Kingston’s seems to me to occupy a unique and important place, and this for two reasons. First, in my opinion he seems to raise those questions about the Existentialist movement which most immediately spring to the mind of any intelligent Christian who finds himself confronted with it. Is the movement a reaction against Christian orthodoxy as such, or is it an attempt to recover certain Christian insights which Christians themselves have largely forgotten? If it is the former, how are we to explain the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>F. T. K.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Existence and Analogy</italic>(p. 64), E. L. Mascall suggests that it would be interesting to discuss the existentialism of St. Thomas Aquinas in relation to contemporary philosophies known by the same name. In the past, Catholic philosophy has been dominated and distorted by an essentialist, Cartesian interpretation of St. Thomas and many have come to regard him as a Christianized Aristotle and his philosophy as a completely idealist, rationalistic and closed system. The dominant place given to atheism and freedom in Sartre’s writings can only be fully understood as a reaction against this essentialist Thomism. In contrast to such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>THE WORLD SITUATION AND THE HUMAN CONDITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Existentialism was first recognized as a valid and also a notorious school of philosophy during the Second World War, especially after the defeat of France. The fall of France was a matter of vital concern for every Frenchman and it would be difficult to overestimate the impact of France’s defeat in 1940 upon the French mind. To many, it was a blind force which had overcome them, for which they could discover no reason. To most, the defeat of France by its traditional enemy—Germany—was deeply humiliating. For almost every Frenchman, the sudden collapse of his country came as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>TIME, SUICIDE AND DEATH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>All the existentialists are united in their opposition to idealist philosophies which ignore space and time as necessary conditions of the human existence. In no way is the finiteness of the human creature more evident than in the fact that he must live an earthly existence, and, since things in time have a beginning and an end, that he must be subject to the mysteries of birth and death. Ignoring these fundamental facts, the idealists sought to transcend the time process by rational system and they imposed a rational pattern upon the course of historical events. In other words, they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>LANGUAGE AND COMMUNION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most noteworthy characteristics of the writings of Marcel, Sartre, Camus and Simone de Beauvoir is that their philosophy is expressed not only in traditional discursive form but also in plays and novels. A question that we must ask is why philosophy is expressed in this way? It would be absurd for rational philosophers such as Spinoza and Leibniz to express philosophy in imaginative works because the subjective idea which the word embodies is reality for them and this reality is beyond any temporal process.</p>
                     <p>Simone de Beauvoir in an article in<italic>Les Temps Modernes</italic>(April, 1946) entitled</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>PHENOMENOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>72</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The method of philosophy which the French non-Christian existentialists choose is phenomenology, which has been inherited from Husserl and Heidegger, and if the approach of Sartre and his followers to philosophy is to be understood their debt to these two German thinkers must be remembered. The Christian existentialists have also, in their own way, been interested in phenomenology. Marcel developed his own phenomenological method before Husserl’s works were known and he is regarded by some as a more authentic phenomenologist than Husserl or the non-Christian existentialists.¹ Gilson affirms that the phenomenological method has effected the most profound study of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>EXISTING AND THE INTELLECT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Professor H. J. Paton, in his<italic>In Defence of Reason,</italic>concludes his chapter on “Existentialism as an Attitude to Life” by saying, “So far as I can see, existentialism is not a theory to argue about, but rather an attitude to decide about—either for or against—unless indeed we decide to ignore it altogether” (p. 214). Whether this is true or not, it is important to see that the main purpose of all existentialists is to restore realism to philosophy. If philosophy is only a theory, then it is restricted to an idealism in which the idea is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>THE ONTOLOGICAL NEED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his Introduction to<italic>L’Etre et l’essence,</italic>Professor Gilson seeks to shed light on some of the ambiguities that have developed concerning the word “being.” The French word “être” is used both as a verb and as a noun. As a verb it signifies that a thing “is” and, as a noun, it signifies one of the things which one says they are. If<italic>x</italic>is a being (un<italic>être</italic>), it does not follow that<italic>x</italic>is, because<italic>x</italic>may be a real or only a possible being. For the sake of clarity, therefore, in order to say in French</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>THE PHILOSOPHERS’ ABSOLUTE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Seldom in the history of thought have men made such absolute declarations of an atheist position as those made by the French non-Christian existentialists. Nietzsche declared that “God is dead” and a whole philosophy has been built up contingent upon that. Sartre writes in<italic>Existentialism and Humanism</italic>(p. 56): “Existentialism is nothing else but an attempt to draw the full conclusions from a consistently atheistic position.”</p>
                     <p>The basic proposition is that the world is absurd because the atheist existentialists can see no sense in it.¹ This discovery of the world’s absurdity results partly from their method because Sartre affirms that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>VALUES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A comparison of values¹ in the writings of Christian and non-Christian French existentialists must necessarily be inadequate because Sartre’s expected work on ethics has not yet been published. However, in Sartre’s own writings and in those of Simone de Beauvoir, a great deal of the ethical approach of the non-Christian existentialists has been revealed.</p>
                     <p>The recognition of any permanent ethical values presents a peculiar difficulty for non-Christian existentialists. As we have seen, the two instruments of truth which Sartre recognizes are reason and immediate sense experience. Immediate sense experience provides the existential index and, because of this, it enjoys a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Nine</label>
                     <title>EXISTING AND RESPONSIBILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>All the existentialists believe that, in this century, the human reality has been degraded more than ever before, and because of this, it has become very difficult for people to see the meaning of human life. The rapid development of techniques has tended to force men to lose their self-respect and become waste-products, despairing of life both intellectually and vitally. In the Nazi concentration camps, not only were the material conditions designed to turn men into beasts, but also the encouragement of suspicion and distrust turned brothers into enemies and devils. Marcel believes that the use of such techniques of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Ten</label>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is a common tendency to regard existentialism as a passing fad rather than as a valid philosophy. This has been largely due to the existentialist writers’ presentation of certain risqué themes as well as to the wide distribution of Sartre’s journalistic and artistic writings. However, this popularizing is due not to a desire for scandal only, but, more fundamentally, to the moral mission which Sartre has assigned himself, to bring as many men as possible to an awareness of themselves and of their freedom. Though there are elements in the philosophies of the non-Christian existentialists which encourage scandal and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vxm95x.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
