<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9df0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">B2430.G494 M46 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Girard, René, 1923-2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memetics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious pluralism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religions.</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Mimetic Theory and World Religions</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Palaver</surname>
               <given-names>Wolfgang</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Schenk</surname>
               <given-names>Richard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781611862621</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781609175443</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Michigan State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>East Lansing</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Michigan State University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.14321/j.ctt1vjqqj6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Those who anticipated the demise of religion and the advent of a peaceful, secularized global village have seen the last two decades confound their predictions. René Girard's mimetic theory is a key to understanding the new challenges posed by our world of resurgent violence and pluralistic cultures and traditions. Girard sought to explain how the Judeo-Christian narrative exposes a founding murder at the origin of human civilization and demystifies the bloody sacrifices of archaic religions. Meanwhile, his book<italic>Sacrifice</italic>, a reading of conflict and sacrificial resolution in the Vedic Brahmanas, suggests that mimetic theory's insights also resonate with several non-Western religious and spiritual traditions. This volume collects engagements with Girard by scholars of Judaism, Christianity, Islam, Hinduism, and Buddhism and situates them within contemporary theology, philosophy, and religious studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our globalized world of today brings with it a unity of humankind such as never experienced before. Opportunities to fi ght hunger and poverty on a worldwide level and to act globally against the threats of climate change have come within the reach of humankind. Globalization, however, also brings with it terrorist threats and related apocalyptic dangers. Concerning religion, the world of today faces two important challenges. We need to overcome an all too simple secularism that reduces religion to a solely private matter, and we have to acknowledge the plurality of religions at the local as well as at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Neither Dawkins nor Durkheim:</title>
                     <subtitle>On René Girard’s Theory of Religion,</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dupuy</surname>
                           <given-names>Jean-Pierre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The greatest disservice that could be done to Girard would be to claim that he invented his theory from scratch. Girard belongs to the great Franco-German-British tradition of religious anthropology that was brought to a premature halt in 1939 by decades of structuralism and poststructuralism: in particular, the French sociological school, with the works of Numa Denis Fustel de Coulanges, Émile Durkheim, and Marcel Mauss; the British anthropological school, with James Frazer, William Robertson-Smith, and the Belgo-British anthropologist Arthur Hocart; not to forget Friedrich Nietzsche and Sigmund Freud who gave these traditions a new momentum. If Girard’s theory is right,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sacrifice in Hegel and Girard</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ramelow</surname>
                           <given-names>Anselm Tilman</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A comparison between G. W. F. Hegel and René Girard on the notion of sacrifice might seem far-fetched; at least it is not immediately clear how to identify the points of contact between both theories. And yet, in a recent text<italic>(Battling to the End)</italic>as well as in conversation, Girard recalls the great influence Hegel had had early on in his thought. Similar to many other French intellectuals in the 1930s, 1940s, and 1950s, Hegel’s influence seems to have come to him by way of Alexandre Kojève. It is noteworthy that an important essay by Georges Bataille connected Kojève’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reason and Revelation:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Important Distinction?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ranieri</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>most decisive shift in his thought occurred when he abandoned an based upon an analysis of political ideas and adopted a method that to gain access to the experiences out of which ideas emerged.¹ This orientation enabled him to penetrate ever more deeply to a level of where apparent differences in ideas were discovered to be similar. After this turn in his thought, much of his theoretical focused on an attempt to articulate a set of terms and relations encompass the most varied kinds of experience. During this process displayed a remarkable openness and willingness to revise his terminology light</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Messianic Moment:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bergson and Girard</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chantre</surname>
                           <given-names>Benoît</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Merrill</surname>
                           <given-names>Trevor Cribben</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <role content-type="translator">Translated by</role>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title of the conference session in which this contribution was originally presented—“Beyond Archaic Religion”—was very well suited to the hypothesis that I would like to defend. Archaic religion, as defined by René Girard in<italic>Violence and the Sacred</italic>, is indeed conceived—even if this conception is only hinted at in 1972—as a prefiguration of Judeo-Christianity. This interpretation of archaic religion, grounded in the description of the scapegoat mechanism, is the first stage in a new approach to the study of Judeo-Christian revelation. Girard positions himself in the lineage of thinkers who have attempted to describe the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Girard and Religion in the Age of Secularism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kallscheuer</surname>
                           <given-names>Otto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me begin with a warning. It might also be read as a plea for excuse: I am neither a true believer in mimetic theory/theology nor a connoisseur of Girardian methodology and its recent developments (if there are any).¹ My reading of René Girard’s oeuvre has been rather sporadic and even somewhat naive. I always took (and after consideration, I still take) the Girardian approach for a general (but also generic) suspicion; I don’t read his theory as a specific (scientific) hypothesis. In the end René Girard’s “big” and iconoclastic thesis—about the scapegoat mechanism as the very origin and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Why Rousseau Cannot Laugh:</title>
                     <subtitle>Structuring Motif—“Achever”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alberg</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeremiah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I begin with a quote from the introduction to René Girard’s<italic>Achever Clausewitz</italic>.¹ I want to use this quote to extract a kind of operational definition of what it means to “achever,” or, according to the English translation, “to complete,” a thinker and then use this as a programmatic outline for this attempt to understand Rousseau and his status as a religious thinker. Girard writes:</p>
                     <p>completing [the achever of the title] the interpretation of [Carl von Clausewitz’s] On War is to say that its meaning is religious and that only a religious interpretation has a chance of reaching what is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Girard and the Feminist Critique of Religion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Intimate Mediation in Kristeva and Girard</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reineke</surname>
                           <given-names>Martha</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After thirty years, as feminist theories in the philosophy of religion, theology, and religious studies approach middle age, on what basis can we reflect on Girard and that feminist critique? Surely, we would most productively move forward were we to home in on aspects of feminist theorizing about religion that have maintained the most saliency. Moreover, feminist theorists of religion would most productively engage Girard in dialogue were they to share with him a sense of urgency about the world that he has conveyed in his most recent works, especially in<italic>Battling to the End</italic>. On both counts, an observation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Girard and World Religions:</title>
                     <subtitle>The State of the Question</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Daly</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Presumably, I have this assignment primarily because I was the program convener for the 2000 COV&amp;R meeting at Boston College under the title “Violence and Institution in Christianity, Judaism, Hinduism, Buddhism, and Islam,” and eventual editor of its papers in<italic>Contagion</italic>9 (2002). When, to begin this task, I asked the major presenters from that conference how their thinking on this subject had developed over the past decade, Francis Clooney, SJ,¹ helpfully informed me that the 1898 work of Silvain Lévi (on whom Girard relied in his recent book,<italic>Sacrifice</italic>)² was now considered to be a classic in the field.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>René Girard and World Religions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kirwan</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mimetic theory’s encounter with world religions may be pictured as a tension between two powerful vectors or currents. The mainstream is the openness to the truth to be found in non-Christian religions, which we find articulated by the Second Vatican Council in 1965 (within a few years of the publication of<italic>Deceit, Desire, and the Novel</italic>), and taken forward in a series of official Roman Catholic pronouncements. I trace these developments not with a sectarian intent, but because these declarations comprise a legitimate heuristic: René Girard himself is a committed Catholic Christian, and among mimetic theorists exploring the implications of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Ambivalence of Interreligious Historiography:</title>
                     <subtitle>Foreign and Domestic Narratives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schenk</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whatever the charges of imprecision that might be raised against the concept of “world religions,” there is one feature that religions claiming this title will necessarily share with one another: an explicit sense of their relation to several other religions with prima facie rights to this same claim. The self-understanding of each world religion is constituted in part by its understanding of other world religions. Precisely for Girardian theory, the perceived initial commonality that makes interrelationality and differentiation unavoidable also makes it likely from the start that world religions are not only expressions of how competitive processes internal to each</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Sacrifice as a Contested Concept between R. Schwager and R. Girard and Its Significance for lnterreligious Dialogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wandinger</surname>
                           <given-names>Nikolaus</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this article is to sketch the development of the concept of sacrifice in René Girard’s thinking, as it developed especially in discussion with Innsbruck systematic theologian and founder of the School of Dramatic Theology there, Raymund Schwager, to briefly reflect on this development in the light of Bernard Lonergan’s theological method (this will show that we are dealing with “religious conversion” understood in a certain sense), and to make some suggestions as to how this can ground interreligious dialogue and provide it with additional significance.</p>
                     <p>In 1978 René Girard confronted his previously developed theory of sacrifice¹ with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Abrahamic Revolution</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Palaver</surname>
                           <given-names>Wolfgang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among scholars dedicated to mimetic theory recent debates raised the question of how Islam is related to Judaism and Christianity. One frequently mentioned starting point is the “Epilogue” in René Girard’s<italic>book Battling to the End</italic>, in which he claims that Islam is a religion that “has used the Bible as a support to rebuild an archaic religion that is more powerful than all the others” (Girard 2010, 214). Could one draw from this and similar remarks the conclusion that Islam is an archaic religion and not at all comparable with Judaism and Christianity, even going as far as rejecting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The “Hellenic” Rationality of Interreligious Dialogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>René Girard, Simone Weil, and Pope Benedict XVI</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Astell</surname>
                           <given-names>Ann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Simone Weil’s<italic>The Need for Roots (L’Enracinement)</italic>, written during the last months of her life (1909–43) and with her dying strength, is a fitting companion piece to<italic>Battling to the End (Achever Clausewitz)</italic>, the last book by René Girard (b. 1923). Compatriots, Weil and Girard each retell the long story of French history from the Middle Ages, beginning in medias res and dwelling upon many of the same modern turning points—1789, 1815, 1914, 1940. Girard explicitly links his own childhood memories of the war years with the Free French radio broadcasts from London and the names of Maurice</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Burning Desires, Burning Corpses:</title>
                     <subtitle>Girardian Reflections on Fire in Hinduism and Buddhism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Collins</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The subject of this essay is the role of fire and its explicit and implicit understandings in the Hindu and Buddhist traditions. At first glance, this appears to be a useful way of narrowing the scope of an essay that began with the impossible task of producing a mimetic analysis of Indian religions. But the scope thus narrowed is still much too broad to be manageable. As in Christianity, Islam, Zoroastrianism, and Judaism, the understanding of fire in the Hindu and Buddhist traditions is in equal measure heterogeneous, historically contingent, and (in some senses) foundational, which makes for a wide</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Girard and Hindu Sacrifice,</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sheth</surname>
                           <given-names>Noel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In dealing with René Girard’s ideas about Hindu sacrifi ce, I concentrate on his book<italic>Sacrifice</italic>¹ since it mostly deals with Vedic, that is, early Hindu, sacrifice.² My article is divided into three parts.³</p>
                     <p>In his book<italic>Sacrifice</italic>Girard pays special attention to sacrifice in the Brāhmaṇas. Although he deals with it later in his book, let me start, in chronological order, with the Puruṣa-Sūkta (Hymn of the [Cosmic] Person) (RV 10.90), in which creation or emanation takes place through the sacrifi ce, and even dismemberment, of the Cosmic Person.ṣ Girard points out that in the last verse the Cosmic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Roots of Violence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Society and the Individual in Buddhism and Girard</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dalton</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacob</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Rospatt</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>René Girard’s complex and sophisticated theory of sacrifice offers insights into the workings of human society that transcend culture and time and, while privileging Christianity and modernity, claim a certain universality. This invites scholars of other cultures and religions to consider the applicability of Girardian thought to their own fields of study. As scholars of Buddhism we take up this challenge by bringing Buddhism into conversation with Girard. Instead of concentrating on a particular text (Schlieter 2009) or genre (Hahn 2009) or practice (Arifuku 2009), we aim for a more comprehensive and general engagement with Girard by suggesting how Buddhism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religious Sacrifice, Social Scapegoating, and Self-Justification</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Peters</surname>
                           <given-names>Ted</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the term<italic>sacrifice</italic>is used to designate practices common to various world religions and used to designate a historical scapegoat at the founding of a social order, are we referring to the same thing? Perhaps not. Th e sacrifi ce of which the Girard school speaks applies to any social order—whether a political order, an ideological organization, a social movement, or such—not merely to an established religious tradition.¹ So, let us pose the question: What is the value of Girardian theory? Is it to illuminate the religious concept of sacrifice or to illuminate human nature in general?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Judaism and the Exodus from Archaic Religion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading René Girard among the World Religions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goodhart</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandor</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>385</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We are coming upon the week when in Judaism we tell the story of the Exodus, the passage from Egypt to the desert where the people led by Moses will gather at the “foot of the mountain” in Rashi’s translation<italic>(b’tachtiyt hahar in Exodus 19:171)</italic>—some say “beneath the mountain”—ready to receive the aseret hadibrot, the ten utterances or commandments. What has always been of special interest to me in the seder (that Jews</p>
                     <p>hold in the diaspora on the first and second night of Pesach or Passover) is the extent to which we are asked (when we read</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Tawhid:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Oneness of God and the Desire for the Good</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ericksen</surname>
                           <given-names>Adam</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the epilogue of his book<italic>Battling to the End</italic>René Girard articulates his growing anxiety concerning the West and Islam since September 11, 2001. He states that “We are witnessing a new stage in the escalation to extremes.”¹ Asan escalation of mimetic rivalry, both Islam and the West are responsible for their participation in the current global crisis of violence. Indeed, Girard claims in the same book, “When violence is involved, wrongs are always shared.”² But it might seem as though violence is endemic to Islam in a way that it is not to the West. Girard invokes Islamic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Islam:</title>
                     <subtitle>Law and Violence (and Nonviolence)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lohlker</surname>
                           <given-names>Rüdiger</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>413</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have to apologize—being not a Girardian—when starting with an idea introduced in the text on “Violence and Religion: Cause or Effect?”: “The question of religious violence is first and foremost a human question, . . . and not a directly religious question” (Girard 2004).</p>
                     <p>This leads me to some remarks on the concept of law in Islam or law relative to Islam (see Lohlker 2011). If we think about law in an Islamic context we are often conflating two concepts: law, called<italic>fiqh</italic>, and Sharia. Talking about law as<italic>fiqh</italic>we mean a complex web of rules</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Girard and the Analogy of Desire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alison</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>427</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the devil is in the details, then God is in the prepositions, and I want today to look at one such preposition: the little word “for.” I think this to be the most diffi cult and delicate word to parse in the whole of theology. Let me explain why. As St. Th omas Aquinas taught us, we cannot say of God what God is, only what God is not. Th is very properly negative approach to God is vital if we are to avoid idolatry. Idolatry is where whatever passes as “god” is in fact a function of our</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1vjqqj6.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>449</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
