<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1551mpq</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Rhetoric and the Writing of History, 400-1500</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kempshall</surname>
               <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780719070303</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781847798985</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Matthew Kempshall</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt155jhjx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book provides an analytical overview of the vast range of historiography which was produced in western Europe over a thousand-year period between c.400 and c.1500. Concentrating on the general principles of classical rhetoric central to the language of this writing, alongside the more familiar traditions of ancient history, biblical exegesis and patristic theology, this survey introduces the conceptual sophistication and semantic rigour with which medieval authors could approach their narratives of past and present events, and the diversity of ends to which this history could then be put. By providing a close reading of some of the historians who put these linguistic principles and strategies into practice (from Augustine and Orosius through Otto of Freising and William of Malmesbury to Machiavelli and Guicciardini), it traces and questions some of the key methodological changes that characterise the function and purpose of the western historiographical tradition in this formative period of its development.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="637"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What follows has its immediate origins in a series of lectures offered to undergraduate historians at Oxford in the summer of 2004. It should therefore begin with an apology, in the strictest sense of the word, to those of my early-modern and modern colleagues within the History Faculty who thought that an undergraduate paper on the history of historiography should begin in<italic>c</italic>. 1500 because that is when, and I quote, ‘proper’ historiography really began. Without wishing to be vague, or get into a jam, had those colleagues said that to a classicist, they would have been met with a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>HISTORY AND HISTORIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>34</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The writing of history in the Middle Ages cannot be reduced to one single formula or definition. Instead, it straddled a huge variety of genres, covering – and often combining – world chronicles, annals, histories of communities, deeds of individuals, hagiographies, biographies, autobiographies and epic poems.¹ Medieval historiography therefore does not correspond to any fixed genre, in terms of either its form or its style – it could be written in prose, in verse or sometimes as both; it could be sung as a<italic>chanson de geste</italic>; it could be sculpted or painted or presented in tableaux; in the case of the ‘estorie’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>RHETORIC AND HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In seeking to establish exactly how the writing of history was conceptualised and practised in the Middle Ages, a sensible starting point is to identify where historiography fitted into a programme of study, that is, where medieval authors would themselves have encountered the writing of history as a body of material and as part and parcel of their education.¹ What becomes immediately apparent is that, initially at least, it would have been as an integral component of the study of grammar and rhetoric – in grammar, as excerpts from classical historians and, in rhetoric, as the theory and practice of narrating</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>INVENTION AND NARRATIVE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The categorisation of classical rhetoric into its demonstrative, judicial and deliberative forms reveals significant differences in emphasis, but also significant similarities in approach, in the way in which the relationship between an individual’s character (<italic>mores</italic>) and deeds (<italic>res gestae</italic>) could, and should, be described by a speaker or writer. The principles which these three categories of rhetoric shared as common ground, however, exerted an impact on medieval historiography that went well beyond engineering the specific didactic, legal or political goals of particular works of history. This influence can be gauged by means of the two standard schemes according to which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>VERISIMILITUDE AND TRUTH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>350</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In setting out the principles by which arguments could be found in order to construct a narrative of people and of events, classical manuals of rhetoric gave central importance to the criterion of verisimilitude. Quintilian may have disagreed with those who thought that the<italic>sole</italic>concern of the orator was verisimilitude,¹ but otherwise medieval authors were presented with a very clear agenda: truth requires the art of rhetoric in order to make it plausible or convincing, in order to give it the appearance or simili tude of truth. This may involve composing or making things up (<italic>fingere</italic>) and the resulting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>HISTORIOGRAPHY AND HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>428</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The influence of classical rhetoric on the writing of history in the Middle Ages centred on the relationship between the depiction of character (attributes of person) and the description of deeds (attributes of events), on the invention of arguments (causation, testimony and proof), and on the construction of a brief, lucid and, above all, verisimilar narrative. This does not mean, of course, that all the principles involved in each one of these areas were applied either simultaneously or consistently across the broad range of writings which the single term<italic>historia</italic>could comprise and across the conventional periodisation of a thousand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>536</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Medieval historiography was neither crude nor credulous nor conceptually unsophisticated. Such characterisations would be no more, and no less, applicable to the writing of history in the early modern and modern periods and, if only on this basis, medieval historians deserve better than to suffer the methodological condescension of posterity. The present study has been designed accordingly as an introduction to a set of interpretative criteria on which works of medieval historiography might be assessed, primarily through examining principles of classical rhetoric which would have been second-nature to writers who had been brought up, directly or indirectly, on the precepts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>552</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155jhjx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>601</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
