<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Ascent into Heaven in Luke-Acts</book-title>
         <subtitle>New Explorations of Luke's Narrative Hinge</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bryan</surname>
               <given-names>David K.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pao</surname>
               <given-names>David W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451496444</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451496443</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506418964</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506418961</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c84g9z"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In comparison with other aspects of Jesus’ life and ministry, his ascent into heaven has often been overlooked within the history of the church. However, considering its placement at the end of the Gospel and the beginning of Acts—the only narrative depictions of the event in the New Testament—the importance of Jesus’ ascent into heaven is undeniable for Luke’s two-volume work. While select studies have focused on particular aspects of these accounts for Luke’s story, the importance of the ascension calls for renewed attention to the narratological and theological significance of these accounts within their historical and literary contexts. In this volume, leading scholars discuss the ascension narratives within the ancient contexts of biblical, Second Temple Jewish, and Greco-Roman literature; the literary contours of Luke-Acts; and questions of historical and theological significance in the wider milieu of New Testament theology and early Christian historiography. The volume sets out new positions and directions for the next generations of interpreters regarding one of the most important and unique elements of the Lukan writings.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bryan</surname>
                           <given-names>David K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pao</surname>
                           <given-names>David W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the voluminous amount of scholarship devoted to Luke-Acts in general, and Lukan Christology and theology in particular, one of the few areas that has received far less attention in the last fifty years is Luke’s dual narration of Jesus’s ascent into heaven in Luke 24 and Acts 1. Prior to the 1980s, ascension scholarship was heavily indebted to two key works. Victoriano Larrañaga,<italic>L’ascension de Notre-Seigneur dans le Nouveau Testament</italic>(1938, original thesis written in Spanish in 1934 and published in Spanish in 1943), focused heavily on the text of the ascension narratives in the Lukan accounts. Gerhard Lohfink’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Ascension Scholarship</title>
                     <subtitle>Past, Present, and Future</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zwiep</surname>
                           <given-names>Arie W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this contribution, I will review recent biblical scholarship on the Lukan ascension narratives, outline points of agreement and areas of ongoing debate, and briefly outline a possible agenda for future research.¹ I roughly take the work of Mikeal Parsons² and myself³ as<italic>termini a quo</italic>. First, I will map some recent developments in textual criticism and their potential repercussions on the reconstruction of the initial text (<italic>Ausgangstext</italic>) of the ascension narratives. Second, since the study of Parsons, narrative criticism and literary approaches have become increasingly popular in Lukan studies, including the study of the ascension narratives. What are the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Jesus’s Ascension through Old Testament Narrative Traditions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Walton</surname>
                           <given-names>Steve</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jesus is not the first to travel to heaven in the Jewish scriptures, nor in the wider Jewish tradition,¹ to say nothing of Graeco-Roman traditions.² The question that naturally arises is to what extent, if at all, these earlier traditions have influenced Luke’s telling of the ascension of Jesus. This essay focuses on two key narrative traditions from the Old Testament (OT) of people travelling to heaven, namely, Elijah (2 Kgs 2:1–18) and, much more briefly, Enoch (Gen 5:24). We shall review these traditions and consider how far their language and themes are echoed in Luke’s accounts of Jesus’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“For David Did Not Ascend into Heaven …” (Acts 2:34a)</title>
                     <subtitle>Reprogramming Royal Psalms to Proclaim the Enthroned-in-Heaven King</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jipp</surname>
                           <given-names>Joshua W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the surprising aspects of Luke’s narration of Jesus’s ascent into heaven in Acts 1:9–11 is the brevity with which Luke describes this event. While there are some similarities with 2 Kings 2:7–12, the account of Elijah’s heavenly rapture is unable to fully explain the meaning of Jesus’s ascent into heaven in Acts.¹ Whereas Elijah’s heavenly location is no longer mentioned again after 2 Kings 2 and exerts no influence on the rest of the narrative, Jesus’s location in heaven continues to exert enormous influence on the rest of Acts.² The importance of Jesus’s location in heaven</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Revised Cosmic Hierarchy Revealed</title>
                     <subtitle>Apocalyptic Literature and Jesus’s Ascent in Luke’s Gospel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bryan</surname>
                           <given-names>David K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1987, Mikeal Parsons revived the narrative significance of Luke’s dual inclusion of Jesus’s ascent into heaven at the conclusion of the Gospel and the beginning of Acts.¹ Parsons argued that Jesus’s ascent supplies a “triumphal exit” to Luke’s Gospel, an interpretation typically affirmed by scholars today who also view the ascension as a concluding “exaltation.”² In spite of this general consensus, it remains debated exactly how this brief conclusion to Luke’s Gospel portrays Jesus as “triumphal” or “exalted,” and how the ascent relates to the preceding narrative of the Gospel.³ In other words, within the Gospel of Luke alone,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Benefactor and Paradigm</title>
                     <subtitle>Viewing Jesus’s Ascension in Luke-Acts through Greco-Roman Ascension Traditions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wallace</surname>
                           <given-names>James Buchanan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whatever may have been the intentions of the author of Luke-Acts when composing the story of the ascension into heaven of Jesus Christ, and whatever may have been the antecedents foremost in his mind, the quotations above from the church fathers Justin Martyr and Tertullian provide sufficient warrant for exploring Greco-Roman ascension traditions as essential contexts for understanding the ascension of Jesus Christ in Luke-Acts. The first generations of readers would immediately have detected a similarity between Jesus Christ’s ascension into heaven and the countless tales of ascension into heaven told in Greek and Roman traditions.³ While Justin will go</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Unity of Luke-Acts and the Ascension Narratives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Porter</surname>
                           <given-names>Stanley E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ascension narratives are found only in Luke-Acts. Whereas we have resurrection accounts of various types in the Synoptic Gospels (Matt 28:1–10; Mark 16:1–8; Luke 24:1–10) as well as John’s Gospel (20:1–8), and mention of the resurrection (or resurrection-ascension) in other places in the New Testament (NT) (see especially Paul’s writings: 1 Cor 15:4, 12–28; Eph 1:20; etc.), and whereas we also have exaltation passages at various places in the NT (e.g., Acts 2:33–34; 5:31; Eph 1:20; Phil 2:9–11; Col 3:1), the ascension itself is only specifically depicted within Luke-Acts (some have suggested</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Jesus’s Ascension and the Lukan Account of the Restoration of Israel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pao</surname>
                           <given-names>David W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the New Testament (NT) writings, only Luke provides an explicit account of the public ascension of Jesus. The significance of Jesus’s ascension in his writings is further accentuated by the fact that it appears in both his first and second volumes. While it is widely acknowledged that the ascension account found at the end of Luke’s Gospel serves to provide a proper conclusion to this gospel (Luke 24:50–53),¹ and the one found at the beginning of Acts serves to introduce the mission of the apostles after Jesus’s departure (Acts 1:9–11),² the programmatic significance of the ascension narrative</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Ascension and Spatial Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sleeman</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“When Jesus ascended into heaven, what happened to the sandals he was wearing?”</p>
                     <p>The question came to me, in more ways than one, out of the blue. It was posed by the late Carl Baron, then Senior Tutor at St. Catharine’s College, Cambridge. I was applying to read geography as an undergraduate and, in addition to a subject-specific interview, all candidates underwent a general interview with the Senior Tutor. Unwittingly or otherwise, spurred perhaps by an eighteen-year-old’s eagerly evangelical responses on an application form, Dr. Baron became the first person to help me link spatial theory and the ascension.</p>
                     <p>I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Lukan Cosmology and the Ascension</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On an episode of the television show<italic>The West Wing</italic>, White House Press Secretary C. J. Cregg meets with the Organization of Cartographers for Social Equality.¹ They want President Bartlett to support legislation for schools to discard the Mercator Projection map in favor of the Peters Projection. Their reason? The traditional map distorts the relative size of countries and continents and thus fosters European imperialist attitudes. Cregg is skeptical, until the cartographers point out that despite their similar size on the Mercator map, Africa is 14 times larger than Greenland. The cartographers show the press secretary the Peters Projection map,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>The Ascension as a Cultic Experience in Acts</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Strelan</surname>
                           <given-names>Rick</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay, I propose that the Acts narrative of the ascension of Jesus (1:6–11) derived from, and was shaped by, the cultic and devotional practices of Luke’s audiences. In these practices, they experienced, often in visions, the exalted Jesus as the ascending Lord. Rather than the narrative determining the practices, these visionary experiences determined the narrative. In this, I imitate to a degree the argument of Hurtado that some early Christians experienced Jesus as Lord in a worship setting, and it was from that experience of him that they developed their christological understandings.¹ The priority and significance of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>What Is This Conversation You Are Holding?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Farrow</surname>
                           <given-names>Douglas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Jesus laid his footsteps alongside those of the two disciples on the road to Emmaus, he enquired of them, “What is this conversation you are holding with each other as you walk?” As one invited to join the present coterie of biblical scholars long enough to offer a brief theological postscript, I want to put the same question.</p>
                     <p>Now, it would not surprise me if I, too, were met with a puzzled look and something like the response, “Are you the only visitor to Jerusalem who does not know the things that have happened there in these days?” For</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Selected Bibliography on the Ascension in Luke-Acts (1995–2015)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c84g9z.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
