<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jktrvp</collection-id>
      <volume>15</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Intimate. Polity and the Catholic Church</book-title>
         <subtitle>Laws about Life, Death and the Family in So-called Catholic Countries</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>DOBBELAERE</surname>
               <given-names>KAREL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PÉREZ-AGOTE</surname>
               <given-names>ALFONSO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">EDS</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789462700277</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789461662118</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Leuven University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Leuven (Belgium)</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Leuven University Press/Presses Universitaires de Louvain/Universitaire Pers Leuven</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1jkts6b"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The waning influence of the Catholic church in the ethical and political debate. For centuries the Catholic Church was able to impose her ethical rules in matters related to the intimate, that is, questions concerning life (from its beginning until its end) and the family, in the so-called Catholic countries in Western Europe. When the polity started to introduce legislation that was in opposition to the Catholic ethic, the ecclesiastical authorities and part of the population reacted. The media reported massive manifestations in France against same-sex marriages and in Spain against the de-penalization of abortion. In Italy the Episcopal conference entered the political field in opposition to the relaxation of several restrictive legal rules concerning medically assisted procreation and exhorted the voters to abstain from voting so that the referendum did not obtain the necessary quorum. In Portugal, to the contrary, the Church made a “pact" with the prime minister so that the law on same-sex marriages did not include the possibility of adoption. And in Belgium the Episcopal conference limited its actions to clearly expressing with religious, legal, and anthropological arguments its opposition to such laws, which all other Episcopal conferences did also. In this book, the authors analyse the full spectrum of the issue, including the emergence of such laws; the political discussions; the standpoints defended in the media by professionals, ethicists, and politicians; the votes in the parliaments; the political interventions of the Episcopal conferences; and the attitude of professionals. As a result the reader understands what was at stake and the differences in actions of the various Episcopal conferences. The authors also analyse the pro and con evaluations among the civil population of such actions by the Church. Finally, in a comparative synthesis, they discuss the public positions taken by Pope Francis to evaluate if a change in Church policy might be possible in the near future. Research by GERICR (Groupe européen de recherche interdisciplinaire sur le changement religieux), a European interdisciplinary research group studying religious changes coordinated by Alfonso Pérez-Agote. Contributors Céline Béraud (Université de Caen), Karel Dobbelaere (KU Leuven/University of Antwerp), Annalisa Frisina (Università degli Studi di Padova), Franco Garelli (Università degli Studi di Torino), Antonio Montañés (Universidad Complutense de Madrid), Maria João Oliveira (University of Porto), Enzo Pace (Università degli Studi di Padova), Alfonso Pérez-Agote (University Complutense of Madrid), Philippe Portier (École pratique des hautes études, Paris-Sorbonne), Jose Santiago (Universidad Complutense de Madrid), Roberto Francesco Scalon (Università degli Studi di Torino), Helena Vilaça (University of Porto), Liliane Voyé (Université Catholique de Louvain)</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOBBELAERE</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PÉREZ-AGOTE</surname>
                           <given-names>ALFONSO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most studies concerning the evolution of Catholicism in Western Europe underscore in general the clear decrease in church practices and, sometimes also, the decline or even the erosion of the orthodox beliefs. However, the loss of the impact of Catholicism on these societies manifests itself also in the changes in certain laws in the domain of ethics, which until very recently, were profoundly marked by the Christian vision. This indicates the diminishing ascendancy of Catholicism over our societies, an ‘exculturation’ that testifies to a further step in the secularization process.¹ Indeed, in the last quarter of the 20 th and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>EUTHANASIA AND THE BELGIAN CATHOLIC WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VOYÉ</surname>
                           <given-names>LILIANE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOBBELAERE</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the ethical domain, Belgium has been one of the first Western European countries to introduce new legislation clashing head on with the prescriptions of the Catholic Church in these matters. In 1990, a law was passed de-penalizing abortion, in 2002 a law authorizing euthanasia and, in 2003, one legalizing samesex marriages. Although the law authorizing euthanasia, under different restrictive conditions, had existed for more than ten years, we nevertheless selected this theme to illustrate the topicality of the ethical problems since euthanasia came very definitely to the fore again recently as a result of two distinct events which stimulated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“MARIAGE POUR TOUS”</title>
                     <subtitle>THE SAME-SEX MARRIAGE CONTROVERSY IN FRANCE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BÉRAUD</surname>
                           <given-names>CÉLINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PORTIER</surname>
                           <given-names>PHILIPPE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Making marriage open to same-sex couples is one of the “new public issues”¹ that are controversial. In France, the passing of the marriage for everyone act gave rise to the expression of and confrontation between very divergent views. Among the opponents of the bill, the Catholics appeared as key players. From August 2012 onwards, some bishops aimed at acting as “whistleblowers”.² In the months that followed, up to the adoption of the bill by the French parliament and even beyond, some Catholics conducted a moral re-armament campaign against<italic>le mariage pour tous</italic>(marriage for everyone), with the aim of challenging</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE ITALIAN CATHOLIC CHURCH AND THE ARTIFICIAL-INSEMINATION REFERENDUM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRISINA</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNALISA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GARELLI</surname>
                           <given-names>FRANCO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PACE</surname>
                           <given-names>ENZO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCALON</surname>
                           <given-names>ROBERTO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Italian biotechnological sector has become a battlefield between the Catholic Church and the various actors who disagree with its positions. They represent various power and knowledge subsystems in a society which has become complex. The conflict also grows out of the paradox of a society – like the Italian – which is partly secularized but can still portray itself as majority Catholic. From the social point of view, Catholicism continues to be the<italic>basso continuo</italic>of collective conscience, although among the Italian population many attitudes and behaviours in the field of faith and religious practice have deviated – either discreetly or decisively</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ETHICAL CHALLENGES OF THE CATHOLIC CHURCH IN PORTUGAL</title>
                     <subtitle>THE CASE OF SAME-SEX MARRIAGE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>VILAÇA</surname>
                           <given-names>HELENA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OLIVEIRA</surname>
                           <given-names>MARIA JOÃO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Portugal is mainly a Catholic country and with significant indicators of religiosity in the European context. However, this fact did not prevent the liberalization of society on fracturing and delicate issues related to customs and bioethics. There have been two referendums on abortion and legislative changes with regard to divorce, gay marriage and medically assisted procreation (without a previous referendum).</p>
                     <p>There is no public debate on euthanasia and there is serious penalization for this practice. These changes were not exactly peaceful and originated more or less enlarged debates, sometimes in a moderate way and sometimes leading to the radicalization of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE CATHOLIC CHURCH FACES ETHICAL CHALLENGES IN SPAIN</title>
                     <subtitle>THE REGULATION OF ABORTION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PÉREZ-AGOTE</surname>
                           <given-names>ALFONSO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SANTIAGO</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MONTAÑÉS</surname>
                           <given-names>ANTONIO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last quarter of the twentieth century, Spain has seen the historical confluence of two social processes which are highly significant for analysing the position of the Spanish Church, and essentially of its hierarchy, when confronted with the ethical challenges which have a ultimately motivated its current resurgence in the public sphere. On the one hand, in various European countries – and also outside Europe – scientific and technological advances in the sphere of human biology have sparked a series of public debates. The regulation of these issues by the national political systems in the countries included in this study – and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>COMPARATIVE SYNTHESIS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DOBBELAERE</surname>
                           <given-names>KAREL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PÉREZ-AGOTE</surname>
                           <given-names>ALFONSO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BÉRAUD</surname>
                           <given-names>CÉLINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The management of death, the regulation of pregnancy termination and medically assisted procreation and the institutionalization of same-sex couples and same-sex parenting: in the different European countries that we have studied, the public authorities are preoccupied by such issues which relate to questions concerning life (from its beginning until its end), sexuality and gender. As per Michel Foucault¹, new bio politics are being developed, a new “government of bodies” (according to Didier Fassin and Dominique Memmi²). This usually concerns women’s bodies, regardless whether it is abortion, medically assisted reproduction – as Frisina writes in the chapter on Italy – or same-sex marriage.³</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AUTHORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1jkts6b.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>COLOPHON</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
