<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt152vpg3</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="doi">10.2307/j.ctt155j380</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Homebrewed Christianity Guide to Jesus</book-title>
         <subtitle>Lord, Liar, Lunatic…Or Awesome?</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FULLER</surname>
               <given-names>TRIPP</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>AUTHOR AND SERIES EDITOR</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451499575</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451499574</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506401256</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506401252</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress Publishers</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt155j380"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Christology is crazy. It’s rather absurd to identify a first-century homeless Jew as God revealed, but a bunch of us do anyway. In this book, Tripp Fuller examines the historical Jesus, the development of the doctrine of Christ, the questions that drove christological innovations through church history, contemporary constructive proposals, and the predicament of belief for the church today. Recognizing that the battle over Jesus is no longer a public debate between the skeptic and believer but an internal struggle in the heart of many disciples, he argues that we continue to make christological claims about more than an “event" or simply the “Jesus of history." On the other hand, C. S. Lewis’s infamous “liar, lunatic, and Lord" scheme is no longer intellectually tenable. This may be a guide to Jesus, but for Christians, Fuller is guiding us toward a deeper understanding of God. He thinks it’s good news—good news about a God who is so invested in the world that God refuses to be God without us.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fuller</surname>
                           <given-names>Tripp</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>You are about to read a guidebook. Not only is the book the sweet “guide book” size, shaped perfectly to take a ride in your back pocket, but the book itself was crafted with care by a real-deal theology nerd. Here’s the thing. The Homebrewed Christianity Guide series has one real goal: we want to think<italic>with</italic>you, not<italic>for</italic>you.</p>
                     <p>The whole “homebrew” metaphor grows from my passion for helping anyone who wants to geek out about theology to do so with the best ingredients around. That’s why I started the Homebrewed Christianity podcast in 2008, and that’s why</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Homebrewed Posse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Lord, Liar, Lunatic … or Just Freaking Awesome</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have discovered a secret way of solving the most perplexing theological questions. My college roommate and I invented it in our dorm room as a way of finding answers to some of our most contentious debates. We were religion and philosophy majors, which means we argued about religion and politics as a kind of recreational sport. When we arrived at an intractable difference of opinions, we settled it like any nineteen-year-old scholar should—by playing a video game. We settled our disputes over a game of Madden 2001, to be exact. We decided that the best way for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Jesus’ Jewish Neighborhood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jesus was Jewish. I know it seems obvious, but here’s a crazy fact: until fairly recently, scholarship about Jesus didn’t really take his Jewishness into account. Throughout the early church, the Middle Ages, and the Reformation, the experts who studied Jesus in the Bible pretty much ignored the fact that Jesus, his disciples, his opponents, and just about everyone who wrote about him in the New Testament were<italic>Jews</italic>. That means Augustine, Aquinas, Luther—they all overlooked the fact that Jesus and the whole cast of characters were Jewish. And to make it even crazier, some of them (cough, Luther,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Abba Says, “Drop the G”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I remember the first time I talked to someone who really had no clue about Jesus—she knew nothing about him beyond his birth story, death story, and accompanying holidays. Her name was Angela, and she was a college sophomore sent to interview a minister from the religion she was least attracted to. That’s probably not how it was written in the syllabus, but it definitely made for a conversation I wasn’t going to pass up.</p>
                     <p>We met at the Coffee Cartel, my local shop, and, after giving a brief apology up front, she was all business. “Look, I don’t</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Reading the Gospels Heresy-Free</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the things about my upbringing I’m most grateful for is the love of Scripture that my parents gave me. I remember thinking I had finally arrived when I was able to read the Bible and pray by myself before bed. I loved it! I read the Bible every night in my bed, so proud of my accomplishment.</p>
                     <p>Then, during Holy Week when I was in fourth grade, I discovered that my Bible was broken.</p>
                     <p>I had decided to read all four Gospel accounts of Jesus’ final week. As a dutiful student of the Bible, I remember charting out</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Anselm, Luther, and the Cootie Collector</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have a confession to make: I used to be a Calvinist. For some, that label means absolutely nothing. For others, it provokes an intense response—Calvinism tends to have that effect. Where I went to college, at a small Baptist school in the South, whether you were a Calvinist really mattered, for it determined which of the fifteen campus Bible studies you could attend. By the prevenient grace of God, I was eventually lured beyond the imaginative cage of John Calvin, and I finally moved out of the Baptist enclave that rivaled Geneva for its lack of theological imagination.¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Getting High with Jesus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the bottom of my first theology paper in college, the professor wrote, “This was an excellent essay. Your confusion around methodological demarcations, categorizing tools for assessment, and some ambiguity around the nature of historical thematization in terms of revelation will not permit a higher grade—but it is clear you will get there. Get a theological dictionary.”</p>
                     <p>I took the paper to a couple of upperclass religion majors for a translation. I was pretty sure the sentence meant something important, but I had no idea what it was. Over the course of an hour I discovered the secret of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Turning Jesus Down</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I was a sophomore in college on September 11, 2001. My roommate Michael and I were getting ready for the school’s mandatory chapel service when the first plane crashed into the World Trade Center. Between the first and second plane hitting, little sense could be made of what, at least on the news, seemed to be a human error. Once we realized these were part of a coordinated attack, the suffering and tragedy experienced by those involved became an existential threat. And all of a sudden, my unexamined and unconscious place within America came to the surface of my psyche.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Skeptic and the Believer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I teach confirmation class, I tend to make a big deal about questions. The process ultimately boils down to the one Jesus put to his disciples: “Who do you say that I am?”¹ It’s my contention, however, that the questions surrounding that question are just as important as the initial question itself. You can easily answer a question and never understand what it’s really about. As a church we can even repeat “the correct” answers to avoid taking the question Jesus posed seriously. Seriously attending to questions not only leads to a more passionate church, but one that has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tripp</surname>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j380.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
