<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS303.K64 1987</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">American poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literary form</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>American Poetry</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Rhetoric of Its Forms</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BLASING</surname>
               <given-names>MUTLU KONUK</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>1987</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300037937</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300237320</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1987</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xp3scx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>An important study that redefines poetic tradition in America. Arguing against the prevailing view that Emerson stands alone at the head of a single line of succession, Mutlu Konuk Blasing proposes four traditions, traceable through modernist and postmodernist poets. She chooses for analysis T. S. Eliot, and Sylvia Plath, in the line of descent from Poe; Wallace Stevens and Elizabeth Bishop, descending from Emerson; Ezra Pound and Frank O'Hara, from Whitman; and Hart Crane and John Ashbery, from Dickinson.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Poetic language, so thoroughly an embodiment of the past, is charged with the cultural memory inscribed in its conventions, forms, and traditions. Yet it begins to be heard in its American inflection only when it begins to register the loss of both the English literary tradition and the political and metaphysical assumptions underwriting the very idea of a legitimate historical authority.</p>
                     <p>Recent studies of American poetry have tended to approach this historical discontinuity with a metaphoric evasion, substituting Emerson for the lost “father” and instituting him as a literary and spiritual authority. Emerson has become a poetic father figure, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Edgar Allan Poe, the Poet to a T</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Edgar Allan Poe’s failure as a poet appears to be a matter of consensus among his English and American readers, who find it difficult to account for his exalted status in France. Yet he is best placed in a transatlantic context, for his failure—and his success—directly stem from his American displacement. Poe not only inaugurates a species of estheticism that modulates into Symbolism, but sounds an abiding inflection of American poetic language, which is heard in the modernism of T. S. Eliot and the expressionism of poets like John Berryman, Robert Lowell, and Sylvia Plath. The reverberations set</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>T. S. Eliot and the Archaeology of Poetry</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a lecture presented at the Library of Congress in 1948, T. S. Eliot acknowledges so early an acquaintance with Poe that he cannot be sure whether his own work has been influenced by him. He then distances himself from his predecessor by focusing on Poe’s relation to the French Symbolists Baudelaire, Mallarmé, and Valéry.¹ This detour through another country and another language is the standard reading of the Eliot-Poe connection: Poe’s insistence on the poem as a formal artifact, as well as his critical self-consciousness, influenced the French Symbolists, who in turn influenced Eliot. Clearly, Eliot shares the Symbolists’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Sylvia Plath’s Black Car of Lethe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The constellation of personal, historical, and esthetic forces that shape Sylvia Plath’s poetic and plot her life traces the same pattern that Poe’s ill-starred poet originally marked. With Plath, we once more begin “in a kingdom by the sea,” before all separations and departures. In such a prelapsarian mythic matrix, human breath, the breath of the sea, and the breath of poetry pulse in unison. Plath recalls this origin in “ocean<italic>1212-W</italic>”: “Breath, that is the first thing. Something is breathing. My own breath? The breath of my mother? No, something else, something larger, farther, more serious, more weary.” This</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Ralph Waldo Emerson:</title>
                     <subtitle>Essaying the Poet</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In being set up as the spiritual and literary father figure of American poetry, Emerson has become a tangle of contradictions. His work has been splintered into numerous “oppositions” and “dialectics,” and his insistence on the necessity of poetic forms has been largely ignored so that he can sustain his role as the father of all his unlikely brood. If obviously antithetical poets come out of Emerson, there must be a basic contradiction between his early or Orphic and late phases, between his essays and poems, between “Bacchus” and “Merlin,” and so on. By restoring the unity of Emerson’s career</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Wallace Stevens:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Exquisite Errors of Time</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Poetry and reality are one.” Wallace Stevens echoes Emerson, but immediately adds “or should be. This may be less thesis than hypothesis. Yet hypotheses relating to poetry, although they may appear to be very distant illuminations, could be the fires of fate, if rhetoric ever meant anything.”¹ If‥‥ And, luckily, it does not, the philosopher knows, and he proceeds to expose his rhetoric of a poetry coincident with reality. And, luckily, it does, the poet knows, and he sets out to prove the “truth” of his rhetoric. Stevens retains the Emersonian distinction between the philosopher and the poet: “If the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>The Re-Verses of Elizabeth Bishop</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Elizabeth Bishop extends Stevens’s revision of Emerson and his bipartite career by engaging in a process of “constant re-adjustment” between subject and object, mind and nature, rhetoric and meters. The seemingly contradictory commentary that her work sustains proves her success in “con-fusing” romantic and modernist oppositions: she has been read as an autobiographical poet with an impersonal touch, as a surrealist given to meticulous observations of natural facts, and as a formalist whose poems are open-ended accumulations of detail.¹ Her distinction is to have developed the kind of diction and formal flexibility that enable her to be at home on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>The Coinciding Leaves of Walt Whitman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Walt Whitman begins by promising to begin again:</p>
                     <p>Have you practis’d so long to learn to read?</p>
                     <p>Have you felt so proud to get at the meaning of poems?</p>
                     <p>Stop this day and night with me and you shall possess the origin of all poems,</p>
                     <p>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                     <p>You shall no longer take things at second or third hand, nor look through the eyes of the dead, nor feed on the spectres in books …¹</p>
                     <p>Appealing neither to Poe’s ravenous</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eight</label>
                     <title>Ezra Pound’s Hard Currency</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ezra Pound wrote in 1933, “Mr. Eliot and I are in agreement … in so far as we both believe that existing works form a complete order which is changed by the introduction of the ‘really new’ work.” But he offered a qualification that measures the radical “disagreement” between the two poets: “‘Existing monuments form an ideal order among themselves.’ It would be healthier to use a zoological term rather than the word monument. It is much easier to think of the<italic>Odyssey</italic>or<italic>Le Testament</italic>or Catallus’<italic>Epithalamium</italic>as something living than as a series of cenotaphs. After all,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Nine</label>
                     <title>Frank O’Hara:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Speech of Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Great art,” Frank O’Hara insists, “is seldom about art”—“except in baroque periods.” Its insights may be so compelling and so pervasive that they can be applied to art as well, but its true subject is the “structure” of nature. In de Kooning’s work, for example, “structures of classical severity” grant “insight into the structure of man’s identification with nature and the play of forces which it involves.” Similarly, “to think that late Mondrian is ‘painting about painting’ is a grievous error,” and “when Keats wrote, ‘Beauty is truth, truth beauty,’—it is a grievous error to think that he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Ten</label>
                     <title>Emily Dickinson’s Untitled Discourse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emily Dickinson’s work represents an ironic comment on nineteenth-century poetics, for she plays against each other the rhetorics that implicitly or explicitly authorize other major nineteenth-century poets. She claims only the privilege of her “provincial” “discemment”;¹ as she puts it in a poem about Thanksgiving Day,</p>
                     <p>Neither Patriarch nor Pussy</p>
                     <p>I dissect the Play</p>
                     <p>[P–814]</p>
                     <p>The lines “dissect” the laws of both nature and the powers that be, exposing the “Play” of “Patriarch” and “Pussy” alike through a writerly intrusion. The<italic>p</italic>- alliteration brings the two parties into proximity, touching each with a hint of the ludicrous, and puts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Eleven</label>
                     <title>Hart Crane:</title>
                     <subtitle>Inscribing the Sublime</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Taking on himself the oppositions that generate the discourse of literary history, Hart Crane assumes a sacrificial role in American poetry. Just as Emily Dickinson dissects Christian and transcendental poetics, Crane plays against each other his two major influences—an Eliotic formalism with its roots in French Symbolism, and a Whitmanic organicism.¹ Crane has been repeatedly judged a failure on the grounds that his Symbolist and Whitmanic visions are incompatible; less often, he has been defended on the same grounds. For example, Sherman Paul sees that the “‘confusion’ in Crane’s work is not inadvertent, as Tate and others believe, but</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Twelve</label>
                     <title>John Ashbery:</title>
                     <subtitle>Parodying the Paradox</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Steeped in the nostalgia of a collective past,”¹ John Ashbery’s poetry exhibits a greater range of stylistic influences than Dickinson’s or Crane’s. Yet his rhetorical strategies are Dickinsonian, for he also places himself “between” the “big,/ Vaguer stuff,” the grander schemas that constitute “the tradition” (<italic>HD</italic>, 34).² Or, as he writes elsewhere,</p>
                     <p>I no longer have any metaphysical reasons</p>
                     <p>For doing the things I do.</p>
                     <p>Night formulates, the rest is up to the scribes and the eunuchs.</p>
                     <p>[<italic>AWK</italic>, 91]</p>
                     <p>More discursive than Dickinson or Crane, Ashbery takes on the larger formulas of articulation, dismantling the “syntax” of their rhetoric. He</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3scx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
