<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125wf1</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">trav17942</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HX40 .T6365 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Communism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Melancholy (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Left-Wing Melancholia</book-title>
         <subtitle>Marxism, History, and Memory</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>TRAVERSO</surname>
               <given-names>ENZO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231543019</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231543018</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/trav17942"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The fall of the Berlin Wall marked the end of the Cold War but also the rise of a melancholic vision of history as a series of losses. For the political left, the cause lost was communism, and this trauma determined how leftists wrote the next chapter in their political struggle and how they have thought about their past since. Throughout the twentieth century, argues<italic>Left-Wing Melancholy</italic>, from classical Marxism to psychoanalysis to the advent of critical theory, a culture of defeat and its emotional overlay of melancholy have characterized the leftist understanding of the political in history and in theoretical critique.</p>
         <p>Drawing on a vast and diverse archive in theory, testimony, and image and on such thinkers as Karl Marx, Walter Benjamin, Theodor W. Adorno, and others, the intellectual historian Enzo Traverso explores the varying nature of left melancholy as it has manifested in a feeling of guilt for not sufficiently challenging authority, in a fear of surrendering in disarray and resignation, in mourning the human costs of the past, and in a sense of failure for not realizing utopian aspirations. Yet hidden within this melancholic tradition are the resources for a renewed challenge to prevailing regimes of historicity, a passion that has the power to reignite the dialectic of revolutionary thought.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="312"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>HAUNTING PASTS WITHOUT UTOPIAS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1967, reconstructing the long trajectory of the uses of Cicero’s sentence<italic>historia magistra vitae</italic>, Reinhart Koselleck stressed its exhaustion at the end of the eighteenth century, when the birth of the modern idea of progress replaced the old, cyclical vision of history. The past ceased to appear as an immense reservoir of experiences from which human beings could draw moral and political lessons. Since the French Revolution, the future had to be invented rather than extracted from bygone events. The human mind, Koselleck observed quoting Tocqueville, “wandered in obscurity” and the lessons of history became mysterious or useless.¹ The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THE CULTURE OF DEFEAT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of socialism is a constellation of defeats that nourished it for almost two centuries. Instead of destroying its ideas and aspirations, these traumatic, tragic, often bloody defeats consolidated and legitimated them. Falling after a well-fought struggle gives dignity to the vanquished and can become a source of pride. Exiled and banished revolutionaries often knew misery and privations, certainly the sufferings of loss, but rarely isolation among the people surrounding them. They always occupied a place of honor within the left and socialist movements, from Heine, Marx, and Herzen in nineteenth-century Paris to the anti fascist émigrés in twentieth-century</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>MARXISM AND MEMORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At first sight, Marxism and memory appear as two foreign continents. Since Marx, many scholars belonging to his intellectual tradition have elaborated philosophies of history or investigated historical temporalities—E. P. Thompson’s studies on time and work discipline in early industrial capitalism are the most known—but have never conceptualized collective remembrance. Opened one century ago by Henri Bergson and Maurice Halbwachs, the scholarly debate on memory deeply shaped sociology, historiography, and philosophy without receiving any significant Marxist contribution. The rare assessments made by Marxist scholars on this topic simply reproduce a classical, positivistic dichotomy between history and memory: memory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>MELANCHOLY IMAGES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The end of real socialism did not produce any significant film on the end of the communist hope. It inspired a wave of aesthetic creations that described the collapse of a world, ranging from tragedy to comedy, from the moral dilemmas and everyday lies to which a totalitarian power submitted individuals and human relations (Florian Henckel von Donnersmarck:<italic>The Life of Others</italic>, 2006) to the ironic nostalgia for a disappeared human environment (Wolfgand Becker:<italic>Good Bye Lenin</italic>, 2003). In Russia, Alexander Sokurov and Aleksei German depicted metaphorically the breakdown of the Soviet regime through the death agonies of Lenin and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>BOHEMIA:</title>
                     <subtitle>BETWEEN MELANCHOLY AND REVOLUTION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Popularized by a novel by Henri Murger in 1846,¹ then consecrated by Puccini in his famous opera, the idea of Bohemia, in its current use, implies a lifestyle and a particular attitude toward aesthetics. Rejection of bourgeois conventions, lack (or voluntary renunciation) of a fixed abode and regular work, frequent visits to cafés, cabarets, and popular taverns, a taste for nocturnal life, ostentatious sexual freedom, a keen penchant for alcohol and drugs, the fair communal share of meager available resources, and even, at times, a certain “sectarianism” colored by the use of secret codes shared only by a select brotherhood</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>MARXISM AND THE WEST</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like all classics, Marx both “transcends” his own time and remains a thinker of the nineteenth century. With an incredibly imaginative strength, he was able to grasp tendencies that, still embryonic in his epoch, developed spectacularly during the following century. This astonishing modernity has led many scholars to interpret his works in naïvely anachronistic terms, as if they had been written in our age. Marx contributed to the forging of our lexicon, but many concepts through which we today apprehend the nineteenth century—for instance, imperialism—simply did not exist during his lifetime, or did not have the same meaning</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>ADORNO AND BENJAMIN:</title>
                     <subtitle>LETTERS AT MIDNIGHT IN THE CENTURY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Deeply shaped by the presentiment of an impending catastrophe, the dialogue between Adorno and Benjamin depicts a melancholy constellation. In a previous chapter, we have already observed the ambivalent assessments of Benjamin on melancholy, as they appear in both his book on the German tragic drama and his strongly critical review of Erich Kästner’s novels. Now, it is important to emphasize the melancholic character of Benjamin himself. According to many witnesses, melancholy was his deepest disposition; it also explains his fascination with<italic>Angelus Novus</italic>, the Paul Klee painting that he acquired in Munich at the beginning of the 1920s, which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>SYNCHRONIC TIMES:</title>
                     <subtitle>WALTER BENJAMIN AND DANIEL BENSAÏD</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Portbou is the Catalan small town where Benjamin committed suicide in September 1940, when he tried to escape from France (figure 7.1). He feared being arrested by the Vichy police and delivered to the Gestapo, as already happened with many other German-Jewish émigrés. In Marseille, he had obtained an American visa thanks to his friends from the Frankfurt School exiled in New York, and he had tried to cross the Spanish border to get to Lisbon, where he might have embarked for the United States. After a perilous journey through the mountain paths, the Guardia Civil had stopped him at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">trav17942.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
