<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbcw0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>EccentriCities: Writing in the margins of Modernism</book-title>
         <subtitle>St. Petersburg to Rio de Janeiro</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Allen</surname>
               <given-names>Sharon Lubkemann</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780719087707</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781526102744</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Manchester; New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Sharon Lubkemann Allen</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18mbdwg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>An innovative, interdisciplinary, incisive scholarly study remapping and redefining domains and dynamics of modernism, EccentriCities: Writing in the margins of modernism critically considers how geo-historically distant and disparate urban sites, concentrating Russian and Luso-Brazilian cultural dialogue and definition, give rise to peculiarly parallel anachronistic and alternative fictional forms. While comparatively reframing these literary traditions through an extensive survey of Russian and Brazilian literature, cartography, urban design and development, foregrounding innovative close readings of works by Gogol, Dostoevsky, Bely, Almeida, Machado de Assis, Lima Barreto, Mário de Andrade, the book also redefines new constellations (eccentric, concentric, ex-centric) for understanding geo-cultural and generic dimensions of modernist and post-modern literature and theory.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="384"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xviii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every work of genius slants the rational plane, or so claim twentieth-century writers as disparate in style and distant in setting as Mário de Andrade and Vladimir Nabokov, re-casting creative consciousness in their respectively ‘hallucinated’ cities of São Paulo and St. Petersburg.¹ While these writers eccentrically reconfigure and relocate creative consciousness in citytexts marked by peculiarly modern tempos and marginocentric topographies, they also recuperate an ancient association between art, alienation and urbanity, central to the Western canon. In work that blurs boundaries between theoretical, critical and creative literature, they align insight and innovation with a deep and diverse literary tradition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Urban contexts, urbane consciousness and the eccentric slant of modernisms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While modernism ranges far beyond the bounds of the city, it emerges from crises concentrated in urban centres and urbane consciousness. Modernist writers converge in St. Petersburg and Rio de Janeiro, Moscow and São Paulo, as in Paris, London, Lisbon, Prague, New York and other cities whose contours filter into their fictions. These cities concentrate publication venues, a reading public and the political and critical establishments that redefine modern literary production. Within a broad Western tradition, works such as Bely’s<italic>Петербург</italic>(<italic>Petersburg</italic>), Proust’s<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>(<italic>In Search of Time Past</italic>), Pessoa’s<italic>O Livro do desassossego</italic>(<italic>The</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Eccentric cities and citytexts:</title>
                     <subtitle>transpositions, translations and transformations of authority and authorship</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Lines linking eccentric cities bend through space and time – stretching between St. Petersburg and Rio de Janeiro by curving through and around a European centre and a Eurocentric history. Until recently, these cities were connected only occasionally by actual contact, more consistently by concentric ripples of modern history. They were linked directly by Portuguese navigators, sailors, soldiers and merchants who headed southeast and southwest to establish Portugal’s portals into Old and New Worlds and to secure its hold on empire, but also sailed northeast with goods and skills that helped build Peter the Great’s naval power and port city, Russia’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Gogol’s open prospects:</title>
                     <subtitle>digressive copy clerks</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If Pushkin’s poema constitutes the cornerstone of the Petersburg text, Gogol’s Petersburg tales fill out the foundation. Yet the fundamental position of both writers’ works is paradoxical, insofar as it does not reflect origin or originality in their usual sense. Rather, it is contingent on their explicit reflection on their status as deviant, deconstructive copies of already-copied Petersburg texts. They represent a fundamental realignment and reification of the citytext, as significant in the domain of Russian literary and cultural history as Catherine’s redrawing of Peter’s blueprint,² resulting in a more dispersed, decentred, eclectic cityscape as well as the solidification of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Dostoevsky’s and Machado de Assis’s unending undergrounds:</title>
                     <subtitle>dead men writing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the fictions of Fedor Mikhailovich Dostoevsky (1821–1881) and Joaquim Maria Machado de Assis (1839–1908) we frequently follow eccentrics who approach others with nervous smiles and satirical smirks. The more ridiculous among them give rise to scandal, provoking laughter within and beyond the bounds of the text. But scandalous laughter resounds even in those fictions whose central eccentric figures seem more self-aware, subtle, successful, more serious social critics and more self-critical. Dostoevsky and Machado de Assis’s streets, corners, side rooms and even elegant sitting rooms are crossed by minor grotesques, filing into their fictions not only from Petersburg</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Hallucinated cities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In one peculiarly odd digression in Gogol’s ‘Overcoat’, Petersburg is blurred through the narrator’s failing memory. In an aside to the reader after having lost track of his hero along some side street, the narrator explains,</p>
                     <p>Где именно жил пригласивший чиновник, к сожалению, не можем сказать: память начинает нам сильно изменять, и всё, что ни есть в Петербурге, все улицы и домы слились и смешались так в голове, что весьма трудно достать оттуда что-нибудь в порядочном виде.¹</p>
                     <p>(Where exactly the clerk who had invited [Akaky Akakievich] lived, unfortunately, we cannot say: our memory is beginning to slip seriously, and all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Postscript:</title>
                     <subtitle>theory of the novel and the eccentric novel’s early play with theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>386</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Theorists such as Felman borrow the spatialized discourse of eccentricity to describe ex-centric developments in recent French fiction, as do Deleuze and Guattari in describing a modern shift from a ‘root-book’ model to a fragmented ‘radicle-system or fascicular’ model.¹ But Russian and Brazilian nineteenth-century literature and early twentieth-century cultural theory anticipate and complicate Deleuze and Guattari’s ideas of modernist fascicular (hybrid, influenced) and postmodern rhizomatic (independent) development. The rhizome (as cultivated and uncultivated text, culture), with its anti-memoried dynamics and mobile middle, ‘pertains to a map that must be produced, constructed, a map that is always detachable, connectable, reversible, modifiable,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>394</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18mbdwg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
