<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR590.M25</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">English poetry</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Romanticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Poetry</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Romanticism and the Forms of Ruin: Wordsworth, Coleridge, the Modalities of Fragmentation</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McFarland</surname>
               <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400855964</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400855969</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1981</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7ztq28"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Despite their hopeful aspirations to wholeness in life and spirit, Thomas McFarland contends, the Romantics were ruins amidst ruins," fragments of human existence in a disintegrating world. Focusing on Wordsworth and Coleridge, Professor McFarland shows how this was true not only for each of these Romantics in particular but also for Romanticism in general.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1981.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="472"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McFarland</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Key to Brief Titles Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>Fragmented Modalities and the Criteria of Romanticism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The phenomenology of the fragment is the phenomenology of human awareness. I look out my study window as I write this sentence and see a fragment made up of fragments: a mass of stone and concrete that is part of New York City: buildings in such a variety of size, shape, and architecture, mostly bad, juxtaposed in such randomness, and showing such heterogeneous effects of time, as to constitute a visual junk heap. I happen to take a book from my shelves, Lucien Goldmann’s<italic>Le Dieu caché</italic>, and see the argument that Pascal’s<italic>Pensées,</italic>a masterpiece even though fragmentary and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>The Symbiosis of Coleridge and Wordsworth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The intellectual relationship of Coleridge and Wordsworth has scarcely any cultural counterpart. It is almost impossible to bring to mind any other two figures, so important each in his own right, but also so dependent the one upon the other during his richest intellectual years. The interchange between Goethe and Schiller occurred after each had established his own reputation and his own mode. That between Socrates and Plato was the relationship of master to pupil, while that between Plato and Aristotle, likewise a master-pupil situation, involved fundamental disagreements. The relationship of Beaumont and Fletcher was perhaps as close as that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Coleridge’s Anxiety</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Much of Coleridge’s existence was a death in life. His deep commitment to the Christian religion was sustained, on the one hand, by the need to feel that there must be something better than the torment in which he so mysteriously found himself and, on the other, by the sense of his inability to cope with his manifold failings:</p>
                     <p>I profess a deep conviction [he wrote] that Man was and is a<italic>fallen</italic>Creature, not by accidents of bodily constitution, or any other cause, which<italic>human</italic>Wisdom in a course of ages might be supposed capable of removing; but diseased</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Significant Group:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wordsworth’s Fears in Solitude</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1818 Keats, in distinguishing the sort of “poetical Character” to which he belonged, contrasted it to “the wordsworthian or egotistical sublime; which is a thing per se and stands alone.”¹ The statement seems to define in an important way a certain irreducible attitude in Wordsworth's life and art. Benjamin Haydon, for instance, said that though Wordsworth was a “great Being,” he could use his intense feelings only “as referring to himself.”² Coleridge, indeed, observed as early as 1799 that “Wordsworth appears to me to have hurtfully segregated &amp; isolated his Being/Doubtless, his delights are more deep and sublime;/but he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Problems of Style in the Poetry of Wordsworth and Coleridge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>216</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we see cultural figures lacquered, dusted, shined, and resting in those handsome display cases called the canon, little is apparent to us but achievement and wholeness. But when we view the process of their life and thought as those figures themselves did, with the sheets of blank paper before them, and with their prospects on the future everywhere bardered and problematic.¹ It is from this second perspective, when</p>
                     <p>nacled with indecision, doubt, and anxiety, then all becomes hinwe see their efforts as tentative and their achievement as only a partial fulfillment of what they hoped, that their humanity comes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>A Complex Dialogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Coleridge’s Doctrine of Polarity and Its European Contexts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In all subjects of deep and lasting Interest,“wrote Coleridge in 1820,”you will detect a struggle between two opposites, two polar Forces, both of which are alike necessary to our human Well-being, &amp; necessary each to the continued existence of the other.”¹ What he here enunciated was an ineradicable characteristic and compelling urgency of his thought. As a commentator has emphasized:</p>
                     <p>Coleridge’s conception of genre is based upon the method of the reconciliation of opposites, which embodies the characteristic method of his thought. . . . The reconciliation of opposites, indeed, is the Archimedes lever of Coleridge’s criticism. His procedure and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>The Psychic Economy and Cultural Meaning of Coleridge’s Magnum Opus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>342</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the E. J. Pratt Library of Victoria University in Toronto there are three clasped vellum manuscript volumes. They, along with a manuscript chapter in a commonplace book in the Huntington Library, and some data in the Berg Collection of the New York Public Library, are what remains of one of the most legendary works ever conceived: the<italic>magnum opus</italic>of Samuel Taylor Coleridge—or as he sometimes called it, “my Great Work.” I say “legendary” advisedly, for by that adjective I mean to focus three aspects of the enterprise: first of all, its fame; secondly, its basis in fact;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SECOND LANDING PLACE.</title>
                     <subtitle>The Place Beyond the Heavens: True Being, Transcendence, and the Symbolic Indication of Wholeness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>382</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the strivings of Coleridge and Wordsworth, as viewed from the shifting perspectives of the pre ceding chapters, all participate in that<italic>ständige Unganzheit</italic>—that continuing incompleteness—seen by Heidegger as an unavoidable limitation of life itself, we might expect the form and purpose of those strivings to reveal themselves, under inspection, as an attempt to overcome or at least to compensate for such fragmentation. We might expect to find that the ceaseless effort discharged into philosophical formulation, interchangeably with the continuously pulsating transformations of spirit into poetic statement, was somehow prompted by the diasparactive condition of our existence.</p>
                     <p>We</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>419</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztq28.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
