<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8bdj</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">ML3830 .C69 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Emotions and cognition</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Emotions in music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy and aesthetics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Music and Embodied Cognition</book-title>
         <subtitle>Listening, Moving, Feeling, and Thinking</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>COX</surname>
               <given-names>ARNIE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>06</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253021601</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253021670</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253021677</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Arnie Cox</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt200610s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Taking a cognitive approach to musical meaning, Arnie Cox explores embodied experiences of hearing music as those that move us both consciously and unconsciously. In this pioneering study that draws on neuroscience and music theory, phenomenology and cognitive science, Cox advances his theory of the "mimetic hypothesis," the notion that a large part of our experience and understanding of music involves an embodied imitation in the listener of bodily motions and exertions that are involved in producing music. Through an often unconscious imitation of action and sound, we feel the music as it moves and grows. With applications to tonal and post-tonal Western classical music, to Western vernacular music, and to non-Western music, Cox's work stands to expand the range of phenomena that can be explained by the role of sensory, motor, and affective aspects of human experience and cognition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like many music students, I spent a good deal of my undergraduate and graduate coursework in music theory focusing on musical structure and making more or less factual observations about how the various elements of music fit together in particular works and styles. Since I enjoyed this kind of study, for my doctoral thesis I planned to take the same approach in analyzing the music of Debussy. But then one day the stove in my apartment stopped working, the repairman came over, and we started chatting. He asked if I was a student up at the college, and I said</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Mimetic Comprehension</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If music cognition is embodied in a musically meaningful way, in the flesh of experience, then we ought to be able to specify just how this occurs. One way begins in imitation of musical sounds and of the physical exertions that produce them. This bodily comprehension of sounds and of sound-producing actions is one of the bases of embodied cognition of music, and it is the central basis that we will be exploring in the following chapters.</p>
                     <p>The issue of musical embodiment may be relatively straightforward in the case of performers, in the sense that performing, planning, and otherwise thinking</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Mimetic Comprehension of Music</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The twenty principles of the mimetic hypothesis that I describe in this chapter are meant to specify the nature of mimetic comprehension of music.¹ The role of mimetic comprehension in music conceptualization (chaps. 4–6) and in the creation of musical affect (chaps. 8 and 9) reflects the details and variables considered here. Although the extent of variability means that mimetic processes do not provide a uniform basis for conceptualization and affective responses, this variability appears to be integral to the nature of musical experience, conceptualization, and meaning.</p>
                     <p>1. Sounds are produced by physical events; sounds indicate the physicality of their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Metaphor and Related Means of Reasoning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout each day we implicitly and explicitly ask<italic>What is that?</italic>and the most direct way in which we answer this question is via categorization, as in naming or recognizing things according animal species, kinds of vegetables, types of musical instruments, and so on. This basic question often takes the richer form of<italic>How shall we understand this?</italic>which we sometimes answer via metaphor—that is, by conceptualizing something from one category in terms of another category to which it normally does not belong. Literary examples, such as Shakespeare’s prating stones (Macbeth) and Maya Angelou’s “I’m a black ocean, leaping</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Pitch Height</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Pitch height” refers to the apparent height of musical pitches: for the most part, height is not a perceptible property of sounds, but the sense that melodies ascend and descend, and that some notes are higher or lower than others, is both strongly motivated and logical. It is the sense and logic of fictional and illusory height that is at issue in this chapter.¹</p>
                     <p>We can begin this exploration by asking what is high about high notes. Various answers may come to mind, perhaps having to do with frequencies, staff notation, and so forth, all of which are part of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Temporal Motion and Musical Motion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I focus on the “horizontal dimension” of musical motion and space. Unlike the concept of<italic>pitch height</italic>, there is no component of the concept of<italic>musical motion</italic>, as defined below, that directly involves literal motion. Or, as Viktor Zuckerkandl (1956) and Judy Lochhead (1989–90) have argued, in most cases musical motion is entirely imaginary. Even more than with pitch height, musical motion is thus not perceptible: what we hear and feel is something other than motion, which we then conceptualize metaphorically as motion. The proposition that we do not hear musical motion may conflict strongly with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Perspectives on Musical Motion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The other day I reached a milestone—several of them in fact. Near my home is a former railroad line that has been converted to a bike trail, and along this path are milestones: mile markers, made of stone, indicating the distance to the next large city. When used metaphorically to conceptualize significant events in one’s life,<italic>milestone</italic>is an expression of the conceptual metaphor states are locations and its corollaries, as are<italic>curriculum vita</italic>(life course), the “verge” of a scientific “break-through,” the concept of “eccentricity,” and the difficulty of “bringing oneself to believe,” for example, that temporal and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Music and the External Senses</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Beyond the spatial metaphors examined in chapters 4–6 are those that draw upon the various senses to conceptualize properties of pitch, timbre, and strength, such as color (chromaticism; timbre as color), clarity, brightness/darkness, softness (piano), strength (forte), warmth, sharpness, sweetness (dolce), and so forth. But as useful as such particular concepts may be, and as interesting as the reasoning processes that produce them may be, in this chapter I focus on the broader topic of how the external senses shape our relationship with the world, including our relationship with music.</p>
                     <p>The five external senses of smell, taste, touch, vision,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Musical Affect</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>176</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The analyses in chapters 4–7 help to show how our musical concepts are conceptualizations of experiences that are seldom if ever simply a matter of what is heard. Musical experience in general also includes what we see, do, and feel, whether we are actually performing or whether we are listening to, recalling, or otherwise thinking about music. In what we have considered so far, the<italic>feeling</italic>component includes the following: the feelings of overt and covert exertions (actual and imagined actions), in both mimetic and nonmimetic forms; the feelings of the anticipation-presence-memory dynamic; the feelings of exerting (actually and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Applications</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I offer three demonstrations of how the ideas in the preceding chapters, particularly chapter 8, might be applied. For this purpose I have chosen the opening of the fourth of Webern’s<italic>Five Movements for String Quartet</italic>(1909) to represent posttonal music performed directly by human exertions, Stockhausen’s electronic work<italic>Studie II</italic>(1954) to represent postcorporeal music, and the topic of dissonance treatment in Western tonal music. I have chosen the Webern and the Stockhausen because the role of affect might seem less obviously relevant here than in some other kinds of music, and because the approach described</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Review and Implications</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have described what I take to be some fundamental processes in musical experience and conceptualization. In addition to specific processes, this includes an essential variability in how these play out in different musical practices, among different individuals, and even for a given individual at different points in one’s life. Specialists might rightly note the many sources I have excluded and the avenues I have only pointed toward or overlooked, but I have attempted to offer a coherent story of the relationship among metaphor, embodiment, and affect—or among concept, flesh, and feeling. I want to close by reviewing a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix I.</title>
                     <subtitle>Mimetic Subvocalization and Absolute Pitch</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix II.</title>
                     <subtitle>Levels of Abstraction among Metaphors</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt200610s.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>287</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
