<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR9080.M29 2009</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Commonwealth literature (English)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Postcolonialism</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Commonwealth countries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Postcolonialism in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Forgiveness in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Reconciliation in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Malouf, David, 1934</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Remembering Babylon</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ondaatje, Michael, 1943</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Anil’s ghost</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kogawa, Joy. Obasan</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kogawa, Joy. Itsuka</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Coetzee, J. M., 1940</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Disgrace</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Commonwealth countries</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Commonwealth countries</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Imagining Justice</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Politics of Postcolonial Forgiveness and Reconciliation</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McGONEGAL</surname>
               <given-names>JULIE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773534582</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773576322</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt81237"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Drawing on critical and theoretical material by thinkers as diverse as Jacques Derrida, Frantz Fanon, Mahatma Ghandi, and Julia Kristeva, Julie McGonegal supplements indigenous models and approaches with those produced within Euro American discourse. In the process, she develops an understanding of forgiveness and reconciliation based on the interventive power of literature. Through insightful readings of four novels, McGonegal demonstrates the ways in which literature can create the conditions that make processes of postcolonial reconciliation possible.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                     <subtitle>Writing Wrongs:Postcolonial Literature and the (Im)possibility of Forgiveness and Reconciliation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Discourses of forgiveness and reconciliation have emerged in the past decade as among the most powerful scripts for interracial negotiations in states struggling with the legacies of colonialism. Even more than the kind of political discourse I sampled in the preface, literary texts meditate on the limits and possibilities of forgiveness and reconciliation. I am concerned here with engaging the competing perspectives on forgiveness and reconciliation that literature provides, and with exploring its potential for opening up new perspectives and new worlds, for imagining alternatives, in other words, to normative conceptualizations of justice. I hope to profoundly rethink the way</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Horizons of Justice:</title>
                     <subtitle>Notes toward a Theory of Postcolonial Forgiveness and Reconciliation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Academic postcolonialism has generally neglected to address the politics of reconciliation, despite the recent emergence of reconciliation political programs and movements in a wide range of national and international contexts. However, one obligation of postcolonial work is to “fully recognize” what Gyan Prakash refers to as “another history of agency and knowledge alive in the dead weight of the colonial past.”¹ This task of recognition necessitates understanding acts of anti-colonial dissent not only as theorizable but as fully productive, conceptually constructive theoretical “events” in their own right. Prakash argues that we might begin to trace the emergence of postcolonial theory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Unsettling the Settler Postcolony:</title>
                     <subtitle>Uncanny Preoccupations in David Malouf’s Remembering Babylon</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although set in a nineteenth-century settlement of Scottish immigrants, David Malouf’s<italic>Remembering Babylon</italic>is profoundly relevant to postcolonial considerations of the contemporary Australian condition. Published in 1993, one year after the watershed trial<italic>Mabo vs. Queensland</italic>overturned the common law precedent that Australia was<italic>terra nullius</italic>, and in the same year that the Australian government devised an official policy of reconciliation, the novel provides a key point of departure for examining a politics of postcolonial reconciliation. In foregrounding the themes of settler envy, settler estrangement, and settler fantasies of authentic belonging – themes that have always lain beneath the Australian national</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Vigils amid Violence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mourning the Dead and the Disappeared in Michael Ondaatje’s Anil’s Ghost</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In their articulation of the hope that forgiveness and reconciliation are possible in the midst of overwhelming violence, the reflections above by Michael Ondaatje concerning the reception of<italic>Anil’s Ghost</italic>may at first seem radically at odds with the vision of the work. For in capturing the despondency surrounding a war to which there seems no foreseeable end, Ondaatje’s novel exposes the intractableness of a conflict that arguably rules out the possibility of a different, more peaceful future.</p>
                     <p>At the centre of Ondaatje’s text is Anil Tissera’s return as a forensic anthropologist to a Sri Lanka ravaged by civil war,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Future of Racial Memory:</title>
                     <subtitle>Redressing the Past in Kogawa’s Obasan and Itsuka</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>These statements by Paul Ricoeur, a French philosopher, and Joy Kogawa, a Canadian writer of fiction, might profoundly discomfit a postmodern academic audience familiar with the problems of humanism. Both thinkers express faith in the possibility of forgiveness at a time in history when such faith might seem naïvely optimistic and at worst dangerously self-deceptive. After all, the conceptual apparatus of forgiveness, to the extent that it involves recollection of and reflection on the past, is patently imbricated with notions of truth and memory; yet a virtual axiom of contemporary thought is that the latter are partial, fragmentary, and intensely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Agonistics of Absolution in a Post-Apartheid Era:</title>
                     <subtitle>Responsibility and the Right of Grace in Coetzee’s Disgrace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the surface the first novel written by J.M. Coetzee in the aftermath of apartheid is remote from and possibly even irrelevant to the enterprise of national reconciliation that South Africa has undertaken as part of its negotiated transition to democratic governance. But although<italic>Disgrace</italic>refuses to foreground its complex and at times bafflingly oblique relation to its own historicity, leaving readers with the task of reading the text into its context, its contemplation of the possibility of forgiveness constitutes a complex engagement with the political realities of the post-apartheid era. Indeed,<italic>Disgrace</italic>is haunted, and perhaps motivated, by the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A few years after I completed an earlier version of this book in the form of a doctoral dissertation, I began to collect some of my thoughts about the relationship between truth and justice. This complex relationship is germane to my project – and has in fact formed its central ideas – but not in ways that I was able to fully articulate or acknowledge at the time of its beginning. A substantial amount of scholarship on the politics of reconciliation deals explicitly and quite polemically with the interplay between truth and transitive justice, and yet somehow I did not anticipate the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This project originally unfolded in the context of the U.S.-led War on Iraq, and while that war has been peripheral to the explicit content of my study, it has shaped its driving ideas in immeasurable ways. Most obviously, it has confirmed my sense that the abandonment of the language of reconciliation for a discourse of enemy warfare and terrorism is a potentially fatal political decision. In making this move, the Bush administration orchestrated, wittingly or not, some of the most sordid acts of violence, some of the most tragic signs of the perverseness of a politics of revenge and retribution.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt81237.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
