<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7p40k</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Middle English Romance and the Craft of Memory</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McKINSTRY</surname>
               <given-names>JAMIE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781843844174</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782045861</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Woodbridge, Suffolk, UK; Rochester, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jamie McKinstry</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt17mvhj3"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In Middle English romances many memories are created, stored, forgotten, and rediscovered by both the characters and audience; such memory work is not, however, either simple or obvious. This study examines the ways in which recollection is achieved and sustained through physical, cognitive, and interpretative challenges. It uses examples such as Sir Gawain and the Green Knight, Sir Orfeo, and Emaré, alongside romances by Chaucer and Malory, to investigate the genre's reliance on individual and collective memorial processes. The author argues that a tale's objects, places, dreams, discoveries, disguises, prophecies, and dramatic ironies influence that romance's essential memory work, which relies as much on creativity as it does accuracy. He also explores the imaginative crafts of memory that are employed by romances themselves. Dr Jamie McKinstry teaches in the Department of English Studies at Durham University, where he is a member of the Institute of Medieval and Early Modern Studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="289"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memories of Romance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Why, indeed, is memory important in medieval romances? This question needs clarification given the many associations and definitions of such a complex cognitive faculty as memory, and the equally wide-ranging scope of this particular literary genre. We should begin by considering what exactly we mean by “memory,” which can be both individual, relating to the thought processes of a single remembering subject, and also collective. To take examples from the romance genre itself, a single knight might be trying desperately to maintain the memory of his love whilst away from home for many years. This is his individual memorial challenge.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Medieval Memories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sight, Thought, and Journey</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We all use our memories everyday and although recent research in neuroscience and its related fields can be highly complex and technical, the subject of these investigations – memory itself – is essential to all human behaviour or existence and the way we interact with other people and the world. We use, and are exposed to, memory all the time and so, in fact, are already well versed in its abilities and limitations whether we recognise our inherent human understanding of the faculty or not. The human awareness of and aptitude for memory forms the basis for influential studies in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Topography, Redaction, and Inheritance:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Initial Steps of Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter it became clear that the remembering subject must be willing to perform memory work in order for the process of recollection to be successful. This was examined in terms of voluntary intellection and, in a medieval romance, such a journey into memory must begin in order for the current romance to exist at all. As was discussed in the Introduction, romances are glittering examples of a golden age of the past and the sense of “looking back” is encoded in the narratives’ use of past places and literary analogues. We are always still very much in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Past Rituals and Present “Forests”:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Craft of Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter it was argued that romances frequently contain memories of other tales, even other versions of the same narrative, which are there for the audience to identify and then apply to the current tale. The process demands careful cognitive effort and also a great deal of creative freedom which is, as was explored in the discussion of classical and medieval theories, at the very centre of medieval<italic>memoria</italic>. It is no surprise therefore that romances also rely upon and encourage the memorial skills of characters and audiences throughout a romance narrative as situations are stored in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Trusting Memory in Romance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter it became clear that the characters and audience are expected to use their memories in imaginative ways in order to establish connections between past and present. The mental challenge was intensified by the drama of present “forests,” or the adverse effects that a perpetually present situation could have on the character’s reputation, loved one, and life. Likewise, the audience is placed under a similar pressure – they must protect the character they have been following and also, by remembering details of the plot, maintain the thematic and moral unity of that particular romance such as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Failed Memories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Forgetting, Lying, Obstructing</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter memory and recollection were instrumental in directing a character’s experience and in shaping the greater theme or moral developed during the course of a tale. Yet, given the creative freedom invited during the process of recollection, memory was never restrictive or overly controlling in the narrative. Rather, characters and the audience retained the free will inherent in voluntary intellection (as was discussed in Chapter 2) which allowed them to choose and recollect in their own way and, to a certain extent, at their own pace. Materials were presented which<italic>could</italic>be used during the process of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Memory of Change:</title>
                     <subtitle>“he that had hadde”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout this study two rules have emerged regarding the process of recollection: firstly, that the past is crucial in shaping responses to a present situation and, secondly, in order for any recollection to be successful,<italic>that</italic>past must be crafted to fit with a current set of circumstances. Certain characters in the previous chapter deliberately denied any such opportunities by imposing boundaries between the present and “true” past or restricting the creative opportunities that were available to form a reconnection with the past. However, when we talk of adapting the present in line with the past, the silent understanding is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Unforgettable or (Un)fortunate Romance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, during the discussion of the three-day tournament in<italic>Ipomadon</italic>, the audience gradually came to expect what would occur each day: the departure of the hunter, Ipomadon changing into a coloured armour, his success in battle, the transformation back into a hunter, his return to the Queen of Sicily, a report of that day’s contest, and finally, the presentation of a hunting trophy. Given such certainty, the audience almost became a narrator, writing (or expecting) events even before they had occurred, guided by memories of the previous day. Given such privileged foreknowledge, situations gained new interpretations such</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lessons in Romance Remembering</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study has asserted that memory (and its associated cognitive and interpretative processes) is essential to a romance’s success as morally satisfying, entertaining, and challenging literature. Moreover, the role of memory can change according to the aesthetics and aims of a particular tale. Consequently, the faculty occupies a prominent role across the romance genre in narratives that are, variously, courtly and complex, metrical and local, or Arthurian and legendary. Memory, as had become abundantly clear, serves an essential, practical function in<italic>episodic</italic>narratives: the faculty allows a character to reaffirm and develop their identity whilst simultaneously maintaining the unity of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mvhj3.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
