<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4v0cc</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN6710.K836 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Comic books, strips, etc.</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Graphic novels</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Narration (Rhetoric)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Contemporary Comics Storytelling</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KUKKONEN</surname>
               <given-names>KARIN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780803246379</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780803248502</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0803248504</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>UNP - Nebraska</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lincoln; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Board of Regents of the University of Nebraska</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ddr8c6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What if fairy-tale characters lived in New York City? What if a superhero knew he was a fictional character? What if you could dispense your own justice with one hundred untraceable bullets? These are the questions asked and answered in the course of the challenging storytelling in<italic>Fables</italic>,<italic>Tom Strong</italic>, and<italic>100 Bullets</italic>, the three twenty-first-century comics series that Karin Kukkonen considers in depth in her exploration of how and why the storytelling in comics is more than merely entertaining.</p>
         <p>Applying a cognitive approach to reading comics in all their narrative richness and intricacy,<italic>Contemporary Comics Storytelling</italic>opens an intriguing perspective on how these works engage the legacy of postmodernism-its subversion, self-reflexivity, and moral contingency. Its three case studies trace how contemporary comics tie into deep traditions of visual and verbal storytelling, how they reevaluate their own status as fiction, and how the fictional minds of their characters generate complex ethical thought experiments. At a time when the medium is taken more and more seriously as intricate and compelling literary art, this book lays the groundwork for an analysis of the ways in which comics challenge and engage readers' minds. It brings together comics studies with narratology and literary criticism and, in so doing, provides a new set of tools for evaluating the graphic novel as an emergent literary form.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many reasons for the rise of comics to a medium of cultural prominence have been put forward in recent years. Paul Douglas Lopes in<italic>Demanding Respect: The Evolution of the American Comic Book</italic>(2009) emphasizes one: “While comic books originally were based on short stories in serial format, now comic books present long-arced narratives with complex storylines. Now the fastest growing market for comic books, graphic novels, presents this art in book-length format, again allowing for complex and compelling storytelling” (2009, xvi). Lopes then goes on to discuss how sophisticated storytelling in comics moves beyond genre boundaries and attracts the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>How to Analyze Comics Cognitively</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first Sunday installment of Milton Caniff’s<italic>Steve Canyon</italic>series (1947–88) presents readers with a formidable density of narrative information: from patterns of black and white on the page, readers can construct an entire story. They identify characters, understand what motivates them and how they relate to each other, and connect their actions and words into a narrative. How does this process work? And how can we harness insights into the cognitive processes involved when reading comics for analyzing them? Milton Caniff, one of the comics authors who set the standards for storytelling in the medium in the 1930s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Textual Traditions in Comics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fables, Genre, and Intertextuality</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A man leaves a note for the woman he has just spent the night with. He asks her to pick up his suits from the dry cleaners and to do his laundry. He mentions that he has helped himself to her spare apartment keys and some money from her purse. “I didn’t want to wake you to ask,” he writes, “and knew you wouldn’t mind” (<italic>Fables</italic>1:30). This man, who treats women like domestic servants and suppliers of money, and disenfranchises them, is none other than Prince Charming, the coveted spouse and the character supplying the happy ending for many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Fictionality in Comics:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tom Strong, Storyworlds, and the Imagination</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On one of his missions in<italic>Tom Strong’s Terrific Tales</italic>(2004), the superhero Tom Strong enters an arctic cave and chances upon a secret Nazi science project which involves the theory that the earth is hollow as well as flying saucers. As it turns out, however, the fantastic subterranean world is not real. Tom Strong and his companions only found what they expected to find and are eventually entrapped by an alien who feeds on human emotions. When Strong defeats the alien, the subterranean world disappears and the arctic plain returns to its original state. This story is one of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Fictional Minds in Comics:</title>
                     <subtitle>100 Bullets, Characterization, and Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The comics series<italic>100 Bullets</italic>opens on a rainy street with the words “Bang. You’re dead ” (1:5). The premise is simple: an agent offers an attaché case of one hundred untraceable bullets and an unregistered gun to people who have been wronged in life. Equipped with the evidence the agent supplies, they have carte blanche to take their revenge. After the opening statement of “Bang. You’re<italic>dead</italic>,” the series spends the remaining one hundred issues of its run exploring the moral and ethical implications of firing or not firing that lethal bullet. The series can be read as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Contemporary Comics Storytelling</italic>, each of the constituents of the title is salient. In the introduction I focused more on the “contemporary” aspect of this book, mapping its place in a time of rising cultural prestige for comics and an era that begins to renegotiate postmodernism. Comics like<italic>Fables</italic>,<italic>Tom Strong</italic>, and<italic>100 Bullets</italic>are literature, not so much because cultural gatekeepers are finally paying attention to them, but because their complex narrative strategies allow to them to participate in and reflect on the contemporary cultural debate. This book has endeavored to analyze the narrative strategies of the three series,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ddr8c6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>232</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
