<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Terms of the Political: Community, Immunity, Biopolitics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ESPOSITO</surname>
               <given-names>ROBERTO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Welch</surname>
               <given-names>Rhiannon Noel</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Campbell</surname>
               <given-names>Timothy</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>series editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823242641</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823246274</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt13x0bdm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Terms of the Political: Community, Immunity, Biopolitics presents a decade of thought about the origins and possibilities of political theory from one of contemporary Italy's most prolific and engaging political theorists, Roberto Esposito. He has coined a number of critical concepts in current debates about the past, present, and future of biopolitics-from his work on the implications of the etymological and philosophical kinship of community (communitas) and immunity (immunitas) to his theorizations of the impolitical and the impersonal. Taking on interlocutors from throughout the Western philosophical tradition, from Aristotle and Augustine to Weil, Arendt, Nancy, Foucault, and Agamben, Esposito announces the eclipse of a modern political lexicon-"freedom," "democracy," "sovereignty," and "law"-that, in its attempt to protect human life, has so often produced its opposite (violence, melancholy, and death). Terms of the Political calls for the opening of political thought toward a resignification of these and other operative terms-such as "community," "immunity," "biopolitics," and "the impersonal"-in ways that affirm rather than negate life. An invaluable introduction to the breadth and rigor of Esposito's thought, the book will also welcome readers already familiar with Esposito's characteristic skill in overturning and breaking open the language of politics.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="176"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>BIOPOLITICS AND COMMUNITY IN ROBERTO ESPOSITO</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LEMM</surname>
                           <given-names>VANESSA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Foucault once said that political theory had still not reckoned with the end of sovereign power. In like fashion, one can say that political theory is only just now starting to confront itself and its languages with the consequences caused by the entrance of biology and biological considerations into questions of government. Roberto Esposito is perhaps the contemporary thinker who has gone furthest in questioning the traditional categories of political thought in light of the emergence of biopolitics. In this accessible collection of essays, he presents his own philosophical enterprise in terms of bridging deconstruction with biopolitics. Esposito is perhaps</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE LAW OF COMMUNITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I’d like to reflect on community beginning with the word’s original Latin root. The meaning that all etymological dictionaries suggest as most probable is the one that combines<italic>cum</italic>with<italic>munus</italic>(or<italic>munia</italic>). Such a derivation is important insofar as it designates precisely what holds the members of a community together. These members are not bound by just any relationship, but precisely by a<italic>munus</italic>—a “task,” “duty,” or “law.” According to the other meaning of the term (which is closer to the first than it might seem), they are bound by a “gift,” but a gift that is to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>MELANCHOLY AND COMMUNITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What kind of relationship exists between these two terms? Is there something essentially “common” in melancholy, and does melancholy have something to do with the very form of community? The answer that the literature on melancholy has offered has often been negative. Within both its pathological interpretation as a sickness of the body and spirit and its positive one as genial exceptionality, melancholy has generally been situated as not only different from community but actually in opposition to it. Indeed, we might say that for much of the interpretative tradition, and most markedly within sociological inquiry, melancholic man has been</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>IMMUNITARY DEMOCRACY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does the term<italic>community</italic>refer to democracy? Might it, or is it too profoundly rooted in the conceptual lexicon of the romantic, authoritarian, and racist Right? This question, first posed in the context of American neocommunitarianism, is emerging once again in Europe, above all in France and Italy, as we venture a new thought about community. This question is not only legitimate but in certain ways quite unavoidable at a time when democratic culture is interrogating its own theoretical mandates and its own future. However, this doesn’t change the fact that the question is incorrect in its very formulation, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FREEDOM AND IMMUNITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before taking up how the theme of freedom relates to community, I would like to consider something even more fundamental that involves the entire political lexicon and the growing difficulty such a lexicon faces in signifying its own object—namely, the political.¹ A true barrier seems to have been erected between language and politics. It is as if politics has escaped from language, as if language no longer has any words with which to name politics. As early as the 1930s, Simone Weil wrote, “On inspection, almost all the words and phrases of our political vocabulary turn out to be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>IMMUNIZATION AND VIOLENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an essay dedicated to Kant as an interpreter of the Enlightenment, Michel Foucault identifies the task of contemporary philosophy in a certain kind of attitude. It has to do with our strained relationship to the present that he calls the “ontology of actuality.” What does he mean? What does it mean to place philosophy at the point, or on the line, in which actuality reveals itself in all the richness of its historicity? What exactly does<italic>ontology of actuality</italic>mean? First of all, the expression implies a shift of the gaze inward, toward ourselves. Situating ourselves ontologically within the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIOPOLITICS AND PHILOSOPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More than fear or hope, perhaps surprise is what recent international events have made us feel. Before they turn out to be positive, negative, or even tragic, international events are first and foremost unexpected. Moreover, they seem to contradict all reasonable calculation of probability. From the sudden and bloodless collapse of the Soviet system in 1989 to the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, and everything that followed, what we can say at a minimum is not only that we couldn’t have imagined them before they occurred but that everything appeared to make their occurrence unlikely. Naturally, every collective event</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NAZISM AND US</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>1933–2003. Is it legitimate to turn once again to the question of Nazism seventy years after it took power? The answer, I believe, can only be yes: not just because forgetting Nazism would represent an unbearable offense for its victims but also because, despite an ever increasing body of literature, something about Nazism remains in the dark, something that touches us. What might it be? What links us invisibly to what we point to as the most tragic political catastrophe of our time, and perhaps of all time? My own sense is that this thing that both troubles and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>POLITICS AND HUMAN NATURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “Letter on Humanism” that Martin Heidegger published in 1946 at the culmination of an historical and biographic defeat seems to spell the end of the secular event of humanism. Despite the attempts to restore humanism to a spiritualist, Marxist, or existentialist form, the great humanist tradition could not withstand the dual trauma of Auschwitz and Hiroshima, in which the opposite of humanity laid waste to the very idea of humanity.¹ Regardless of the direct and even instrumental conditions that underpin the drafting of the “Letter,” the need of such an epistemological break is central to Heidegger’s text: a culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TOTALITARIANISM OR BIOPOLITICS:</title>
                     <subtitle>TOWARD A PHILOSOPHICAL INTERPRETATION OF THE TWENTIETH CENTURY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Toward a philosophical interpretation of the twentieth century</italic>. How should we understand this expression? What meaning should we assign it? We might suggest two different answers to these questions, which are in some ways even contradictory. The first is the classic answer, associated with the great twentieth-century philosophical tradition of Husserl, Heidegger, and Sartre, to mention a few of the most well-known names. This answer calls for a reading of contemporary historical events through an interpretative lens that philosophy itself provides and singles out as the only one capable of grasping its essence. Whether such an interpretive lens is identified</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TOWARD A PHILOSOPHY OF THE IMPERSONAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Never before has the notion of the person constituted such an indispensable point of reference for all philosophical, political, and juridical discourses that lay claim to the value of human life as such. Setting aside ideological and theoretical differences, not one of them casts doubt on the importance of the category of the person, which is the indisputable (and undisputed) premise of each perspective. This tacit convergence is especially evident in the contentious field of bioethics. Actually, though, the clash (however bitter) between secularists and Catholics hinges upon the precise moment in which a living being can be considered a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>COMMUNITY AND VIOLENCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Humankind has always seen community and violence as inherently related. Such a relation is, in fact, at the heart of the most important expressions of culture across history, be they of art, literature, or philosophy. The first graffiti etched in prehistoric grottoes depicted the human community through scenes of violence (hunting, sacrifice, battles). So too would war be the theme of the first great poem of Western civilization. Almost all world literatures, from the Hebrew to the Egyptian to the Indian, open with interhuman conflict and its images of violence and death to confirm for us a connection between community</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13x0bdm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
