<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BP166.23 .B85 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Quran</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Theology</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Theology</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Creation (Islam)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Creation</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Biblical teaching</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>God's Creativity and Human Action</book-title>
         <subtitle>Christian and Muslim Perspectives</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MOSHER</surname>
               <given-names>LUCINDA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MARSHALL</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <role content-type="editor">Editors</role>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781626164864</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">162616486X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Georgetown University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Georgetown University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1trkk09"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>A record of the 2015 Building Bridges Seminar for leading Christian and Muslim scholars, this collection of essays explores the nature of divine and human agency through themes of creation's goal, humankind's dignity and task, and notions of sovereignty. Part I sets the context for the book with "Human Action within Divine Creation: A Muslim Perspective" by Mohsen Kadivar of Duke University and "On the Possibility of Holy Living: A Christian Perspective" by Lucy Gardner of Oxford University. The rest of the book includes paired essays-one from a Muslim perspective, one from a Christian perspective-that introduce scriptural material with commentary to aid readers in conducting dialogical study. In her conclusion, coeditor Lucinda Mosher digests the illuminating small-group conversations that lie at the heart of the Building Bridges initiative, conversations that convey a vivid sense of the lively, penetrating but respectful dialogue for which the project is known. This unique volume will be a valuable resource to scholars, students, and professors of Christianity and Islam.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PARTICIPANTS IN BUILDING BRIDGES SEMINAR 2015</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book presents the proceedings of the fourteenth annual Building Bridges Seminar, convened at the Georgetown University School of Foreign Service in Doha, Qatar, May 3–6, 2015, with university president John J. DeGioia present as host and participant. Launched in 2002 as an initiative of the Archbishop of Canterbury—and with the stewardship of Georgetown University since 2013, this gathering of scholar-practitioners of Islam and Christianity convenes annually, alternating between Muslim- majority and Christian-majority contexts, for deep study of selected texts pertaining to a carefully chosen theme. The circle of participants is always diverse ethnically and geographically, and balanced</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Human Action within Divine Creation:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Muslim Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KADIVAR</surname>
                           <given-names>MOHSEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human action within divine creation has been the subject of long and controversial discussions among Muslims since the eighth century, first as the subject of study and debate in commentaries on the Qurʾān and Ḥadīth and then continuing as one of the first problems of Islamic theology. The Muslim philosophers and mystics engaged deeply in the subject and enriched its literature from their specific perspectives.</p>
                     <p>We may classify the Muslim perspectives on this important subject under esoteric and exoteric approaches. The perspective of all mystics such as Ibn al-ʿArabī and some philosophers such as Shahab al-Din Suhrawardī and Mulla Sadrā,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On the Possibility of Holy Living:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Christian Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GARDNER</surname>
                           <given-names>LUCY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Faced with a task that feels like trying to pack the world into a suitcase, I have deliberately decided not to attempt a hurried historical overview of Christian disagreements about the nature of our existence—and our freedom, in particular. Instead, I offer a brief personal theological guide to negotiating the thematic landscape from one particular Christian point of view. This touches upon Christian beliefs about the person of Christ (the doctrines of the Incarnation and the Trinity, in particular), which cannot be fully explored here. It is, however, my hope that these reflections will demonstrate something of the ways</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>God’s Creation and Its Goal:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Muslim Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SIDDIQUI</surname>
                           <given-names>SOHAIRA ZAHID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of god’s Creation and its purpose is a perennial one that has both stumped exegetes of the Qurʾān and caused theologians to be embroiled in intense debates over the centuries. In offering a reflection on this topic, it is important to connect scriptural reflections on specific verses in the Qurʾān to their theological implications throughout Islamic intellectual history. To this extent, personal reflections on verses of the Qurʾān will be tethered to the more technical theological inquiries they contributed to. More specifically, these inquiries are (1) What does the mere presence of creation reveal about God’s nature? (2)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>God’s Creation and Its Goal:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Christian Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BAUCKHAM</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That god created “heaven and earth” or simply “all things” is a fundamental Christian belief, repeatedly stated in scripture and featuring in the ecumenical creeds. It entails an absolute difference between God and all that is not God—absolute in the sense that this difference is incomparable with any of the relative differences between creatures. The difference can be stated in a number of ways. For example, it means that all creatures are utterly dependent on God for their very existence as well as for being the creatures they are and for all that makes for their flourishing. This absolute</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Scripture Dialogue 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>God’s Creation and Its Goal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <sup>21</sup>People, worship your Lord, who created you and those before you, so that you may be mindful [of Him].…</p>
                     <p>
                        <sup>29</sup>It was He who created all that is on the earth for you, then turned to the sky and made the seven heavens; it is He who has knowledge of all things.…</p>
                     <p>
                        <sup>117</sup>He is the Originator of the heavens and the earth, and when He decrees something, He says only, “Be,” and it is.</p>
                     <p>
                        <sup>190</sup>There truly are signs in the creation of the heavens and earth, and in the alternation of night and day, for those with understanding,<sup>191</sup>who remember God</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Creativity, Covenant, and Christ</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gallaher</surname>
                           <given-names>Brandon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“God is with us” (Isa. 8:10). These comfortable words, that comfortable name, “Immanuel” (Matt. 1:23; Isa. 7:14) (Hebrew, “God is with us”), Jesus Christ, are words Christians cannot say without fear and trembling, without a hearty gratitude for God’s awesome grace revealed in creation through Christ, who is the King before the ages and who has wrought salvation in the midst of the earth (Ps. 74:12). For in Christ, through Christ, and by Christ, in the Christian understanding, we have God, we know God, and we and all creation with us are lifted up, illumined, and become grateful sons of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>To Be Khalīfa:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Human Vocation in Relation to Nature and Community</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAKAKE</surname>
                           <given-names>MARIA MASSI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If we ask the question, what is humankind’s purpose or vocation on earth, the clearest Qurʾānic answer is: to be<italic>khalīfat Allāh fi’l-arḍ</italic>, to be God’s representative or vicegerent on earth. Theologically, this is understood to be the ultimate reason for humankind’s creation, fall, and exile, and the reason human beings are equipped with intrinsic knowledge as well as guidance from God. It explains why they are entrusted with free will and why other creatures are described as subservient to them. Serving as God’s representative to the rest of creation entails a dual responsibility toward both God and creation. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Scripture Dialogue 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Dignity and Task of Humankind within God’s Creation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <sup>26</sup>Then God said, “Let us make humankind in our image, according to our likeness; and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the birds of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the wild animals of the earth, and over every creeping thing that creeps upon the earth.”</p>
                     <p>
                        <sup>27</sup>So God created humankind in his image,</p>
                     <p>in the image of God he created them;</p>
                     <p>male and female he created them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <sup>28</sup>God blessed them, and God said to them, “Be fruitful and multiply, and fill the earth and subdue it; and have dominion over the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Human Freedom and Divine Sovereignty:</title>
                     <subtitle>Muslim Perspectives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAMZA</surname>
                           <given-names>FERAS Q.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In muslim theological discourse, the terms used to discuss the question of free will versus divine predetermination did not directly emerge from the Qurʾānic lexicon, though concepts such as God’s decree and preordainment (<italic>al-qaḍāʾ wa’l-qadar</italic>), specifically in conjugated expressions such as<italic>qaddara Allāh</italic>or<italic>qaḍa Allāh</italic>, are well-known Qurʾānic refrains. To a large extent, from as early as the mid-second/eighth century, the theological discourse coalesced around a number of technical terms that were simply the obvious Arabic vernacular for the concepts and questions implied by the main topic: terms such as<italic>jabr</italic>(compulsion),<italic>tafwīḍ</italic>(delegation),<italic>iktisāb</italic>(acquisition),<italic>ikhtiyār</italic>(choice), or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Human Action within the Sovereignty of God:</title>
                     <subtitle>Christian Perspectives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KÄRKKÄINEN</surname>
                           <given-names>VELI-MATTI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To make my discussion of human action within the sovereignty of God manageable and useful for this particular occasion, I limit its scope in significant ways. I do not seek to respond to the denial of human freedom by those natural scientists to whom world processes are deterministic to the point of eliminating any true notion of freedom. Nor do I take up the equally strong rejection of human freedom by neuroscientists and philosophers of mind who argue that everything humans do is caused by our “neurons”—that is, neuroscientific determinism. I have discussed and defeated these forms of determinism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Scripture Dialogue 3:</title>
                     <subtitle>Human Action within the Sovereignty of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>And when your Lord took from the Children of Adam, from their loins, their seed and made them bear witness over themselves, [asking them,] “Am I not your Lord?” They said, “Yea, indeed we do so bear witness”; lest you should say on the Day of Resurrection, “Indeed of this we were unaware.”</p>
                     <p>Humankind were but a single community, but then differed. And were it not for a [decreed] word that had already preceded from your Lord, it would have been decided between them regarding that over which they differed.</p>
                     <p>Everyone acts according to his [particular] character (<italic>shakila</italic>).</p>
                     <p>Our Lord,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Discussion in Doha:</title>
                     <subtitle>Listening in on the Building Bridges Process</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MOSHER</surname>
                           <given-names>LUCINDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Georgetown university’s school of Foreign Service in Qatar (SFS-Q) provides a congenial atmosphere for appreciative conversation—the sort of frank and spirited exchange at the core of the Building Bridges Seminar. In 2015 SFS-Q provided us a spacious lounge with comfortable furniture and ample space for buffet-style meals, an adjacent meeting room large enough for closed lectures and plenary discussions to take place “in the round,” and, nearby, a small classroom for each of our four dialogue groups. It is in these predetermined groups, balanced by religion and gender as best as can be, that the main work of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1trkk09.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABOUT THE EDITORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
