<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PQ673.P55 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">French literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">20th century</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Erotic literature, French</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Pornography</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Censorship</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">France</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Forbidden Fictions</book-title>
         <subtitle>Pornography and Censorship in Twentieth-Century French Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Phillips</surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745312170</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781849645140</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>LONDON; STERLING, VIRGINIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John Phillips</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt18fs6m6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>‘Phillips discusses texts by Apollinaire, Pierre Loüys, Georges Bataille, Pauline Réage, Alain Robbe-Grillet, Tony Duvert, Elizabeth Barillé and Marie Darrieussecq, engaging in different levels of critical analysis so as to emphasize intertextual and parodic elements in one case, or points of possible identification in another.’ TLS French culture has long been perceived by the English-speaking reader as somehow more ‘erotic’ than its Anglo-Saxon equivalent. Forbidden Fictions is the first English-language study devoted exclusively to the wide spectrum of French literary pornography in the twentieth century. John Phillips provides a broad history of the genre and the associated moral and political issues. Among the texts examined in detail – all selected for their literary or sociopolitical importance – are landmark works by Apollinaire, Louÿs, Bataille, Réage, Robbe-Grillet, Arsan, and Duvert. Phillips challenges current politically correct trends in literary criticism and stereotyped censoring discourses about pornography to provide a new reading of each text and to illustrate the genre’s potential for social subversion. Forbidden Fictions addresses the most controversial issues of contemporary sexual politics, such as objectification, sadomasochism, homoeroticism and paedophilia, with particular emphasis on the feminist debate on pornography. In the light of current controversy over the control of pornography, this is a timely and scholarly review of the ethical, moral and social arguments surrounding the censorship of sexually explicit material.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Note on Translations/Editions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Erotic Novel and Censorship in Twentieth-Century France</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>French culture has long been perceived by the English-speaking reader as somehow more ‘erotic’ than Anglo-Saxon culture. This impression is partly due to the large numbers of pornographic publications which have been imported from Paris since the sixteenth century, first into England and later into the United States, but also to the peculiarly French association of pornography and subversion, hence the fascination that the genre has held for well-known and highly regarded writers from Rabelais to Robbe-Grillet. The choice of modern French (as opposed to any other nation’s) pornography as object of study is, therefore, justified by the unique existence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Pornography, Poetry, Parody:</title>
                     <subtitle>Guillaume Apollinaire’s Les Onze Mille Verges</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was not until 1970 that the first legal edition of the pornographic novel,<italic>Les Onze Mille Verges</italic>, bearing the name of Guillaume Apollinaire, was published. The heirs to his estate had finally admitted the existence of the book, written over 60 years earlier, and which has been described as the most explicit and violent erotic novel ever written in French. As Jean-Jacques Pauvert observes, there was no immediate public outcry, although only two years previously, in 1968, the<italic>Commission de protection de l’enfance et de la jeunesse</italic>had attempted to prosecute Pauvert himself for illicit publication of the work,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Sexual and Textual Excess:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pierre Louӱs’s Trois Filles de leur mère</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like the man who wrote them, the novels, stories and poems of Pierre Louӱs (1870–1925) overflow with an irrepressible and childlike<italic>joie de vivre</italic>and, in the case of both man and work, the dominant trait is excess. The extreme emotions of a romantic adolescence, the practical jokes of a young poet and, later, an extravagant self-indulgence, whether in the consumption of cigarettes or in the socially less acceptable tastes of the libertine, all of these excesses in Louӱs’s life and character are reflected in his writing, both in the critically acclaimed published canon and in the erotic works</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Masochism and Fetishism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Georges Bataille’s Histoire de l’œil</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Introducing the Gallimard edition of Georges Bataille’s complete works, Michel Foucault declares him to be one of the most important writers of the century.¹ It is certainly true that his work covers an impressively wide area: during the course of his life (1897–1962), Bataille wrote studies in sociology, anthropology, economics, philosophy, art and literary criticism as well as novels and poems, and it is difficult to appreciate his work fully without some knowledge of the whole range of his writing. His first book, the short novel,<italic>Histoire de l’œil</italic>was published secretly by René Bonnel in 1928, under the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>‘O, Really!’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Pauline Réage’s Histoire d’O</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a piece in<italic>The New Yorker</italic>in August 1994, the writer and literary journalist, John de St. Jorre gave a detailed account of an interview with Dominique Aury, writer, translator and critic, in which Aury revealed that she and Pauline Réage are one and the same. In other words, Dominique Aury is the pseudonymous author of<italic>Histoire d’O</italic>, the first published novel of modern times to be both explicitly erotic and written by a woman. One of the greatest literary enigmas of the postwar years had finally been resolved.¹</p>
                     <p>The novel takes the form of a third-person narrative, recounting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Emmanuelle and the Sexual Liberation of Women</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Emmanuelle Arsan’s first novel,<italic>Emmanuelle</italic>, was published secretly in 1959 by Eric Losfeld in Paris, at a time of renewed public interest in erotic writing. Recent court cases in France had led to the unbanning of works by Henry Miller, Boris Vian and the Marquis de Sade. At the same time, the 1950s had seen the illicit and usually anonymous publication of many new erotic novels. In particular, Pauline Réage’s<italic>Histoire d’O</italic>(1954), Vladimir Nabokov’s<italic>Lolita</italic>(1955) and Jean de Berg’s<italic>L’Image</italic>(1956); all of these, in their different ways, had prepared the ‘cultured’ French reader for the more explicit</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Progressive Slidings of Identity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alain Robbe-Grillet’s Projet pour une révolution à New York</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>nouveau roman</italic>or New Novel is a term coined in the 1950s by Alain Robbe-Grillet himself to denote his own work and that of a number of other writers, principally Nathalie Sarraute, Claude Simon, Michel Butor, Robert Pinget, Samuel Beckett and, initially at least, Marguerite Duras, all of whom were published by Les Éditions de Minuit, and who shared a rejection of the traditional novel’s approach to plot, characterisation and form, and so were considered experimental and avant-garde. As John de St. Jorre says of William Burroughs’s<italic>Naked Lunch</italic>, however, most New Novels remain difficult and at times inaccessible</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Homotextuality:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tony Duvert’s Récidive</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Born in 1945, Tony Duvert is the author of a dozen works of fiction, all of them homoerotic, and of two polemical essays. Although Duvert has never achieved the public acclaim of a Duras or the notoriety of an Arsan, the undoubted literary merit of much of his writing has not gone entirely unrecognised: his fifth novel,<italic>Paysage de fantaisie</italic>, won the Prix Médicis, a literary prize that rewards innovation, in 1973. Duvert now lives in seclusion in a small, provincial French town and has had no direct contact with his publisher, Éditions de Minuit, for many years. His last</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>‘Enfin, une érotique féminine?’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Two Contemporary Novels by Women</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In its thematic preoccupations with masturbatory fantasy and its essentially romantic treatment of sexual attraction, Élisabeth Barillé’s<italic>Corps de jeune fille</italic>, which was published in France in 1986 and in England as<italic>Body of a Girl</italic>in 1989, is an excellent example of contemporary erotic writing by women. Barillé displays a remarkable maturity of style, her narrative voice fizzing with ironic wit and more than a touch of self-mockery. Her first fictional publication (the author is also a journalist) is not so much a novel as a series of vignettes about sex written from a young woman’s point of view</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt18fs6m6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
