<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Memories of Asaph</book-title>
         <subtitle>Mnemohistory and the Psalms of Asaph</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jacobson</surname>
               <given-names>Karl N.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506423463</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506423469</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506418728</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506418724</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kgqv1h"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Although the Psalms of Asaph (Pss. 50, 73‒83) contain a concentration of historical referents unparalleled in the Psalter, they have rarely attracted sustained historical interest. Karl N. Jacobson identifies these Psalms as containing cultic historiography, historical narratives written for recitation in worship, and explores them through mnemohistory, attending to how the past is remembered and to the rhetorical function of recitation in the cultic setting. Asaph “remembers" the past as a movement from henotheism to Yahwism as the core memory that informs a new historical situation for worship participants.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="230"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction and History of Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The biblical psalms attributed to Asaph (Psalms 50, 73–83) exhibit the most concentrated collection of historical referents in the Psalter. These historical referents, embodied in the Asaphite collection, serve as the marshals of Israel’s historical memory and establish a cultic framework in which Israel’s memory is formed, its history represented, and its identity shaped. My contention is that the historical material in these psalms, paired as it is with a broad vocabulary of remembrance, is a form of cultic historiography that is principally attested in Asaph and is distinctive of the Psalter.</p>
                     <p>As a group, the Asaphite Psalms contain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Theoretical Considerations:</title>
                     <subtitle>History and Communal Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even a cursory reading of the psalms that contain historical referents precludes an understanding of this material as history or historiography in any critical, modern sense. These referents are not objective reportings of the past. But if the referents in these psalms are not history-writing per se, what then are they?</p>
                     <p>Because of the frequent use of vocabulary having to do with remembering and forgetting in association with these referents, “memory” seems to provide a plausible designation of both form and function. One might well see in this material a collection of memories of formative experiences. Asaph’s memories are not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Mnemohistory and the Asaphite Corpus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Maurice Halbwachs recognized that any given community or nation typically consists of a collection of groups. In the case of ancient Israel, the socioreligious collective was complex, and the contributions of numerous individuals and groups can be discerned in the composition of the Hebrew Bible. In the Hebrew Bible at large, there are bodies of material that record, retell, and reshape the people’s past; from the Pentateuch through the prophets, the remembered past is an integral part of the biblical material.¹ It is within the ranks of the keepers of Israel’s memory that Asaph finds his place. Yet within the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>How Asaph Remembers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To reiterate one of the tenets of this study, when historical references are employed in and with the language of memory, there is a rhetorical function and impact of the psalm that is different than it would otherwise be if the mnemohistorical referent were either absent or if some other<italic>Erinnerungsfigur</italic>were employed. Within the Asaphite corpus of the Psalter, there are two forms in which a historical referent is found.¹ The Psalms of Asaph offer both clear, intentional historical referents (explicit mnemohistory) and unintentional holdovers or reflections of older traditions and practices (residual mnemohistory).</p>
                     <p>Explicit mnemohistory is marked by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Psalm 78:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Heart of What Asaph Remembers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Psalm 78 is the longest, by far, of the so-called historical psalms (cf. Psalms 105, 106, 135, 136), and the second longest of all the psalms (cf. Psalm 119). Psalm 78 is also the core of the Asaphite mnemohistory, the heart of what Asaph remembers, not only in terms of its relative length and scope and its physical location in the midst of the collection, but in terms of its relative date and influence.¹</p>
                     <p>What we have represented in Psalm 78 is, in one sense, the better part of Israel’s national history as a united monarchy, from its beginning to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>What Asaph Remembers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If Psalm 78 is the core of the Asaphite mnemohistory, it is by no means its only locus. There is a great deal of mnemohistorical material across the Asaphite collection that appears to different extents and in various applications.</p>
                     <p>Mnemohistory in the Psalms of Asaph is not uniform in its appearance or application. There is no single pattern or formula for what is recalled, how it is recalled, or how its recollection will function within a given psalm. There is a range of length and detail that the remembered past exhibits in the Asaphite Psalms, and it would be overreaching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Excursus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Residual Memories in the Asaphite Corpus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is, in addition to the intentional, explicit mnemohistory of the Asaphite Psalms, which seeks to preserve and apply the remembered past, what may be called residual mnemohistory. It consists of information that while not a part of the conscious mnemohistorical agenda of the Asaphites is nevertheless preserved in the corpus that bears their name.</p>
                     <p>Residual mnemohistory is not intentionally marked, as is the stuff of explicit mnemohistory, but it may be recognized in the ostensible context out of which the psalm arises or in anachronisms that give one a sense of older religious sensibilities or tradents embedded in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Conclusions:</title>
                     <subtitle>Why Asaph Remembers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It has been shown that the Asaphite Psalms (50 and 73–83) exhibit the most concentrated collection of historical referents in the Psalter. This material is distinctive both in terms of its content (when compared to other Levitical collections and other individual psalms) and in its function. In the cultic poetry of the Asaphite material in particular, there is a ritualization of the act of shared remembering, engendered through recourse to the record of historical subjects or moments. The historical referents embodied in the Asaphite collection serve to preserve and pass on Israel’s historical memory and to establish a cultic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Name and Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqv1h.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
