<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Political Mind</book-title>
         <subtitle>or 'How to Think Differently'</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Laird</surname>
               <given-names>Kieran</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748623860</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748630226</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Kieran Laird</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1r21s0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Explores how contemporary developments in political theory and neuropsychology can be used to explore the political implication of the relationship between conscious and nonconscious thought.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Political Mind</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In 2000 an interesting argument developed between Apple Macintosh computers and the Church of Satan. Apple had been running an advertising campaign that used black-and-white photographs of famous historical people considered to have been influential in bringing about some change of perspective on behalf of their contemporaries superimposed with the slogan ‘Think different’. This appealed to the Church of Satan, an organisation born in San Francisco in the late 1960s and citing individualist freethinkers such as Nietzsche, Twain and Franklin as influences, as well as including Freud, Jung and Foucault on its suggested reading list. The Satanists were also enamoured</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Neuroscience of Consciousness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>It has become a standard refrain of contemporary social theory that, as we begin the twenty-first century, our culture seems as incoherent and fractured as our mental life. Ideas exist in juxtaposition, contradicting each other at certain levels and complementing at others. The exploration of the interrelationship between these planes and layers of culture, as well as those of consciousness and selfhood, are what fuels art and literature and what occupies the psychiatrist’s couch. At the heart of our culture is still the irresistible promise of Enlightenment rationality: that the world is there to be explained and bettered. The raw</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Politics of Neuroscience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The neurological material in the foregoing chapter operates within an ontology and epistemology that many in the social sciences have long fought against. At its hard scientific edge, this belief holds that human behaviour is fully explicable through close study of the operations of the brain. All social science and theory would therefore, in time, be superseded by an all-embracing explanatory vocabulary of neurophysiological brainstates. Before we can proceed to unpack such material for use in a political context, this fundamental concern must first be addressed.</p>
                     <p>It is argued that the best way to engage with this debate is to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Political Use of Emotion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>So far we have seen research from neuropsychology that illustrates the role which nonconscious processing plays in our mental lives. This is connected to the world around us through the role of the body in processing and cognition. One further aspect of this picture is emotion and affect. This chapter will seek to investigate the emotive aspect in thought and the debates as to its biological or social nature. Without going too far down the well-worn road of the nature/nurture debate, it is fairly uncontroversial to claim a socially constructed aspect to emotional experience and expression, even if one believes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Endlessly Repeating Ourselves:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narrative and Self-Repetition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>With our satanic question ever in sight, one of our main concerns must be the possibility of change. To think differently, for creative thought to occur, there must be change: at the psychological level and then projected out into the world. The question of breaking out of the confines of the influence of genetic mental structure and socialisation is also a question of how patterns of thought may change. This then is the relation that the present chapter bears to the rest of the book; our experience of time is the experience of change, primarily in terms of linearity, through</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Psychological Revolt</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Having constructed a conceptualisation of the mind and its connection to its surroundings as well as having painted a picture of the present environment it finds itself in, the psychological possibility of critique remains to be examined. It is easy to state that the mind is shaped wholly by a combination of neurophysical parameters and social experience, but the very fact that one feels so resistant to this idea shows the merits of deeper examination. Consciousness rebels against the notion that its limits can be so circumscribed and the artistic, cultural and philosophical labour of our species is a record</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Political Nonconscious</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we have looked at some themes concerning the role of consciousness in thinking differently. To similarly examine the role of the unconscious and nonconscious is, however, more problematic. The lack of insight we have into our mental life below the conscious level, and the seeming antithesis between mental functioning at such levels and social structures, makes the mapping of the former to the latter difficult. The problem has, however, already been addressed by theorists who have attempted to unpack the Freudian unconscious in political terms and it will be useful to canvas such attempts before moving</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Skilful Means</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>Buddhism likens its psychological techniques to a raft that is used to cross a river, the river being <italic>dukkha</italic>. The raft is merely a tool to be used to gain the further shore and then to be abandoned, its task fulfilled. Likewise, the conceptual apparatus used by Buddhism to effect change should not be clung to after their task is fulfilled. (One may ask whether the task of positive mental transformation is ever at an end and schools such as Zen do posit an ongoing process). These techniques are dubbed ‘skilful means’ and are the conceptual toolkit of Buddhist philosophy</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1r21s0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
