<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8m3</collection-id>
      <volume>234</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DS754.25.Q252004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1644-1795</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Qing Formation in World-Historical Time</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Struve</surname>
               <given-names>Lynn A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2004</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674013995</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781684173983</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1684173981</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Asia Center</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge (Massachusetts); London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tfj908"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>For many years, the Ming and Qing dynasties have been grouped as “late imperial China," a temporal framework that allows scholars to identify and evaluate indigenous patterns of social, economic, and cultural change initiated in the last century of Ming rule that imparted a particular character to state and society throughout the Qing and into the twentieth century. This paradigm asserts the autonomous character of social change in China and has allowed historians to create a “China-centered history." Recently, however, many scholars have begun emphasizing the singular qualities of the Qing. Among the eight contributors to this volume on the formation of the Qing, those who emphasize the Manchu ethos of the Qing tend to see it as part of an early modernity and stress parallel and sometimes mutually reinforcing patterns of political consolidation and cultural integration across Eurasia. Other contributors who examine the Qing formation from the perspective of those who lived through the dynastic transition see the advent of Qing rule as prompting attempts by the Chinese subjects of the new empire to make sense of what they perceived as a historical disjuncture and to rework these understandings into an accommodation to foreign rule. In contrast to the late imperial paradigm, the new ways of configuring the Qing in historical time in both groups of essays assert the singular qualities of the Qing formation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="448"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Maps and Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Glahn</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For three decades, historians of China have situated the Qing dynasty within a “late-imperial” epoch of Chinese history stretching from the midsixteenth to the early twentieth century. The late-imperial paradigm was conceived in reaction to the long-dominant characterization of China before the Opium War as caught in a repetitive “dynastic cycle” that reproduced an essentially inert “traditional” society until China was fully exposed to the forces of modernization issuing from the Western world. The late-imperial framework instead sought to identify and evaluate indigenous patterns of social, economic, and cultural change initiated in the last century of the Ming dynasty that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Struve</surname>
                           <given-names>Lynn A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As was intended, the various contributors to this volume have interpreted “the Qing formation” somewhat differently. We all agree, however, that it had something to do with a series of events that took place in the eighth decade of the sixteenth century since the birth of Jesus Christ (“the 1580s”), to use the calendrical scheme now hegemonic in the global sphere. In the calendrical scheme that<italic>then</italic>was hegemonic in the sinitic culturesphere, it was in the second ten-year period (the first sixth of a new sexagesimal cycle) of the “Wanli” reign, that of the thirteenth emperor of the Ming</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER I</label>
                     <title>The Qing Empire in Eurasian Time and Space:</title>
                     <subtitle>Lessons from the Galdan Campaigns</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Perdue</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can we place the first century of the Qing dynasty in worldhistorical time? Earlier generations of historians could not even conceive of this question. For Hegel and Marx, China until the nineteenth century was the land of eternal stagnation, embalmed in an airless coffin, never an active participant in the formation of the only progressive civilization, that of the West. Later historians, supporting nationalist and modernization movements, altered the vision slightly to include “change within tradition,” but they still cut off nearly all of imperial China’s history from the modern world. Today, no one can ignore the spectacular rise</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Qing Formation, the Mongol Legacy, and the ‘End of History’ in Early Modern Central Eurasia</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Millward</surname>
                           <given-names>James A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume, and the conference that produced it, have come at an apt historiographical moment. New data and new interpretations have led in recent years to something of a paradigm shift in how the Qing is viewed by historians of China (Rawski 1996). At the same time, the developing field of world history has been seeking new approaches to the last few centuries of accelerated global communication and integration, approaches that avoid “the West and the rest” dichotomies. Working China into such approaches has not been simple: while comparativists labor to relate China to frameworks based on European historical experience,¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Did Guns Matter?</title>
                     <subtitle>Firearms and the Qing Formation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This battle scene is described in the eyewitness account of Dzengšeo, a Manchu officer who served in the Qing army during the war to suppress the Rebellion of the Three Feudatories, which inflamed south ern China from 1673 to 1681.¹ In the end the government forces won, ensuring the continuation of Manchu rule. The cannons mentioned in the description of the battle, whether fired from the government or from the rebel side, owed a considerable debt to European military technology, as the war effort was heavily conditioned by the willingness of one Belgian Jesuit, Ferdinand Verbiest, to design and cast</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Contingent Connections:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fujian, the Empire, and the Early Modern World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wills</surname>
                           <given-names>John E.</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the study of world and comparative history for early-modern times, we have come to a new appreciation of the importance of different shapes of state-building. The European pattern of territoriality, citizenship, and multiple centers of competitive, mobilizing state-building activity, sometimes called “mercantilist,” is seen as building on continuities in political culture reaching back to the ancient Mediterranean. In the “gunpowder empires” of the Islamic world, which figure along with the Ming and Qing as the great early-modern “agrarian empires,” growth of trade and population can be seen openir.. g the way to inchoate regional state-building efforts that challenged the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>The Qing Formation and the Early-Modern Period</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rawski</surname>
                           <given-names>Evelyn S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I cite studies of the early Qing period to argue that what might called the “Qing formation” bears many of the hallmarks of the early-modern paradigm used to characterize European history in the seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries. In outlining my reasons for taking this stance, I place this work in the context of the others in this “Early Modern?” part of the volume.</p>
                     <p>Although Jack Goldstone takes a position diametrically opposed to mine, we agree on many important points, including the historical uniqueness of the British Industrial Revolution.</p>
                     <p>If early-modern history is intended solely to explain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Neither Late Imperial nor Early Modern:</title>
                     <subtitle>Efflorescences and the Qing Formation in World History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goldstone</surname>
                           <given-names>Jack A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Words are just words, but they bedevil our efforts to write a meaningful history of the world when they limit our discourse and therefore our understanding of patterns and trends. I would like to suggest that we are missing a word for the opposite of “crisis.” The trends that we commonly encounter in comparative and global histories are growth, stagnation, stability, and crisis. Yet this vocabulary is stunted, and it is biased in ways that have made it difficult to recognize the dynamics of premodern societies.</p>
                     <p>Growth comes in several flavors, to be sure. There is Kuznetzian “modern economic growth”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>The Diachronics of Early Qing Visual and Material Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hay</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Not long ago it was common in Western scholarship to portray Qing China as one of the modern West’s several contrasting Others, on the assumption that the Chinese were imprisoned in their own past, from which they would be rescued by the forces of modernization or Westernization. After World War II, this version of the Qing “story” was updated within the framework of a concept of “later Chinese history,” which evolved into the more specific “late-imperial China.” This revision gave the Qing period a new and more sympathetic image as the historical moment when Chinese society and culture contended with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Chimerical Early Modernity:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Case of ‘Conquest-Generation’ Memoirs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Struve</surname>
                           <given-names>Lynn A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This statement typifies attitudes about history and memory in midseventeenth-century Chinese memoirs. The author, like everyone everywhere, past or present (for all we know, since there exists no large body of memoirs earlier than the seventeenth century in China and Europe), grants that his memory is incomplete but insists that what he does remember is basically sound. Like many Chinese scholar-officials in all eras, he wants later generations to be able to understand the truth about “historical” matters that he knew firsthand, and he goes to extraordinary lengths to make that possible. Displaying an acuity about the relative value of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Han-Script Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj908.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>413</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
