<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5p4vbx</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Patrick Chamoiseau</book-title>
         <subtitle>Recovering Memory</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>McCUSKER</surname>
               <given-names>MAEVE</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">Series Editors</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SMYTH</surname>
               <given-names>EDMUND</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FORSDICK</surname>
               <given-names>CHARLES</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781846310485</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781846313738</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Liverpool University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Liverpool</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Maeve McCusker</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gn6cf5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This timely new book skilfully examines the work of the award-winning writer Patrick Chamoiseau. Considered by many as one of the most innovative writers to hit the French literary scene in over 40 years, Chamoiseau made his name with his book Texaco (published in 1992 and winner of the highest literary prize in France, the Prix Goncourt). His books have gone on to sell millions and his work has been translated by a number of academic presses. McCusker sets the author in context, providing a valuable contribution to ‘memory studies’ by looking at literary representation of memory in Martinique, a society founded on slavery but now politically assimilated to the metropolitan centre, France.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the early 1990s, the islands of the French-speaking Caribbean – the<italic>départements d’outre-mer</italic>, Martinique and Guadeloupe, as well as Haiti, the first Black republic – have been the site of a heightened and intense debate around historical memory. These islands – and notably Martinique – have already witnessed a long-standing tradition of theoretical self-analysis and identitarian debate, and have produced a number of thinkers (Frantz Fanon, Aimé Césaire, Edouard Glissant) who have anticipated and contributed to what we now call postcolonial discourse. Yet the contemporary centrality of the concern with collective memory, its pervasive and almost obsessive force, is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Beginnings:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Enigma of Origin</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Chronique des sept misères</italic>, Chamoiseau’s first novel, establishes many of the key concerns which will be further explored in his later writings. It deals throughout, and in a very direct way, with the confrontation between memory and oblivion, and presents a pessimistic diagnosis of the possibilities for memory, and hence self-knowledge, in contemporary Martinique. The novel is structured around a fall from grace: it traces the island’s transition from an economy based on the local Creole market in the early twentieth century to its brutal entry into the world of modernity, consumerism and global capital in the aftermath of World</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>‘Une tracée de survie’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Autobiographical Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapter explored the ways in which the absence of any sense of a stable, identifiable beginning, whether historical or mythical, motivates narrative and inflects form in Caribbean fiction, and specifically in<italic>Chronique des sept misères</italic>. In many ways, the autobiographical impulse expresses much the same need, in that it represents a quest for origins of a particular, but similarly elusive, nature. While, as we will see in later chapters, the elderly fictional protagonist is a privileged source of both the personal and the collective past, Chamoiseau’s autobiographies foreground the child as a vector of individual memory, although in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Memory Re-collected:</title>
                     <subtitle>Witnesses and Words</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relationship with the past is one of the most fraught aspects in the negotiation of a postcolonial identity, and indeed history is frequently figured in postcolonial writing as a restraining or a restrictive force. For Joyce’s Stephen Dedalus history, famously, is the nightmare from which he wants to awake, while Salman Rushdie’s Saleem Sinai describes himself as being ‘handcuffed to history’ on the opening page of<italic>Midnight’s Children</italic>. Such images of entrapment or restraint testify to the oppressive ‘presentness’ of the past in the postcolonial imaginary. As we have already seen, in the context of the Caribbean – where</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Memory Materialized:</title>
                     <subtitle>Traces of the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Memory is at once an innate capacity, and an intangible ‘store’ of past experiences, sensations, abilities and events. But as recent studies of memory have repeatedly underlined, it is mediated through and stimulated by<italic>things</italic>: sites, monuments or archives in the public domain, and paraphernalia, possessions or souvenirs in the personal sphere. In his highly critical study of the prevalence of memory as an explicit theme in recent writing, Kerwin Klein argues that contemporary memory is frequently vested in ‘a dramatically imperfect piece of material culture, and such fragments are best if imbued with pathos’. These memorial tropes, he argues,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Flesh Made Word:</title>
                     <subtitle>Traumatic Memory in Biblique des derniers gestes</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This study began with a reading of Chamoiseau’s first novel,<italic>Chronique des sept misères</italic>, and reaches its end with his most recent, and most ambitious, to date,<italic>Biblique des derniers gestes</italic>(2002).¹ The striking similarity in the very titles of the two texts gestures towards a continuity of thematic preoccupation, and indeed of structure, across the<italic>œuvre</italic>as a whole. This coherence can be seen for example in the fact that<italic>Biblique</italic>, like<italic>Texaco</italic>and<italic>Solibo</italic>, opens in the debased contemporary present, and then projects back in time, uncovering a more vital, if painful, Creole past. The novel’s hero, Balthazar</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the transition that has been traced in this monograph, from an æsthetics of re-collection and transcription to a poetics of materiality, the body has emerged as a primary site of both fictional and autobiographical memory, an archive and an active witness. It is appropriate that this study should end with further consideration of<italic>Biblique</italic>because, as we have seen, this novel focuses on the body to an unprecedented degree, and because the text exemplifies many of the tensions which have lain at the heart of my analysis more generally, such as the fraught borderline between nostalgia and ‘authentic’ memory,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gn6cf5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
