<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxsmzj</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BJ1401.F39 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Good and evil</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Feminist theory</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Feminist Philosophy and the Problem of Evil</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SCHOTT</surname>
               <given-names>ROBIN MAY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>11</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253348586</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253027740</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253027748</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Hypatia, Inc.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1zxz0w2"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Any glance at the contemporary history of the world shows that the problem of evil is a central concern for people everywhere. In the last few years, terrorist attacks, suicide bombings, and ethnic and religious wars have only emphasized humanity's seemingly insatiable capacity for violence. In Feminist Philosophy and the Problem of Evil, Robin May Schott brings an international group of contemporary feminist philosophers into debates on evil and terrorism. The invaluable essays collected here consider gender-specific evils such as the Salem witch trials, women's suffering during the Holocaust, mass rape in Bosnia, and repression under the Taliban, as well as more generalized acts of violence such as the 9/11 bombings, the Madrid train station bombings, and violence against political prisoners. Readers of this sobering volume will find resources for understanding the vulnerability of human existence and what is at stake in the problem of evil.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="344"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Evil, Terrorism, and Gender</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schott</surname>
                           <given-names>Robin May</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If anyone should think that evil is a problem of the past and not of the present, a glance at the history of the twentieth century proves otherwise. In that century, the atrocities of war escalated dramatically; between 1900 and 1990, there were over four times as many war deaths as in the preceding four hundred years. In 1990 battlefields included Afghanistan, Angola, Colombia, El Salvador, Ethiopia, Guatemala, India, Kuwait, Lebanon, Liberia, Mozambique, Peru, Somalia, South Africa, Sri Lanka, Sudan, and Tibet (Vickers 1993, 2). To these one must add the battles of the Gulf War and the genocides in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Devil’s Insatiable Sex:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Genealogy of Evil Incarnate</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Denike</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In part, this chapter takes up a challenge that Michel Foucault (1989) posed in an interview and that he himself had entertained throughout his genealogical histories of madness and sexuality. The challenge, specifically, is “to write a political history of truth,” a history—or histories—that ascertain the kinds of power relations that are implicated in the production and circulation of knowledge, and particularly, in the “official discourses” that are accepted as “true.” Such a genealogical approach, as Foucault defined it in the context of this interview (1989, 137–39), concerns the truth games played with “sex” and “sexuality,” though</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Irigaray’s To Be Two:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Problem of Evil and the Plasticity of Incarnation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jaarsma</surname>
                           <given-names>Ada S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As this epigraph signals, an awareness of “sin” emerges out of Luce Irigaray’s central assertion of sexual difference as the essential ethical and philosophical problem. Irigaray asserts that a rejection or refutation of sexual difference risks committing an ultimate sin. Through this claim, we can glimpse a problematic of evil emerging out of Irigaray’s project that cannot be easily or quickly delimited. Irigaray herself traverses this problematic in her texts, elaborating sources of brokenness and violence as well as concomitant possibilities for regeneration (see, e.g., 1993b, 1993d, and 1996). Rather than mobilizing traditional concepts like “moral evil” or “natural evil,”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Genocide and Social Death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Card</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay develops the hypothesis that social death is utterly central to the evil of genocide, not just when a genocide is primarily cultural but even when it is homicidal on a massive scale. It is social death that enables us to distinguish the peculiar evil of genocide from the evils of other mass murders. Even genocidal murders can be viewed as extreme means to the primary end of social death. Social vitality exists through relationships, contemporary and intergenerational, that create an identity that gives meaning to a life. Major loss of social vitality is a loss of identity and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Holes of Oblivion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Banality of Radical Evil</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Birmingham</surname>
                           <given-names>Peg</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her 1945 review of Denis de Rougemont’s<italic>The Devil’s Share</italic>(1944), Hannah Arendt argues, “The reality is that the Nazis are men like ourselves; the nightmare is that they have shown, have proven beyond doubt, what man is capable of.” She writes, “In other words, the problem of evil will be the fundamental question of postwar intellectual life in Europe” (1994, 134). Certainly, nearly three decades of Arendt’s writing have offered readers ample arsenal for debate about whether she changes her mind on the nature of evil, whether the radical evil she attempts to comprehend in<italic>Origins of Totalitarianism</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Banal Evil and Useless Knowledge:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hannah Arendt and Charlotte Delbo on Evil after the Holocaust</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Geddes</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three related divisions currently mark scholarship on evil. The first is the divide between studies of perpetrators and studies of victims. In the field of Holocaust studies, this division is a matter of principle for some scholars, who focus solely on the testimonies and histories of the victims. One rationale behind refusing to study the perpetrators of the Nazi horrors is the belief that they do not deserve the dignity even of being made objects of study. Behind the work of those who study the perpetrators is the idea that unless we understand how it was that humans came to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>February 22, 2001:</title>
                     <subtitle>Toward a Politics of the Vulnerable Body</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bergoffen</surname>
                           <given-names>Debra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On February 22, Marlise Simons of the<italic>New York Times</italic>reported that the United Nations International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) found three Bosnian soldiers guilty of crimes against humanity. Their offense? Rape. The court’s ruling opens a new chapter in international law. In Simons’s words: “In its first trial dealing exclusively with sexual violence, the United Nations war crimes tribunal today found three former Bosnian Serb soldiers guilty of raping and torturing Muslim women and girls. It also convicted two of the three men of enslaving their captives, the first time that an international tribunal has prosecuted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Obscene Undersides:</title>
                     <subtitle>Women and Evil between the Taliban and the United States</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Franks</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter was originally written in November 2000, almost a year before the World Trade Center attacks took place. Since then, the international perception of the Taliban has shifted greatly. Formerly perceived as a largely irrelevant, though brutal, foreign regime, the Taliban became the subject of intense international focus after September 11, 2001. More recent events compelled me to alter aspects of my argument that were based on the West’s seeming indifference to Afghanistan and to examine the dramatic changes in policy and rhetoric that the United States effected in the months following the WTC attacks.</p>
                     <p>The concept of “evil”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Cruelty, Horror, and the Will to Redemption</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arnault</surname>
                           <given-names>Lynne S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In U.S. American mainstream popular culture, the idea that meaning can be reclaimed from even the cruelest of circumstances is highly cherished. For a myriad of reasons, many Americans are deeply invested in believing that there must be some good purpose and final ending to the suffering caused by cruelty. In Charles Taylor’s words, “We want our lives to have meaning, or weight, or substance, or to grow towards some fullness. … But this means our<italic>whole</italic>lives. If necessary, we want the future to ‘redeem’ the past, to make it part of a life story which has sense or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Terrorism, Evil, and Everyday Depravity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>On</surname>
                           <given-names>Bat-Ami Bar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The appropriation of the term “evil” by President George W. Bush’s administration has caused me to hesitate in thinking about terrorism as “evil.” Quite quickly after the Al Qaeda attacks of September 11, 2001, the Bush administration began to deploy the term “evil” in conjunction with the term “axis” and referred, with the phrase “an axis of evil,” to the Al Qaeda network and the weave of individuals, organizations, and especially states that support it (Bush 2002). The connection of “evil” with “axis” in this context is probably intended to evoke memories of World War II and use them to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Responding to 9/11:</title>
                     <subtitle>Military Mode or Civil Law?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Card</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is it justifiable to set aside rules of war in responding to opponents who did the same? Can war on terrorism respond to evil without doing further evil? Such questions invite reflection on the concepts of evil, war, and terrorism. My objectives in so reflecting are: (1) to identify issues that should complicate good answers; and (2) to consider how other nations, whose security may be jeopardized, might justifiably respond to decisions of target nations who do as they see fit to protect themselves. In pursuing the second objective, I explore analogies with the responses of states to women who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Naming Terrorism as Evil</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jaggar</surname>
                           <given-names>Alison M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within days of the dramatic attacks that occurred on September 11, 2001, the editors of<italic>Hypatia</italic>invited several feminist philosophers to consider whether those attacks, and terrorism more generally, should be described as evil (Schott 2003, 5).¹ In the intervening four years, marked by further terrorist attacks on Western countries, references to terrorism as evil have become commonplace in the political discourse of the United States. The present discussion offers some reasons for resisting this characterization. I do not attempt to justify terrorism, but I suggest that the language of evil, because of its theological and absolutist associations, is distinctly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Vertigo of Secularization:</title>
                     <subtitle>Narratives of Evil</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lara</surname>
                           <given-names>María Pía</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Those who hurried to write something about September 11, 2001, were prone to make errors of judgment because the events of that day were so difficult to comprehend. A few years have passed, and this act of terrorism still haunts us. The legacy of terror is something that will reverberate in our global era until we are capable of properly analyzing this new type of terrorism that worships death and destruction, disguising itself behind the excuse of fundamentalist “religious views.” If we are to believe the terrorist’s claims of righteousness, their means and their ends were disproportionate. Clearly, their ultimate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Willing the Freedom of Others after 9/11:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Sartrean Approach to Globalization and Children’s Rights</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mui</surname>
                           <given-names>Constance L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Murphy</surname>
                           <given-names>Julien S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean-Paul Sartre has said that hell is other people, referring to the other’s freedom as the greatest threat to our own freedom (1976, 45). The terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001, which turned lower Manhattan into a roaring inferno, represent a profound experience of evil. In less than ninety minutes, nineteen young al-Qaeda hijackers on a suicide mission killed more than three thousand people. In the aftermath of that fateful day, our nation struggled to comprehend the enormity of evil in their horrific acts. We quickly learned that the attacks were linked to a notorious Saudi terrorist named Osama bin</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Terrorism and Democracy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Between Violence and Justice</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aguado</surname>
                           <given-names>María Isabel Peña</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Giles</surname>
                           <given-names>Jana María</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At the same time that this essay was beginning to take form, four bombs exploded in London, sowing seeds not only of terror and panic but also of mistrust and rancor. For Britain, it was a new attack, but the wounds and cries, the desperation and faces of horror, the anxiety of waiting in hospitals, as well as the official discourse of condemnation are all too familiar. Certainly, the British government appears to have been quite prudent in measuring out images and scenes of panic and pain. One has only to note the difference between two images publicizing the attack</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Those Who “Witness the Evil”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Peacekeeping as Trauma</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Razack</surname>
                           <given-names>Sherene H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is said that a Canadian speechwriter in the Bush administration coined the phrase “axis of evil” that has been so much a part of American political vocabulary since the September 11, 2001, terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center and the Pentagon (Walker 2002). If this is true, it is fitting. For the better part of the 1990s, Canadian peacekeepers have described their activities in Somalia, Rwanda, Haiti, Bosnia, Kosovo, and Croatia as encounters with “absolute evil.” The American president and the Canadian peacekeeper quoted above¹ both imagine the international as a space where civilized peoples from the North</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>The Evils of the September Attacks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ruddick</surname>
                           <given-names>Sara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The attacks of September 11, 2001, caused, and could be expected to cause, pain, injury, and death; terror and grief. The victims of the attack had no distinct relation to the attackers; no grounds for predicting attack; no means of protecting themselves or others; no time for leaving, mourning, or celebrating their lives and loves. These attacks were undeniably terrible. Were they also evil?</p>
                     <p>The September attacks were called evil on the day they occurred. “Today,” the President announced to the Nation, “thousands of lives were despicably ended by evil.”¹ Almost immediately, America was called to a Manichean struggle of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Feminist Reactions to the Contemporary Security Regime</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Young</surname>
                           <given-names>Iris Marion</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The American and European women’s movement of the late 1970s and early 1980s contained a large segment organizing around issues of weapons, war, and peace. By the early 1990s, the humor and heroism of women’s peace actions had been all but forgotten. Prompted by events in the United States and the world since September 2001, and by the rhetoric of U.S. leaders justifying some of their actions, I do think that there are urgent reasons to reopen the question of whether looking at war and security issues through a gendered lens can teach us all lessons that might further the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1zxz0w2.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
