<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f89qq</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Early Cinema and the "National"</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Abel</surname>
               <given-names>Richard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bertellini</surname>
               <given-names>Giorgio</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>King</surname>
               <given-names>Rob</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>17</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780861966899</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780861969159</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0861969154</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>John Libbey Publishing</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington, IN</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John Libbey Publishing Ltd.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1bmzncx"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>While many studies have been written on national cinemas, Early Cinema and the "National" is the first anthology to focus on the concept of national film culture from a wide methodological spectrum of interests, including not only visual and narrative forms, but also international geopolitics, exhibition and marketing practices, and pressing linkages to national imageries. The essays in this richly illustrated, landmark anthology are devoted to reconsidering the nation as a framing category for writing cinema history. Many of the 34 contributors show that concepts of a national identity played a role in establishing the parameters of cinema's early development, from technological change to discourses of stardom, from emerging genres to intertitling practices. Yet, as others attest, national meanings could often become knotty in other contexts, when concepts of nationhood were contested in relation to colonial/imperial histories and regional configurations. Early Cinema and the "National" takes stock of a formative moment in cinema history, tracing the beginnings of the process whereby nations learned to imagine themselves through moving images.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="104"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Abel</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bertellini</surname>
                           <given-names>Giorgio</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>King</surname>
                           <given-names>Rob</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>nation</italic>and the<italic>national</italic>have long circulated as useful, supposedly definitive categories in cinema history. One can find them in early film manufacturer catalogues such as the 1896 Lumière sales catalogue of films shot in distant parts of the globe and organized according to country of origin. Or in early trade press attempts “to classify the film product of the world”, such as<italic>New York Dramatic Mirror</italic>’s 1908 compilation of the “distinguishing characteristics” or “infallible ear marks” of films produced by different countries.¹ Or in early histories of the cinema’s aesthetic development, such as Léon Moussinac’s<italic>Naissance du cinéma</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Early cinema as global cinema:</title>
                     <subtitle>the encyclopedic ambition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gunning</surname>
                           <given-names>Tom</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Early cinema is a global cinema.” “National cinema only appears later in film history.” I would endorse both these statements as important historical principles, and might restate them, borrowing a phrase from my colleague Michael Raine, one of the finest historians of Japanese cinema, as “cinema was international before it was national”. However, immediately a flurry of problems intervene, mainly dealing with terminology. What do we mean by: “global”, “international” or even “national”? I am reminded of a story I heard from my former colleague Homi Bahbha (my apologies to him if my memory is not exact). Interviewing an executive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Nationalizing attractions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Auerbach</surname>
                           <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Like most of us, I manage to wear more than one academic hat, having been trained in literary analysis, which I continue to pursue, along with my research in early cinema for the past decade or so, with American studies serving as something like a bridge between these two very different modes of representation, the verbal and the visual. Given the pressure to be “interdisciplinary” (whatever that means, exactly), I tried at first to combine these two interests, but have since learned the hard way that it is sometimes best to keep your hats separate. Attempting to import key operational</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Images of the “National” in early non-fiction films</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kessler</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>22</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 21 September 1896 a young Frenchman, sent abroad by the Lyon-based firm Lumière, records a Tyrolese dance, a<italic>Schuhplattler</italic>, with a<italic>Cinématographe</italic>camera.¹ The young man’s name is Constant Girel,² twenty-three years old, and the scene he films is set in Cologne, possibly somewhere in a public park, far from the Alps where Tyrolese dancers are part of the local folklore. Obviously, the dancing couple are performers who are part of a Tyrolese show and otherwise present on a stage somewhere in Cologne a spectacle that – apparently – is exotic enough for audiences in the Rhineland (similar shows can be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>National and racial landscapes and the photographic form</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bertellini</surname>
                           <given-names>Giorgio</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How do historians usually address the relationship between early cinema and national differences? There is a wealth of methodological approaches. They range from discussions of subject matter, social themes, historical circumstances (i.e. Spanish-American War, World War I), genre/intertextual form (i.e. the western film), institutional affiliation (i.e. the Albert Kahn Archive, the Dutch Colonial Institute), economy of production, marketing, and cultural reception (i.e. French cinema in the USA).</p>
                     <p>Less often is the notion of national difference articulated with racial difference and then included in discussions about cinema’s<italic>formal and technological relationship with other media of visual representations</italic>– particularly when scholars stress</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Sound-on-disc cinema and electrification in pre-WWI Britain, France, Germany and the United States</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Brien</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the following essay I examine sound-on-disc cinema prior to World War I through a framework of national and urban comparisons. The objective is to explore sound-on-disc’s international diffusion as an example of how the cinema’s uneven global development, its geographical diversity, was conditioned by regional variations in electric power. The focus on sound-on-disc thus involves an argument that bears implications for cinema history as a whole. One aspect of the argument concerns difficulties posed to the established nation-state film historiography by electrification, a sub-or transnational phenomenon more than a national one.</p>
                     <p>The essay is organized in three parts. First,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Mind-reading/mind-speaking:</title>
                     <subtitle>dialogue in ‘The Birth of a Nation (1915) and the emergence of speech in American silent cinema</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liepa</surname>
                           <given-names>Torey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the seemingly uncanny pithiness of Al Jolson’s famous lines, “Wait a minute! Wait a minute! You ain’t heard nothin’ yet”, in 1927, speech was not new to the cinema. In fact, speech had played a substantial role in silent films for nearly two decades. Dialogue intertitles and character-written inserts allowed cinematic representations to extend beyond the pictorial exterior and into the linguistic consciousness of characters. Silent film dialogue, however, brought more than a symbolic image of individual consciousness to the cinema. Reflecting a broader social matrix of language and power, written dialogue gave voice to the cultural politics endemic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Living Canada:</title>
                     <subtitle>selling the nation through images</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Braun</surname>
                           <given-names>Marta</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keil</surname>
                           <given-names>Charlie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Distinctively in the Western world, Canada’s identity as a nation was forged at the same moment as technologies of mechanized reproduction became prevalent. Early cinema, indeed, assumed a privileged place in defining Canada to its inhabitants and to the larger world. No set of texts reinforces cinema’s role in the formative nation-building exercise more clearly than the changing program of film series known as<italic>Living Canada</italic>, first exhibited in 1903. Living Canada offers a revealing example of the ways in which film was employed to envision and give form to concepts of nation at that crucial time before World War</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Early cinema and “the Polish question”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Skaff</surname>
                           <given-names>Sheila</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The failure of the first local filmmakers to earn broad recognition for their achievements fulfilled the expectations of the inhabitants of the Polish nation – a stateless entity in parts of the Kingdom of Prussia, Russian Empire, and Austro-Hungarian Empire comprising ethnically, religiously, and linguistically diverse populations committed to the restoration of eighteenth century borders – perfectly. In no other aspect of Polish national culture was fatalism more widespread, more profound, or more advantageous for foreign entrepreneurs. In Warsaw, this fatalism was manifest in initial praise, and eventual dismissal, of the first short films to document the daily routines and weekend pleasures</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Our Navy and patriotic entertainment in Brighton at the start of the Boer War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gray</surname>
                           <given-names>Frank</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Britain, as an imperial power, dominated the world at the end of nineteenth century. Jan Morris described it succinctly as, “the largest empire in the history of the world, comprising nearly a quarter of the landmass of the earth, and a quarter of its population”.¹ Its role as a global superpower was to assert its political and economic authority, especially in Africa and Asia. The so-called Pax Britannica (British peace) was a product of this status. It was expressed profoundly in 1900 by the fact that Britain and its global interests were defended by its navy – the largest navy in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>“An England of our Dreams”?:</title>
                     <subtitle>early patriotic entertainments with film in Britain during the Anglo-Boer War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Christie</surname>
                           <given-names>Ian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Anglo-Boer War of 1899–1902 has long been known as one of the first conflicts in which modern media played an important role, with photographic illustration, telegraphy and film all actively involved.¹ But it would be more accurate to say that these “new media” were finding their place amid the established media of print and performance. Rather than stake a simple claim for the novelty of film, historians of the medium and its place in visual culture can offer the more complex insights that arise from tracing how film borrowed from and echoed the themes expressed in other media,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>“The transport of audiences”:</title>
                     <subtitle>making cinema “National”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Klerk</surname>
                           <given-names>Nico</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The materials that are the subject of this essay, films and their accompanying printed texts, were produced in the early and mid-1910s by the Association Koloniaal Instituut, in Amsterdam. This association was founded in 1910 as a centre for the promotion of science, education, trade, and manufacture. Alerted by a lack of interest in the Dutch colonies, in particular the East Indies (now Indonesia), the association’s founders conceived of the Colonial Institute as a center for the collection and study of data and objects of, and the dissemination of knowledge about, Dutch overseas territories. Besides exhibitions, publications or lectures, they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Enlisting early cinema in the service of “la plus grande France”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Norindr</surname>
                           <given-names>Panivong</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The use of the term “enlisting” in my title is not meant simply to marshal the image of a nation at war but to suggest the potential or promise of early cinema in reconfiguring the new boundaries of the French imperial nation-state,¹ a sociopolitical system that linked a parliamentary republic, the Third Republic, to an administrative empire of colonies and protectorates. “L’idée coloniale”, to use Raoul Girardet’s term, entered popular French consciousness as “la plus Grande France”, so named after the French imperial doctrine² conceived after the bloody aftermath of the Great War to challenge the hegemony of the British</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Teaching citizenship via celluloid</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dahlquist</surname>
                           <given-names>Marina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1910, Francis Oliver, the Chief of the Bureau of Licenses in New York City, conducted a study of moving picture theaters and concluded: “the motion picture theaters which were just now being condemned by a great many people, [are] a potent factor in the education of the foreign element and therefore an advantage to the city”.¹ Challenging misgivings that moving pictures suggested “bad” ideas, he further claimed “that many foreigners who could neither read nor write were enabled through the proper kind of pictures to get a good working idea of the customs of this their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Fights of Nations and national fights</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mayer</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My subject, a brief film shot for American Mutoscope &amp; Biograph (AM&amp;B) by Billy Bitzer, initially attracted me because four of the six episodes are cleverly choreographed variety stage acts – i.e. theatrical vaudeville sketches – restaged for the camera. Each sketch is undeniably abridged, but not otherwise altered: filmed straight-on in what appear to be single takes, the camera set-ups and lighting (or exposures) sometimes differ for different episodes. As a theater historian aware of how many scraps of the Victorian theater – narratives, genres, staging, effects – can be recovered from early film, I scour these films for evidential remnants, and Fights</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Japan on American screens, 1908–1915</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Waller</surname>
                           <given-names>Gregory A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Japan invaded the United States sometime in May 1910. Or at least that is what a<italic>Moving Picture World</italic>editorial claimed in its 28 May 1910 issue, as it contemplated a forthcoming release entitled,<italic>Love of Chrysanthemum</italic>.<italic>Moving Picture World</italic>readily identified this Vitagraph film as yet one more refashioning of<italic>Madame Butterfly</italic>, that is, a contemporary story in which an ill-fated, cross-cultural and inter-racial romance between a Japanese woman and an American man ends with her suicide. For this preeminent American trade magazine, the “Japanese Invasion” was not literally a matter of spies, immigrants, or imported goods, and not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Nationalist film-going without Canadian-made films?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moore</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In urban, English Canada, the First World War was a significant marker of Canadian independence, maturing into a nation after British colonial adolescence. In defense of the British motherland, Canada found its national pride. This is especially applicable to Ontario, where stalwart Loyalist patriotism and a remarkable volunteerism signaled how Toronto would eventually eclipse Montreal culturally, industrially and economically as the national metropolis, having already done so in fact in the war effort.¹ But a Toronto-centric Canadian nation would never have that metropolis as a sentimental focus, neither as the heartland of a folk or an avant-garde culture, nor even</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>The cinema arrives in Italy:</title>
                     <subtitle>city, region and nation in early film discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Welle</surname>
                           <given-names>John P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I<italic>n Early Cinema in Russia and Its Cultural Reception</italic>, Yuri Tsivian reconstructs the response to early cinema of an educated Russian public. In describing the methodology he adopts for analysing written traces of early cinema, he writes:</p>
                     <p>At the input we have a simple moving image, at the output we get a “reception text” ... The task of those who take up the study of cultural reception is quite similar to that of the Rorschach psychologist: to summarize and interpret the recurrent associations and fixed ideas that each culture reads into the “moving smudges” of early cinema.</p>
                     <p>Tom Gunning describes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Wondrous pictures in Istanbul:</title>
                     <subtitle>from cosmopolitanism to nationalism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Balan</surname>
                           <given-names>Canan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay presents a panorama of the evolution of viewing conventions in Istanbul, in the late 19th and early 20th centuries (from the 1890s to the 1930s). Within the Ottoman Empire, Westernist, Turkist and Islamist schools of thought were in keen competition when the cinématographe arrived in Istanbul, in 1896. Traces of the discursive space configured by these schools are quite visible in Turkish cultural history, specifically in the history of cinematic spectatorship. A set of binary oppositions – between East and West, between National and International, and, finally, between Islamist and Secular – dominated the framework for reactions to the cinématographe.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>The emergence of nationally specific film cultures in Europe, 1911–1914</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garncarz</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this essay, I wish to introduce the notion of “national film culture”, trace the process of the emergence of nationally specific film cultures in Europe, and offer an explanation for that emergence, which I hope will be fruitful for the USA and other countries as well.¹ Germany will be my main case study because it has been the focus of my empirical research on early cinema. Through the notion of national film culture I wish to avoid the usual ideological and essentializing connotations implicated in the term “nation”. As a concept, national film culture aims to define popular culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>The Norwegian municipal cinema system and the development of a national cinema</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Iversen</surname>
                           <given-names>Gunnar</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his latest book, Messages (2005), Brian Winston lashes out in typical parent terrible fashion against the concept of nationality in media history. “It is not for nothing that the industry has always been organised around ‘territories’ and ‘markets,’ not ‘nations’”, he writes before concluding, “Film ‘nations’ are the concern of criticism, history and cultural politics”.¹</p>
                     <p>Cinema was from the outset a matter of transnational co-operation. Ideas of national identity and national policies regulating the film business, however, shaped several aspects of film production, distribution, and exhibition. Most obviously, national film production involved strategies of opposition to, and resistance against,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>Spanish lecturers and their relations with the national</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sánchez-Salas</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay addresses the question of how the concept of the national provides a context for the work of the Spanish lecturer in early cinema. As is well known, previous studies have always stressed that the film lecturer was responsible for mediating between the screen and viewers, for whom, at least in the beginning, moving pictures were something strange.¹ Also we should not forget that he was dealing with a specific public, determined not only by the period of time, but also by the location. Generally, histories of early cinema have analysed film lecturing from a local perspective. In the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>Joseph Dumais and the language of French-Canadian silent cinema</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lacasse</surname>
                           <given-names>Germain</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The rampant and winged vulgarity that is infiltrating our lives by means of the cinema, the gramophone, and even more so by the radio, the emporium and other establishments where articles, often overpriced, are sold cheap, is starting to trouble the informed public, people who value traditions as much as they value our forefathers’ language.”¹</p>
                     <p>Between 1910 and 1960 or so, the religious authorities in Québec as well as the lay conservatives who supported them would voice that opinion, a quotation from Joseph Dumais, an odd character who was a renowned diction teacher in the early 20th century. He also</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>Localizing serials:</title>
                     <subtitle>Translating daily life in Les Mystères de New-York (1915)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Canjels</surname>
                           <given-names>Rudmer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Near the end of 1915, the young French writer Philippe Soupault witnessed an unprecedented cinematic inundation that flooded Paris and left distinctive markers in French daily life.</p>
                     <p>One day you saw huge posters, as long as snakes, stretching out along the walls. At each street corner a man, his face covered with a red handkerchief, was pointing a revolver at the unconcerned passersby. You thought you heard galloping, a motor kicking over, screams of death. We descended on the cinemas and understood that everything had changed. Pearl White’s smile appeared on the screen; this almost ferocious smile announced the upheavals</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>Seeing the world while staying at home:</title>
                     <subtitle>slapstick, modernity and American-ness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keeler</surname>
                           <given-names>Amanda R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between 14 January 1915 and 22 April 1915, Mabel Normand and Roscoe “Fatty” Arbuckle released six films in the “Mabel and Fatty” series for Keystone Films, including<italic>Mabel and Fatty’s Wash Day</italic>,<italic>Mabel and Fatty’s Simple Life</italic>,<italic>Fatty and Mabel at the San Diego Exposition</italic>,<italic>Mabel, Fatty and the Law</italic>,<italic>Mabel and Fatty’s Married Life</italic>, and<italic>Mabel and Fatty Viewing the World’s Fair at San Francisco</italic>. A year later they made a seventh film in the same series titled<italic>Fatty and Mabel Adrift</italic>, longer and more elaborate than the previous six mentioned.¹ Throughout the 1910s Normand and Arbuckle made numerous</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>“A purely American product”:</title>
                     <subtitle>tramp comedy and white working-class formation in the 1910s</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>King</surname>
                           <given-names>Rob</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>236</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In February 1915, Jeff Davis, the self-styled “King of the Hobos”, took the stage of New York’s Hammerstein’s theater to give audiences a tramp’s perspective on their nation’s history. America, Davis explained, was a nation founded on the tramp spirit. “He said Christopher Columbus was the first hobo ‘gink’ – since Queen Isabella had to ‘ stake him’ for the trip over.” Yet, while Davis admired Columbus as a hobo prototype, he was less enthusiastic about others who had followed the explorer’s trans-Atlantic journey: he ended his act by calling for immigration restriction, the better to give the American-born a shot</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26</label>
                     <title>The “Chinese” conjurer:</title>
                     <subtitle>orientalist magic in variety theater and the trick film</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Solomon</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the main roles in the ballet<italic>Parade</italic>, the historic collaboration that brought Jean Cocteau, Pablo Picasso, and Erik Satie together with Serge Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes, is the “Chinese” Conjurer. Set outside of a fairground show, this 1917 one-act<italic>ballet réaliste</italic>features a series of performers whose feats are meant to draw paying spectators inside. The ballet’s eponymous “parade” began with a dance choreographed and performed by Léonide Massine that consisted of a series of leaps and an elaborate pantomime of several conjuring tricks: drawing an egg from his sleeve, swallowing it, and producing it from his toe, then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>27</label>
                     <title>A note on the national character of early popular science films</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gaycken</surname>
                           <given-names>Oliver</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Various nations produced popular science films during the first twenty years of cinema history. The first systematic production of films on scientific topics for a wide audience came about in England, where F. Martin Duncan’s “The UnseenWorld” series, made for the Charles Urban Company, debuted in 1903. In late 1909 and early 1910, there was a flourishing of<italic>films de vulgarisation scientifique</italic>in France, following the success of Jean Comandon’s microcinematographic films produced for Pathé-Frères. In the USA, George Kleine published a catalogue of educational subjects in 1910, and soon thereafter the Edison Manufacturing Company made a foray into popular</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>28</label>
                     <title>European melodramas and World War I:</title>
                     <subtitle>narrated time and historical time as reflections of national identity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nasta</surname>
                           <given-names>Dominique</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Andrin</surname>
                           <given-names>Muriel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present essay is an attempt to set the bases for a theory of trans-national identity based on philosopher Paul Ricoeur’s discussion of<italic>mimesis</italic>in his seminal three-volume collection of essays,<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>.¹ Having re-read Ricoeur on several occasions, we have come to the conclusion that his discussion of the dichotomy<italic>narrated time/historical time</italic>, which draws on Aristotle, quite surprisingly fits the contents and style of several European films from the early 1910s.</p>
                     <p>Our particular focus on the relationship between five European melodramas shot between 1913 and 1915 – in France, Belgium, Denmark, Italy and Germany – and the context surrounding</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>29</label>
                     <title>“Cow-punchers, bull-whackers and tin horn gamblers”:</title>
                     <subtitle>sensational literature, and early American cinema</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Phillips</surname>
                           <given-names>W. D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On September 25, 1907, the American Mutoscope &amp; Biograph Company began to advertise<italic>Terrible Ted</italic>, a one-reel comedy directed by Joseph A. Golden, in which a pre-pubescent protagonist falls asleep reading the story paper<italic>Wild West Weekly</italic>¹ and dreams himself into an episodic series of sensational adventures before being wakened by his mother in the parlor of their bourgeois home. This film has previously been discussed by several other early cinema scholars,² yet for the purposes of this essay it is noteworthy primarily for its lampooning of sensational story forms popularized by the cheap print industry (dime novels, story papers,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>30</label>
                     <title>Early ethnographic film and the museum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fuhrmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Wolfgang</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ethnographic use of motion pictures has generally been considered lagging in comparison to the growing worldwide popularity of cinema in the early 20th century.¹ Although largely true, recent studies suggest that the situation in Germany did not follow this pattern. As Martin Taureg has shown, German ethnography’s theoretical focus on material culture combined with the country’s cinema reform movement to produce a notable early interest in the use of motion pictures as both research tool and teaching aid.² Nonetheless, what sounds like another German<italic>Sonderweg</italic>(special path) in the history of the ethnographic film requires further qualification.</p>
                     <p>Certainly, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>31</label>
                     <title>Black hair, black eyes, black heart:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theda Bara and race suicide panic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hain</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dark, exotic image of Theda Bara (Theodosia Goodman, 1885–1955), a transitional figure between late Victorian propriety and early 20th-century modernity, embodied a host of fears and desires felt by American audiences in the 1910s. Towards the end of 1915, the year that Bara shot to fame as “The Vampire” in a clumsy but wildly popular film called<italic>A Fool There Was</italic>(1914), her studio, Fox Film Corporation, issued a publicists’ report stating that in the past year, 162 babies had been named “Theda”. That the press release enthusiastically proclaimed that these newborns were “all white!”¹ speaks of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>32</label>
                     <title>Who is the “right” star to adore?:</title>
                     <subtitle>nationality, masculinity and the female cinema audience in Germany during World War I</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haller</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the early 20th century, movie stars often seemed to offer everything that real men did not. This essay explores how the female cinema audience in Imperial Germany responded to male movie stars and how their emerging movie fandom was linked to the contemporary discourse about nationality, national identity and patriotism during World War I. A telling example for this discussion is the German fan magazine debate about whether or not it was acceptable to “adore” the Norwegian actor Gunnar Tolnaes, who played characters as “foreign” as an Indian maharaja, instead of the German supreme commander, Paul von Hindenburg.</p>
                     <p>After</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>33</label>
                     <title>From Switzerland to Italy and all around the world:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Joseph Joye and Davide Turconi collections</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yumibe</surname>
                           <given-names>Joshua</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay discusses the Joseph Joye and Davide Turconi Collections: two interconnected collections that derive from film prints originally distributed in Switzerland and Germany at the turn of the century. After their initial release, a Jesuit priest, Josef Joye, collected the prints from the second-hand market and used them for educational and religious purposes in the Protestant region of Basel, Switzerland during the 1900s and early 1910s. While the prints were used in a specific local and national context, they also have gone on to re-circulate in various transnational contexts. In the 1960s the Italian film historian, Davide Turconi, inspected</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>34</label>
                     <title>The imagination of early Hollywood:</title>
                     <subtitle>movie-land and the magic cities, 1914–1916</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bean</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>332</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What does it mean to speak of “movie-land”? In her 1915 essay for<italic>Feature Movie Magazine</italic>, reporter Edith Johnson obsessively lauds the land of movies as a locus of the “real”, a topography far removed from the parameters of the stage where “painted scenery, lights, etc., all add to the illusion”. But “[i]n movieland”, she intones, “there is real scenery, the forests and streams form the backgrounds, and when the brave girl plunges into the sea ... she is required to take a real plunge into a real-for-sure sea”.¹ Not everyone, of course, appreciated a “real-for-sure sea”, and it may</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Editors and contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>343</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzncx.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
