<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16311j0</collection-id>
      <volume>12.1</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ignatius, of Loyola, Saint, 1491-1556 Exercitia spiritualia</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spiritual exercises</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Water</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Matter of Life and Death</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Habel</surname>
               <given-names>Norman</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Trudinger</surname>
               <given-names>Peter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781921511752</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781921817359</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>ATF Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Hindmarsh, SA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt163t9p7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This volume of essays deals with the critical issue of water and a lack of it. It deals with the scientific, theological, biblical and social issues.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="268"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>Water: A Matter of Life and Death</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Habel</surname>
                           <given-names>Norman</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many of us have sat with Jesus beside Jacob’s well. We have been struck by that remarkable moment when Jesus asks for water from a Samaritan woman who came to draw water from the well. She is amazed that Jesus would ask for water from a Samaritan. Jews and Samaritans did not share—especially water.</p>
                     <p>Jesus breaks the barrier. She is not unclean or alien in his eyes. She is accepted and invited not only to share water, but also to share the water of life which Jesus offers. She is no longer an outcaste. She is a sister who</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Thou Shalt not Covet the Environment’s Water</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Paton</surname>
                           <given-names>David C</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Murray-Darling Basin stretches from southern Queensland across most of New South Wales and into Victoria and South Australia, and has been described as Australia’s food bowl. By the last decade of the twentieth century, eighty per cent of the most profitable farm enterprises within Australia were within the Basin. Economic wealth and productivity grew from the ability to extract water from the rivers of the basin for irrigation. The growth in irrigation during the second half of the twentieth century largely went on without careful consideration of the quantities of water available and little appreciation of the variability in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Australian Water Law:</title>
                     <subtitle>Property, The Constitution and an Anticommons Tragedy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Babie</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brindal</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any treatment of the water resource in Australia must, inevitably, confront the murky depths of its legal and political regulation, found both in common law emanating from courts and in legislation enacted by Parliaments. We use the plural here, for this law developed over centuries, first in England, Australia’s legal ancestor, and then, having been received as a consequence of the English acquisition of sovereignty, in the Australian courts and Commonwealth, State and Territory Parliaments. Make no mistake: coming to terms with water law is no easy task. Indeed, those who are expert in the area have spent years developing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Rising Sea, Drifting Bones, Dispersing Homes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Havea</surname>
                           <given-names>Jione</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter engages some of the trials with which the rising sea gifts islanders in Oceania, and beyond.¹ Whether climate change or global warming causes the sea to rise, and rise, perpetuated by human action or not, is beyond the focus of this chapter. My concern is with an existential predicament: the sea is rising on the shores of Oceania and this pushes islanders (1) to rethink our beliefs and understandings, (2) to grieve at the unearthing of the remains of ancestors from beach-front graves, and (3) to relocate our understandings of homes and gathering sites because they are no</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Water:</title>
                     <subtitle>More than a Symbol</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ayre</surname>
                           <given-names>Clive W</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When astronomers gaze out into deep space, or examine the Martian landscape, one of the things they are seeking is an indication of the presence of liquid water, and the reason is a simple one. Water means the possibility of life. It is quite literally a matter of life and death, both for human and all other life on planet Earth.</p>
                     <p>My aim in this paper is to consider water first as a religious symbol, but then also as something far more than that. My approach is based on a practical theology paradigm in which theory and praxis interact in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abraham, Isaac and the Problem of Water</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deutschmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Barbara</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Various assumptions are made by this writer as she takes up the task of pursuing the water traditions of the book of Genesis. The most important is that these ancient pericopes are all worthy of scrutiny in their own right and not just as passing places on the way to some bigger theme.¹ A respectful engagement with the texts of these ancient stories reveals much about the artistry of the writers and the earthiness of the God who gave rise to them.</p>
                     <p>The other assumption is that the physical settings of the stories are essential to those stories and provide</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Story of Jonah as Told by the Sea</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Person</surname>
                           <given-names>Raymond</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stroede</surname>
                           <given-names>Phoebe</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>In Conversation with Jonah,</italic>Person develops his own reader-response approach to the Jonah narrative by combining observations from the field of conversation analysis with the reader-response theory of Wolfgang Iser.¹ He discusses the different narrative elements of the Jonah story (plot, character, atmosphere, and tone) and provides a reader-response commentary—that is, a commentary by the implied reader of the text. According to Iser, the ‘implied reader’ cannot be located within the text or even outside of the text in actual readers, but must be found in the ‘interaction between text and reader’.² In this interaction, ‘text’ and ‘reader’</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Partnering the Waters in Luke 8:22–25</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Elvey</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years the predictions of climatologists that climate change is likely to prompt an increased frequency of extreme weather events seem to have been borne out in the experience of Australians. On Saturday 7 February 2009, fuelled by extreme heat and years of drought, fires swept through forests and towns to the north and east of Melbourne, Australia. In fires too fierce to fight and too swift to outrun, just over 170 people lost their lives; whole towns such as Marysville were destroyed, and countless native and domestic animals died or were injured. Around the same time, parts of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>‘Give the Girl a Drink’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading John 4 from a Dry, Parched Land</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cadwallader</surname>
                           <given-names>Alan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I begin to offer a reading of one of the most famous stories of early Christianity, that of the encounter over water between Jesus and the Samaritan woman, two potent realities stand before Australians. The first is the ongoing issue of sale by tender of a large cotton farm, Cubbie station, which is in southern Queensland. The second is a report into the state of the freshwater breeding ground for pelicans on the Coorong waterways in south-eastern South Australia (a stretch of water made famous by the book and film called ‘Storm Boy’).</p>
                     <p>Cubbie Station is far from unique</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>To Hear what Water is Saying to the Churches</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Daly-Denton</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret M</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, as more and more Christian traditions retrieve the ancient practice of baptism by immersion, there has been increasing scope for artists to create baptismal pools that give visual expression to the rich symbolism that Christianity has traditionally attached to water. The new baptismal fonts at Salisbury Cathedral and the Cathedral of Our Lady of the Angels in Los Angeles, both dramatically located at the entry point to the liturgical space and both featuring the flow of ‘living’ water, are particularly inspiring examples. Reflecting on this development, the liturgist Gordon Lathrop expresses the hope that the sight of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt163t9p7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
