<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Genre Theory and Historical Change</book-title>
         <subtitle>Theoretical Essays of Ralph Cohen</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rowlett</surname>
               <given-names>John L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>27</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813940120</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813940125</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Virginia Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Charlottesville; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1v2xtv6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Ralph Cohen was highly regarded as the visionary founding editor of<italic>New Literary History</italic>, but his own theoretical essays appeared in such a scattering of publications that their conceptual originality, underlying coherence, and range of application have not been readily apparent. This new selection of twenty essays, many published here for the first time, offers a synthesis of Cohen's vital work.</p>
         <p>In these pages Cohen introduces change and continuity as essential modes of discourse in the study of literary behavior, an approach that can produce reliable narratives of literary, artistic, and cultural change. Here Cohen conceptualizes and develops a compelling, innovative theory of genre that promotes a systematic study of historical change, offering rewarding insights for twenty-first-century scholars.</p>
         <p>This collection of essays is a distillation of the scholarship of renowned literary genre theorist Ralph Cohen.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="432"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Editor’s Note</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Providing contemporary literary studies with the most adequate and compelling theory of genre available, Ralph Cohen has made accessible to scholars everywhere a systematic historical procedure for generating reliable explanatory narratives of literary, artistic, and cultural change. Such an extraordinary claim may seem extravagant and he would never have made it himself. Yet he would urge readers to weigh its legitimacy, a challenge now made possible with the collection of these transformative essays, eight of which are published here for the first time.</p>
                     <p>Ralph Cohen needs no introduction. However, introducing his theoretical papers is necessary because he never collected his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On the Interrelations of Eighteenth-Century Literary Forms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Modern critics, in discussing neoclassical genres, have insisted on the rigidity of forms, while acknowledging that eighteenth-century critics disagreed about and poets seemed to diverge from this “rigidity.” Austin Warren wrote: “That genres are distinct—and also should be kept distinct—is a general article of Neo-Classical faith. But if we look to Neo-Classical criticism for definition of genre or method of distinguishing genre from genre, we find little consistency or even awareness of the need for a rationale.”¹ James Sutherland, in<italic>A Preface to Eighteenth Century Poetry,</italic>declared: “You knew where you were with Pastoral, Elegy, Epic, and the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Origins of a Genre:</title>
                     <subtitle>Descriptive Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem I have set for myself—the origins of a genre: descriptive poetry—belongs to the area of historical poetics (within the larger domain of historical semiotics). Such an inquiry I take to be central to the question: How do literary works relate to one another diachronically or synchronically? The genesis of a genre presupposes that “genre” is a proper and valuable theoretical concept; I shall argue that it is, but it seems reasonable to draw attention to two types of antigenre argument. The first is that every work has its own form and is important only to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Literary Theory as a Genre</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My argument in this paper shall be as follows: literary theory is a literary genre. In consequence of this, literary theory has generic continuity, while undergoing changes in its parts and functions. It is interrelated with other genres in terms of parts and methods, and it is analyzable with them as a member of a group, movement, or period. By considering literary theory as a genre, I mean to eliminate the following as redundant or meaningless questions: Is literary theory nonhistorical? Is literary theory cumulative? Is literary theory modeled upon scientific theory? Is a literary theory verifiable? Is literary theory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Joys and Sorrows of Literary Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I call this essay “The Joys and Sorrows of Literary Theory” because literary theory is a deliberate form of human action, of writing, and all such actions have consequences that range from joy to sorrow for the actors and the audience. My allusion to<italic>The Joy of Sex</italic>and<italic>The Sorrows of Young Werther</italic>is neither accidental nor arbitrary. The pleasures of the text and the anxiety of deconstruction are but two aspects of modern theory, but they do serve to indicate the passion with which theorists write theory. Roland Barthes has described the different pleasures of a text, including</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>History and Genre</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I call this paper “History and Genre” though history is a genre and genre has a history. It is this interweaving between history and genre that I seek to describe. In<italic>The Political Unconscious</italic>Fredric Jameson wrote that genre criticism has been “thoroughly discredited by modern literary theory and practice.”¹ There are at least three reasons for this. First, the very notion that texts compose classes has been questioned. Secondly, the assumption that members of a genre share a common trait or traits has been questioned, and thirdly, the function of a genre as an interpretative guide has been questioned.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Do Postmodern Genres Exist?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Critics and theorists who write about postmodern texts often refer to “genres” as a term inappropriate for characterizing postmodernist writing. The process of suppression results from the claim that postmodern writing blurs genres, transgresses them, or unfixes boundaries that conceal domination or authority, and that “genre” is an anachronistic term and concept. When critics offer examples of postmodern novels, for example, they cite omniscient authors who are parodied or undermined. They point to selfconscious addresses to the reader in<italic>If on a Winter’s Night</italic>and note the selfconscious foregrounding of literary artifice that undermines the generic assumption that a novel</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Reviewing Criticism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Literary Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>122</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literary theory has joined a host of other subjects that in our time have been pronounced dead: the author, the novel, God, concrete poetry, archetypal and genre criticism. As Terry Eagleton inters literary theory, he finds that from its grave arise the blossoms of a theory of culture. Literary theory, which once seemed the counterpart of scientific theory, has ceased to search for the “method” by which literature could be studied.¹</p>
                     <p>Like scientific method, literary method has turned out to be a fiction. The need to give coherence to literary study has met with grave doubts about the coherence or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Materialities of Communication:</title>
                     <subtitle>Genre/Media</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I begin by positioning myself within this colloquium on “Materialities of Communication.” I use the term “positioning” to note the physical presence of the speaker’s table and the obvious fact that now I am observed as yesterday I was an observer. Let us say that I am a conscious instrumentality of transmitting and receiving communications. I am prepared to accept the notion that I and each of us is a complex system, but clearly systems that are complexly intertwined with other systems.</p>
                     <p>One such intersection is with the persons and their papers and commentaries at the colloquium. My consciousness of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Genre Theory, Literary History, and Historical Change</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last half of the twentieth century generic theory has reemerged as a critical force, in part owing to discussions of genre by Northrop Frye, R.S. Crane, and Rosalie Colie. More recent genre theory has reexamined the novel (Michael McKeon’s<italic>The Origins of the English Novel</italic>1660–1740), the essay (Alexander J. Butrym’s<italic>Essays on the Essay: Redefining the Genre</italic>), the short story (Susan Lohafer and Jo Ellyn Clarey’s<italic>Short Story Theory at a Crossroads</italic>), satire, elegy, lyric, tragedy, and others. New theories of genre had been advanced by Mikhail Bakhtin in his work on Dostoevsky and in translations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What Are Genres?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Genres exist in nonverbal activities no less than in verbal. There are history paintings, portrait paintings, abstract paintings, as there are kinds of architecture and music genres. But if we wish to describe or explain or interpret these genres we use language—descriptive explanations and interpretation are themselves genres. I make this acknowledgment in order to indicate the range of this paper: I limit myself to our statements about speech and written genres. Since this is the first paper to be presented at this conference on genre, I want to assess the situation of genre criticism and theory as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Innovation and Variation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Literary Change and Georgic Poetry</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of literary history inevitably involves the study of literary change, and any explanation of change must distinguish among the types of change that are possible. These include changes within the work of a single writer, changes among different writers who share common ends, like the Scriblerus group (this can include, as well, changes in what are called “schools,” “movements,” and “periods”), changes in the forms of genres, changes in style, changes in critical interpretation. It is apparent that the term “change” identified with these many different literary situations—and they are not all that one can name—needs</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Historical Knowledge and Literary Understanding</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My argument shall be that the historical study of literature is a necessary condition for any literary analysis. As critics and scholars, we invoke historical assumptions in our practice, our methods, and our theory. The problem, therefore, is to present a conception of historical knowledge and literary understanding that will acknowledge this phenomenon and make practice consonant with it. And to do this, one must begin by recognizing the historical nature of literary study. In this essay I shall be using examples from my own work in progress—a study of literary change from Milton to Keats—and although I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Some Thoughts on the Problems of Literary Change 1750–1800</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Literary change is intertwined with problems of individual change and social change. Human beings undergo physiological as well as cultural changes just as societies undergo institutional, political, religious, and technological changes. Although in our time concern with all types of change has become common because of the increased rapidity of social and technological changes, the desire, even need, to understand change in the Western world has a long philosophical history, as can be seen from the remarks of Heraclitus and Parmenides.</p>
                     <p>To confine one’s inquiry to a very limited segment of time and to confine it to a body of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Literary History and Literary Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although I shall address myself to literary history and literary theory, because this relation is central to our time, this is not the traditional relation that, for centuries, interested scholars. The traditional contrast established by Aristotle was between<italic>history</italic>and<italic>poetry.</italic>He distinguished between them by declaring that “poetry is something more philosophic and of graver import than history, since its statements are of the nature rather of universals, whereas those of history are singulars. By a universal statement I mean one as to what such or such a kind of man will probably or necessarily say or do—which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Propaedeutic for Literary Change</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I wish in this short paper to touch on three aspects of literary change: (1) the nature of change; (2) the kinds of change; (3) explanations of change. I do not wish to debate the meanings of the term “literary,” and I shall, therefore, assume that what is “literary” is what authors, critics, theorists have identified at the same time or at different times as “literary.” The fact that such authorities may disagree about the significance of “literary” will in no way affect the inquiry I propose. My aim is to offer a propaedeutic for a study of literary change.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Generic History as New Literary History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It gives me great pleasure to return to the University of Konstanz because it is here that Hans Robert Jauss elaborated his theories of aesthetic reception and hermeneutical analysis, and it is here that Wolfgang Iser propounded his theories of the act and process of reading and of functional history. For more than a decade the three of us have collaborated in presenting to scholars the values of literary theory and its importance for the study of literature. I take this occasion to acknowledge their important contributions not only to<italic>New Literary History</italic>but to the study of literature in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Generation of Conceptual Changes in Literary Study</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since a centennial is an opportunity to look backward and forward, I have chosen a subject that I feel is appropriate to the occasion: the generation of conceptual changes in literary study. The kind of changes I refer to are what Foucault called epistemic changes, what Meyer Abrams has characterized as a change from a pragmatic to an organic orientation, what the anthropologist Clifford Geertz calls “an alteration of the principles of mapping. Something is happening to the way we think about the way we think.”¹ The conceptual change I refer to is what Brian McHale and other postmodern critics</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interpreting Interpretations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Poetry and Repression</italic>Harold Bloom remarks that every strong poem, at least since Petrarch, has known implicitly what Nietzsche has taught us explicitly: that there is only interpretation, and that every interpretation answers an earlier interpretation, and then must yield to a later one. But this statement is undercut by another made at the outset:</p>
                     <p>Strong poets present themselves as looking for truth<italic>in the world,</italic>searching in reality and in tradition, but such a stance, as Nietzsche said, remains under the mastery of desire, of instinctual drives. So, in effect, the strong poet wants pleasure and not truth;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Renewing the Eighteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The past decade has seen the publication of<italic>The New Eighteenth Century</italic>(1987), “A New History of the Enlightenment?” (1992), and a considerable number of reinterpretations of the century. Writing the interpretation of an earlier historical time, contemporary critics and theorists correctly insist that they see the past through the eyes of the present. But what in our divided and fragmented world governs our visions or perceptions of the past? We insist on the need for self-reflection, on the analysis of our principles, but these are inevitably governed and constricted by the perceptions we have received and constructed.</p>
                     <p>It is,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Generating Literary Histories</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>358</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My aim here is to inquire why and how some recent literary histories have come to be written or rewritten. I consider this inquiry important because it challenges us to understand our own desire for historicity, our sense of our own mortality; not only because we are conscious of a nuclear possibility, but because in this century we have become conscious of the readiness of human beings to end the lives of others. We live with the consciousness of what has been repressed, and despite our desire to expose the repressed, there always remains a remnant that eludes us. This</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography of Ralph Cohen’s Essays</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>375</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1v2xtv6.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>383</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
