<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Reading Daniel as a Text in Theological Hermeneutics</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hebbard</surname>
               <given-names>Aaron B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227173640</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227903421</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Wipf and Stock</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf34k"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Reading Daniel as a Text in Theological Hermeneutics sets out to read the book of Daniel as a narrative textbook in the field of theological hermeneutics. Employing such disciplines as historical criticism, literary criticism, narrative theology, and hermeneutics, this work seeks to maintain an interdisciplinary outlook on the book of Daniel. Two inherently linked perspectives are utilized in this reading of Daniel. First is the perception that the character of Daniel is the paradigm of the good theological hermeneut; theology and hermeneutics are inseparable and converge in the character of Daniel. Readers must recognize in Daniel certain qualities, attitudes, abilities, and convictions well worth emulating. Essentially, readers must aspire to become a Daniel. Second is the standpoint that the book of Daniel on the whole should be read as a hermeneutics textbook. Readers are led through a series of theories and exercises meant to be instilled into their theological, intellectual, and practical lives. Attention to readers is a constant endeavor throughout this thesis. The concern is fundamentally upon contemporary readers and their communities, yet with sensible consideration given to the historical readerly community with which contemporary readers find continuity. Greater concentration is placed on what the book of Daniel means for contemporary readers than on what the book of Daniel meant in its historical setting. In the end, readers are left with difficult challenges, a sobering awareness of the volatility of the business of hermeneutics, and serious implications for readers to implement both theologically and hermeneutically.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="244"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The book of Daniel¹ is all about interpretation, or at least it is according to the reading represented here. This is not to say, of course, that what we are about to embark upon is the only reading, nor is it an attempt to debunk the vast amount of historical-critical attention given to Daniel<sup>B</sup>. Quite the contrary; as we will notice, this reading of Daniel<sup>B</sup>not only invites other readings, but nearly insists upon their presence. We must further assert that this reading is not only cognizant of the historical situated-ness of the original text but also—and distinctively—of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>A Hermeneutic Reading of Daniel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our reading of Daniel<sup>B</sup>is consciously hermeneutical, both in theory and practice as the very literature itself demands. Theoretically we read Daniel<sup>B</sup>as a literary construct intended to teach the reader how to go about doing the business of interpretation. We come to these conclusions by means of praxis, by actually doing the business of interpretation. Such a relation between theory and practice becomes indicative of the mysterious points of entry and exit of our hermeneutical circle.</p>
                     <p>In our reading much attention will be given to the role of the reader, but before we begin to read Daniel<sup>B</sup>, we need</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Narration in Daniel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Narration in Daniel<sup>B</sup>makes for one of the most fascinating studies of narration in the Hebrew and Christian canons. Of the sixty-six books of the Protestant Christian canon, none display such intricacies and complexities as multiple narrators, characters as narrators, a Gentile convert as a narrator, and the intermittent shifting of their roles. Each narrator in Daniel<sup>B</sup>has a specific purpose and viewpoint in his narration, and not always are they in complete agreement with each other, or at least this is how it seems on the surface. The coherence of these narrational voices, however, essentially lies in the hermeneutical end;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Introduction to Danielic Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At last we have come to a point when we engage in a close reading of the text of Daniel<sup>B</sup>. This task becomes challenging for several reasons; primarily, since we are viewing the whole corpus of Daniel<sup>B</sup>as an exercise in hermeneutics, the entire narrative must receive comment. Therefore, we must consider the entire book but with a specific agenda, which limits our perspective to only those matters that directly pertain to Daniel<sup>B</sup>as a textbook in hermeneutics, thus distinguishing it from a normative commentary format. The first issue that we must address is the debate that is ongoing in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Undergraduate Courses—Danielic Hermeneutics in Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The introduction to Danielic hermeneutics is laid out in Daniel 1, as we have seen in our previous chapter. The next five chapters of Daniel<sup>B</sup>are presented to the reader primarily by the Narrator with one remarkable story co-narrated by Nebuchadnezzar. Essentially the reader in Daniel 2–6 is being given the theoretical side of hermeneutics, which we shall deem here as the “undergraduate courses” in this Danielic school of hermeneutics.</p>
                     <p>We have established the introductory nature of Daniel 1. Chapter 2 is therefore the first court-tale in a series of five that follow. The initial linguistic switch occurs in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Graduate Courses—Danielic Hermeneutics in Praxis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chapter 7 of Daniel<sup>B</sup>is the beginning of a new section within the narrative; this is not only an overwhelmingly accepted consensus among Danielic historical-critical scholars,³ but it is also a natural division for reading Daniel<sup>B</sup>as an exercise in hermeneutics. While there are precious few issues on which Danielic scholars concur,₄ the division of the book between 2–6 and 7–12 is probably the most agreed upon.Scholars like D. S. Russell₅ and John J. Collins₆ who advocate different sources and dates between the earlier half of the book and the latter half of the book are most pronounced</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Reader as Hermeneut</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have in this reading attempted to find the significance for the pistic, sophic, and interpretive community as it engages in the reading of Daniel<sup>B</sup>. Therefore we have taken the time and effort to display how the contemporary ideal/competent reader might interact with Daniel<sup>B</sup>as text along the way. We reach a point now when our reading of the text is completed and we must make some necessary comments regarding the general implications left for the reader. Rather than a reiteration of the reader’s interaction with smaller episodes, we need to make some broader and more sweeping generalizations about the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf34k.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
