<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1995.9.M63S37 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Motherhood in motion pictures</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mothers in motion pictures</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Motion pictures</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Screening Motherhood in Contemporary World Cinema</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sayed</surname>
               <given-names>Asma</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781772580440</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1772580449</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Demeter Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bradford, ON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Demeter Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1rrd9dn"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Using a variety of critical and theoretical approaches, the contributing scholars to this collection analyze culturally specific and globally held attitudes about mothers and mothering, as represented in world cinema. Examining films from a range of countries including Afghanistan, India, Iran, Eastern Europe, Canada, and the United States, the various chapters contextualize the socio-cultural realities of motherhood as they are represented on screen, and explore the maternal figure as she has been glamorized and celebrated, while simultaneously subjected to public scrutiny. Collectively, this scholarly investigation provides insights into where women’s struggles converge, while also highlighting the dramatically different realities of women around the globe.Using a variety of critical and theoretical approaches, the contributing scholars to this collection analyze culturally specific and globally held attitudes about mothers and mothering, as represented in world cinema. Examining films from a range of countries including Afghanistan, India, Iran, Eastern Europe, Canada, and the United States, the various chapters contextualize the socio-cultural realities of motherhood as they are represented on screen, and explore the maternal figure as she has been glamorized and celebrated, while simultaneously subjected to public scrutiny. Collectively, this scholarly investigation provides insights into where women’s struggles converge, while also highlighting the dramatically different realities of women around the globe.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Intersectional Interventions in Global Cinema:</title>
                     <subtitle>Introducing the Maternal</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SAYED</surname>
                           <given-names>ASMA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the advent of silent film, motherhood has been represented on the big screen across the globe. Mother characters populating the backdrops of cinematic narratives are noteworthy both for what they reflect about culture and for the ways that they affect cultural attitudes and ideas about the roles, relationships, and potentialities of women and mothers. The screen often echoes unrealistic expectations that too often become the model to which women hold themselves and to which their societies likewise measure them. Films are both a product and replication of socio-cultural and political shifts. Examining films from a range of countries and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Obāchan’s Garden:</title>
                     <subtitle>Maternal Genealogies as Resistance in Canadian Experimental Documentary</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WILSON</surname>
                           <given-names>SHEENA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mothers and the experience of motherhood have been historically overwritten by patriarchal practices that accord some lives and certain life stories greater value. Fiction and non-fiction stories by and about mothers—particularly the stories of poor women, working women, and women of colour—have gone largely unrecorded. What remains are patriarchal daughter-centred stories of young women who move from one male protector to another: father to husband to son. As a response to this history of literary and cultural production, the telling of mother-stories can be reclaimed as an act of resistance, whether mothers are telling their own stories, or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>“Every Child Is a Mother’s Blessing”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mothers and Children in Ana Kokkinos’s Blessed</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>THOMPSON</surname>
                           <given-names>VERONICA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ana kokkinos’s 2009 film<italic>Blessed</italic>is based on<italic>Who’s Afraid of the Working Class?</italic>, an Australian play first produced by the Melbourne Workers Theatre in 1997 and directed by Julian Meyrick.<italic>Who’s Afraid of the Working Class?</italic>is comprised of four interwoven narratives each written by a different playwright—“trash” by Andrew Bovell, “money” by Patricia Cornelius, “dream-town” by Melissa Reeves, and “suit” by Christos Tsiolkas. As Julian Meyrick writes in her introduction: the play was “born from anger” at the “vast betrayal the Kennett Government had perpetrated on all Victorians” (Bovell et al 3). Premier Kennett’s Liberal Government, in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Discourses of the Maternal in the Cinema of Eastern Europe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SYWENKY</surname>
                           <given-names>IRENE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Approaching the development of the cinematic tradition in Eastern Europe necessarily calls for a historical contextualization of this phenomenon in the framework of the cataclysmic socio-political changes that shaped the region throughout the twentieth century. Representations of maternal space in films are conditioned by the ideologies and social institutions that shape understandings of women’s role in society, and, as such, they also explore connections between motherhood, social order, and articulations of private and public spheres. Focusing on the cinematic tradition of Eastern Europe, the chapter explores the construction of motherhood from a socio-historical and political perspective during the early Soviet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>(Re)Producing Globalization:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Labouring Maternal Body in Maria Full of Grace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WINGARD</surname>
                           <given-names>JENNIFER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How do the flows of global capital impress themselves on the female body? Much of the feminist literature on globalization discusses the ways women are affected by global economies, politics, and migration. The economic imperative to cross borders, and what this border crossing means to the identities of both communities and individuals, has been examined.¹ This work is vital to understanding how global capital affects the opportunities and identities of those forced to navigate it, but this focus on borders and identities often obscures the ways in which “the body” is affected by the flows of globalization.</p>
                     <p>The body, according</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Don’t Slap Yo’ Gran’Momma:</title>
                     <subtitle>Tyler Perry and Madea</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DREHER</surname>
                           <given-names>KWAKIUTL L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My watching of tyler perry’s play<italic>Madea’s Family Reunion: The Play</italic>marked my first encounter with his matriarch Mabel “Madea” Simmons. This six foot tall black mother who arrives from her sister’s funeral in a satin candy-apple red belted peplum suit holding a cigarette in her hand proved difficult to process. In the play, even her friends and family do not know what to do with her. After the services, the flustered party meets at Madea’s house. A discussion of the elder’s behaviour at the funeral serves as a verbal prelude to Madea’s arrival. “Oh, I don’t know I don’t</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Disrupting and Containing Motherhood:</title>
                     <subtitle>Challenging Subversive Representations in Waitress and Frozen River</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAVIDSON</surname>
                           <given-names>RACHEL D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Instead of feeling excitement or joy upon hearing she is pregnant, Jenna Hunterson, the protagonist of Adrienne Shelly’s 2007 independent film,<italic>Waitress</italic>, resents her unborn child. In the above internal narration, Jenna expresses anger towards her child after her abusive husband finds the pile of cash that she had hoped to use to run away and start a new life; he uses it to purchase a crib. Jenna’s character in<italic>Waitress</italic>stands in stark contrast to the prevailing cultural ideal of “the good mother” stereotype because she is unapologetically anti-motherhood. Similarly, Ray, the leading figure in Courtney Hunt’s 2008 independent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Mother as Failed Communist Muttirepublik in Wolfgang Becker’s Good Bye Lenin!</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WANSINK</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The berlin wall and life behind the iron curtain remain popular topics for German filmmakers. Communist East Germany actually only came into existence after the end of World War II, when Germany was divided into four separate zones, each occupied by Great Britain, France, the United States, and the Soviet Union. In 1949, the Soviets declared the Soviet zone its own country, and the German Democratic Republic (GDR) was born, becoming a satellite country of the Soviet Union. The communist government was a dictatorship, in which the people were denied rights such as the freedom of speech, assembly, and press.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>“Mother-Subjects” in Canadian Film:</title>
                     <subtitle>Off-Focus or Off-Screen?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAWKES</surname>
                           <given-names>TERRI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From my standpoint as an academic, cinema and theatre practitioner, and mother, I am disturbed by what I perceive to be a lack of representation of mothers as central characters in cinema and theatre. In “The Invisibility of Motherhood in Toronto Theatre: The Triple Threat,” I looked at the employment experiences of seven “mother-actors” in the Greater Toronto Area and identified their uniquely inherent challenges in maintaining acting careers within the patriarchal institutions of motherhood (Rich 13), theatre, film, and television (Hawkes 247-269). I examined current maternal theories that can explain what may have contributed to this mother invisibility: shift</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Fortune Favours the Brave:</title>
                     <subtitle>Brenda Chapman’s Efforts to Tell a Mother-Daughter Story of Conflict and Love in a Fairy Tale Film</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PERSHING</surname>
                           <given-names>LINDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LENOX</surname>
                           <given-names>AMANDA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARTINEZ</surname>
                           <given-names>MELISSA DEMI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The 2012 pixar-animated film<italic>Brave</italic>explores the struggles mothers often experience in raising daughters while attempting to negotiate competing interests and societal demands. The mother, Queen Elinor is determined to teach her eldest child Merida the skills that she needs to survive and succeed in the patriarchal culture of tenth-century Scotland. Elinor’s attempts to train her sixteen-year-old daughter to think and act “like a lady” conflict with Merida’s athleticism, youthful exuberance, and liberated visions of self-determination and independence. Brave focuses on the conflicts that Elinor and Merida experience in acting on their divergent worldviews. The female-centred storyline—with a primary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Demeter-Kali Rising:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fierce Mother in Harry Potter</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>IVORY</surname>
                           <given-names>S. HILARY ANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1996, Jungian scholars Marion Woodman and Elinor Dickson claimed that the Great Goddess as Great Mother archetype had initiated a change in the patriarchal “conscience”¹: “[The Great] Mother goes far beyond the passive and pleasant nurturing Mary [mother of Jesus]; she is the Dark Goddess Kali, the Mother who brings creation out of destruction” (7). Based on the popular books, the<italic>Harry Potter</italic>film series, which focuses on the bravery and unshakeable loyalty of young people in the face of impossible evil and overwhelming odds—a basic story line in many classic children’s literary books—supports Woodman and Dickson’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Alien versus Terminator:</title>
                     <subtitle>Representations of Motherhood in Science Fiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JOHNSTONE</surname>
                           <given-names>RACHAEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Science fiction provides a unique opportunity to engage with and rethink ideals of motherhood through its presentation of futuristic and parallel universes as rational alternatives to known reality.¹ As a genre, science fiction questions social norms and breaks down barriers, including sex, race, and class without significant cultural backlash; indeed, the<italic>Star Trek</italic>series was responsible for the first interracial kiss on television. By distorting norms and expectations through the creation of new worlds, and through the inclusion of non-human entities, the genre has reconceptualized stereotypes of ideal motherhood in innovative ways. Often, the portrayal of motherhood is neither a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Mamá de las Mariposas:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cinematic Portrayals of Mercedes Mirabal and Reclaiming Maternal History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ZIMMERMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>TEGAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter compares two twenty-first century Dominican films:<italic>In The Time of the Butterflies</italic>(2001), directed by Mariano Barroso, and<italic>Trópico de Sangre</italic>(2010), directed by Juan Delancer. In particular, I am concerned with the cinematic portrayals of the historical figure Mercedes Reyes de Mirabal (1898-1981), more commonly known as Mamá Mirabal, who was mother of the Dominican Republic’s national heroines, the Mirabal sisters, affectionately referred to as<italic>Las Mariposas</italic>(which translates in English as The Butterflies).¹ The subject matter of both films centres on the lives of the Mirabal family leading up to and after the deaths of three</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>Motherhood and Identity in Contemporary Argentine Cinema</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERNS</surname>
                           <given-names>FERNANDO GABRIEL PAGNONI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Argentine classical films illustrate the reality of a nation built through the efforts of immigrants, who wanted for their children a better life in the young Argentina of the early nineteenth century. In these films, a mother’s role is clear and unambiguous: to sacrifice herself for the sake of her children—even giving her own life if necessary—so that they could be promoted in social, economic, and cultural ways. However, in the1980s, with the return of democracy in Argentina and Latin America, a break happened in the hegemonic discourse of the stereotypical ideal mother figure (as well as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Maligned Mothers:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Coatlicue to La Malinche and Back</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SANTOS</surname>
                           <given-names>CRISTINA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>300</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her book<italic>the monster within</italic>:<italic>The Hidden Side of Motherhood</italic>, practising psychoanalyst Barbara Almond explores the idea of “maternal ambivalence” as the “monster within.” She takes an interdisciplinary approach, pulling from her own medical cases, personal experiences, and literary examples to discuss the “darkside to womanhood” (xiii), when mothering and/or motherhood is not automatically self-fulfilling for a woman (3). Socio-cultural conditions create what Paul Ricoeur might call¹ a “prefiguration” and idealization of the self-sacrificing mother figure that lives (and dies) for her children. But what happens when women are unwilling or unable to fulfill this unobtainable ideal of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Motherhood and Masculinity in Atiq Rahimi’s Syngue Sabour</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DEHNAVI</surname>
                           <given-names>ELLI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Syngue sabour</italic>[<italic>the patient stone</italic>] (2012), directed by Atiq Rahimi, the Afghan-French novelist and filmmaker, is an unconventional film that boldly crosses the red lines of Afghan culture and dares to break the taboos of the fatherland by addressing sex, body, and sensuality, the most denied and hidden aspects of womanhood in traditional Afghan society. The film, which is based on Rahimi’s novel of the same title published in 2008, is the story of a young mother of two children in war-ridden Afghanistan looking after her husband, who is in a coma after being shot in the neck. She finds</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16.</label>
                     <title>Indian Cine-maa:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Body of Patriarchal Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JHAMTANI</surname>
                           <given-names>RAMITA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>340</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For over a hundred years, Bollywood—India’s Hindi language cinema—has cradled and nurtured the dreams, hopes, and fantasies of its growing audiences. Amid the glorious, larger than life portrayals of human relationships, mighty heroes, complex plots, perfect endings, myriad of traditions, and the glitter and glamour, stands the quintessential<italic>maa</italic>—the venerated mother figure, who has come a long way in the past hundred years. While the mother figure has indeed undergone many transformations in popular Bollywood films from the 1950s to the present day, a critical analysis of the celebrated mother characters reveals that regardless of the characterization,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17.</label>
                     <title>The “New” Indian Mothers in Popular Bollywood Films</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>AYOB</surname>
                           <given-names>ASMA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>356</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary bollywood filmmakers are increasingly questioning the links between the depiction of women, patriarchy, and national discourses that were considered normative in the early 1900s. The representation of mother figures in popular Bollywood films¹ has changed considerably over the years. This paper explores the representations of “ diasporic” mother figures as portrayed in popular films post-1990 and takes into consideration the effects of feminist consciousness, which, in turn, has been fuelled by globalization. Indian diaspora audiences are increasingly engaging in processes of identification with the themes of Bollywood films. As Gokulsing and Dissanayake rightfully note, diasporic Bollywood films promote modernization,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18.</label>
                     <title>The Aesthetics of (Dis)Empowered Motherhood in Iranian Cinema (1965–1978)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHEIBANI</surname>
                           <given-names>KHATEREH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>374</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the wake of tremendous changes on political, social, cultural and economic levels, the last thirteen years before the Iranian Revolution of 1979 were the most dynamic years for Iranian national cinema, in both commercial and intellectual areas. Iranian society was on the brink of a revolution that would change the future of a country and the region. At the same time, the Iranian film industry entered a new phase of commercialization that appealed to mass audiences more than ever. The films that were made in this period became a pedestal for the post-revolutionary cinema, which later prospered in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd9dn.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>420</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
