<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Real and the Sacred</book-title>
         <subtitle>Picturing Jesus in Nineteenth-Century Fiction</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GATRALL</surname>
               <given-names>JEFFERSON J. A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472119325</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472120253</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.5339783"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The figure of Jesus appears as a character in dozens of nineteenth-century novels, including works by Balzac, Flaubert, Dickens, Dostoevsky, and others.<italic>The Real and the Sacred</italic>focuses in particular on two fiction genres: the Jesus redivivus tale and the Jesus novel. In the former, Christ makes surprise visits to earth, from rural Flanders (Balzac) and Muscovy (Turgenev) to the bustling streets of Paris (Flaubert), Seville (Dostoevsky), Berlin, and Boston. In the latter, the historical Jesus wanders through the picturesque towns and plains of first-century Galilee and Judea, attracting followers and enemies. In short, authors subjected Christ, the second person of the Christian trinity, to the realist norms of secular fiction. Thus the Jesus of nineteenth-century fiction was both situated within a specific time and place, whether ancient or modern, and positioned before the gaze of increasingly daring literary portraitists. The highest artistic challenge for authors was to paint, using mere words, a faithful picture of Jesus in all his humanity. The incongruity of a sacred figure inhabiting secular literary forms nevertheless tested the limits of modern realist style no less than the doctrine of Christ's divinity.</p>
         <p>The international "quest of the historical Jesus" has been amply documented within the context of nineteenth-century biblical scholarship. Yet there has been no broad-based comparative study devoted to the depiction of Jesus in prose fiction over the same time period.<italic>The Real and the Sacred</italic>offers a comprehensive survey of this body of fiction, examining both the range of its Christ types and the varying formal means through which these types were represented. The nineteenth century-despite forecasts of God's death at the time-not only revived older Christ types but also witnessed the rise of new ones, including<italic>le Christ proletaire</italic>, the Mormon Christ, the Buddhist Christ, and the Tolstoyan Christ. Novelists played a crucial role in the invention and popularization of the historical Jesus in particular, one of modernity's major figures.</p>
         <p>These pioneering works of fiction, written by authors of diverse religious and national backgrounds, laid the formal groundwork for an enduring fascination with the historical Jesus in later fiction and film, from Mikhail Bulgakov's<italic>Master and Margarita</italic>to Mel Gibson's<italic>The Passion of the Christ</italic>. The book is enhanced by a gallery of illustrations of the historical Jesus as depicted by nineteenth-century artists.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="306"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In “Jesus Christ in Flanders” (1831), Honoré de Balzac recounts the fateful voyage of a ferryboat headed for the port of Ostend. The boat embarks with passengers from all walks of life: up front sit a young cavalier, a young lady, her mother, a clergyman, a merchant, a scholar, and the pilot; the “poor people”—including an old soldier, two peasants, a mother, and her baby—sit in the stern.¹ They are joined by a “stranger” (312), the last passenger to board. During the short voyage, a great tempest arises, and as the boat takes on water and begins to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>The Jesus Novel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1830, the English writer Harriet Martineau published a short novel titled<italic>Traditions of Palestine.</italic>Given her trailblazing career as the “first woman sociologist,”¹ Martineau’s biographers tend to reserve no more than passing reference to this youthful work from her oeuvre. Martineau nevertheless claimed to “cherish” this “little volume” alongside<italic>Eastern Life, Past and Present</italic>(1848)—a freethinker’s travelogue to the Holy Land—above all her other writings. After its success in London, the novel was republished in the United States, later translated into French, and reprinted as late as 1892, more than a quarter century after the author’s death.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Pictorial Blasphemy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In May 1850, John Everett Millais’s<italic>Christ in the House of His Parents</italic>was exhibited at the Royal Academy in London, where it provoked a torrent of invective in the press. In Millais’s painting, Christ is depicted as a child apprentice in his father’s carpenter shop. Joseph, Anne, and an assistant laborer hover over a workbench; a young, half-naked John the Baptist walks with a bowl of water amid the wood shavings on the shop floor. The left hand of the boy Jesus, meanwhile, is bleeding from a recent wound, which he holds up for an anxious Mary to see,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Sublime Portrait</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mid-nineteenth-century portraits of Jesus were not as controversial in fiction as they were in realist painting. Whereas John Everett Millais, Nikolai Ge, and Édouard Manet broke with long-standing iconographic traditions, portraits of Jesus in fiction from the same time period were innovative, in large part, by the fact of their existence. Extended literary portraits are not a common feature of premodern imaginative retellings of gospel narrative. The life of Jesus, as the canonical gospels suggest, need not accommodate descriptions of the Christ image. In the 1830s and 1840s, authors of fiction began hesitantly to describe the body of Jesus thanks</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Archaeology of the Christ Image</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two archaeological limits circumscribed the image of the historical Jesus over the second half of the nineteenth century. The first was approached with Raffaele Garrucci’s discovery of a graffito, or “scratching,” at the Palace of the Caesars in Rome in 1856 (see figure 10). That same year, Garrucci, an archaeologist and Jesuit priest, had published a seminal monograph on the graffiti of Pompei.¹ For a small group of scholars and enthusiasts scouring Rome for ancient Christ images, all the scratchings of Pompei would pale in comparison with what Garrucci found carved into the plaster of a beam on the Palatine:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Metapoetics of the Christ Image</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The genres of fiction and painting devoted to the realist Christ can be visualized as an intermedial grid. Along the vertical axis runs a time line connecting the figure of the historical Jesus, at the top, with that of the fully modernized Christ, below. The horizontal axis is divided between fiction, on the left, and painting, on the right. Into each of the four corners are grouped the dozens of works of fiction and scores of paintings throughout the nineteenth century that depict the figure of Jesus in realist style: Jesus novels and historical paintings occupy the top corners; Jesus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Eclipse of the Christ Image</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Lev Tolstoy’s folktale “Where Love Is, There God Is Also” (1884), the protagonist, a pious shoemaker, hears what he believes to be Christ’s voice one night in his sleep: “Martin! Watch outside tomorrow, I’m coming.”¹ The next day, Martin sees, passing before his window, an old man struggling through the snow, a soldier’s wife out begging with her newborn, and an elderly market woman quarrelling with a boy thief. One by one, Martin invites these guests into his home, listens to their troubles, and assists them however he can. At the end of the day, disappointed at not having</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Jesus Movie</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1897, toward the end of the period covered in this book, a new genre emerged alongside the constellation of visual and literary arts dedicated to a realist Christ image: the Jesus movie. There are many ways in which the early history of the Jesus movie echoes that of the Jesus novel more than a half century earlier, from the new genre’s immediate international scope to the hesitant, incremental advance of its pictorial resources. Over the years of 1897 and 1898 alone, French and American production companies, each working in relative isolation, made about half a dozen known Jesus movies,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SELECTED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5339783.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
