<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccg6</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS645 .P785 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Psychology</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Marxist criticism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Postcolonial criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Psychoanalytic Mediations between Marxist and Postcolonial Readings of the Bible</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Liew</surname>
               <given-names>Tat-siong Benny</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Runions</surname>
               <given-names>Erin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780884141679</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780884141662</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>SBL Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1gk0831"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first sustained conversation between Marxism, postcolonialism, and psychoanalysis in biblical studies</p>
         <p>This volume pursues critical readings of the Bible that put psychoanalysis into conversation with Marxist and postcolonial criticism. In these essays psychoanalysis provides a way to mediate between Marxism's materialist groundings and postcolonialism's resistance against empire. The essays in the volume illuminate the way empire has shaped the biblical text by looking at the biblical texts' silences, ruptures, oversights, over-emphases, and inexplicable elements. These details are read as symptoms of a set of oppressive material relations that shaped and continue to haunt the text in the ascendancy of the text in the name of the West.</p>
         <p>Features:</p>
         <p>Essays and responses from multiple perspectives and geographical locations, including Africa, Australia, Oceania, Latin America, and North AmericaPsychoanalysis that considers how the traumas of colonialism manifest both materially and psychicallyClose readings of biblical texts</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="258"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Psychoanalytic Mediations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Runions</surname>
                           <given-names>Erin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liew</surname>
                           <given-names>Tat-siong Benny</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The essays in this volume question whether and how psychoanalytic readings might mediate between the important materialist grounding of Marxism and the poststructuralist analysis of exclusion and oppression in postcolonialism. Taken together, these essays consider how the unconscious workings of the very real material exploitations of capitalism and colonialism (ancient and modern) are variously worked out in the biblical text and its afterlives, via fetish or antifetish, storytelling, silence, dream work, and fantasy.</p>
                     <p>Why this volume, and why now? a reader might ask. Are Marxism and psychoanalysis still going concerns in humanities scholarship? Hasn’t Marxism been questioned as too universalist,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conversations in Africa:</title>
                     <subtitle>Postcolonial and Marxist Hermeneutics, and a Psychoanalytical Fulcrum?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Punt</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeremy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In South African biblical studies, postcolonial work finds itself in an unenviable position. It is often overlooked, notwithstanding the focus and concern of a postcolonial hermeneutical approach to include and give voice to the muted voices of the colonized, the voiceless, the marginalized, or the oppressed. Postcolonial investigations of disproportionate power relationships at the geopolitical as well as subsidiary levels, and at social and personal levels of the powerful ruler and the subaltern, remain un(der) utilized. So, too, do investigations of the interrelationship and debunking of (apparent) distinctions and contrasts between center and periphery.¹ Postcolonial biblical interpretation’s focus on relationships</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Imperial Fetish:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Anti-imperial Readings of the Bible</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boer</surname>
                           <given-names>Roland</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My argument is that the current spate of “anti-imperial” studies of the Bible manifests a fetishism of empire. I understand fetish here in two senses, one in line with Freudian psychoanalysis, in which the fetish marks both the disavowal of castration and the affirmation that the penis is still there, albeit displaced onto another object, the other following a marxist trajectory in which the fetish becomes an element of the socioeconomic context, indicating a transfer of powers between human beings and object fetishized. however, unlike a trend—which really began with Theodor adorno and the Frankfurt school and runs through</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Freud, Adorno, and the Ban on Images</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boer</surname>
                           <given-names>Roland</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is less recognized than it should be that Theodor Adorno’s key noncategory of the<italic>Bilderverbot</italic>, or ban on images, owes as much to overturning sigmund Freud’s argument concerning idolatry as it does to the biblical ban on images. Of course, both bounce their thoughts off the second commandment of Exod 20 (and Deut 5). Yet Freud’s interpretation runs the risk of replicating precisely what the ban seeks to overcome, for the abstraction he espies in the ban is precisely the move that reinstalls idolatry. For this reason, Adorno seeks to deploy the ban on images in a way that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The End-or Medium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Havea</surname>
                           <given-names>Jione</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Talanoa</italic>, among the natives of Oceania, is story, telling, and conversation, together (Havea 2010a). It is not one or the other of those, or one in the place of the others, but one in relation to the other two.<italic>Talanoa</italic>is the three—story, telling, conversation—weaving, multiplying. The three come together as one; they are one. if one receives more attention, that one serves as a reminder for the other two. The one that is at the foreground calls attention to the ones that are not as present or that have been neglected or repressed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Talanoa</italic>—story, telling, conversation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Haunting Silence:</title>
                     <subtitle>Trauma, Failed Orality, and Mark’s Messianic Secret</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liew</surname>
                           <given-names>Tat-siong Benny</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ending of mark’s story of Jesus is “one of the most widely-known problems in New Testament studies, involving both text-critical and exegetical issues” (Hurtado 2009, 427). My teacher in graduate studies, Mary Ann Tolbert, has argued that the seemingly disappointing and tragic ending—with the women disciples leaving the empty tomb in fear and in silence after they were told to tell Jesus’s male disciples the good news of Jesus’s resurrection and a future reunion with them in Galilee in 16:7– 8¹—is Mark’s rhetorical ploy to put the ball on the court of markan listeners and readers, since</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Gospel of Bare Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reading Death, Dream, and Desire through John’s Jesus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liew</surname>
                           <given-names>Tat-siong Benny</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jacques Lacan (2001, 341) has famously declared that “it is not enough to decide on the basis of its effect—Death. it still remains to be decided which death, that which is brought by life or that which brings life.” Of course, for Lacan, whose psychoanalysis has much to do with one’s relations to death and the dead (Luepnitz 2003, 232), there is a difference between biological and psychic death and hence between mortality and vitality. Nevertheless, his statement does highlight, in a delightfully ironic way, how talk about death can—or should—be both specific and ambiguous at the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Psychoapocalypse:</title>
                     <subtitle>Desiring the Ends of the World</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pippin</surname>
                           <given-names>Tina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the ticket line to see<italic>2012</italic>with my “The Politics of Apocalypse” class one semester, we met a woman who was returning for a second viewing of the film because she found it so believable. “This is the way it’s really going to happen,” she shared. “This movie shows exactly how the world is going to end; I have to see it again to catch all the details. after you see it you just want to be nice to people.” This viewer had crossed over into the film’s fantastic vision of the end; in fact, she was an enthusiastic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response:</title>
                     <subtitle>Disseminations (and/or Sublimations) of the Death Drive</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Jennings</surname>
                           <given-names>Theodore W.</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Psychoanalysis may be viewed (following suggestions by Paul Ricoeur [1970] in<italic>Freud and Philosophy</italic>) as a hermeneutics, specifically as a hermeneutics of desire. it traces or tracks the imprint of desire first in the dream and then in a variety of behavioral symptoms (jokes, slips of the tongue, as well as bodily symptoms). This hermeneutics is, however, never simple since desire is constitutionally conflicted, divided, deflected, and disguised. Thus desire is never only or primarily what it seems. it is constitutionally enigmatic. it is this that necessitates something like a science of desire, an analytics of desire.</p>
                     <p>The essays in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Response:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ideology of Universalization</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Petterson</surname>
                           <given-names>Christina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This collection of essays sets out to analyze how psychoanalytical approaches may mediate between or engage with either postcolonial and/or marxist biblical interpretation, producing new ways of understanding all. Judging by the history and end result of this volume, this is easier said than done. Before I begin, I would like to express three hesitations that will inform my response.</p>
                     <p>My first hesitation is that placing the three approaches (postcolonialism, marxism, and psychoanalysis) side by side lends a depth and importance to postcolonialism, while in my opinion it has yet to prove its worth. I should emphasize that I am</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Den Himmel überlassen wir / Den Engeln und den Spatzen”:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Tupiniquim Response</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Silva</surname>
                           <given-names>Fernando Candido da</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In August 1549, only a few months after his arrival at what he called “Terras do Brasil” along with Tomé de Sousa’s armada (first governor-general), Father Manuel da Nóbrega (1955, 57–67) wrote, from the Baía de Todos os Santos to his brethren in Coimbra, an informative letter regarding the Jesuit endeavor in the Americas. In that letter, the future first provincial of the Jesuits in Brazil did more than describing; he projected the dilemmas of<italic>his civilization</italic>in this land “that has a thousand-league coast all populated by people.” The Tupiniquim and Tupinambá—those who “sleep in hammocks made</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ancient Sources Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1gk0831.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Modern Authors Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
