<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt234wk8</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BH81.W66 1999</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Placing Aesthetics</book-title>
         <subtitle>Reflections on the Philosophic Tradition</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wood</surname>
               <given-names>Robert E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780821440452</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0821440454</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Ohio University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Athens</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Robert E. Wood</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1j7x66b"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Examining select high points in the speculative tradition from Plato and Aristotle through the Middle Ages and German tradition to Dewey and Heidegger,<italic>Placing Aesthetics</italic>seeks to locate the aesthetic concern within the larger framework of each thinker's philosophy.In Professor Robert Wood's study, aesthetics is not peripheral but rather central to the speculative tradition and to human existence as such. In Dewey's terms, aesthetics is "experience in its integrity." Its personal ground is in "the heart," which is the dispositional ground formed by genetic, cultural , and personal historical factors by which we are spontaneously moved and, in turn, are inclined to move, both practically and theoretically, in certain directions.Prepared for use by the student as well as the philosopher,<italic>Placing Aesthetics</italic>aims to recover the fullness of humanness within a sense of the fullness of encompassing Being. It attempts to overcome the splitting of thought, even in philosophy, into exclusive specializations and the fracturing of life itself into theoretical, practical, and emotive dimensions.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="432"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>I</label>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fine Art and the Field of Experience</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is surely sense to the notion that one ought to approach every study in terms of empirical acquaintance with the objects of the study. In fact, how else could one begin? Thus in approaching matters aesthetic, one should have firsthand acquaintance with art objects as well as with the beauties of nature and, if possible, with artistic practice. We are surely not exempt from that requirement. However, every study except philosophy begins with certain presuppositions which it is not the task of that study to analyze. Thus Euclidean geometry takes its point of departure from the possibility of beginning</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>II</label>
                     <title>PLATO</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In my treatment of Plato, the first of the great philosophers to address matters aesthetic, I begin to flesh out more fully the framework considerations I have offered in the previous chapter by an interpretation that builds a whole world of meaning, encompassing every aspect of human existence. There is a sense in which one might say that Plato’s philosophy is essentially an aesthetic. Beauty plays a central role in his thought, though he has some harsh things to say about its appearance in art. However, in spite of the latter, his own works exhibit an artistry unmatched in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>III</label>
                     <title>ARISTOTLE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The approach i took in the introduction to locating fine art in the broader scheme of things human was basically Aristotelian. Let us review it at this point. I took an inventory of the uses of the term<italic>art</italic>in ordinary experience, ranging them in a hierarchy of broadest to narrowest usage and setting them in a system of contrasts. At the broadest level art is contrasted to nature. Aristotle expands on that by providing an insight into the nature of a nature: a nature<italic>(phusis)</italic>is a principle of motion and rest, of development and completion, that is intrinsic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IV</label>
                     <title>PLOTINUS AND THE LATIN MIDDLE AGES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though the artistic practice of the Middle Ages was unparalleled, especially in the construction of the cathedrals that housed magnificent sculptural and pictorial works and were filled with the haunting sounds of Gregorian chant, it might not be too far off the mark to claim that, from the point of view of aesthetics (i.e., reflection on the nature of art and beauty), the thought of the Middle Ages was essentially derivative. Indeed, among the major thinkers, the great philosopher-theologians, besides citation and paraphrase of traditional sources, one finds very little sustained treatment of aesthetic matters, and almost nothing of any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>V</label>
                     <title>KANT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once on immanuel kant’s tombstone stood the words, “The starry skies above, the moral law within.”¹ They are taken from the closing paragraphs of his<italic>Critique of Practical Reason</italic>, the second work in his critical project. The beginning of the quotation reads: “Two things fill the heart with ever new and increasing admiration and awe<italic>[Bewunderung und Ehrfurcht]</italic>….”² The starry skies above are the object and model for mechanistic science. In Newtonian mechanics the laws that govern the stars govern all terrestrial motions as well. It was such knowing that furnished the exemplar of knowing analyzed in the first part</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VI</label>
                     <title>HEGEL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A first approach to G. W. F. Hegel may be taken in terms of a comparison between two ideal-typical positions: what I will call the Enlightenment heritage and Orthodox Christian Theology. The approach is ideal-typical in that it develops in terms of a projection of certain tendencies in different thinkers that are viewed as heading toward an ideal term that may be held<italic>in toto</italic>by none of them, but that illuminates tendencies in them all. And I want to approach the three positions—Enlightenment, orthodox Christian, and Hegelian—in three areas: theology, anthropology, and Christology. I take this approach</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VII</label>
                     <title>SCHOPENHAUER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One way of looking at Arthur Schopenhauer’s thought is to view it as a synthesis between Kant and Plato (together with Plotinus) on the one hand and the Indian tradition on the other. Schopenhauer’s early work<italic>On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason</italic>was straight Kantian analysis.¹ Recall in Kant the three levels of form, which function as filters or glasses through which the world of appearance is constituted. The first level is that of the forms of sensibility—space and time—which furnish the encompassing frame of all appearance; the second, the level of the categories</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VIII</label>
                     <title>NIETZSCHE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One might say that the founding experience of Friedrich Nietzsche’s philosophy is the experience of the death of God. It is announced, like Plato’s thought, in poetic form through the Parable of the Madman in<italic>The Gay Science</italic>. Nietzsche describes a madman who lit a lantern in the morning hours and went in search of God, like Diogenes, who claimed that the light of day was not sufficient to reveal an honest man. The madman’s audience of unbelievers mocked him, asking whether God had gotten lost or emigrated. The madman proclaimed that God was dead and that he and they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IX</label>
                     <title>DEWEY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Outside of hegel and Schelling, there is no major philosopher who has devoted as much attention to the aesthetic or given it as central a role as John Dewey. This may come as a surprise to some. In their standard two-volume survey of American philosophy, Elizabeth Flower and Murray Murphey do not even mention Dewey’s<italic>Art as Experience</italic>, in spite of their relatively extensive period-by-period, work-by-work survey of his publications.¹ And yet for Dewey the aesthetic furnishes the basic measure of everything human.</p>
                     <p>The centrality of the aesthetic is linked to the centrality of experience, for in Dewey’s view, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>X</label>
                     <title>HEIDEGGER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From martin heidegger’s first major work,<italic>Being and Time</italic>, his thought has focused on the notion of Being, but the method of his approach was phenomenology, the method characterizing my own introduction. Heidegger’s approach falls in the line of his teacher, Edmund Husserl, the founder of Phenomenology. Husserl understood Phenomenology to be comprehensive philosophy; it is at least permanent prolegomenon, acknowledged or not, to any philosophy. Phenomenology comes from two Greek terms,<italic>phainomenon</italic>, appearance, and<italic>logos</italic>, essence. Phenomenology is a comprehensive descriptive inventory of all the essential ways in which appearance—that is, presence to consciousness—occurs: direct evidence in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>XI</label>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In conclusion, let me summarize, clarify, and extend my leading contentions, focusing discussion on the interrelation of form and what I am calling<italic>the aesthetic center</italic>.¹ In so doing, I will rehearse the primary evidences on which I have rested throughout. I have been developing a series of related theses: first, that human nature is culture creating, condemned by its nature to giving form, to shaping by choice, in itself and its offspring, the potential chaos that ontological openness sets on an animal base; second, that the region aesthetics addresses is the heart as the developed center between intellect, will,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>ON SCULPTURAL PRODUCTION</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>347</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>391</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>410</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1j7x66b.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>414</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
