<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Grecanici of Southern Italy</book-title>
         <subtitle>Governance, Violence, and Minority Politics</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pipyrou</surname>
               <given-names>Stavroula</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>28</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780812292985</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0812292987</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press, Inc.</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PHILADELPHIA</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Pennsylvania Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dfnrzt"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Grecanici are a Greek linguistic minority in the Calabria region of Italy, remnants of a population that has resided there since late antiquity. Their language represents a holdover from the Middle Ages, at least, and possibly even to the Greek colonies of the classical period. For decades the Grecanici passionately fought to be recognized by the Italian state as an official linguistic minority, finally achieving this goal in 1999. Violence, corruption, and mismanagement are inextricable parts of the social fabric, but Grecanici have crafted the means to invert hegemonic culture and participate in the power games of minority politics.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>The Grecanici of Southern Italy</italic>provides a comprehensive ethnography that examines the ways the minority developed and sustain enduring cultural forms of solidarity and relatedness. Stavroula Pipyrou proposes the concept of "fearless governance" to describe overlapping and sometimes contradictory systems of power, authority, and relational networks that enable the Grecanici to achieve political representation at the intersection of local, national, and global encounters. Refuting easy assumptions of top-down governmental influence, Pipyrou shows how the Grecanici find political representation through the European Union and UNESCO, state policy, civic associations, family networks and illegal organizations; not being afraid to take risks, incur wrath, lose friends, or risk death in challenging the political status-quo.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Note on Superscripts for Foreign Words and Phrases</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>The Governance of Endangered People</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I walk with my friend Gianni in his natal village high in the mountains of<italic>area Grecanica</italic>, he suddenly starts speaking in Grecanico. He warns me that if we want to avoid being seen by other villagers who will definitely want to invite us into their homes, an offer we could not refuse, we should head down this dark alley. We are walking side by side with our heads down—thank God he is unable to see the astonishment written across my face. I keep walking and manage to respond in a calm voice that this indeed is a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Meet the Grecanici</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A prolific number of studies on minorities have shed light on the historical and political genealogies of what is meant by minority status in Europe (see Cowan 2000, 2010). Scholars such as Jennifer Jackson Preece (1997), Mark Mazower (2004), and Jane Cowan (2010) examine the historical predicament of developing a comprehensive UN framework toward the protection of minority populations after 1918. Looking at the issue of the minorities from a top-down perspective, these studies delve deeply into the logics of treaties and the thorny position of minority recognition on a pan-European level. Subsequently, nation-state recognition of minorities was a criterion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>The Vicissitudes of Civil Society</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In July 2006, one of the Greek associations in Reggio Calabria, comprised mainly of Greek nationals of the diaspora, invited a high-ranking member of parliament from the governing Greek New Democracy party to visit South Italy. The association acted as a mediator between the mayor of Reggio Calabria, Giuseppe Scopelliti, and the Greek government, and the invitation was intended to foster relations of good will between Reggio Calabria and Athens. According to the president of the Greek association, the meeting was conceived of as a New Democracy initiative toward pastoral care for Greek communities abroad. The association went to great</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Hegemonic Networks, Kinship Governance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kinship, Herzfeld argues, “carried the dead weight of outmoded assumptions” (2007:315). Like Fabian’s (1983) perceptions regarding the subject of anthropology, kinship became the “Other,” perpetually locked in direct association with Africanist structuralist theory. Nevertheless, kinship “has insidiously slipped back everywhere” (Herzfeld 2007:315) and is here to stay. Grecanici kinship is highly politicized and contributes to dense networks of governance and representation. With a strong emphasis on patrilineality, kinship is a political and genealogical order with far-reaching consequences for socioeconomic organization. The coordination of the next generation of relatives is desired by people who know exactly their own lines of relatedness.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Messy Realities of Relatedness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So far I have discussed conventional kinship organization among the Grecanici, based predominantly on sharing the same blood. Alongside blood kin, further lines of relatedness are pursued that create equally strong politicized links between the related parties, thus forming dense networks for minority governance. This chapter discusses<italic>amicizia</italic>(friendship) and<italic>comparatico</italic>or<italic>Sangiovanni</italic>(godparenthood)¹ in order to account for kinship-like arrangements that infiltrate political domains. Civil society factions are predominantly based on friendship, godparenthood, and kinship, creating an ultra-dense matrix for claims to national and international resources available for the governance of the linguistic minority. In their desire to create</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Ancestors, Saints, and Governance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Under the generic rubric “Italian mafia” are classed the four well-known underworld organizations that exist in Italy: Cosa Nostra in Sicily, ’Ndrangheta in Calabria, Camorra in Naples, and Sacra Corona in Puglia (Gambetta 1988; Fentress 2000; Lupo 2009; Dickie 2011). In discourse, the term “mafia” is often used interchangeably with any of the aforementioned “mafias,” as an indicator of specific dispositions and type of organization.</p>
                     <p>’Ndrangheta is one of the most successful networks of political representation in Reggio Calabria that exceeds solely violence and extortion (Gambetta 1988:168–70). In local oral and textual accounts, examined in this chapter, ’Ndrangheta is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>An Invitation to Dance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As we have seen, Grecanici governance is based on elaborate contexts of relatedness, a collapsing spatiotemporal arena encompassing the living and the dead, affective items such as religious relics and icons, divine entities, and associationism. This matrix may also be captured in the persona of ’Ndrangheta. The profile of ’Ndrangheta as oscillating between earthly joys and heavenly possessions allows for a theorization of power as continually reestablished and circulated between humans and nonhumans.</p>
                     <p>Stories about rare mafiosi free gifts, discussed in the previous chapter, drastically influence local perceptions of ’Ndrangheta. Public religious celebrations are another context where ’Ndrangheta personhood can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>Minority on the Fringes of Europe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I left Reggio Calabria, I felt I had left a part of myself back in the field. “Making relatedness” between the ethnographer and the research participants reveals the deep humanistic nature of the ethnographic adventure (Gay y Blasco 2012b). The final story narrates the relationship between Venere and the ethnographer. While Venere is an actual person, she also stands as a metonymy for the complex networks of relatedness present in Reggio Calabria on which fearless governance is built.</p>
                     <p>Venere is a middle-aged woman renowned for her beauty and kindness. I met Venere through her daughter: “My mother adores Greek</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dfnrzt.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
