<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Executed God</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Way of the Cross in Lockdown America</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Taylor</surname>
               <given-names>Mark Lewis</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451492675</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1451492677</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506401454</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506401457</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress Publishers</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>2</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt155j3fk"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The new edition of Mark Lewis Taylor’s award-winning The Executed God is both a searing indictment of the structures of “Lockdown America" and a visionary statement of hope. It is also a call for action to Jesus followers to resist US imperial projects and power. Outlining a “theatrics of state terror," Taylor identifies and analyzes its instruments—mass incarceration, militarized police tactics, surveillance, torture, immigrant repression, and capital punishment—through which a racist and corporatized Lockdown America enforces in the US a global neoliberal economic and political imperialism. Against this, The Executed God proposes a “counter-theatrics to state terror," a declamation of the way of the cross for Jesus followers that unmasks the powers of US state domination and enacts an adversarial politics of resistance, artful dramatic actions, and the building of peoples’ movements. These are all intrinsic to a Christian politics of remembrance of the Jesus executed by empire. Heralded in its first edition, this new edition is thoroughly revised, updated, and expanded, offering a demanding rethinking and recreating of what being a Christian is and of how Christianity should dream, hope, mobilize, and act to bring about what Taylor terms “a liberating material spirituality" to unseat the state that kills.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface to the Second Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>The Executed God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To consider the executed God and the spiritual practices it entails will demand some important preparatory work. Christians have written a great deal on the notion of Jesus’ crucifixion and death. What new turn is taken when we emphasize today, as this book does, that Jesus’ death was an execution?</p>
                     <p>I will begin by acknowledging the ways some traditional theologians have spoken of Jesus’ death as disclosing a “crucified God” and will then suggest the difference it makes to speak of an “executed God.” In Baldwin’s terms, this concept of an executed God, I suggest, can help make us “larger,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part I. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“We are trapped in the jaws of something shaking the life out of us.” With these words from his historical novel,<italic>Philadelphia Fire</italic>, John Edgar Wideman conveys a sense of what it means to be caught out on stage, vulnerable at the point of having one’s life taken, shaken out, by what I have term “the theatrics of state terror.” Wideman’s discernment carries rage and lament. It is full of frustration and fear. There is consternation and a vexed wrestling with the entrapping “jaws” that belong … well, to “something.” State terror’s theatrics are like that, unleashing forces that brutalize</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Lockdown America:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Theater of Terror</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In my own church in Trenton, New Jersey, Tamika rose, with all of her thirteen years of age, to share a concern before the adults went to their “Prayers of the People” during Sunday morning worship. “We had a hard week in school,” she shared. “For two days we were on lockdown.” Her metaphor of<italic>lockdown</italic>was applied to her classmates’ being denied study hall privileges, but it is derived from the world of prison life. Today’s children and youth often use the metaphors of prison life to portray their own lives outside of prison. In 1995, when mass incarceration’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Theatrics and Sacrifice in the U.S.-Led Imperium</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The overall argument of this chapter is that the state terror that targets poor communities<italic>within</italic>the United States, and racialized ones in particular,¹ is also part of the U.S. state’s pursuit of a<italic>global</italic>sovereignty. The U.S. deploys abroad both “soft power” (cultural influences and ideologies of U.S. “American exceptionalism”) as well as the brutal economic policies of neoliberal capitalism. These ways of pursuing global sovereignty are regularly supported by the threat or actuality of the terrors of overt or covert war. Lockdown America is, then, a<italic>national</italic>site of state terror that is also integral to a<italic>global</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Part II. Introduction]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Howard Thurman, in<italic>Jesus and the Disinherited</italic>, writes of a Christianity born as a “technique of the oppressed” in imperial Rome.¹ Part Two traces that technique’s appearing today as a “counter-theatric to state terror” in Lockdown America. Crucial to this technique is what Thurman points to as the “vital content” of the concept of love for the enemy. This can seem ludicrous. What force might any such concept of love have today given the opposition we face from Lockdown America, sustained by its histories of indigenous genocide, institution of chattel slavery, and by its global domination of Latin American, African,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Way of the Cross as Adversarial Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Christian groups and communities of faith have often sponsored programs that address issues of economic inequality, the poor, and the imprisoned. Such Christians have also stepped forward with their prison ministries and projects in anti-racism and advocacy for gender and sexual justice. Some of these are necessary for challenging Lockdown America. In other cases, as with some church “prison ministries,” Christians are in fact part of the problem, reinforcing today’s U.S. political ideologies that drive the U.S. criminal justice crisis.¹</p>
                     <p>In this chapter I begin to show Christian resistance as more than a programmatic add-on to its ministry, as more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Stealing the Show:</title>
                     <subtitle>Way of the Cross as Dramatic Action</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The way of the cross is adversarial, yes, but the embodied expression of that way under conditions of empire is neither violent tactical maneuvering nor passive endurance. Both of these responses may be necessary in certain situations. But the binary of violence/nonviolence is not the most important consideration when weighing how to express an adversarial politics. The greater question is how effective action is possible—action that will, in fact, resist and transform. This chapter turns to the second defining characteristic of Jesus’ way of the cross after its adversarial politics: the forging of dramatic action. It points to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Building Peoples’ Movements - 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Demilitarizing U.S. Police and Decarcerating the U.S.A.</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With this chapter, we come, now, to stand on the precipice of action, as we begin the first of two chapters interpreting the way of the cross as “building peoples’ movements.” A book does not create action; it might, though, create spaces where we open ourselves toward it. In a book, perhaps, we can measure ourselves and the needs of our era—exposing, feeling, and thinking through the injuries and pain created by structural violence, “fingering its jagged grain,” as Ralph Ellison is oft-quoted to have said of the blues’ musical impulse.¹ That impulse will be needed if we are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Building Peoples’ Movements - 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Abolishing Capital Punishment(s)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Building people’s movements amid and against Lockdown America also includes organizing against the U.S. death penalty, which at the federal and state levels assigns death as penalty for over 60 crimes.¹ Opposing it is surely no more important than the demilitarizing of policing in the U.S. or decarcerating the nation, which I have discussed in the previous chapter. Nevertheless, work against the death penalty is no mere add-on, some “extra-issue” to be raised. Instead, it is intrinsic, or ought to be, to our work against the carceral violence encountered in U.S. policing practice and mass incarceration, as well as in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                     <subtitle>Christian Living: Toward a Fullness of Rebellion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>451</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Executed God</italic>abounds with the rhetoric of opposition; or, so it may seem to many readers. Opening with a lament regarding Christendom’s betrayal of faith in the Jesus of Galilee and Golgotha, I move to a critique of Lockdown America as embodying a theatrics of state terror, seeking to show further how it serves the interests of<italic>Pax Americana</italic>, the ordered peace imposed by projects of U.S. global sovereignty and corporate power.</p>
                     <p>Indeed, the rhetoric of opposition is especially strong when, throughout Part Two, I present the way of the cross (with its three dimensions of adversarial politics, dramatic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Select Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>473</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>479</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Names Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>485</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt155j3fk.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>529</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
