<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9m0s24</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Divine Simplicity</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Biblical and Trinitarian Account</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BARRETT</surname>
               <given-names>JORDAN P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506424828</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506424835</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fortress Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>MINNEAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tm7gkh"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>Divine Simplicity</italic>engages recent critics and address one of their major concerns: that the doctrine of divine simplicity is not a biblical teaching. By analyzing the use of Scripture by key theologians from the early church to Karl Barth, Barrett finds that divine simplicity developed in order to respond to theological errors (e.g., Eunomianism) and to avoid misreading Scripture. The volume then explains how divine simplicity can be rearticulated by following a formal analogy from the doctrine of the Trinity in which the divine attributes are identical to the divine essence but are not identical to each other.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="220"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barrett</surname>
                           <given-names>Jordan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book began as a dissertation at Wheaton College under the supervision of Kevin Vanhoozer. The aim of the project is to present the biblical roots of the doctrine of divine simplicity and to clarify its connection to the doctrine of the Trinity. In short, I argue that the divine name(s) and indivisible operations of the Trinity<italic>ad extra</italic>are the biblical roots of the more developed doctrine of divine simplicity. Similar to the doctrine of the Trinity and its biblical derivation, divine simplicity is a culminating doctrine based on these two roots. This means that the origin of divine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>Divine Simplicity in Contemporary Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary theological treatments of the doctrine of God and his perfections often neglect the doctrine of divine simplicity.¹ Discussions of simplicity are more often found in philosophical literature,² and the theologians who do address it usually express concerns instead of its importance. Chapter 2 will detail how the doctrine of divine simplicity has always had critics. However, reactions to the doctrine in the latter half of the twentieth century were of a different kind and greater degree. Although criticisms of divine simplicity are nothing new, modern theology developed a new narrative of the origins and content of divine simplicity that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>Early Christian Approaches to Divine Simplicity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The doctrine of divine simplicity has a long history involving complex accounts that interweave philosophy, scripture, and theology. Without a doubt, there is no single doctrine of divine simplicity that remained perfectly unaltered throughout the Christian tradition. Perhaps this is because, as Christopher Stead argues, throughout the early church various senses of divine simplicity were used to speak about God without ever clarifying which sense was in use. In other words, “we must not think that simplicity is itself a simple notion.”¹ However, the simplistic versions of divine simplicity represented in much contemporary theology—primarily from critics—might lead others</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Divine Simplicity in Medieval Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Divine simplicity is not merely a contextual doctrine limited to patristic theology, nor is it more properly located in the scholastic theology of the Middle Ages. Having been a significant teaching in both the East and West, it was an important doctrine inherited by theologians as a way of both reading scripture and speaking of God. In this section, I will briefly examine the continued importance of divine simplicity in Pseudo-Dionysius, John of Damascus, Anselm, and Peter Lombard. After this, I will transition to the doctrine’s culmination in the theology of Thomas Aquinas. With the exception of Pseudo-Dionysius, there is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Divine Simplicity from the Reformation to Karl Barth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following the patristic and medieval conceptions of divine simplicity, the Reformation and post-Reformation mark a time of significant change. Yet does this mean that the doctrine of divine simplicity itself changed? Surely, it was not at the center of the Reformation debates, but that does not mean that it received little or no attention from the Reformation to the early modern periods. In this chapter, I will begin with a brief overview of the Reformation and early modern approaches to God and divine simplicity. Next, I will continue the approach of previous chapters—choosing representative theologians who espouse the doctrine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Biblical Roots of Divine Simplicity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The goal of the previous historical chapters was both to hear and to describe the ways in which various theologians articulated the doctrine of divine simplicity in relation to scripture. There was no burden to argue that some or even all examples were truly biblical in their portrayals. Rather, it was found that these theologians understood divine simplicity to be compatible with scripture and therefore made use of the doctrine in their teachings and writings. Even so, this does not fully release them from the charges brought against them (or the doctrine itself) by contemporary critics. It is easy to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>A Trinitarian Account of Divine Simplicity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapters demonstrated that divine simplicity developed in opposition to false teaching (e.g., gnostics, Eunomius), subsequently received further development and clarification (by, for example, Basil, Gregory of Nyssa, and others), and remained a standard Christian doctrine until later in the nineteenth century. Its biblical roots, implicit throughout the tradition, were identified in the last chapter as deriving from scripture’s habits of (1) using the many names or descriptions of God’s nature and (2) ascribing God’s various works to the indivisible operations of the Trinity<italic>ad extra</italic>. If this is correct, then the critics of divine simplicity have misunderstood the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tm7gkh.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
