<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC423.184 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Democracy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Peace</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Democratic Peace</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Political Biography</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ish-Shalom</surname>
               <given-names>Piki</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780472118762</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780472029150</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Michigan Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Ann Arbor</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Michigan</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3998/mpub.5558805"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Democratic Peace Thesis holds that democracies rarely make war on other democracies. Political scientists have advanced numerous theories attempting to identify precisely which elements of democracy promote this mutual peace, often hoping that Democratic Peace could be the final and ultimate antidote to war. However, as the theories were taken up by political figures, the immediate outcomes were war and the perpetuation of hostilities.</p>
         <p>Political theorist Piki Ish-Shalom sketches the origins and early academic development of the Democratic Peace Thesis. He then focuses on the ways in which various Democratic Peace Theories were used by Bill Clinton and George W. Bush both to shape and to justify U.S. foreign policy, particularly the U.S. stance on the Israeli-Palestinian situation and the War in Iraq. In the conclusion, Ish-Shalom boldly confronts the question of how much responsibility theoreticians must bear for the political uses-and misuses-of their ideas.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="266"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A NOTE TO THE READER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Childless though he was, Immanuel Kant is the towering (or assumed) father of many offspring, one of which is the subject of this book: the theories of democratic peace; those theories that try to explain the absence (or near absence) of war between consolidated democracies. And just as Kant’s hometown of Königsberg changed hands and names throughout its history, so the theories of democratic peace have gone through transformations, assuming different incarnations, or different sorts of idea structures. This book is about the political biography of those theories, and it will analyze the complex sociopolitical process by which they migrated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>THEORY AS A HERMENEUTICAL MECHANISM:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Theoretical Model</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter sets out the theoretical model for the book: a model explaining the conditioned power of theories. In order to establish my theory, I aim to use hermeneutics—though with a slight twist. Hermeneutics is usually understood as the art of reading and interpreting texts. I want to stress, however, the dual nature of hermeneutics. Although hermeneutics indeed interprets texts, it is also a more active intellectual endeavor of interpreting reality once reality is conceived as an unwritten text. That is not to say that reality is nothing but a text or even to claim it is a text</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>DEMOCRATIC PEACE AS THEORETICAL CONSTRUCTIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1964 we saw the revival of the Kantian republican peace, and the start of a process that epitomizes the first stage of theory as a hermeneutical process as depicted and analyzed in this book—in other words, the stage when meaning becomes attached to political concepts through academic discourse. A relatively obscure and neglected article by Dean Babst, published in 1964, predated the later flowering of the democratic peace research agenda. Babst’s theoretical observation was revived during the 1970s and 1980s, when a growing number of researchers reaffirmed an interesting empirical phenomenon: that democracies never—or, as the qualified</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>DEMOCRATIC PEACE AS A PUBLIC CONVENTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The multiplicity of configurations and the multiplicity of options within each configuration support the claim that theory indeed is a theoretical construction, or a mode of political thought in Freeden’s sense. Theories offer not just explanations for complex phenomena, but also an inclusive understanding of the phenomena. They do this by defining the political concepts and thus decontesting them. This is a point worth stressing: theories do offer explanations—that being their manifest function, after all—but on a prior and deeper level, they define political concepts for<italic>us</italic>and in so doing, equip<italic>us</italic>with a road map to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>WORD-LORDS:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Israeli Right’s Mobilization of the Rhetorical Capital of Democratic Peace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On June 24, 2002, President Bush brought out a new plan for peace between Israel and the Palestinians. That plan, which became known as the “Roadmap,” was based on a two-state solution and presented two novelties: (1) for the first time, the United States committed itself publicly and officially to an independent Palestinian sovereignty, and (2) for the first time, the United States also conditioned Israeli concessions on Palestinian democratization. This chapter explores the role of the democratic peace thesis in bringing about these novelties: it examines how the thesis was mobilized politically by Israeli politicians to advance their ideological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>THE CIVILIZATION OF CLASHES:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Neoconservative Reading of Democratic Peace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A specter is haunting American neoconservatism—the specter of promoting democracy. It exorcises whatever prudence conservatism might otherwise espouse; it drives neoconservatives’ grand strategy to experimentalism that otherwise they would condemn as “social engineering.” This chapter explores the part played by the democratic peace thesis in bringing this about, and examines another case in which the theory of democratic peace underpinned a political conviction—the political conviction that framed the American neoconservative grand strategy of promoting democracy by force.</p>
                     <p>The specter—or urge—to democratize runs counter to several philosophical and political tenets that supposedly hold conservatives back from foreign</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>THE THREE FREE WORLD THEORIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>142</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Democratic peace is a theory of democracy, by democracy, for democracy; it is supposed to explain the behavior of democracies, it was conceived in democracies, and its political representations were put into use for the sake of democracies. The focus of this book is a free world theory. But democratic peace thesis is not the only free world theory. There are others; for example, soft power and the capitalist peace theory (or thesis). Soft power is connected to democracy in that its emphasis is on influence by consent, the supposedly democratic approach to influence, rather than by coercion. Though power</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>THEORIZING AND RESPONSIBILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Tumultuous are the lives of theories. Conceived in the serenity of academy, they may find themselves forced into the real world and subjected to the vicissitudes of politics. This migration of theories from academia to the real world is what raises the question of theoreticians’ responsibility. Are the theoreticians responsible for the real-world ramifications, political harms, and moral wrongs resulting from their theorizing, and what sort of responsibility do they bear? The political biography of the democratic peace thesis discussed earlier in the book will help us answer these questions.</p>
                     <p>This chapter basically argues that social science theoreticians¹ are not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>Zooming In, Zooming Out</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though faltering at times, the democratic peace theories have thriving lives. The aim of this book has been to trace those lives, understand them theoretically, and assess them in normative terms. Theoretically, the migration of theory to the nonacademic world was conceptualized through the hermeneutical mechanism model. By focusing on a theory’s internal structure as an assemblage of political concepts, this book conceptualizes theories as theoretical constructions, a form of idea entity, and moreover, a form of political thought: a configuration of decontested political concepts arranged together, each conferring meaning on the others and receiving meaning from them. Thus, theories</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REFERENCES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">mpub.5558805.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
