<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR4148.P6F4 1985</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Blake, William, 1757-1827</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political and social views</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Social Vision of William Blake</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FERBER</surname>
               <given-names>MICHAEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400857647</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400857643</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1985</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7ztzd7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This fresh look at the social and political themes of Blake's poetry shows that he was a phenomenologist of liberation," who contested the dominant ideology of his time and who still speaks passionately to our fears and hopes.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1985.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="270"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Concept of Ideology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the past fifteen years or so English and American scholars have been catching up with the Continent in their theoretical discussions of the concept of ideology and its application to literature. A good deal of their work has been to translate, interpret, and extend the major theories: those of Georg Lukács (especially during his brief phase around 1922 as an independent Marxist), Antonio Gramsci, the Frankfurt School (Theodor Adorno, Walter Benjamin, Herbert Marcuse), Jean-Paul Sartre, and French structuralist Marxists such as Louis Althusser. In England, almost alone, Raymond Williams has been patiently working out his own theory of “cultural</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Blake’s Ideology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At centennial celebrations of the Glorious Revolution of 1688, many a toast to liberty and the rights of Englishmen was followed by another toast to that revolution’s philosopher, John Locke. “Locke” was a regular feature of the rhetoric of liberty. When the Dissenting interest preached parliamentary reform it did so in the name of its “holy of holies,” the Great Liberator.¹ Addressing the Society for the Commemoration of the Revolution a year after the centennial, the Dissenting minister Richard Price adduced a list of Lockean rights that included the right to cashier governors. Burke indignantly observed that he was not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Brotherhood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two metaphors govern nearly all of Blake’s formulations of social life: brotherhood and membership. Membership in a body is one of the most ancient images by which individuals have tried to grasp a sense of belonging to a group, and in various forms it is a central analogy in classical, Christian, and modern political thought. Brotherhood is probably an equally ancient notion—certainly brotherhoods are found in many traditional societies—but while the language of fraternity persists into our day, the idea has attracted only occasional scrutiny by Christian thinkers and virtually none by secular theorists. Of the great trinity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Nature and the Female</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is sometimes argued that Blake was a “revolutionary naturalist” for a few years following the French Revolution in 1789,¹ the chief exhibit in this case being “The voice of the Devil” in<italic>The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</italic>(4). It is not nature that the Blakean devil endorses, however, but “Energy” and “the Body.” The Body, furthermore, is “a portion of Soul” as perceived by our five senses. These five senses being “in this age” only the remnant of the “enlarged &amp; numerous senses” of a former age (11), the Body is presumably a temporary but necessary illusion. When we</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Liberty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have had several occasions to compare Blake to Milton, Winstanley, and other seventeenth-century writers and to consider the relation of his historical moment to theirs. In this chapter I want to dwell on the central theme of Blake’s ideological affiliation to the radicals of the Commonwealth period—liberty—and especially on the tradition of Christian antinomianism. As this affiliation has not been fully discussed before, I will give it more space than his relations with contemporaries or the details of his own elaboration of the theme, both of which Erdman and others have treated at length. The resulting imbalance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Labor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The opposite of liberty, Christian or civil, is slavery, but slavery is also the antithesis of creative labor. When we allow a tyrant to get control of our spirits or our cities, the first thing he will do is put us to work at backbreaking and stultifying tasks. Blake felt the tyranny of the English Church and state not only in its censorship and prosecution of radical writers but also in the way it governed public taste, driving radical artists to drudgery for the market. The Hebrew slaves built pyramids for the Egyptians; Blake engraved other people’s designs for other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Time, Eternity, and History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>152</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the realm we enter when our imagination is fully awake, Blake at first preferred the term “infinite.” “He who sees the Infinite in all things sees God.” Ezekiel wanted to raise men “into a perception of the infinite.” The Atlantic Ocean has already barred out the “infinite mountains of light” (of Atlantis) and now threatens to overwhelm America, “another portion of the infinite.” Oothoon tells how her “infinite brain” was inclosed in a circle by those who instructed her in Lockean philosophy (E 3, 39, 56, 47). By the time of the Lambeth prophecies, however, “infinite” is giving way</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Blake’s Apocatastasis</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It will be in keeping with the theme of this chapter to begin it by doing what we can to redeem one of the most scandalously intractable passages of<italic>Jerusalem</italic>.</p>
                     <p>Here Los fixd down the Fifty-two Counties of England &amp; Wales</p>
                     <p>The Thirty-six of Scotland, &amp; the Thirty-four of Ireland</p>
                     <p>With mighty power, when they fled out at Jerusalems Gates</p>
                     <p>Away from the Conflict of Luvah and Urizen, fixing the Gates</p>
                     <p>In the Twelve Counties of Wales &amp; thence Gates looking every way</p>
                     <p>To the Four Points: conduct to England &amp; Scotland &amp; Ireland</p>
                     <p>And thence to all the Kingdoms &amp; Nations &amp; Families of the Earth[.]</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                     <subtitle>The Seven Eyes of God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7ztzd7.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
