<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt125wf1</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">vazq17484</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JA79. V39 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political ethics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Governmental accountability</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Power (Social sciences)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Moral and ethical aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Political Responsibility</book-title>
         <subtitle>Responding to Predicaments of Power</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>VÁZQUEZ-ARROYO</surname>
               <given-names>ANTONIO Y.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780231541466</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0231541465</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Columbia University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Columbia University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7312/vazq17484"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Scholars in the humanities and social sciences have turned to ethics to theorize politics in what seems to be an increasingly depoliticized age. Yet the move toward ethics has obscured the ongoing value of political responsibility and the vibrant life it represents as an effective response to power.</p>
         <p>Sounding the alarm for those who care about robust forms of civic engagement, this book fights for a new conception of political responsibility that meets the challenges of today's democratic practice. Antonio Y. Vázquez-Arroyo forcefully argues against the notion that modern predicaments of power can only be addressed ethically or philosophically through pristine concepts that operate outside of the political realm. By returning to the political, the individual is reintroduced to the binding principles of participatory democracy and the burdens of acting and thinking as a member of a collective. Vázquez-Arroyo historicizes the ethical turn to better understand its ascendence and reworks Adorno's dialectic of responsibility to reassert the political in contemporary thought and theory.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="360"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alfred cobban once offered a memorable judgment about political science that proved to be prescient: “A good deal of what is called political science, I must confess, seems to me a device, invented by academic persons, avoiding that dangerous subject politics, without achieving science.”¹</p>
                     <p>Today, academic political theory is at the very least equally vulnerable to the charge of “avoiding that dangerous subject politics.” A less political cast of mind than that of many a practitioner of political theory in the Anglo-American academy is hard to fathom. Even if the salience of an academic and hyperprofessionalized cast of mind has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>HISTORICIZING THE ETHICAL TURN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In spite of the prevalence of ethical tropes in theoretical discussions in North Atlantic scholarly circles, an explicit embrace of the ethical turn in the humanities and social sciences has not been as prominent as that afforded to other so-called turns—including the cultural, linguistic, theological, psychoanalytic, and affective turns—of the past thirty years. Indeed, in contrast with previous turns, the ethical turn displays an almost apologetic reluctance about its self-identity: uneasiness and ambiguity define the attitude of many theoretical proponents of the turn, even if its political practitioners—humanitarians and human and animal rights advocates, among others—are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>RESPONSIBILITY IN HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Responsibility is now a fashionable concept in political theory, philosophy, and critical theory, and,<italic>ceteris paribus</italic>, that is a good reason not to write about it. Large bodies of work exist expounding its various connotations and meanings, ranging from questions of accountability and guilt to the need to respond to alterity. And yet there is something rather elusive about the political connotations of contemporary invocations of responsibility within the context of the turn to ethics in the humanities and social sciences, an elusiveness that at first glance seems largely due to hyperindividualized, abstract, and unhistorical thematizations of responsibility. Indeed, recent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>AUTONOMY, ETHICS, INTRASUBJECTIVITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One upshot of the contemporary ethical turn is the proliferation of solipsistic philosophical accounts of responsibility. If discussions of political and ethical responsibility historically emphasized social and intersubjective relations, the dominant philosophical formulations of responsibility privilege autonomy and<italic>intra</italic>subjectivity, even when abstract invocations of<italic>inter</italic>subjectivity are adduced. Modalities of solipsism that engage in Platonic soul-crafting and dwell on the inner life of the subject, her mental reality, over consideration of the predicaments of power she inhabits, or how these are historically constituted, politically sanctioned, and socially reproduced situations that thoroughly mediate that subjectivity. But these modalities of solipsism suggest something</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>ETHICAL REDUCTIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If the problems inherited from the Kantian tradition, including the critique leveled by Nietzsche, contributed to<italic>intra</italic>subjective ideas of responsibility, it is Emmanuel Levinas’s work that has mediated the prevalence of the concept in efforts to overcome the “autonomous subject” and thus presumably formulate<italic>inter</italic>subjective theories of responsibility that give primacy to the Other. Indeed, Levinas is the sage in most transatlantic theorizations of ethical responsibility as “responsibility to the Other.” He is credited with formulating the overcoming “of the very horizon of egology,” an overcoming that paves the way to “re-conceptualize responsibility as a being ‘for the other,’” something</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>ADORNO AND THE DIALECTIC OF RESPONSIBILITY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Kafka’s popularity,” Adorno observed, is due to “that comfort in the uncomfortable which has made of him an information bureau of the human condition, be it eternal or modern, and which knowingly dispenses with the scandal on which his work is built.” He goes on to say that Kafka’s work “is assimilated into an established trend of thought while little attention is paid to those aspects of his work which resist such assimilation, and which, precisely for this reason, require interpretation.”¹ Ironically, Adorno’s work has arguably suffered an even harsher fate.² Even if his work is often praised, especially his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>POLITICAL ETHIC, VIOLENCE, AND DEFEAT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the United States a first impression would imply that the ethical turn has crystallized around a particular discourse of catastrophe that emerged in the last decade of the twentieth century. With a fin de siècle mindset, various cultural and literary historians argued for the centrality of catastrophe, as a historical experience, concept, or narrative trope, in understanding the era that had just come to an end. In the early 1990s, cultural critic Cathy Caruth already referred to it as “our own catastrophic era.”¹ About a decade later, the editors of a collection of essays on mourning and loss echoed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">vazq17484.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
