<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT771.3 .R69 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Faith</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophical theology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Catholic Church</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Doctrines</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Three Dynamisms of Faith</book-title>
         <subtitle>Searching for Meaning, Fulfillment, and Truth</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ROY</surname>
               <given-names>LOUIS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813229799</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813229805</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1wq8z40"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Is the faith journey a matter of reflection, of emotion, or of obedience? Is there valid and convincing evidence that does enable human beings to assent to Jesus Christ and his message? What is the influence of cognitive assumptions and of affective tende</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="256"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our contemporary West’s humanism is colored by intense psychological preoccupations. It is also marked by a certain indifferentism: indifference to—and distrust of—organized religion with its institutional and doctrinal apparatus.¹ Having distanced themselves from long-established church teachings, many non-churchgoers are simply disaffiliated from any particular Jewish or Christian denomination. Some of them nevertheless maintain they are still “religious.” Yet, a fast-growing segment of North Americans reject the label “religious” and prefer to call themselves “spiritual.”²</p>
                     <p>Skepticism toward ecclesiastical talk has become prevalent, commencing with the Baby Boom Generation (1946–65). Insofar as Generation X (1966–85) is concerned, many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>The Issue of Hope as the Starting Point</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sociologist Peter Berger highlights one of the major differences between premodern and modern societies. In the former, one could find a great measure of fate, inasmuch as the possibilities of changing practices and conducts were restricted. In medicine, in nonscientific techniques, in methods of education, and so forth, there was little room for maneuvering. By contrast, “the modern individual … lives in a world of choice…. He must choose in innumerable situations of everyday life; but this necessity of choosing reaches into the areas of beliefs, values, and worldviews.”¹ This necessity of choosing he calls “the heretical imperative,” from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>The Bible’s Challenge to Human Wisdom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In their journey toward faith or toward a more mature faith, a good number of hikers walk with two legs. The first leg is human hope; the second leg is the biblical message addressed to humanity. Trekkers who, without having responded yet to the summons of the Bible, are nevertheless seriously thinking about the human predicament, may be considered (from a Christian perspective) as walking with one leg. Of them, Clement of Alexandria wrote, “Those who do anything or utter anything without the word of truth are like people struggling to walk without a foothold.”¹ By contrast, many of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Thomas Aquinas on the Word Embodied in Christ</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter introduces a medieval thinker, Thomas Aquinas, and investigates how he understands several central aspects of the act of faith. Since it is very important to take account of the affective side of faith, we shall begin with his views on the interaction between faith and love. Thereafter, I shall vindicate the centrality of the First Truth, which intellectually grounds faith in a God whose presence, self-revelation, and self-communication are real. Next, we shall ponder the way Aquinas assesses the role and compass of human reason in the faith experience. We shall end with a description of what he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>John Henry Newman:</title>
                     <subtitle>AN APOLOGY FOR CHRISTIANITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout his life, John Henry Newman (1801–90) was concerned with the challenge that the rationalism of his time, which he often called “liberalism,” addressed to Christianity. In this chapter, therefore, we shall concentrate on aspects of his thought that shed light on his account of the faith process—a process he viewed as much broader and deeper than any rationalist methodology. In this respect, most innovative and valuable are his notions of “real apprehension” and “inference.”</p>
                     <p>One of his groundbreaking works,<italic>An Essay in Aid of a Grammar of Assent</italic>, is composed of two parts, as Edward Caswall of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Bernard Lonergan:</title>
                     <subtitle>HUMAN INTENTIONALITY AND FAITH</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Bernard Lonergan (1904–84) was, in my estimation, the premier Roman Catholic theologian of the twentieth century. Basically a Thomist, he nevertheless displayed remarkable creativity in the areas of epistemology, method, and historical consciousness.¹ His contribution to a theology of faith hinges upon two conversions: religious and intellectual. Accordingly, after briefly characterizing a third kind of conversion, the moral one, which is less important here for a theology of faith, this chapter shows the impact of religious and intellectual conversion.² The first two sections discuss the interaction between<italic>religious</italic>conversion and the role of the word and of belief; the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Three Structuring Dynamisms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have listened to reflections on the drama of hope, to the Bible, to exegetes, and to a good number of philosophers and theologians, principally Thomas Aquinas, John Henry Newman, and Bernard Lonergan. So I assume my readers are ready for an actualization of Christian faith in accordance with the concerns, hesitancies, worries, and questions about affective fulfillment, the meaning of human life, and truth, which were described in the introduction and in chapter 1. With respect to Lonergan’s levels of intentionality, I situate affective fulfillment on the fourth level, meaning on the second, and truth on the third.</p>
                     <p>At</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Confirming the Tripartite Structure</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our preceding chapter described the tripartite structure of living faith. I now intend to uncover more fully the grounds and the implications of that structure. So this chapter aims at enriching our account of the human progress toward faith.</p>
                     <p>The first section of this chapter will explain the importance of the distinctive roles that meaning and truth play in the attraction to God. Second, stages will be differentiated in the process of coming to believe. Third, some light will be thrown upon the complementarity of feelings and insights. Fourth, we shall ask whether religious experience is the main criterion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A Pastoral Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Come then, Lord my God, teach my heart where and how to seek You, where and how to find You.”¹ Thus St. Anselm of Canterbury addresses God in the prayer that launches his celebrated allocution on the existence and the nature of God. In our twenty-first century, can we localize this “where and how” somewhat differently, in accord with cultural situations that are not the same as those that prevailed in the eleventh century? In response to this query, this book has situated the beginnings of Christian faith in the anthropological locus constituted by uncertainties and doubts regarding human hope.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1wq8z40.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Subject Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
