<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8c0t</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GR581.Y43 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Zombies</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Year's Work at the Zombie Research Center</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>COMENTALE</surname>
               <given-names>EDWARD P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JAFFE</surname>
               <given-names>AARON</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253013873</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253013927</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253013925</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Indiana University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzg4q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>They have stalked the horizons of our culture, wreaked havoc on moribund concepts of dead and not dead, threatened our sense of identity, and endangered our personal safety. Now zombies have emerged from the lurking shadows of society's fringes to wander the sacred halls of the academy, feasting on tender minds and hurling rot across our intellectual landscape. It is time to unite in common cause, to shore up defenses, firm up critical and analytical resources, and fortify crumbling lines of inquiry. Responding to this call, Brain Workers from the Zombie Research Center poke and prod the rotting corpus of zombie culture trying to make sense of cult classics and the unstoppable growth of new and even more disturbing work. They exhume "zombie theory" and decaying historical documents from America, Europe, and the Caribbean in order to unearth the zombie world and arm readers with the brain tools necessary for everyday survival. Readers will see that zombie culture today "lives" in shapes as mutable as a zombie horde-and is often just as violent.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="544"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Zombie Research Center FAQ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COMENTALE</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JAFFE</surname>
                           <given-names>AARON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We’re sure you’ve noticed that zombies are everywhere these days. Why else would you be reading this book? As it says in the stairwell: THE END IS EXTREMELY FUCKING NIGH. [#zombies.] In the bunker, out on the rooftop, inside and out back, stalking the horizon, zombies pose significant threats to both human identity and human civilization.<italic>Who are they? What do they want? How do they</italic>“<italic>think</italic>”?<italic>What do they mean?</italic>The recent explosion of zombies in film, literature, graphic novels, video games, and fan culture is inescapable. Even sociology, philosophy, and literary theory have gotten into the zombie act,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Zombie Psychology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WATT</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two scenes in Ruben Fleisher’s<italic>Zombieland</italic>(2009) emblematize key psychical and affective dimensions of much zombie culture, dimensions that are often subordinated in critical discussions to such terms as<italic>terror</italic>or<italic>horror</italic>or neglected altogether. At first glance the earlier of these scenes seems almost silly—so much fodder for gifted actors to exploit—and irrelevant both to the film’s narrative and to the larger psychical and affective issues inherent to such recent films as 28<italic>Days Later (2002), Shaun of the Dead (2004), Pontypool (2009),</italic>and others. After Tallahassee (Woody Harrelson), zombie exterminator extraordinaire and one of the film’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Zombie Demographics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JAFFE</surname>
                           <given-names>AARON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first is marked by a silhouetted human form, shambling along the interface between earth and sky; a head flops to one side. In a word: zombie! A corpse that doesn’t know it’s dead, as George A. Romero defined the concept, a concept he still refuses to name out loud. “A Zombie being a corpse that won’t give in and admit it,” reads the communiqué in<italic>Pacific Islands Monthly</italic>from the outermost rim, even earlier, arriving right after V-J Day (49). The uplink from Zombieville reports that “the sea is flat, an opaque disc of green-blue . . . without</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Zombie Spaces</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HASSLER-FOREST</surname>
                           <given-names>DAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past decade the zombie has been transformed from a movie monster that appeared primarily in American underground cinema and Italian horror films to a ubiquitous trope in popular culture. Instantly recognizable to general global audiences, yet flexible enough to serve both as a legitimate monster and as the punch line to a bad joke, the figure of the mindless undead has clearly found resonance in late capitalist culture and has been connected to a wide range of concepts and ideas. In the same way that Marx and Engels related the system of industrial capitalism to the figure of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Zombie Media</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOHMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>ERIK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Taken as a whole, George A. Romero’s body of work has most often been thought to mark shifts in cultural anxieties—anxieties around the Vietnam War and the civil rights era, the rise of a consumer economy, the relation of science and the military during the Cold War, the war in Iraq, and the irruptive spectacle of terrorism—anxieties that his films not only embody but also critically respond to, and all of which have been well documented. Yet, by regarding these films as markers of cultural anxieties or repressions, such readings either implicitly or explicitly tend to use psychological</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Zombie Health Care</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHAPIRO</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Wildfire,” the fifth episode of AMC’s<italic>The Walking Dead</italic>’s first season, shows a crisis many Americans are currently facing.¹ In the aftermath of a zombie attack, the human survivors must prevent their killed loved ones from returning as zombies. One woman, Carol, refuses to let the group’s men take responsibility for “decraniating” her prone life partner. “He’s my husband,” she says before splattering his gray matter onto the viewing lens. The scene cuts to another woman, Andrea, cradling her dead sister and waiting for the first sign of reanimation. Over a soundtrack of sentimentalized music, Andrea mournfully says, “Amy. Amy.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Zombie Physiology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RAGLIN</surname>
                           <given-names>JACK</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While it has become de rigueur to portray the zombie onslaught as a war, this analogy is in fact seriously flawed and can result in lethal outcomes for humans who hew to orthodox strategies of offensive or defensive warfare. Consider that zombie warfare is not driven by a religious motive or geopolitical objective. Beyond the common innate drive to consume human flesh, zombies exhibit no cooperative group objective. Moreover, zombie predation does not appear to be driven by any planned or organized strategies conforming to the strictures of either traditional or terrorist warfare, although as described later, sufficient densities of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Zombie Performance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SATTAR</surname>
                           <given-names>ATIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The zombie consumes us. It occupies our minds, books, screens, and streets; devours and squanders our flesh and bodies; infects us with disease; and overwhelms our very social order. And yet we chase after zombies. In recent years we have facilitated their rise as a veritable cultural phenomenon, compelling them into our movie-theater screens in greater and faster-moving hordes than ever before, into our homes with shows like<italic>The Walking Dead,</italic>and onto our college campuses with Humans vs. Zombies, a live-action game of survival. Even the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Zombie Race</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>COMENTALE</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It begins with a thump, or rather, a scrape and a thump.<italic>Shhh-thump.</italic>The monster appears first as sound and then rhythm, or, rather, counter- rhythm. Its presence is made known, paradoxically, by its double absence, one physical and the other temporal.</p>
                     <p>It lags, behind itself, drags itself, before itself, somewhere in back of you, in front of you, over your shoulder—always where it is not.<italic>Shhh-thump.</italic>Its second beat is scarier than the first, not just because it is louder, closer, but because it recalls the first. The monster is always in two—two spaces, two times. It</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Zombie Politics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MORTON</surname>
                           <given-names>SETH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Carl Grimes, the cowboy-hat-wearing son in<italic>The Walking Dead,</italic>gives his father, Rick, a cold reminder about the world they live in: “The costumes, the candy—everyone walking around, acting like nothing is happening around them. They’re all stupid. The roamers [zombies] don’t go away because you can’t see them. I hate this place, Dad. It doesn’t feel real. It feels like everyone is playing pretend. . . . I don’t want to get used to this. It will make us weak” (Kirkman 16). This cynical political philosophy—more “pragmatic than argumentative”—marks Carl as a member of Generation Zombie</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Zombie Postfeminism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RUTHVEN</surname>
                           <given-names>ANDREA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While Julia Kristeva doubtless did not have in mind the undead corpse of the zombie when she wrote of the abject and how it forces death upon the living, the walking dead undeniably embody abjection. It is not strange, then, that in representations of zombies, in film, literature, television, or other media, the primary focus is on how the humans who have not been infected confront and battle those who have returned from the dead. Those who engage in zombie fighting are necessarily confronting and denying the death (among other things) that the posthuman monster represents. This analysis of Seth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Zombie Linguistics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SOLDAT-JAFFE</surname>
                           <given-names>TATJANA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Zombies don’t make good conversation partners. When Sydney and Grant, the two main characters in<italic>Pontypool</italic>(2009), realize that the disease that transforms humans into zombies might be carried through language—specifically, English language—they look for a source. In the sudden realization that<italic>understanding</italic>language is the source, Sydney asks Grant, “How do you stop understanding? How do you make it strange?” Such questions point to crucial issues concerning the nature of human language and the possibility of zombie language. First, they Tatjana Soldat-Jaffe encourage us to examine general definitions of language use and communication. Must language always involve</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Zombie Arts and Letters</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EBURNE</surname>
                           <given-names>JONATHAN P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Genre fiction is project-based art. Whether cowboy Western or intergalactic sci-fi, genre writing entails a double inventiveness according to the set of directives imposed upon each story in advance. On the one hand, by definition such writing exercises a creative function following explicit conditions of constraint, whether formal, aesthetic, historical, moral, or economic. From the pulps to the remainder bin, genre fiction necessarily knows its limits; this is part of its “project.” On the other</p>
                     <p>hand, it also recognizes and formalizes these limits as constraints in the first place, a gesture as constitutive of a genre’s artistic project as any</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Zombie Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GIBSON</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>416</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Here is a list, very incomplete, of things one should keep in mind when attempting to write seriously about zombies. Zombies do not exist. Zombies are not related to werewolves or vampires.¹ Zombies are not, literally, mindless consumers, enraged proletarians, or stupid Americans—although some were perhaps once these things—and there is little use in casting them, even metaphorically, as<italic>essentially</italic>such, especially when attempting to offer a “theory of zombies.” This is because zombies do not form a natural kind, not even a<italic>fictional</italic>natural kind. Wiithin the genre, zombies vary greatly in behavior, cognitive power, and athletic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Zombie Cocktails</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SCHNEIDER</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Betsy Connell, female lead in Jacques Tourneur’s<italic>I Walked with a Zombie</italic>(1943), confesses that is she isn’t in fact familiar with zombies, her interlocutor, Dr. Maxwell, first tells her that she is dealing with “a ghost, the living dead” and then informs her more cheerfully that the Zombie is also a drink, at which point Betsy finds herself on more familiar territory. “I tried one once,” she says, “but there wasn’t anything dead about it.” Uttered in 1943 at the height of Hollywood’s tiki craze, these lines are no doubt an inside joke. By this time, actors and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword:</title>
                     <subtitle>Zombie Archive</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>NEALON</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY T.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>465</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Year’s Work at the Zombie Research Center</italic>both constitutes its own unique archive and contributes to the growing archive of scholarly work on what might be the central figure that traverses our present, the zombie. When taking stock of this archive, or any archive for that matter, one is inevitably forced to ask the question, Why create a research archive around this topic rather than another? Why zombies, why now?</p>
                     <p>There are of course myriad—sometimes conflicting, always compelling—answers to that question on offer in this volume, and likewise within the wider scholarly zombie archive, but almost all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>475</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>507</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzg4q.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>511</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
