<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt4z6vm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BL980.G8D36 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fire walking</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fire walking</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spiritual healing</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Spiritual healing</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Greece</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Religious life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Firewalking and Religious Healing</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Anastenaria of Greece and the American Firewalking Movement</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Danforth</surname>
               <given-names>Loring M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400884360</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400884365</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Princeton, New Jersey; Chichester, West Sussex</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1989</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dxg8pg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>"If the Saint calls you, if you have an open road, then you don't feel the fire as if it were your enemy," says one of the participants in the Anastenaria. This compelling work evokes and contrasts two forms of firewalking and religious healing: first, the Anastenaria, a northern Greek ritual in which people who are possessed by Saint Constantine dance dramatically over red-hot coals, and, second, American firewalking, one of the more spectacular activities of New Age psychology. Loring Danforth not only analyzes these rituals in light of the most recent work in medical and symbolic anthropology but also describes in detail the lives of individual firewalkers, involving the reader personally in their experiences: he views ritual therapy as a process of transformation and empowerment through which people are metaphorically moved from a state of illness to a state of health. Danforth shows that the Anastenaria and the songs accompanying it allow people to express and resolve conflict-laden family relationships that may lead to certain kinds of illnesses. He also demonstrates how women use the ritual to gain a sense of power and control over their lives without actually challenging the ideology of male dominance that pervades Greek culture. Comparing the Anastenaria with American firewalking, Danforth includes a gripping account of his own participation in a firewalk in rural Maine. Finally he examines the place of anthropology in a postmodern world in which the boundaries between cultures are becoming increasingly blurred.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="424"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the postmodern world of the late twentieth century it has become increasingly difficult to sustain the notion that even the most “exotic” people anthropologists write about—from the Trobriand Islanders to the Yanomamo—live in totally alien, isolated, and self-contained cultures. Our world has grown smaller; its societies and cultures, unique and diverse though they are, are now woven together in a complex web of interconnections and mutual influences that forms a thoroughly interdependent “world system.” In response to the many serious challenges posed by such a world, anthropology today, like other disciplines in the humanities and the social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>I</label>
                     <title>The Festival of Saints Constantine and Helen</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Old Yorgakis Yavasis stood in front of the icons of Saints Constantine and Helen and crossed himself three times. He lit a small incense burner, made the sign of the cross with it in front of the icons, and placed it on a large trunk underneath the icon shelf. As the thick, sweet-smelling smoke clouded up around him, Yavasis placed a hand on each of the two icons and stood motionless. Suddenly all the gold coins and jewelry, all the silver votive offerings and little bells, that hung from the icons began to jingle and rattle quietly.</p>
                     <p>Yavasis carried the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>II</label>
                     <title>The Interpretation of Religious Healing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Anastenaria is concerned with healing in the broadest sense. It is both a religious ritual and a form of psychotherapy. Any attempt to understand the Anastenaria as a system of religious healing must therefore integrate approaches from medical anthropology with those from the anthropological study of religion. It must bring together the concerns of transcultural psychiatry and those of symbolic anthropology. Such a synthesis, which constitutes an interpretive or hermeneutic approach to the study of ritual therapy, provides the theoretical framework for this study of the Anastenaria.</p>
                     <p>The tradition of interpretive anthropology has adopted a fundamentally semiotic approach to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>III</label>
                     <title>The Anastenaria</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The village of Ayia Eleni is located fifteen kilometers south of Serres, an important commercial center in the eastern part of Greek Macedonia with approximately forty thousand inhabitants. The Strymonas River flows nearby on its eighty-kilometer journey from the Bulgarian border to the Aegean Sea. It is the water of the Strymonas distributed through an elaborate irrigation network that is largely responsible for the high standard of living that the people of Ayia Eleni and the other villages of the Serres basin have come to enjoy.</p>
                     <p>In 1976 Ayia Eleni had a population of just over seven hundred people. They</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IV</label>
                     <title>From Illness and Suffering to Health and Joy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>84</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Anastenaria religious healing is brought about by the transformation of a person’s relationship with Saint Constantine from a negative one involving illness and suffering to a positive one involving health and joy, a transformation that takes place when a person becomes an Anastenaris and acquires the supernatural power of the Saint. A person’s relationship with Saint Constantine can, therefore, be seen as a powerful metaphor for the person’s social, psychological, and physiological condition. The Anastenaria provides people who are in a weak, vulnerable, or subordinate position with a spirit idiom that they can use to gain power over</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>V</label>
                     <title>History, Folklore, Politics, and Science</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>132</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Russia and Turkey were at war. That’s when all the old villages around Kosti were destroyed: Tripori, Stavrohori, Kastania, Palioklisia. Turkish bandits were fighting the Tartars. They burned down the villages, and everyone fled. Later people came together in one place and founded Kosti. The first person to settle there was an old man named Kostis.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>In the beginning he lived all alone with his family in a cave up in the mountains. As it turned out, his children were forced to marry each other; brothers married sisters. The church forbids this, but sometimes it happens by accident. Here it</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VI</label>
                     <title>The Celebration of Community in a Changing World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Anastenaria not only plays an important part in the personal lives of individual Anastenarides, it also plays a central role in the collective life of the village of Ayia Eleni and the community of Kostilides as a whole. The Anastenaria has been a powerful symbol for the shared identity of the Kostilides ever since their arrival as refugees in Greek Macedonia. It epitomizes all that it means to be a Kostilis in a society that is experiencing the homogenizing effects of mass media, a national educational system, and rapid modernization and urbanization. In addition, the festival of Saints Constantine</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VII</label>
                     <title>A Full Moon Firedance in Maine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>An American “stole the show” at the firewalk that took place yesterday in Langadas</italic>.¹</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Together with the Anastenarides of the region an American crossed the glowing coals three times without suffering any burns at all</italic>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The forty-year-old man from Maine said he had taken part in similar firewalks in other countries</italic>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>After receiving permission from the Anastenarides the American, whose name was Ken, passed quickly over the burning coals three times in his bare feet</italic>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The third time the Anastenarides told him to remain on the coals with them longer, but he declined and left</italic>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>It should be noted that</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>VIII</label>
                     <title>The American Firewalking Movement</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Firewalking is certainly one of the most dramatic activities that take place at the many classes, seminars, and workshops attended by the increasing number of Americans who hope to bring about a “New Age” of peace, unity, and higher consciousness through personal growth and spiritual transformation. By the 1980s a wide range of belief systems, social causes, and healing practices, whose origins lay in the counterculture of the 1960s, had come together under the general rubric of New Age phenomena. The women’s movement, the environmental movement, and the peace movement; health food, renewable resources, and appropriate technology; parapsychology, astrology, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>IX</label>
                     <title>Contemporary Anthropology in a Postmodern World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I Left the United States for Greece in August 1974 to begin my research on the Anastenaria, I had a fairly traditional idea of what ethnographic fieldwork would be like. I was an American, a graduate student in anthropology, and I had been brought up as a member of a liberal Protestant church in a white, upper-middle-class suburb of Boston. I was going to live in a Greek village, a warm emotional place where people ate exotic food outdoors late at night and men embraced each other in public—a place where people lived lives that were somehow more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dxg8pg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
