<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BV4680.C3813 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ten commandments</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Murder</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Thou Shalt Not Kill: A Political and Theological Dialogue</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>CAVARERO</surname>
               <given-names>ADRIANA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SCOLA</surname>
               <given-names>ANGELO</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="translator">Translated by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Groesbeck</surname>
               <given-names>Margaret Adams</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Sitze</surname>
               <given-names>Adam</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823267347</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823267385</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16f8cb0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this fascinating and rare little book, a leading Italian feminist philosopher and the Archbishop of Milan face off over the contemporary meaning of the biblical commandment not to kill. The result is a series of erudite and wide-ranging arguments that move from murder and suicide to just war and drone strikes, from bioethics and biopolitics to hermeneutics and philology, from Theodor Adorno and Max Horkheimer to Hannah Arendt and Michel Foucault, from Torah and Scripture to art and literature, from the essence of human dignity and the paradoxes of fratricide to engagements with Levinasian ethics. Less a direct debate than a disputation in the classical sense, Thou Shalt Not Kill proves to be a searching meditation on one of the unstated moral premises shared by otherwise bitterly opposed political factions. It will stimulate the mind of the novice while also reminding more advanced readers of the necessity and desirability of thinking in the present.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="128"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TRANSLATORS’ NOTE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>POINT OF DEPARTURE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whosoever destroys one man is counted by Scripture as though he had destroyed the whole world. This is also true of Cain who killed Abel, his brother, as it is written in the Scripture:<italic>The voice of thy brother’s blood crieth unto Me</italic>(Genesis 4.10). Though he may shed the blood (<italic>dm</italic>) of only a single person, the text uses the plural:<italic>dmym</italic>(“bloods”). This teaches us that the blood of Abel’s children, and his children’s children, and all the descendants destined to come forth from him until the end of time—all of them stood crying out before the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>COMMANDMENTS AND COVENANT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This introductory framework should suffice to demonstrate that the very concept of “commandment,” when linked to the precepts of the Decalogue, requires a clarification that restates the authentic law. If we are to grasp the meanings of moral law in its actual cultural context, we cannot possibly trust some sort of common sense without immediately getting lost in a maze of multiple misunderstandings and contradictions. We will have to find ways to peel off the sedimented crust formed by the usual meanings and to strip ambiguity from the very debates that should have critically illuminated the problems.</p>
                     <p>Unavoidably, therefore, if</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CHRISTIANITY AND RATIONAL, UNIVERSAL MORALS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That the “ten words” are originally and always the major criteria of religious morals does not mean that the rational, moral conscience (or the “natural” conscience that is, in a limited sense, non<italic>revealed</italic>) may be incapable of truth. The vicissitudes of the late Middle Ages (especially with the rediscovery of Aristotle and the work of Thomas Aquinas) and then of modernity have shown the importance of the rational, moral conscience—its autonomous ability to construct an ethical form. Theological thought, likewise, has been able to recognize that revelation does not substitute for but rather conserves moral autonomy, which, thus recognized,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>YOU SHALL NOT KILL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“You shall not kill” is the commandment in the Decalogue that expresses the inviolable value of human beings’ lives in the eyes of God. From the standpoint of the rational moral conscience and of philosophical thought, to what does this correspond? What part of God’s vision of man is visible even to human reason?</p>
                     <p>God sees his image in man. Philosophical reason, meanwhile, is able to see in man an exceptional gift—his capacity to open himself up to the entire horizon of reality, with his interest and questioning, his intuition and reasoning, his desire and affection—that positions him</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>RESPONSIBILITIES AND CHALLENGES:</title>
                     <subtitle>BURNING ISSUES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is clear that, for whoever lives within the Judeo-Christian tradition, the first responsibility that issues from the commandment “You shall not kill” consists of deciding to remain within the covenant-pact and thence too of advocating that all men follow the dictates of rational, universal moral law. This responsibility is never obvious; it ever renews itself, and indeed its perennial renewal is an inexhaustible source of wonder and joy. The covenant-pact and the rational recognition of the splendor of the truth of fundamental moral experience, which shines in every man, is not a thing of the past. It is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A SPECIAL LAW</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The entire Torah, in its minute descriptions, is concentrated in the ‘Thou Shalt not kill’ that the face of the other signifies,”¹ writes the Jewish philosopher Emmanuel Lévinas. Aside from finding a confirmation in Jewish doctrine, this sentence sums up Lévinas’s thought as a whole—a radical ethic of nonviolence that, reached through the author’s anomalous reading of the sixth commandment, can serve as an introduction to our theme here. We begin with Lévinas because we believe in the rhetorical efficacy of contrasts. And, in this case, the contrast is considerable. Against almost all tradition, Lévinas reads the commandment as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BRIEF PHILOLOGICAL NOTE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have claimed here that “You shall not kill” is the sixth commandment, but the numbering of the commandments is notoriously controversial. Jewish tradition follows rabbinical teaching on the subdivision of the Decalogue (the<italic>deka-logoi</italic>, the<italic>Ten Words</italic>,<italic>Aserat ha-Dibrot</italic>) and privileges its formulation in Exodus (20.13), where “You shall not kill” comes as the sixth Word. Looking instead at the version in Deuteronomy (5.17), in conformity with the catechism of Luther (1529) and the Council of Trent (1564), Christian tradition customarily relegates the prohibition against homicide to the fifth position. In the Gospels, meanwhile, Jesus reviews the commandments several</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CRIME AND PUNISHMENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In April 2010 the D’Orsay Museum in Paris opened an exhibition that drew thousands of visitors. They were attracted first of all by its irresistibly fascinating title: “Crime and Punishment.” The reference to Dostoyevsky’s masterpiece is explicit. In the minds of the show’s curators, crime is synonymous with murder: its paintings, photographs, illustrations, and other forms of documentation all display, in various modes, the crime of murder—that is, the individual offense. As for punishment, it is largely understood in juridical terms. Its symbol is the guillotine: the “merciful” machine, created by the French Revolution to kill in an egalitarian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WHEN KILLING IS LAWFUL AND JUST</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No matter how often it sings the praises of peace, the Bible abounds with massacres and wars carried out against the enemies of Israel in the name of God. The cultural semantics of monotheistic religions are notoriously characterized by a crude and ferocious vocabulary of violence.¹ The episode of the golden calf may serve as an example. There an infuriated Moses shouts: “This is the message of Yahweh, the God of Israel: ‘Gird on your sword, every man of you and quarter the camp from gate to gate killing one his brother, another his friend, another his neighbor.’”² As for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TO CUT LIFE SHORT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The special law of the sixth commandment—in other words, its inability to be proposed as an absolute prohibition—finds a crucial touchstone in the absolute nature of its very object: death and its irreversibility. To kill is to mete out death. In the other commandments, life is not the issue, and the consequence of transgression is not irrecoverable. If I rob, I can restitute or repay. If I give false testimony, I can retract it. But for death—at least on the plane of earthly existence—there is no remedy. For whoever has a mortal body, to kill strikes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>A WEAK COMMANDMENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>78</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The sixth commandment appears a weak commandment no matter from what cultural vantage point you look at it. Not weak because, in private or in war, men continue to kill one another. (They continue to steal, give false testimony, and violate other imperatives of the Decalogue as well.) No: it is weak<italic>per se</italic>because of the inconsistency of its conceptual framework and the contradictions that run through it historically. Even its recent adaptation to the parameters of the bioethical controversy, where it presents itself as a final attempt to make the prohibition against killing absolute, ends up dragging the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>IN THE BEGINNING</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>80</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem of the double beginning of the human race is one of the many problems for interpretation posed by the account of Genesis. Born not of woman but created by God on the sixth day, Adam and Eve live in the Garden of Eden in a state that knows no sorrow, no toil, and, above all, no death. Already freed from the human condition of being born an infant, Edenic humanity is also missing the fundamental characteristic recognized as human by nearly all cultures: mortality. As in ancient Greece, in the prehistoric time before Pandora’s box was opened, there</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HOMO NECANS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scholars from various disciplines currently hold the opinion that homicide is an anthropological constant, a distinctive trait of the universally understood human spirit, a bloody trademark of the species. It appears we must say much the same for war as a permanent factor in the history of man and for the transcultural presence of vendetta in archaic societies. Tribal avenger or warrior—and founder of community—the masculine figure resides in the stories of the origin in many versions, with a certain documentable persistence. And when research like this takes up the evolutionary model and turns to looking into the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>YOU SHALL NEVER KILL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1984, delivering a speech commemorating peace in Europe, Emmanuel Lévinas underlines how the West lacks “a sensibility in which the scandal of murder is not suppressed even when the violence is rationally necessary.”¹ If the vitalist mask of the subject holds war inevitable and even healthy, the rationalist mask holds it all the more necessary to secure peace. Intuiting that the two masks demonstrate a substantial complicity and distrusting an idea of peace that continues to be based on war, Lévinas elaborates a radical critique of violence that is based on an atypical reading of the sixth commandment—or,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE SEX OF CAIN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>And if Cain had been a woman? The hypothesis is obviously absurd, and it is so for more than one reason. Even though Eve has an important role in the Edenic scene of sin that establishes humanity as a mortal species, the homicidal and fratricidal act that initiates human history provides for no woman. Something analogous happens to Pandora, the first woman according to Hesiod, from whose belly is born death in addition to other ills for the human race: the lineage that then descends from her is exclusively male, often brothers or those united in the warrior brotherhoods, whose</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16f8cb0.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
