<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt13kh41m</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD241.B78 1992</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Hermeneutics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Hermeneutics Ancient and Modern</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BRUNS</surname>
               <given-names>GERALD L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>25</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>1992</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300063035</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300157154</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1992</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1dszwtv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this wide-ranging meditation on the nature and purpose of hermeneutics, Gerald L. Bruns argues that hermeneutics is not merely a contemporary theory but an extended family of questions about understanding and interpretation that have multiple and conflicting histories going back to before the beginning of writing.What does it mean to understand a riddle, an action, a concept, a law, an alien culture, or oneself? Bruns expands our sense of the horizons of hermeneutics by situating its basic questions against a background of different cultural traditions and philosophical topics. He discusses, for example, the interpretation of oracles, the silencing of the muses and the writing of history, the quarrel between philosophy and poetry, the canonization of sacred texts, the nature of allegorical exegesis, rabbinical midrash, the mystical exegesis of the Qur'an, the rise of literalism and the individual interpreter, and the nature of Romantic hermeneutics. Dealing with thinkers ranging from Socrates to Luther to Wordsworth to Ricoeur, Bruns also ponders several basic dilemmas about the nature of hermeneutical experience, the meaning of tradition, the hermeneutical function of narrative, and the conflict between truth and freedom in philosophy and literature. His eloquent book demonstrates the continuing power of hermeneutical thinking to open up questions about the world and our place in it.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="340"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>WHAT IS HERMENEUTICS ABOUT?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let me try to situate my book by taking up, in some fairly familiar ways, the question of what sort of thing hermeneutics might he and what its point is. The simplest answer is that hermeneutics is a tradition of thinking or of philosophical reflection that tries to clarify the concept of<italic>verstehen</italic>, that is, understanding. What is it to make sense of anything, whether a poem, a legal text, a human action, a language, an alien culture, or oneself? The difficulty is that this is not an entirely coherent question; or rather, the question of understanding turns up in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Truth and Power in the Discourse of Socrates</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is in the spirit of these words by Heidegger that I want to ask about the discourse of Socrates—how he talks, how he sounds, and also what it is to understand him; and I mean all of this to be taken pointedly as a hermeneutical question. What is it for anyone, including Socrates, to understand Socrates? This is the question at issue in Plato’s<italic>Apology</italic>, where Socrates talks about himself and claims to tell the truth about himself, and it is at issue again in the<italic>Symposium</italic>, where a drunken Alcibiades claims to speak the truth of Socrates</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Thucydides, Plato, and the Historicality of Truth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It must be acknowledged that hermeneutics belongs to the realm of opinion, or rhetoric, rather than to the realm of truth, or philosophy.¹ But it seems part of every hermeneutical desire to cross the threshold of rhetoric and to speak, well, philosophically. My purpose in this chapter is to consider one or two ancient examples of this desire. These examples are related to the question of tradition, that is, the question of how we stand with respect to all that comes down to us from the past. A main problem about tradition is that things do not seem exactly to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Canon and Power in the Hebrew Bible</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>64</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first thing to be said about the Hebrew Scriptures is that we have very little evidence as to how they came into existence. Nineteenth-century textual criticism dispelled once for all the idea that Moses was the author of the sacred books; and indeed, it is now hard to see how a notion of authorship can be applied to these texts in any significant way. The British scholar Peter R. Ackroyd has summarized the current opinion as follows: “It is only rarely that we can point to individuals as authors—the author of Job, the author of Ecclesiastes perhaps, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Allegory as Radical Interpretation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Radical interpretation” means the redescription, in one’s own language, of sentences from an alien system of concepts and beliefs. My thought is that this idea describes, in a rough, preliminary sort of way, the logic of allegorical interpretation, at least in the case of someone like Philo Judaeus, who lived in Alexandria about the time of Christ and produced a number of commentaries on the Septuagint, the (almost legendary) Greek translation of the Hebrew Bible, in order to make sense of it in terms of the concepts and beliefs of Hellenistic culture. In this context making sense does not mean</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Hermeneutics of Midrash</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I want to examine in some detail a midrashic text that, from a hermeneutical standpoint, seems to articulate most fully the ancient rabbinical conception of what it means to interpret the Scriptures. In spite of its reputation, midrash is not just a sort of edifying companion to the Bible that goes off by itself; it is a genuinely hermeneutical practice in the sense that its purpose is to elucidate and understand scriptural text as such.¹ But what counts as understanding in this case? In Philo we saw that understanding and interpretation are internal to the practice of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Ṣūfīyya:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE MYSTICAL HERMENEUTICS OF AL-GHAZĀLĪ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Not all texts are for reading. Of course, the word<italic>text</italic>itself contradicts this idea. Discourse from a textual standpoint is not so much expression as ciphering and concealing, that is, plotting and weaving, layering and folding, structuring and packing; and these are metaphors that call for reading in the strong modernist sense of analytical action. Texts impose tasks that it seems natural for us to characterize in the language of instrumental reason—of grasping and penetrating, getting on top of and breaking down, unpacking and laying bare. The text is an object defined by our ability to reduce and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Scriptura sui ipsius interpres:</title>
                     <subtitle>LUTHER, MODERNITY, AND THE FOUNDATIONS OF PHILOSOPHICAL HERMENEUTICS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Bible studied in the medieval schools was, we know, a glossed text, the<italic>Glossa Ordinaria</italic>, in which each verse is surrounded by notes and commentaries handed down from the Church Fathers.¹ In effect, the biblical text was materially embedded in the history of its interpretation. If one were to look for a symbolic moment of transition between ancient and modern hermeneutics, one might choose the winter semester of 1513–14, when Martin Luther began preparing his first lectures as professor of theology at the University of Wittenberg. He was to lecture on the Psalms and wanted each of his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Wordsworth at the Limits of Romantic Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter I want to try to gloss the above passage, with its reference to something that looks very much like the Stanislavsky method of getting into character, where one loses oneself in the construction of someone else. Imagine a theory of poetry as acting, in which the distinction between being and acting loses its ontological force. As it happens, glossing this passage will mean situating Wordsworth within the history of interpretation, by which I mean the history that concerns itself with the question of understanding. What is it that happens when something, or someone, makes sense, or maybe</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>On the Tragedy of Hermeneutical Experience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hermeneutics is made up of a family of questions about what happens in the understanding of anything, not just of texts but of how things are. This is different from the usual question about how to make understanding happen, how to<italic>produce</italic>it the way you produce a meaning or a statement where one is missing. For hermeneutics, understanding is not (or not just) of meanings; rather, meaning is, metaphorically, the light that a text sheds on the subject (<italic>Sache</italic>) that we seek to understand. Think of<italic>Sache</italic>not as an object of thought or as the product or goal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>What Is Tradition?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My purpose in this chapter is not to try to clarify the hermeneutical concept of tradition in the usual analytical style but rather to work through a number of dialectical reversals in which the concept seems to play itself out, as if it were trying to resist conceptualization. Anyhow I cannot promise to produce a clear idea of what tradition is. Possibly it will be enough if I can just make it harder for people to speak of tradition in the usual way, which is to say, without a second thought—much the way Terry Eagleton speaks of it in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>On the Radical Turn in Hermeneutics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hermeneutics belongs to multiple histories and so cannot be made into any one thing that begins and ends and suffers conceptual revolutions along the way, although in our effort to make sense of hermeneutics this is very much the sort of story we are apt to be looking for and inevitably come to rely on. Thus in the second part of<italic>Truth and Method</italic>Gadamer sketches out a history of hermeneutics that begins with the romantic idealism of Hegel, Schleiermacher, and Dilthey, where hermeneutics is defined in terms of a consciousness whose objects are the products of an expressive spirit</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Against Poetry:</title>
                     <subtitle>HEIDEGGER, RICOEUR, AND THE ORIGINARY SCENE OF HERMENEUTICS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title is meant to take us back to the quarrel between philosophy and poetry that Socrates already regarded as ancient. My sense is that every hermeneutical situation has the structure of this quarrel, which is governed by a logic that is by turns exclusionary and allegorical. Plato’s idea seems to have been that poetry embodies something (we’re not sure what) that interferes with the sort of discourse Socrates is trying to set up and that he seems to be practicing in texts like the<italic>Republic</italic>, where one statement follows another more or less justifiably or according to some principle</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>TOWARD A HERMENEUTICS OF FREEDOM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I’ve said in this book that our relationship with texts, or with the world (or with other people), seems inadequately served by the concept of meaning. I expect now that someone will take me to be saying that texts, etcetera, are meaningless and that hermeneutics is one more thief in the postmodern night. It is true that hermeneutics is not always reputable and that one should always double one’s locks. But a serious hermeneutical lesson that one might draw from this book is that nothing, unfortunately, is meaningless; rather there are more meanings than we know what to do with,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>311</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1dszwtv.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
