<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Spirits of Crossbones Graveyard</book-title>
         <subtitle>Time, Ritual, and Sexual Commerce in London</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hausner</surname>
               <given-names>Sondra L.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253021243</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253021472</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253021472</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>BLOOMINGTON; INDIANAPOLIS</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Sondra L. Hausner</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2005wdm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Every month, a ragtag group of Londoners gather in the site known as Crossbones Graveyard to commemorate the souls of medieval prostitutes believed to be buried there-the "Winchester Geese," women who were under the protection of the Church but denied Christian burial. In the Borough of Southwark, not far from Shakespeare's Globe, is a pilgrimage site for self-identified misfits, nonconformists, and contemporary sex workers who leave memorials to the outcast dead. Ceremonies combining raucous humor and eclectic spirituality are led by a local playwright, John Constable, also known as John Crow. His interpretation of the history of the site has struck a chord with many who feel alienated in present-day London. Sondra L. Hausner offers a nuanced ethnography of Crossbones that tacks between past and present to look at the historical practices of sex work, the relation of the Church to these professions, and their representation in the present. She draws on anthropological approaches to ritual and time to understand the forms of spiritual healing conveyed by the Crossbones rites. She shows that ritual is a way of creating the present by mobilizing the stories of the past for contemporary purposes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="250"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                     <subtitle>SET AND SETTING</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>2</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On November 23, 1996, a London playwright and performer by the name of John Constable had a shamanic vision. In it, a totemic Goose appeared to tell him her tale. She was the spirit of a particular Goose, one who hailed from the jurisdiction of Winchester. In fact, she identified as a Winchester Goose, argot for a medieval prostitute. She and her fellow Winchester Geese had been sex workers in what were called “stews” (or “stewes”) or brothels—or, in later colloquial accounts, “nunneries”¹—on London’s South Bank, in what is now the Borough of Southwark, a mere five hundred</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Myth of the Winchester Goose</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>32</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mythic reality is a strange and ethereal one, one of those few places in the human social universe unconstrained by the limits of time. Whether we embrace the functionalism of the Polish British fieldworker Bronislaw Malinowski or the structuralism of the great French theorist Claude Lévi-Strauss, myth is eternal, as it is designed to be. Its source and its power are both attributable to that particular, enduring capacity of myth to transcend time: mythic narrative creates, sustains, and maneuvers the very origin of our existence. We use the stories of our beginnings to recount—to ourselves and our kin—how</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Medieval Bankside</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the early decades of the Christian era, over many centuries of first Roman and then Saxon occupation, the Borough of Southwark appears to have been populated with a steady stream of merchants, migrants, and miscreants. The Borough’s social and architectural roots lie deep in English history, then, but the beginnings of the Southwark we see today are best dated to the central Middle Ages, around the turn of the first millennium, when the area begins to become a diverse location of high-ranking church officials, religious institutions, and foreign travelers on their way to London. As London grows in population</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Shamanism and the Ritual Oscillation of Time</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What shamans do, the world over, is heal people. They are the conduits to other worlds where cures are available, when the ills that might plague an individual do not lie in this one. Like anyone else on the borders of society, a shaman occupies an ambivalent role: he is powerful and dangerous, necessary but marginal. He may know the ways of nature—and probably does, better than most, because he is closer to it—but as a result he may be seen as farther away, in symbolic terms, from being human. Sherry Ortner’s (1974) famous parallel between women and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Virgin Queen and the English Nation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Redcross Way, the location of our modern ritual, is home to the spirits of a flock of dead prostitutes who are buried in land that lies somewhere between a modern London transport system and an Anglican cathedral. Communing with these spirits and with the London of old—nay, with the Southwark of old—we have a contemporary shaman, who reminds us that we stand before a “singlewomen’s graveyard,” although in truth it is a much later site than the one he refers to in the account of the Tudor chronicler and lay cartographer John Stow. And attending these memorials of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Southwark, Then and Now</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>148</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>All politics, it is said, are local: the manipulation of time, too, must be enacted somewhere. In the story at hand, our ritual takes place in Southwark, a borough that is 300,000 strong in a twenty-first-century London that is vibrantly expanding. Formally incorporated into the City of London in its present form as late as 1965 (Johnson 1969:385), Southwark is one of the densest boroughs in the contemporary capital: the 2011 census lists almost 10,000 residents per square kilometer, double the average for London (and twenty times the average for England, which has always had a large rural population).¹ Some</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                     <subtitle>MAKING THE PRESENT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>178</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The way people construct themselves—and are constructed by others—takes place against the larger discursive frame or backdrop that is culture. Or better, groups construct themselves and others against historical frames that produce culture in the present, and that simultaneously reconstruct the events of the past. That is to say: our narratives about the past explain the way we find ourselves circumscribed in the present. History is constructed to explain the present; historical trajectories determine the cultural or symbolic terms of engagement through which group identities are articulated and against which they are defined. These are fluid processes, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                     <subtitle>CROSSBONES GARDEN</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ten years of activism do not go unnoticed when they touch a cultural chord. In the spring of 2015, one of John’s lobbying goals—to open a garden for Crossbones—came to fruition. Some years earlier, Bankside Open Spaces Trust, a neighborhood charity that works to create “precious patches of green amongst the concrete and glass of Bankside”¹ had been easily won over to the campaign to create a memorial garden. That it would be dedicated to the sex workers of old was less important, perhaps, than that it would offer another grassy corner in the steely metropolis. And with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PERMISSIONS FOR TEXT AND PHOTOGRAPHS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2005wdm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
