<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">KF4575.T87 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Judicial review</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Constitutional history</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">United States. Supreme Court</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Law</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Red, White, and Blue</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Critical Analysis of Constitutional Law</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tushnet</surname>
               <given-names>Mark</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>With a New Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Levinson</surname>
               <given-names>Sanford</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780700621026</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780700621033</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0700621032</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University Press of Kansas</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Lawrence, Kansas</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University Press of Kansas</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ch7988"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The first paperback edition of a classic of American constitutional theory. The book is divided into two parts. In Part I Professor Tushnet appraises the five major competing "grand theories" of constitutional law and interpretation, and, argues that none of them satisfy their own requirements for coherence and judicial constraint. In Part II the author offers a descriptive sociology of constitutional doctrine and raises critical questions as to whether a grand theory is necessary, is it possible to construct a coherent, useful grand theory, and is construction of an uncontroversial grand theory possible?Professor Tushnet's new Afterword is organized in parallel fashion to the original text. Part I offers a new survey of the contemporary terrain of constitutional interpretation. Part II provides an extended discussion of the most prominent of contemporary efforts to provide an external analysis of constitutional law, the idea of regime politics. This includes discussion of major court decisions, including<italic>Bush v. Gore</italic>and<italic>Citizens United.</italic>
         </p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="376"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword to the Paperback Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A classic, it is said, is a work, whether art, literature, or scholarship, that can profitably be re-encountered throughout one’s life, with added appreciation when one places even a presumptively well-known work in the context of a later time. By any of these measures, Mark Tushnet’s<italic>Red, White, and Blue: A Critical Analysis of Constitutional Law,</italic>is a classic, and Jeff Tulis and I, as coeditors of the Constitutional Thinking series at the University Press of Kansas, are delighted to be the agents of its republication more than a quarter-century after its initial publication in 1988. It can be read</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The past few years have seen a remarkable revival of interest in comprehensive normative theories of constitutional law. These grand theories, as I will call them, attempt to provide justifications for the exercise of the power of judicial review in a democracy, that is, the power that courts whose judges are appointed for life have which allows them to displace decisions made by representatives of the people. Current interest in grand theory is striking for two reasons. First, despite the existence of competing grand theories, each one is in its essentials a revived and purified version of an earlier grand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Jurisprudence of History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1985 public controversy erupted over apparently esoteric questions of constitutional theory. Attorney General Edwin Meese III gave a widely publicized speech criticizing the Supreme Court and arguing that the Court should return to a “jurisprudence of original intention,” in which it would construe the Constitution precisely in line with the intentions of the framers. Three months later Justice William Brennan delivered an equally well publicized speech, generally taken to be a response to Meese, that rejected such a jurisprudence as impossible.¹ Meanwhile a less widely noted controversy over following precedent has been simmering. Liberals who formerly admired courts for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Jurisprudence of Democracy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The liberal tradition insists that, in the making of public policy, no one’s view of the good take priority over anyone else’s view.¹ If public policy is to be made it must result from the aggregation of individual preferences. That aspect of the liberal tradition generates an approach to constitutional law that John Hart Ely calls “representation reinforcing review.” If policy is to be based on the aggregation of preferences, there is a strong prima facie case that policy should be made through voting. The voting process asks people to express their preferences; policies based on those revealed preferences emerge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Jurisprudence of Philosophy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>108</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One day, as Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes was leaving to go to the Supreme Court, a friend said to him, “Well, off to do justice again!” Holmes is said to have replied, “Sonny, I don’t do justice; I just make sure that people play by the rules.” The preceding chapters have shown that judges in the liberal tradition cannot merely ensure that people play by the rules. Holmes’s quip suggests that there is nothing else that they can do, and thus, if the preceding chapters are correct, that they cannot do even that. But the justice’s friend appealed to a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Antiformalism in Constitutional Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The preceding chapters have examined a number of efforts to explain why a small group of people, called judges, should be allowed to displace the otherwise legally authoritative decisions of a somewhat larger group of people, called legislators, who are selected by processes that seem closer to the normatively attractive mechanisms of democracy than those used to select judges.¹ These efforts attempt to provide “formalist” solutions to the countermajoritarian difficulty with which the liberal tradition is concerned. This chapter examines antiformalist attempts to displace concern with the countermajoritarian difficulty rather than to allay that concern. It argues that these antiformalist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Intuitionism and Little Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The preceding chapters have explained the important role that grand theory plays in the liberal tradition. They have also suggested that grand theory cannot be made coherent today because of the erosion of the republican tradition. So far, though, we have considered only one theory at a time. Perhaps the theories could be combined so that their strengths reinforce each other and the strengths of one cancel the weaknesses of another. Unfortunately that strategy will not work. In discussing each grand theory I made two general kinds of arguments. First I developed an internal critique of the theory. That critique</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Constitution of Government</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many of the criticisms developed in Part I are familiar to constitutional scholars. The presentation here is distinctive only because it accepts<italic>all</italic>the familiar criticisms. This skepticism about “the rule of law” characterizes Legal Realism, a school of thought from which my arguments are descended. The first section of this chapter describes Legal Realism’s attack on the theory of the rule of law at the heart of the liberal tradition and introduces a discussion of some jurisprudential responses to the Realist challenge. The second section examines a recent development in constitutional theory—structural review—that is another heir to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Constitution of the Bureaucratic State</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since 1970 the Supreme Court has been grappling with the constitutional aspects of the welfare state. It held in<italic>Goldberg v. Kelly</italic>that the Constitution guarantees a relatively formal hearing to any recipient of public assistance whose benefits are threatened with termination.¹<italic>Goldberg</italic>was the Court’s recognition that the growth of the welfare state required some response from those who regard enforcing the Constitution as a primary method of regulating government conduct.² Prior to the 1950s benefits received from the government were taken to be privileges, not rights, and were therefore immune from regulation under constitutional norms.³ Yet it seemed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Constitution of Religion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The constitutional law of religion is “in significant disarray.”¹ States may subsidize the purchase of books by students at religious schools, but they may not subsidize the purchase of globes.² States may engage in ritualistic invocation of religious norms, but they may not attempt to inculcate the norms that give sense to the rituals.³ Exempting from the Social Security system those who oppose participation for reasons based on religious belief threatens the integrity of the tax structure,⁴ but exempting the same people from the education system does not substantially affect<italic>its</italic>integrity.⁵ Forms of aid to nonpublic schools that are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Constitution of the Market</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Today’s prevalent political theories describe the task of social institutions, such as the market and the political process, as aggregating the preferences of society’s members. (See, for instance, Chapter 2.) Social institutions themselves, however, influence the preferences that they are then supposed to aggregate.¹ It is difficult to understand how the aggregation can coherently take place when preferences are not exogenous to the institutions.</p>
                     <p>This chapter examines some institutional dimensions of the construction of preferences in the United States by exploring the constitutional law applicable to the regulation of campaign finance, commercial speech, and pornography. The topics are connected, as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The basic argument of this book is fundamentally simple: the liberal tradition makes constitutional theory both necessary and impossible. It is necessary because it provides the restraints that the liberal tradition requires us to place on those in power, legislators and judges as well. It is impossible because no available approach to constitutional law can effectively restrain both legislators and judges: If we restrain the judges we leave legislators unconstrained; if we restrain the legislators we let the judges do what they want.</p>
                     <p>It is possible to reject the proposition that constitutional theory is necessary and impossible, and people usually</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword to the Paperback Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Undoubtedly<italic>Red, White, and Blue</italic>would be a different book if I wrote it today.¹ Some of the topics I discussed would now be classified as falling within the domain of constitutional history rather than in that of constitutional law. Other topics of interest today were not on my radar screen in the 1980s. And, of course, there have been developments within some of the approaches to constitutional interpretation that I did discuss—most notably, originalism. Fully updating<italic>Red, White, and Blue</italic>would mean writing an entirely new book, and I would not be interested in using a book written</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Cases</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>General Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>353</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ch7988.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>358</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
