<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Ways of the Word</book-title>
         <subtitle>Learning to Preach for Your Time and Place</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Brown</surname>
               <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Powery</surname>
               <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780800699222</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">080069922X</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506410302</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506410308</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortres</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt19qgg2f"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Preaching, and the discipline of preaching, is at a crossroads. The changing realities of church and theological education, the diversity of our classrooms, and our increasingly complex community contexts leave us in search of tools to help train a rising generation of preachers for a future whose contours are far from clear. In Ways of the Word, a dynamic team of master preachers, Sally A. Brown and Luke A. Powery, speaks with one voice their belief that preaching is a witness to the ongoing work of God in the world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powery</surname>
                           <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powery</surname>
                           <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Every book has its backstory. It can be difficult to pinpoint where that backstory begins; but it is safe to say that this one began in an e-mail exchange. Picture two preacher-homileticians hammering on their computer keyboards in offices some 150 yards apart on an East Coast seminary campus: “We could do this—a new textbook” // “right—tapping into our traditions, Baptist-Pentecostal/Reformed—and crossing race and gender too” // “for changing classroom demographic?” // “right!” //”Spirit-driven” // “yes” // “you serious?” // “of course.”</p>
                     <p>Such exchanges formed part of a larger web of animated dialogue about the changing realities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Spirit-Animated Event of Preaching</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powery</surname>
                           <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Preaching is risky business. It is risky because, frankly, its divine aims are impossible to achieve, humanly speaking. There is no set of rules any of us can follow, no book we can read (this one included), that guarantees that when you step up to a pulpit and open your mouth, the words that reach listeners will be a word that is God’s own. We can speak with consummate rhetorical skill of things theological, but only God’s animating Spirit makes our preaching a life-transforming, world-changing message.</p>
                     <p>As the chapters of this book hope to show, the skill sets that preaching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A Spirit-Driven Theology of Preaching</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powery</surname>
                           <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During my first year in seminary, on a particular weekday in Princeton Seminary’s Miller Chapel—essentially a Presbyterian meetinghouse built for worship in 1834—the preacher spoke of the Spirit as if she was his best friend and closest confidante. This seniorclass student began to preach and as he proclaimed, he interjected the phrase, “Help me, Holy Ghost!” One time. Two times. Three times—and then I lost count of how many times he said, “Help me, Holy Ghost!” Maybe he was praying for himself in the moment because he realized the sermon wasn’t going over too well in this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Preaching and Prayer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powery</surname>
                           <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It may not always be obvious to human eyes, but to the One who sees the heart as an altar, it is clear that what is inside preachers is just as important as what comes outside of preachers through words and actions. In the long view of life, it may be possible to discover that an altered life is an altar-ed life, though in the micro-moments of the everyday this may be hard to discern. Even more, when it comes to preaching, we may not be so sure what impact the spiritual life truly has on our preaching and what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Preaching as an Act of Worship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As any naturalist would tell us, if we want to understand how a living creature normally functions, we need to observe it in its natural habitat. Something similar is true of preaching. There are undoubtedly people whose lives have been transformed by a sermon they picked up on the car radio while driving across Texas or stumbled upon while searching the Internet for a long-lost friend. But a stand-alone sermon, like a single shot from a film, is lifted out of its native setting. In this chapter we consider preaching in relation to its natural context, Christian worship.</p>
                     <p>The worship</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Preacher as Interpreter of Word and World</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human beings are nonstop interpreters. From the moment we awake, we interpret our experience through all our senses. The rumble of a truck in the dark of early dawn prompts us to wonder if we remembered to put out the trash. We sniff the cream carton and decide to take our morning coffee black. Gathering clouds prompt us to grab an umbrella on the way out the door. On the morning commute, a sudden flash of dozens of red brake lights ahead alerts us to stalled traffic. In the hallway on the way to the office, a coworker’s smile lifts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Interpreting Scripture for Preaching</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scripture has been the indispensable, authorizing source of Christian sermons since Christianity’s beginnings. The sermons of Peter, Stephen, and Paul in Acts all draw on Old Testament texts. The book of Hebrews, thought by some to be a collection of early Christian sermons, draws on material across the Old Testament, especially the Psalms. This chapter provides you with a disciplined, prayerful, and scholarly process for engaging Scripture. Exegetical work (close grammatical, historical, and theological study of a text) is supported in this method by meditative Scripture reading using the centuriesold process called<italic>lectio divina</italic>(“divine reading”).</p>
                     <p>The living word of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Designing the Sermon’s Form</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A while back, a pastoral search committee asked me to come help them think about preaching. Confronted with dozens of pastors’ dossiers and hundreds of sermons, they asked, “How do you know what to look and listen for?” When we met, I started by asking each one at the table to answer one question: “Let’s say that on your way out of church, you’ve turned to your neighbor and remarked, ‘Now,<italic>that</italic>was a good sermon!’ Why would you be saying that? What makes a sermon ‘good’?” Among the nine or ten folks around the table there were at least</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Embodying the Sermon</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powery</surname>
                           <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Harlem Renaissance writer James Weldon Johnson describes a sermonic scene in Kansas City that prompted his collection of poems and sermons known as<italic>God’s Trombones</italic>. He says this riveting preaching moment was “a very rhythmic dance, and [the preacher] brought into the play the full gamut of his wonderful voice, a voice—what shall I say?—not of an organ or a trumpet, but rather of a trombone. … He intoned, he moaned, he pleaded—he blared, he crashed, he thundered. … I was, perhaps against my will, deeply moved; the emotional effect upon me was irresistible.”¹ Johnson illuminates the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Preaching and Technology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Powery</surname>
                           <given-names>Luke A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter, we learned how the Word became flesh in Jesus Christ and the ways in which this deepens our understanding of the role of the human body in preaching. While this is true, it is also obvious that in this digital age, some may assert that the Word has also now become digital. One cannot deny technology’s pervasive presence in society, including the church and its preaching. The fact of technology and its use will not be disappearing anytime soon; thus, this chapter will explore what it means to engage technologies in preaching and some of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Preaching and Christian Formation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Brown</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A few minutes before five o’clock on a Sunday afternoon cars are pulling into the parking garage beside a multilevel, steel-and-glass structure in the redeveloped downtown of a Midwestern city. The building complex is inviting. With covered walkways and shaded benches, open courtyards and play areas, it invites the passersby to explore. Windows of all sizes and shapes reflect the late-afternoon sun.</p>
                     <p>Signs point to businesses and human-service enterprises throughout the four levels of the complex. There is a daycare center here for children, a community center with programs for grade-school age kids and senior adults, a couple of cafés,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19qgg2f.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
