<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6nwr0t</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1997.P474D38 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Piano (Motion picture)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Kiss of the spider woman (Motion picture)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Puig, Manuel. Beso de la mujer araña</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Northern exposure (Television program)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Postmodernism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Postmodern Texts and Emotional Audiences</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Davis</surname>
               <given-names>Kimberly Chabot</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>09</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781557534798</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781612490243</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Purdue University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>West Lafayette, Indiana</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2007</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Purdue University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt6wq429"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Chabot Davis analyzes contemporary texts that bond together two seemingly antithetical sensibilities: the sentimental and the postmodern. Ranging across multiple media and offering a methodological union of textual analysis and reception study, Chabot Davis presents case studies of audience responses.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>Sentimental Postmodernism, Identification, and the Feeling Audience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Postmodern literature and film have often been characterized by a thematic obsession with the disintegration of families, communities, and larger socio-political ties. Rather than painting such dark themes with the brush of tragedy, postmodern texts often adopt a tone of mocking irony or disaffected nihilism. Kathy Acker’s parodic avant-garde fiction, for example, is a complex meditation on contemporary nihilism, on the “nothingness everybody now seems to want” (<italic>In Memoriam to Identity</italic>263). The hipness of postmodern disaffection was cemented with the popularity of Quentin Tarantino’s film<italic>Pulp Fiction</italic>(1994), which turns an absence of morality into fodder for black comedy.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>Critical Hybridity and the Building of Methodological Bridges</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theory and method informing this study can best be described as a dialectical mediation between dissimilar cultural genres and between antagonistic scholarly traditions. The critical dialectic of sentimental postmodernism allows me to illuminate theoretical biases and blind spots in scholarship concerning both postmodernism and popular affective genres. While many theorists of postmodern culture pay lip service to the idea that postmodernism breaks down the division between high and popular culture, most of their exemplary texts are nonetheless high art or avant-garde works. Focusing on irony, self-reflexivity, avant-garde aesthetics, and poststructuralist ideas about language, many of these critics draw a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>The Piano and Feminist Political Identification</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most “talked about” feminist films of the 1990s, Jane Campion’s<italic>The Piano</italic>provoked vehement debate among both film critics and female viewers. At one otherwise tame New Year’s Eve party in 1996, as I described my research to a woman I had just met, she launched into a violent diatribe against the film, which soon attracted five or six others, who began shouting out their own reviews. The fiery conversation ended when another woman stormed off, declaring that she couldn’t bear to see her favorite film so maligned, to see Ada “dragged through the mud” once again.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>Northern Exposure and Postmodern Utopian Communities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Once one of the most popular programs on television and winner of an Emmy for Best Drama in 1991–92,<italic>Northern Exposure</italic>was unusually highbrow television fare, offering viewers weekly philosophical ruminations about cultural pluralism, democracy, gender and sexuality, and the meaning of artistic production. Many television critics have commented that<italic>Exposure’</italic>s demise after six seasons (1990–95) was less surprising than the fact that this intellectual show ever commanded such a large following. Ranked in the Nielsen top-15 for three seasons, the program spawned several fanclubs, including an Internet newsgroup (alt.tv.northern-exp). While “quality” television programs aimed at affluent and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Kiss of the Spider Woman and the Politics of Camp</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With its thematic focus on identification and leftist politics, Manuel Puig’s<italic>Kiss of the Spider Woman</italic>is a paradigmatic text of sentimental postmodernism. Since the text is also centrally concerned with the politics of mass culture and of homosexuality, it bears some relationship to the critical practice called “camp.” Many critics have analyzed<italic>Kiss of the Spider Woman</italic>as a work of “gay fiction,” but none has attempted to situate Puig’s text or its film and musical adaptations in relation to camp as a gay or queer critique of heterosexual mass culture and its value systems. Any academic discussion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                     <subtitle>Cross-Group Empathy before and after 9/11</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Without these detailed case studies of the impact of sentimental postmodernism upon readers and viewers, an analysis of the politics of this hybrid style would be incomplete and highly speculative. My contextual and empirical work with audiences is crucial to the conclusion that much of the political power of sentimental postmodernism can be found in the intense identifications that it fosters both within and across sexual identities, genders, and ethnicities. Much of the current critical work about identification has been produced by textual scholars writing from psychoanalytic perspectives. While these textual theorists have given us valuable insights concerning the ambivalent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix A</title>
                     <subtitle>Annotated Transcript of an Interview for the Kiss of the Spider Woman Case Study</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>C.G.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>KCD</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix B</title>
                     <subtitle>Transcript of an Interview for The Piano Case Study</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>D.M.</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>KCD</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix C</title>
                     <subtitle>Questionnaire for the Northern Exposure Fan-club</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt6wq429.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
