<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn31p0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Forgetting Differences</book-title>
         <subtitle>Tragedy, Historiography, and the French Wars of Religion</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Frisch</surname>
               <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748694396</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748694402</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Andrea Frisch</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt16r0hwb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This study argues that the political and legislative process of forgetting internal differences, undertaken in France after the civil wars of the sixteenth century, leads to subtle yet fundamental shifts in the broader conception of the relationship between readers or spectators on the one hand, and the matter of history, on the other. These shifts, occasioned by the desire for communal reconciliation and generally associated with an increasingly modern sensibility, will nonetheless prove useful to the ideologies of cultural and political absolutism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Editor’s Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hutson</surname>
                           <given-names>Lorna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Learning to Forget</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Focused on France in the period 1560–1630, this study examines the impact in France of the monarchical call to extinguish the memory of the Wars of Religion on post-war national historiography and on the elite sense of History more generally. This policy of<italic>oubliance</italic>is no doubt best known through the 1598 Edict of Nantes’s call, in the first sentence of its opening article:</p>
                     <p>que la memoire de toutes choses passées d’une part et d’autre, depuis le commencement du mois de mars mil cinq cens quatre vingtz cinq jusques à nostre avenement à la couronne, et durant les autres</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Clemency, Pardon, and Oubliance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his exhaustive study of an “event without a history,” as he calls it, Denis Crouzet sets the St. Bartholomew’s Day massacre in the context of French Renaissance dreams of community.¹ According to Crouzet, at the time of the massacre, the French king, Charles IX, was at the center of several competing visions of French concord. The most dramatic of these visions imagined the king as the agent of divine justice in its Old Testament form: a series of writers advocated the use of violence to rid France of heresy and thus reunite the French. Others, most notably the chancelier</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>History without Passion:</title>
                     <subtitle>National Historiography in the Age of Oubliance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the article on the city Mâcon in his 1697<italic>Dictionnaire historique et critique</italic>, Pierre Bayle devotes a long, convoluted<italic>remarque</italic>to the question of whether he should include material about the Wars of Religion in his work.² He begins by paraphrasing the sixteenth-century edicts of pacification that urged the French to extinguish memories of the conflicts: “it would be desirable that the memory of all of those inhuman acts had been abolished in the first place, and that all the books that spoke about it had been thrown into the fire.”³ Those who hold that memories of the conflicts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Tragedy as History:</title>
                     <subtitle>From the Guisiade to Garnier</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pierre Matthieu was certainly not the first to characterize the French Wars of Religion in terms of tragedy. The intersection between history and tragedy was a commonplace in French writing about the wars from all sides, and in many different genres. An anonymous 1562 “Advertissement à la Royne mere du Roy” complains to Catherine de Médicis about the treatment of the Huguenots, using a theatrical metaphor to warn the queen mother that she risks becoming the main character in the tragedy represented by a France at civil war:</p>
                     <p>Si vous ne vous esveillez de ce sommeil, il vous sera mortel,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>From Emotion to Affect</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In light of works like the<italic>Guisiade</italic>or the<italic>Mort de Coligny</italic>, as well as Robert Garnier’s relentlessly grim depictions of tragic distress, we might be moved to ask Pierre Bayle’s question, this time of tragedy: how could tragic theater, with its moving representations of explosive political intrigues and interfamilial violence, possibly have functioned as an instrument of reconciliation in the wake of the Wars of Religion?</p>
                     <p>In his comprehensive<italic>History of French Dramatic Literature in the Seventeenth Century</italic>, Henry C. Lancaster remarks that “Civil war doubtless retarded the growth of the French stage.”² Yet he concludes his discussion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By approaching the rhetoric of<italic>oubliance</italic>primarily as a strategy for reconciliation, I have sought to move the focus of my analysis away from the concept of forgetting and towards that of forgetting differences.<italic>Oubliance</italic>, in the texts studied here, does not entail censorship of the past so much as its reframing. The paratexts and programmatic statements I have highlighted afford insight into the ways in which elite writers forged the rhetorical tools with which they and their readers could reconcile themselves to their troubling recent past, and thus to one another.</p>
                     <p>Two central theses emerge from the material studied</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16r0hwb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
