<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Only Mind Worth Having</book-title>
         <subtitle>Thomas Merton and the Child Mind</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gardner</surname>
               <given-names>Fiona</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Williams</surname>
               <given-names>Rowan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718894412</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718844745</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fiona Gardner</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1p5f2w5"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In The Only Mind Worth Having, Fiona Gardner takes Thomas Merton’s belief that the child mind is “the only mind worth having" and explores it in the context of Jesus’ challenging, paradoxical, and enigmatic command to become like small children. She demonstrates how Merton’s belief and Jesus’ command can be understood as part of contemporary spirituality and spiritual practice. To follow Christ’s command requires a great leap of the imagination. Gardner examines what it might mean to make this leap when one is an adult without it becoming sentimental and mawkish, or regressive and pathological. Using both psychological and spiritual insights, and drawing on the experiences of Thomas Merton and others, Gardner suggests that in some mysterious and paradoxical way recovering a sense of childhood spirituality is the path towards spiritual maturity. The move from childhood spirituality to adulthood and on to a spiritual maturity through the child mind is a move from innocence to experience to organised innocence, or from dependence to independence to a state of being in-dependence with God.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="242"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Williams</surname>
                           <given-names>Rowan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Becoming a child again: the first reaction may be a feeling that this would be wonderful—no responsibility, no battling with expectations, no long memories of failure and ambiguity. But when Jesus of Nazareth tells us to become like children, and when spiritual masters urge us to connect with the “child mind,” they are not being nostalgic or sentimental. They are drawing our attention to something we all instinctively recognise. There is something that our habitual adult consciousness has lost or buried, and it must be found, not as a comforting reinstatement of half-forgotten happiness but as a breakthrough to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction to Jesus’ Command, to Thomas Merton, and to Ideas about the Spirit of the Child</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In three of the four gospels Jesus commands those wanting to follow him to change, to receive his teachings and experience discipleship as a young child:</p>
                     <p>Truly I tell you, unless you change and become like children, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven. (Matt 18:3)</p>
                     <p>Truly I tell you, whoever does not receive the kingdom of heaven as a little child will never enter it. (Mark 10:15; the exact same words are repeated in Luke 18:17)</p>
                     <p>What did Jesus mean by his statement to become like children—or the “little children” of Mark and Luke? What does it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Infancy and Rebirth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the small child everything is of interest and natural. He or she enters into the world that surrounds them with great energy. In one sense there are few boundaries and so the child imbues everything with equal interest. “He enters into the world of things with all his senses . . . everything is alive, full of eyes and ears . . . the child is initiated into the secret life of ordinary objects, often the most miniscule.”¹ The tiny details matter and there can be either a pleasurable rapturous immersion or the opposite—great desolation.</p>
                     <p>It has been</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Thinking about God as Parent and God as Child</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Can we love God as a parent? How confusing does this become if we also love God as the Christ child—indeed as the eternal child within us? Reading the Bible suggests that envisaging God as both parent and child, though a paradox, is yet conceivable and that the one does not cancel out the other. Both are about relationship; one way to understand the everchanging relationship with God is to consider the psychodynamics. As Lancelot Andrewes (1555–1626) expressed it, “Christianity is a meeting.”¹ Using the term “psychodynamics” implies that the relationship with God is never static. It involves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Influence of Monastics, Saints, and Theologians on Thomas Merton’s Thinking on the Child Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thomas Merton was living the scriptures through the monastic offices, reading extensively the works of the religious, the lives of the saints, and the work of theologians. In his writings and especially in the journals many are cited and some of these are selected here to be discussed in the context of the child mind. Bernard of Clairvaux (1090–1153) was a French abbot and primary builder of the reforming Cistercian monastic order. Guerric of Igny (<italic>c</italic>. 1070/80–1157) was a Cistercian abbot. Thomas Merton was steeped in Cistercian monastic thinking. He wrote a book on Bernard called<italic>The Last</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Child’s Mind is Buddha’s Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Eastern thought has long understood the value of the child mind in the adult seeker for spiritual maturity. The child mind is seen as a place of surrender, alertness, and nakedness. It is seen as a space where there is little if any self-consciousness; there is no judgment of others. It is a time of humility. It involves an awareness of the person’s nothingness—where the person is no -thing. The child mind recognizes the person’s smallness and yet connection in the scheme of things, and in Eastern practices it is seen as a state that can be developed through</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Shadow and the Disguise:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Adult Life of Care</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From both the Western and Eastern traditions it is acknowledged that characteristics of childhood are seen as essential for the spiritual life. So what goes wrong as we get older and why is it so hard to hold on to the promise of childhood spirituality? One helpful way to begin to think about it is to understand that as we grow as children we become increasingly compliant and then turn away from the vivid feelings we knew as children. As we learn to fit in and pick and choose certain words and phrases to describe what is happening and what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Enchanted World, the Tendency towards Dis-enchantment, and the Possibility of Re-enchantment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For all small children life is mysterious and mostly incomprehensible until the adults caring for them begin to help them form a pattern, a routine, and then a sense of coherent order, and, so, purpose gradually emerges. The small baby is subject to strong and sometimes overwhelming feelings, both good and bad, and hopefully is helped to manage this by the containing presence of a caring and loving adult. In the next chapter we will discuss what happens when this is not the case. As small children begin to play and if their imaginations and creativity are allowed to flourish,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Secret Life of the Wounded Child</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For some people the very idea that childhood can be meaningfully associated with joy and so in any meaningful way carefree is unrealistic. A significant number of children have experiences of emotional, physical, and sexual abuse, and others are neglected. Some may have experienced a restrictive illness or disability, or been exposed to loss or upsetting situations by the adults or by friends or siblings in their lives. A difficult or damaged childhood will cast a long shadow and can lead to an inability to trust and problems in later relationships. The lack of trust can lead to a sense</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Finding Spiritual and Psychological Healing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Frequently the person damaged in childhood yearns for some form of healing; though it may not be clear what form that healing could take. The part of the child that needs to be heard and recognized, and so to emerge into the light, is the wounded child part whose feelings have been hidden as a way of self-protection. It could be said that an invitation from the divine child or the true self within each person encourages each person to step out of the constraints of convention and expectation to explore and to be healed both psychologically and spiritually. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>An Invitation to Look and Find Paradise</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Present-moment awareness is about creating a gap in the constant busyness of the mind. This also means a break in the continuum between what is past and what lies ahead. It is through such a clear space that new and creative possibilities are born. The closing down of present-moment awareness in the small child happens as the weight of the adult life of care and rational thought gradually but relentlessly obscures the enchanted world. The possibility of re-enchantment and sometimes the invitation to move from the grown-up life of care can come from a child: from being in the presence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Dancing in the Water of Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The theologian Dorothee Soelle thought that in the materialist West we are “orphan-like in relation to nature,”² and that in earlier cultures visions and experiences of another reality were commonplace—especially in early childhood. Even in our contemporary culture the small child does not discriminate between aspects of creation through accepting one thing such as the butterfly, and rejecting another such as the slug, until they are encouraged to do so. Anything and everything is amazing and is worthy of notice and interest until judgement sets in and positive values are apportioned to one thing and negative attributes to others.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Poetry:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Language of the Child Mind</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Poets and poetry have been drawn on already throughout this book for certain poets seem able to articulate so well aspects of the child mind. This chapter explores why this might be and focuses on the characteristics of the language of poetry. For as a form of expression poetry usually communicates authenticity. Poets speak and write of a way of looking at the everyday with a sensitivity that can take the hearer and reader beyond that everyday into another level of consciousness. Perhaps there are ways that some poetry can tap directly into the unconscious of the reader or hearer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>The Divine Play of God:</title>
                     <subtitle>Play and Creativity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This contemporary tale (origin unknown) contains the care worn adult whose vision and senses are blunted. As all these are stripped away the light begins to return and the image of God returns as a small child ready to play. Play, creativity, and the imagination are not only aspects of childhood but are characteristics of the spirit of the child that remain still potentially available in the adult. In absorbed play and concentrated creativity self-consciousness can be forgotten and the disguise or the false self is left behind. Play can also be a way to integrate the shadow and all</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>The Internal Landscape of the Child Mind and Models of Spiritual Maturity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thomas Merton was constantly struggling with the question of identity, and in his search for spiritual integrity and thereby maturity he engaged in a continual struggle to be free from an imprisoning and distorting self-consciousness that plagued him and, he believed, all human beings to a greater or lesser extent. He included in this searching both grace and psychology and he saw that these could work together, sometimes being in conflict. Merton was searching for full identity in Christ and for what spiritual maturity might mean, and from glimpses of his work the suggestion in this book is that he</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Epiphanies of the Child Mind</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thomas Merton’s vocation was to live what he discovered about himself, in that way he was always open to becoming and there was always potential for change. For the adult Merton the child mind is linked to the experiential, to a theology of feeling and a condition of simplicity. This means to be without artifice, unpretentious, aware of the unconscious and so awake to the illusory nature of the world—and so able to speak truth to power. The foundation for this is a dependence on God framed within the concept of mercy exemplified in God’s relationship with his creation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the things that happened when writing this book is that more and more examples have leapt out at me of people who had experienced the idea of the child mind and so as adults exemplified the spirit of the child. For example, watching the 1928 film made by Carl Dreyer of the trial of Joan of Arc I was moved when she confessed before her martyrdom: “Yes, I am His child.” Another find was dipping into the life of the poet Francis Thompson and reading his words where he said to look for him in the nurseries of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibiliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2w5.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
