<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PL2461.Z7H46 1991</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chinese classics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, Confucian</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Scripture, Canon and Commentary</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Comparison of Confucian and Western Exegesis</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>HENDERSON</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400861989</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400861985</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1991</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zvb8n"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In this major contribution to the study of the Chinese classics and comparative religion, John Henderson uses the history of exegesis to illuminate mental patterns that have universal and perennial significance for intellectual history. Henderson relates the Confucian commentarial tradition to other primary exegetical traditions, particularly the Homeric tradition, Vedanta, rabbinic Judaism, ancient and medieval Christian biblical exegesis, and Qur'anic exegesis. In making such comparisons, he discusses some basic assumptions common to all these traditions--such as that the classics or scriptures are comprehensive or that they contain all significant knowledge or truth and analyzes the strategies deployed to support these presuppositions. As shown here, primary differences among commentarial or exegetical traditions arose from variations in their emphasis on one or another of these assumptions and strategies. Henderson demonstrates that exegetical modes of thought were far from arcane: they dominated the post-classical/premodern intellectual world. Some have persisted or re-emerged in modern times, particularly in ideologies such as Marxism. Written in an engaging and accessible style, Scripture, Canon, and Commentary is not only a challenging interpretation of comparative scriptural traditions but also an excellent introduction to the study of the Confucian classics.</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1991.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="260"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PERIODS OF CHINESE HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ABBREVIATIONS AND SHORT FORMS USED IN THE NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>COMMENTARIES and commentarial modes of thinking dominated the intellectual history of most premodern civilizations, a fact often obscured by the “great ideas” approach to the history of thought and by modern scholars’ denigration of the works of mere exegetes and annotators. Until the seventeenth century in Europe, and even later in China, India, and the Near East, thought, especially within high intellectual traditions, was primarily exegetical in character and expression. As José Faur has observed, “The most peculiar aspect of the medieval thinker is that he developed his ideas around a text and expressed them as a commentary.”¹ Even those</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>ORIGINS AND ANTECEDENTS OF THE CLASSICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE CONFUCIAN canon (or canons) is as diverse in its origins and complicated in its development as that of almost any major classical or scriptural tradition.¹ Its antecedents may plausibly be traced back to such variegated sources as the oracle-bone divination of the second millennium b.c. and to folk songs and sayings by early inhabitants of the North China Plain. Although standard versions of the canon were fixed under the Han dynasty, with a major reformation coming more than a millennium later in the Sung era, classical scholars continued to propose revisions and re-enumerations of the classics in the centuries</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>INTEGRATION, DEVELOPMENT, AND CLOSURE OF CANONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>CANONIZATION, the identification and stabilization of a body of classical or sacred texts that is declared to be authoritative, frequently proceeds by political, ecclesiastical, or literary fiat.¹ Such fiats are often confirmed by high-powered councils and supported by such forceful political figures as the Emperor Wu (Han Wu-ti) in Han China and the Emperor Constantine in the late-Roman West.</p>
                     <p>Councils and kings certainly played a significant role in the establishment of Confucian canons in the Han era. As early as 136 b.c., the Emperor Wu, acting on the advice of Tung Chung-shu (c. 179—c.104 b.c.) and other Confucian scholars,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>ORIGINS, DIMENSIONS, AND APOTHEOSIS OF COMMENTARIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>HE RANGE of works typed as “commentary” may vary widely. By a narrow definition, a commentary may refer only to a running gloss on a text generally recognized as classical or scriptural.¹ A wider conception would identify much of the literature of the postclassical, or “silver,” age in several civilizations or traditions as forms of commentary (or, in some cases, hidden commentary) on the classics. Barry Holtz, for example, has remarked that almost all of Jewish literature, from the legal codes of the Middle Ages to the Hasidic homilies of the nineteenth century, “presents itself as nothing more than interpretation,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>COMMENTARIAL ASSUMPTIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE MOST UNIVERSAL and widely expressed commentarial assumption regarding the character of almost any canon is that it is comprehensive and all-encompassing, that it contains all significant learning and truth. As Jonathan Z. Smith has written, “Where there is a canon we can predict the necessary occurrence of a hermeneute, of an interpreter whose task it is to continually extend the domain of the closed canon over everything that is known or everything that is.”¹ This is true not only of classical or scriptural canons, such as Homer, the Christian Bible, the Torah, the Qur’ān, the Veda, and the Confucian</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>COMMENTARIAL STRATEGIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>LIKE THE SIX OR SEVEN basic commentarial assumptions outlined in the preceding chapter, the strategies and arguments used by exegetes to support those assumptions are common to several classical and scriptural traditions. It is, after all, reasonable that similar sets of presuppositions regarding the character of the classics or scriptures should have called forth similar arguments for establishing the truth of those conceptions. But although such common commentarial strategies as allegory, the idea of accommodation, and scholastic or modal distinctions appear<italic>somewhere</italic>in most major traditions, these traditions differ significantly among themselves in the extent to which they employ particular</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>DEATH AND TRANSFIGURATION OF COMMENTARIAL WORLD VIEWS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>200</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE TRANSITION from commentarial forms and modes of discourse to modern scholarship and criticism is one of the most important in the intellectual history of mankind. Prior to the twentieth century, though, such a transition occurred in only three of the major traditions surveyed here: the biblical, the Homeric, and the Confucian (and in this last only incompletely). Despite the similarities in the commentarial assumptions and strategies employed in all the major traditions covered here, they parted ways in the speed and direction with which they entered (or made) the modern intellectual world. In at least two of these traditions,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>GLOSSARY OF CHINESE NAMES, TERMS, AND TITLES IN THE TEXT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SELECTED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zvb8n.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
