<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Holy One in Our Midst</book-title>
         <subtitle>An Essay on the Flesh of Christ</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Gordon</surname>
               <given-names>James R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781506408347</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1506408346</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506408354</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506408354</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortress</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1b3t7gp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Holy One in Our Midst: An Essay on the Flesh of Christ aims to defend the doctrine of the extra Calvinisticum—the doctrine that maintains the Son of God was not restricted to the flesh of Christ during the incarnation—by arguing that it is logically coherent, biblically warranted, catholically orthodox, and theologically useful. It shows that none of the standard objections are devastating to the extra, that the doctrine is rooted in the claims of Christian Scripture and not merely a remnant of perfect being philosophical theology, and that the doctrine plays an important role in contemporary theological discussion. In this way, James R. Gordon revives an important Catholic doctrine that has fallen out of favor in contemporary theology. Secondarily, this project aims to integrate biblical, philosophical, and systematic theology by showing that the tools and methods of each distinct discipline can contribute to the goals and aims of the others.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gordon</surname>
                           <given-names>James R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gordon</surname>
                           <given-names>James R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Flesh of Christ and the Extra Calvinisticum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The doctrine known as the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>states that the eternal Son of God, during his incarnate life on earth, was not enclosed by or limited to the physical body of Jesus Christ but continued to uphold the universe by virtue of maintaining a form of presence beyond or outside Jesus’ physical body.¹ This counterintuitive area of Christology has received little attention in the history of theological reflection, so much so that Edward Oakes has claimed that “no topic in Christology ... is more arcane than that of the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>.”² Despite being an “esoteric topic of Christology,”³ there are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Flesh of Christ in Modern Theology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Objections to the Extra Calvinisticum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first chapter we highlighted the significance of the doctrine known as the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>and attempted to identify some important areas of discussion that have gone unaddressed. In addition, we offered a preview of the cumulative-case argument to be constructed and identified the major goals of this project. Specifically, we claimed that there have been no extended statements of or responses to the theological objections to the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>; the question of the doctrine’s overall coherency has largely been ignored by its adherents and is quickly appealed to by its detractors. Because of this confusion, chapters 2 and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Logos and the Flesh of Christ:</title>
                     <subtitle>Responding to the Objections to the Extra Calvinisticum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the previous chapter we attempted to state clearly the theological objections to the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>in the theologies of Isaak Dorner, the mature Karl Barth, Bruce McCormack, and Darren Sumner. Taken together, the five objections outlined in chapter 2 cast a large shadow over the<italic>extra</italic>and lead one to question whether the doctrine has persuasive force, let alone positive doctrinal value—that is, whether the objections are indeed insurmountable. The present chapter will demonstrate that none of the major theological objections to the<italic>extra</italic>conclusively provides a sufficient reason for abandoning the doctrine. The following two chapters will</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Temple of God and the Flesh of Christ:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Constructive Argument for the Extra Calvinisticum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 2 we outlined the major objections to the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>, which we subsequently defused in chapter 3. In this chapter, we will proceed by making our own constructive argument for the<italic>extra</italic>; however, before doing so, we will note the specific modes of argumentation that have often been used to defend the<italic>extra</italic>. Whereas chapter 5 will attempt to show that the<italic>extra</italic>serves numerous purposes in theological discourse, the present chapter attempts to illustrate that theologians have arrived at an affirmation of the<italic>extra</italic>in a variety of different ways and to offer an argument for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>(De)Limiting the Flesh of Christ:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Proper Dogmatic Uses of the Extra Calvinisticum</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter offers an account of the proper and improper dogmatic uses of the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>. In order to do so, we will refute the suggestion that the<italic>extra</italic>ought to function only in a small, christological capacity, examine two of the most significant positive uses of the<italic>extra</italic>in modern theology, suggest three specific theological<italic>loci</italic>the<italic>extra</italic>informs, and propose a way to discern what sorts of dogmatic uses of the<italic>extra</italic>are illegitimate.</p>
                     <p>As we discussed in chapter 1, the most recent study on the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>, Andrew McGinnis’s<italic>The Son of God beyond the Flesh</italic>, traces</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Why One Ought to Embrace the Extra Calvinisticum</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapters have attempted to mount a cumulative-case argument for the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>by highlighting the doctrine’s significance to groups with various theological interests, surveying uses of and objections to the doctrine throughout the Christian tradition, clearing the ground of logical obstacles to the doctrine, examining the doctrine’s place in Scripture, and offering suggestions for contemporary theological usage of the doctrine. In so doing, we have accomplished the three main goals of this project mentioned in chapter 1: (1) to state and defuse the objections to the<italic>extra Calvinisticum</italic>, (2) to provide warrant for the<italic>extra</italic>by showing (a)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1b3t7gp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>242</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
