<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Luther and Liberation</book-title>
         <subtitle>A Latin American Perspective</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Altmann</surname>
               <given-names>Walter</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781451482683</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">145148268X</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781506408033</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1506408036</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Augsburg Fortres</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>2</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fortress Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt17mcsdm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>With the approach of the 500th anniversary of Martin Luther’s inauguration of the Protestant Reformation and the burgeoning dialogue between Catholics and Lutherans opened under Pope Francis, this new edition of Walter Altmann’s Luther and Liberation is timely and relevant. Luther and Liberation recovers the liberating and revolutionary impact of Luther’s theology, read afresh from the perspective of the Latin American context. Altmann provides a much-needed reassessment of Luther’s significance today through a direct engagement of Luther’s historical situation with an eye keenly situated on the deeply contextual situation of the contemporary reader, giving a localized reading from the author’s own experience in Latin America. The work examines with fresh vigor Luther’s central theological commitments, such as his doctrine of God, Christology, justification, hermeneutics, and ecclesiology, and his forays into economics, politics, education, violence, and war. This new edition greatly expands the original text with fresh scholarship and updated sources, footnotes, and bibliography, and contains several additional new chapters on Luther’s doctrine of God, theology of the sacraments, his controversial perspective on the Jews, and a new comparative account with the Latin American liberation theology tradition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boff</surname>
                           <given-names>Leonardo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Latin American theology occurs along two main lines. In one, one interrogates faith and tradition from the questioning of historicalsocial reality, particularly the large oppressed majorities. One discovers in these sources heretofore unsuspected dimensions that attune with the demands of liberation coming from everywhere. In the other, historical-social reality is illuminated with perspectives derived from faith, tradition, and the great theologians. There emerges the prophetic-denunciatory side of Christianity, its liberationist inspiration, and its unwavering utopian horizon, sustaining hope and utopias.</p>
                     <p>It is from these two strands that one re-reads Luther. He is one of the fathers of the modern emancipatory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Altmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Walter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Luther at the Crossroads Between the Old and the New</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Reformation originated in the action of the Augustinian monk Martin Luther (1483-1546). Luther’s outstanding importance in his own time and his relevance still today are too obvious to ignore. However, nothing is more inappropriate for Luther than to simply celebrate him.¹ For “What is Luther?” asked Luther in 1522, describing himself as “poor and stinking maggot fodder,” and his name as “wretched,” so that no one should call themselves “Lutheran,” but simply “Christian.” In any case, “Neither was I crucified for anyone.”²</p>
                     <p>One of the altar paintings by Lucas Cranach, the Elder, in the Church of the City (<italic>Stadtkirche</italic>)</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The God of Life Against All Falsehood of the Idols of Death</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of God is raised differently, according to various cultural, socio-economic, and political contexts. In developed and affluent capitalist countries the question of God is largely raised in the context of the expansion of atheism. It is not always a well-elaborated theoretical atheism, but rather a widespread practical atheism.</p>
                     <p>First, society itself is organized without taking into account God’s existence, or at least, God’s interference. This is largely the result of modernity and its rationalism, including most notably its achievements in the scientific, industrial, and technological fields. which seem to suggest that God is a totally disposable entity or,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>In the Cross of Christ, Victory over All Evil</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>How can we understand the redemptive work of Christ, according to Luther, and what is its significance for us today, in our specific context?</p>
                     <p>Luther lived exactly at the beginning of the conquest and colonization of Latin America by the Spanish and the Portuguese. If we look at the history of the research and images of Jesus throughout these centuries, we find how differently the issues are highlighted in Central Europe and Latin America.</p>
                     <p>As we have seen, the Reformation of Luther occurred in a time of profound transition.¹ Feudalism gave way to the first forms of mercantile capitalism. Absolute</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Conversion, Liberation, and Justification</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his novel<italic>Aunt Julia and the Scriptwriter</italic>, the renowned Peruvian writer Mario Vargas Llosa describes with irony a character “in a certain sense much, much more grave” than a criminal type, that is, “a believer.” Gumercindo Tello, a Jehovah’s Witness, is accused of raping a girl of thirteen. In him one can detect</p>
                     <p>that serenely stubborn gaze of a man who knows, who has no doubts, who has solved all his problems. Rather short in stature, he was a young man, doubtless not yet thirty, whose frail physique, nothing but skin and bones, proclaimed to the four winds his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Scripture—Instrument of Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Has the Bible been largely forgotten by Protestants and has it equally become the book of the Catholics? Or are we deceived by the impression that there are among Protestants signs of fatigue in the use of the Bible, while among Catholics a climate of novelty has installed itself? Doesn’t Protestant Bible reading tend to be repetitive, while Catholic reading conveys creativity and renewal?</p>
                     <p>Although it is advisable to avoid generalizations, there is no doubt that the relationship of the Catholic Church with the Bible has changed significantly since Vatican II. In previous Catholic practice the Bible was an almost</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Church—Poor People of God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is known that Christianity came to Latin America through the Catholic Church, in the process of the conquest and colonization of the continent by the Spanish and Portuguese.¹</p>
                     <p>Although there have always been some prophetic and independent voices, the Church as an institution was tied to the State and to the purposes of conquest and domination of the Iberian crowns. Through the<italic>patronato</italic>system, the priests and missionaries were royal functionaries. In the service of the crown, the cross allied itself with the sword.</p>
                     <p>The model and project impelling this process were what came to be called in Spanish</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Sacraments</title>
                     <subtitle>Tomb or Cradle of Christian Community?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sacramental practice suffers, in a fairly general way, from a strong ambiguity. Quite widespread in Brazilian Lutheranism—and, if I am seeing correctly, in Catholicism too—is an individualist, magical, and uncommitted understanding of the efficacy of the sacraments. It refers to the practice of the sacraments as a holy recourse to divine forces, able to remedy problems and existential angst—even physical illnesses—without resulting in a deepening of faith, strengthening of community, and a commitment to love of the neighbor.</p>
                     <p>In the ecclesial celebration of the sacraments, I have experienced, like many other people, ups and downs in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The Reign of God in Church and State</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I am interested in the question of “Church and State” because of the urgency and priority it acquires, when we focus on the fate of the people, the oppressed and, ultimately, all of humanity.</p>
                     <p>Certainly, it is a particularly pressing issue in our Latin American historical moment and context, when in many countries, after secular independence, domination and oppression, sharpened by the struggle for survival, attempts to dignify life through reducing poverty and social inequality are tested. Never should the church distance itself or exercise neutrality in social and political questions, even less when it unveils real possibilities of building</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>The Political Calling and the Church</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This treatise is one of the most important from 1520. That year Luther’s relationship with the Catholic Church was extremely tense,even more than in 1517, the year he wrote the 95<italic>Theses</italic>.</p>
                     <p>One can distinguish four basic objectives of this treatise:</p>
                     <p>1. to solicit the German nobility to act decisively against the poverty prevailing all across the German estates;</p>
                     <p>2. to denounce the exploitative and conservative action on the part of the institutional Church in this situation;</p>
                     <p>3. to defend the cause of the Reformation, stripping the Roman Church of its claim to political power; and</p>
                     <p>4. to discredit the ecclesiastical ideology and theology</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Education</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luther’s first treatise on educational issues, written in 1524, is mainly what will be considered here, being a more programmatic writing.² The second,<italic>A Sermon on Keeping Children in School</italic>,³ from 1530, contains essentially the same ideas but is a more casual and pastoral piece. After six years, some cities had created schools, following Luther’s proposals. The problem was then parents’ resistance in sending their children to school, as they would lack their labor as workhands. The 1530 treatise is, then, an exhortation to parents to send their children to school.</p>
                     <p>The old medieval educational system was in crisis, a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The Economy and the Community</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1520, Luther wrote a sermon on usury. In 1524, he picked up the theme again, writing the work<italic>Trade and Usury</italic>, which is the main subject of this assessment on Luther’s conception of economics. The writing on the “common chest” of Leisnig from 1523 was selected to represent a creative and innovative attempt to tackle the main social problems that Luther detected. In 1539/40 Luther would again focus on issues of economic policy in a specific and particularly virulent writing against the practice of usury,³ demonstrating how this particular concern was not merely occasional but corresponded to a deep</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>War</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The situation to which this writing of 1529 responds is very clear. At the time of writing, the Ottoman Turkish forces were besieging Vienna and threatened to take all of Europe. At the time of its publication, the resistance had managed to break the siege. However, while writing, Luther thought that Vienna was falling and his feeling was that the threat to Europe was extremely dramatic and real.</p>
                     <p>Luther chose the suggestive literary genre of an “army sermon” and adopted an intensely apocalyptic tone. Because that trait does not appear so clearly in other writings, it is all the more</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Resistance and Violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Do people who profess the Christian faith have the right and perhaps the duty to resist the constituted authorities? What would be legitimate means for a necessary resistance, and what would not? These questions will guide us in this chapter in our examination of Luther’s theology. We selected the main passages from the writings of the Reformer around the Peasants’ War. Still, to deduce Luther’s theology on the question of resistance to authorities only from these writings (a period of a few months) gives only a partial and thus, distorted picture. Therefore, one must take into account Luther’s positions in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Luther—Defender of the Jews or Anti-Semite?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>303</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A good hermeneutic understands the effort toward objectivity but not the pretense of neutrality.¹ The subject “Luther and the Jews”² is an illustrative example. The study is to be done in the context of the oppressive weight of the history of the persecution of the Jews and in the full consciousness of Jewish suffering. Without losing sight of this frame of reference, one has the duty to seek to expose and evaluate the question as objectively as possible.³</p>
                     <p>The Jews have suffered a long history of prejudice, discrimination, persecution, and violent death. Much of this suffering was inflicted by Christians</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>What Did Luther Want, in the End?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>323</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Luther seems to have many faces—in part, for external reasons. He lived in a turbulent time of profound transformations in all sectors: in culture, economy, social and political order, religion, and in morality. Luther never had the privilege or the misfortune of being able to reflect with an inner or outer distance on the historical process in upheaval. Not only was he forced to think, speak, and act in the middle of events; the facts themselves, so to speak, rained down on him, while others barreled him over. Generally, however, he retained a peculiar and surprising freedom of belief</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Matthew 25:31–46</title>
                     <subtitle>Justification and Liberation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The well-known parable of the so-called “Judgment of the Nations” has inspired the doctrine and social action of the churches.</p>
                     <p>The great social encyclicals of the Catholic Church almost invariably cite it, particularly verse 40.¹ Vatican Council II also invokes it when it exhorts us to become “to make ourselves the neighbor of every person . . . and of actively helping him.”² The IECLB also refers to this parable when, from it, the church introduces its social position confessing “our failure.”</p>
                     <p>We have omitted ourselves as part of our communities, where we close our eyes to what is happening</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>The Reception of Luther’s Concept of Freedom in Latin American Liberation Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I propose an exploration of the possible contribution of Martin Luther’s concept of freedom to the Latin American theologians’ adoption of the concept of liberation. It is a systematic endeavor, rather than a historical analysis. As seems obvious, it is not possible to trace any direct link between Luther’s concept of freedom and Latin American liberation theology—and even an indirect relationship is difficult, if not problematic. This chapter proposes, above all, to expose influential Latin American liberation theologians’ understanding of Luther through examples. In addition, I limit myself to surveying non-Lutheran theologians, to verify the alliance of Luther beyond</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue</title>
                     <subtitle>500 Years of Reform and Beyond</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>403</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>October 31, 2017, will be the culmination of celebrations in preparation and already underway for the 500th anniversary of the Reformation. Luther will be persistently evoked. The center of attention will be, without doubt, the town of Wittenberg, Germany, where Luther worked and wrote virtually all his voluminous works. However, he will be remembered all around the world. For the movement of the Reformation, which began there, and took shape over the centuries and in diverse ways, has spread to all continents. It will be, therefore, not a “German” but a “global” anniversary.</p>
                     <p>The LWF will hold its twelfth global</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>407</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Biblical Passages</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>423</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Luther's Writings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>427</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Names</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>431</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Subjects</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17mcsdm.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
