<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d4txdg</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Beyond Bali</book-title>
         <subtitle>Subaltern Citizens and Post-Colonial Intimacy</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Dragojlovic</surname>
               <given-names>Ana</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <role>Series Editor</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Esposito</surname>
               <given-names>Adele</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9789462980648</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9789048530038</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Amsterdam University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Ana Dragojlovic</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Amsterdam University Press B.V.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d8hb16"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This ethnography explores how Balinese citizens produce postcolonial intimacy-a complex interaction of claims to proximity and mutuality between themselves and the Dutch under colonialism that continues today. Such claims, Ana Dragojlovic explains, are crucial for the diasporic reconfiguration of kebalian, or Balinese-ness, a concept that encompasses the personal, social, and cultural complexities involved in Balinese identity in Dutch postcolonial society. This identity enables Balinese migrants to see themselves as carriers of unique cultural traditions both promoted by and in disagreement with Dutch cultural values.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Herzfeld</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What happens when a minority group in a fraught, conflict-ridden colony finds itself a distrusted entity within the new nation-state, its sacrifices in the cause of national independence swept aside by suspicions that its members are not loyal to the emergent realities of majority rule? What happens when its members intermarry with the hated colonizers, or flee to the colonizers’ European land in search of work? What do terms like heritage and history mean to them, against the background drumbeat of an increasingly fierce nationalism?</p>
                     <p>Ana Dragojlovic’s richly recounted, lovingly written, and often intensely moving ethnography explores the transnational anxieties</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is an ethnography that charts reconfigurations of<italic>kebalian</italic>(Balineseness) – a notion that encompasses the personal, social, and cultural complexities involved in being persons and collectives of Balinese ethnicity in post-colonial Dutch society. I explore how Balinese subaltern citizens engage in discourses and materialities of the colonial in the present by asserting claims of proximity between themselves and the Dutch on the basis of colonial history through an active production of what I call postcolonial intimacy. My understanding of Balinese subaltern citizens’ claims of proximity that emerged so prominently in my ethnographic material urges me not to see</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Kebalian, Long-Distance Nationalism, and the Balinese Left in Exile</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early Saturday morning on 24 January 2004, I took a tram to Slotermeer, a neighbourhood located in the western part of Amsterdam. For the first time in my fieldwork, I was on my way to attend the<italic>Galungan-Kuningan</italic>, a pan-Balinese festival that takes place once every 210 days according to the Balinese<italic>uku</italic>calendar.¹ This festival celebrates the victory of virtue (<italic>dharma</italic>) over evil (<italic>adharma</italic>). In Bali, celebrations of<italic>Galungan-Kuningan</italic>take place at all temples, accompanied with particularly rich offerings.<italic>Galungan</italic>is the first day of the ten-day festival during which it is believed that deities and ancestral spirits descend</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Balinese Post-Colonial Pedagogies and Contested Intimacies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 9 May 2009, I attended the wedding ceremony of Pak Wayan and his partner Thomas at the city hall in one of the largest towns in South Holland. I had met Pak Wayan some years earlier when he first moved to the Netherlands, sponsored by his then partner Paul, whom he had met in Bali. The Netherlands was the first country to make marriage and adoption available to same-sex couples, doing so in 2001. The move allowed Paul and Wayan and other same-sex couples to obtain an entry visa and, later, permanent residency for Wayan on the basis of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>‘Shared Cultural Heritage’ and the Visible and Invisible World Overseas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I analyze the Balinese reception of a major exhibition featuring Balinese royal regalia obtained during the Dutch colonial conquest. This analysis allows me to tease out the correlations that my interlocutors make between the looted objects and their own Balinese presence in contemporary Dutch society. I argue that Balinese interpretative understandings of Balinese-Dutch historical connectivities generate specific knowledge production about ‘shared cultural heritage’. The heritage I talk about here is one that differs from that of Dutch policymakers’ conception of ‘shared heritage’ but also from interpretations that might be found in an exclusively Balinese context. In other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>A Balinese Colonial Drama without the Balinese?</title>
                     <subtitle>Interethnic Dynamics in Post-Colonial Commemorations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 10 June 2009, I was invited by Ibu Setia, another one of my long-term interlocutors and one of the founding members of the dance group<italic>Bali Ayu</italic>, to attend the group’s dance performance in Nijmegen, the largest city in the eastern part of the Netherlands. The performance was to take place at the Stadsschouwburg, Nijmegen’s main theatre, as a prelude to<italic>Puputan, Val van Bali</italic>(<italic>Puputan</italic>, The Fall of Bali), to be performed by the choir Colourful City Koor.¹ Established in 2003 at a time when public discourses on failed multiculturalism were just beginning to heat up, the Colourful</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>My Home is Your Home</title>
                     <subtitle>The Possibilities, Challenges, and Failures of Home Making</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In early February 2004, at the invitation of some of my Balinese friends, I attended a<italic>pasar</italic>gathering in Utrecht where my friends were going to be performing a classical Balinese dance accompanied by I Komang Suaka, a multidisciplinary Balinese artist of whom I had heard before. Suaka is a painter, an installation artist, and the leader of pop band ‘Burning Seed’, which was also scheduled to perform that day. I arrived at the venue accompanied by my friends in the early afternoon to give the dancers enough time to have a quick rehearsal on the new stage as well</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anxieties about Marginality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In late May 2014, Ibu Dani, a long-term interlocutor of mine, came to visit me in my home in Leiden. As soon as she entered the house, I noticed how exceptionally upset she was. She handed me a bag with ingredients for the<italic>kangkung, tempe</italic>, and<italic>babi ketjap</italic>¹ we were planning to cook that evening and exclaimed, fuming: ‘Too many ignorant foreigners live in this country! This is too bad … too bad I tell you. Are you writing about this!?’ She then explained what caused her outburst of anger.</p>
                     <p>On the way to my house, Ibu Dani had stopped</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author’s Biography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d8hb16.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
