<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Supper at Emmaus</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>OLSEN</surname>
               <given-names>GLENN W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813228945</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813228952</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1hjb0d8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Supper at Emmaus traces various important intellectual topics from the ancient world to the modern period. Generally, as in its treatment of the question of whether the long-standing contrast between cyclical and linear views of history is helpful, it introduces important thinkers who have considered the question. A preoccupation of the book is the appearance and reappearance across the centuries of patterns used to organize temporal and cultural experience. After an opening essay on transcendental truth and cultural relativism, the second chapter traces a distinction, common in historical writings during the past two centuries, between an alleged ancient classical "cyclic" view of time and history, used to describe the claimed repetitiveness of and similarities between historical events ("nothing is new under the sun"), and a contrasting Jewish-Christian linear view, sometimes described as providential in that it moves through a series of unique events to some end intended by God. In the latter, history is "about something," the education of the human race or the redemption of humankind. As in each of the remaining essays, the book then attempts to draw out the limitations of what the current consensus on this topic has become. It does this for such things as our current understanding of religious toleration, humanism, natural law, and teleology. Some of the essays, such as those on debate about Augustine's understanding of marriage or the concluding illustrated essay on the baroque city of Lecce, are published for the first time. Others are based on previously published contributions to the scholarly literature, though generally each of these chapters concludes with a postscript that engages with current scholarly debate on the subject.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This volume follows the format of my<italic>On the Road to Emmaus: The Catholic Dialogue with America and Modernity</italic>(Washington, D.C.: The Catholic University of America Press, 2012). Most of its chapters originated in contributions to scholarly conferences and congresses—American, Israeli, Polish, and Spanish—and were first published in a variety of American and European journals and Congress<italic>ACTA</italic>, some of the latter not easily accessible. Generally each chapter concludes with an afterword about the article, engaging with current debate and considering bibliographic references that have appeared after the article’s original publication. The style of each chapter generally follows</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Transcendental Truth and Cultural Relativism:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Historian’s View</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>That marvelous venture in cross-cultural study,<italic>Eranos</italic>, devoted its 1951 meeting to the theme “Man and Time.”¹ When the papers given at this meeting were translated and published in English, they were introduced by a short essay, “The Time of Eranos,” by Henry Corbin.² In a few pages Corbin launched a frontal assault on some of the most cherished assumptions of the history profession—indeed, on the very idea of “explanation” as it occurs across the sciences today. His analysis seems to me so correct and freighted with such significance that I would like to devote this chapter to explaining,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Problems with the Contrast between Circular and Linear Views of Time in the Interpretation of Ancient and Early Medieval History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>More than a generation ago, Arnaldo Momigliano, in attacking many conventional contrasts between, for instance, a so-called Jewish and a so-called Greek view of time, argued that the contrast between a Greek or pagan circular time and a Jewish-Christian linear time could not be sustained.¹ Of Momigliano’s contemporaries, perhaps no one more persistently had made and was to continue to make this contrast than Mircea Eliade, who presented Judaism and Christianity as transcending the celestial cycles of ancient religion: “repetition was transcended, for the first time, by Judeo-Christianism, which introduced a new category into religious experience: the category of<italic>faith</italic>.”²</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Marriage, Feminism, Theology, and the New Social History:</title>
                     <subtitle>Dyan Elliott’s Spiritual Marriage</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Is it true that the ancient practice of spiritual marriage, the mutual and voluntary giving up of sexual intercourse in marriage for reasons of piety, “engages the contradictions of the Christian theory of marriage that were already in place by the end of the fourth century”? Is it true that for St. Paul “the reproductive function of marriage is … obliterated and marriage is narrowly defined as a prophylactic measure against incontinence”? Is it true that the post-Pauline biblical writers, having set the seal on female submission and reproductive capacity, mark “the beginning of the end of orthodox Christianity as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Augustine’s View of Marriage:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Clash of Interpretation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scholarship progresses and regresses through the clash of interpretation, and the truth of one scholar or generation is not necessarily that of another. There are many reasons for this, ranging from the limitations of a given scholar to a priori commitments, which may lead one to misread a body of documents because of an idée fixe or through anachronism. If this is true in general, how much more so in the case of a thinker like Augustine, never ashamed to change his mind and so pivotal in the development of the West and of Christianity? We acknowledge the acuteness of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Setting Boundaries:</title>
                     <subtitle>Early Medieval Reflections on Religious Toleration and Their Jewish Roots</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of toleration has no beginning. Tolerance and intolerance, the instincts to welcome and to exclude, have been practiced by each individual and every people. From its beginnings Judaism regarded itself as the religion of a chosen people that drew lines of separation between itself and others (especially in the matter of purity) while also welcoming the stranger. Christianity and Islam acted similarly. This chapter explores particular ways in which Judaism’s approach to the problem of tolerating those with whom it could not comfortably live a shared life influenced its daughter faiths, especially Christianity.</p>
                     <p>In the Early Middle Ages,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>The Middle Ages in the History of Toleration:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Prolegomena</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though the Whig grand narrative of history on which most of us were brought up has been under attack for some time—witness the writings of Herbert Butterfield (1900–1979)—it continues to permeate our culture. Essentially at first a narrative to explain the gloriousness of the Glorious Revolution of 1688—that is, the triumph of Protestantism and parliamentarianism over Catholicism and monarchy—the narrative has been quite adaptive and has been a carrier of a tale of progress built around the desirability of commerce, money-making, science, technology, and democracy. The Middle Ages, because not exactly characterized by any of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Reflections on a Giotto Exhibit:</title>
                     <subtitle>Does Joseph Ratzinger’s The Spirit of the Liturgy Satisfactorily Draw the Liturgical Differences between East and West in the Late Middle Ages?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From March 6 through June 29, 2009, an exhibit on Giotto (c. 1267–1337), “Giotto and the Fourteenth Century: The Sovereign Master of Painting,” was held at the Vittoriano in Rome. The exhibit showed twenty works by Giotto himself and 130 illustrating his influence. I was able to visit it in early June, and the following records a reflection that came to me at that time on one aspect of Giotto’s achievement. I have nothing particularly novel to say about Giotto himself, but seeing some of his works up close did reinforce the common judgment on how alive they are.¹</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Humanism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Struggle to Possess a Word</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The broad outlines of the story are well known. They center on the prestigious place of the Renaissance in the grand narrative of Western civilization—that is, in the narrative of ultimate progress that so many have imbibed from their earliest years and, despite all, still cling to.¹ According to this narrative, Western man began gloriously in Greece, more generally in the classical world, but then fell into darkness in the Middle Ages, only to recover—or perhaps surpass—ancient achievement in the Renaissance, the age of rebirth. At the heart of this rebirth was “Renaissance humanism,” a turning from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>The Natural Law:</title>
                     <subtitle>The First Grace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>223</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The prospects of natural-law thinking can seem dim indeed, in spite of some recent able defenses.¹ Nevertheless, or perhaps precisely because of this, it is incumbent upon contemporary Catholic intellectuals to make their contribution to the modest revival of the natural law tradition such defenses represent. It seems to me that, in order to be fruitful, this contribution must avoid two extremes. On the one hand, it should not simply return to the older manual tradition of construing natural law, lest it underwrite a new dualism between nature and grace.² On the other hand, granting that the newer, very striking,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>The Return of Purpose</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In E. A. Burtt’s classic formulation, “the central metaphysical contrast between medieval and modern thought, in respect to their conception of man’s relation to his natural environment,” is that:</p>
                     <p>For the dominant trend in medieval thought, man occupied a more significant and determinative place in the universe than the realm of physical nature, while for the main current of modern thought, nature holds a more independent, more determinative, and more permanent place than man … [in the Middle Ages] on the teleological side: an explanation in terms of the relation of things to human purpose was accounted just as real</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Lecce’s Baroque longue durée</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Olsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Glenn W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Olsen</surname>
                           <given-names>Suzanne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Baroque was out of fashion in many circles in especially the second half of the twentieth century, though there were exceptions—for instance, the early music movement and the pride taken in their Baroque architecture by cities such as Braga in Portugal, Rome itself, and a number of southern Italian and Sicilian cities.¹ One tendency of various forms of modernism, if thought was given to the matter, had been to see the Baroque as grandiloquent.² In terms of Christian architecture and music, this understanding was present in many people’s interpretations of the “noble simplicity” asked for by the Second</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1hjb0d8.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>327</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
