<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Stranger Magic</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Warner</surname>
               <given-names>Marina</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674055308</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780674065079</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Marina Warner</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt2jbtr6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Our foremost theorist of myth, fairytale, and folktale explores the magical realm of the imagination where carpets fly and genies grant prophetic wishes. Stranger Magic examines the profound impact of the Arabian Nights on the West, the progressive exoticization of magic, and the growing acceptance of myth and magic in contemporary experience.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="560"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Warner</surname>
                           <given-names>Marina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Through all the twists and turns the<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>have undergone, the central theme remains, and remains known to every hearer and every reader: Shahrazad has been sentenced to die in the morning by the Sultan Shahriyar who, in revenge for the infidelity of his Sultana (he found her and all her handmaidens cavorting with slaves), has decided to marry a virgin every night and cut off her head in the morning. The vizier is ordered to find the bride and then, in the morning, to take her away to die; candidates are running out, but his eldest daughter, Shahrazad,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 1</label>
                     <title>The Fisherman and the Genie</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An old fisherman living in great poverty with a wife, his son and two daughters, throws his net into the sea one moonlit night, and has no luck: his first haul is the carcass of a donkey, his second an old jar full of sand and clay, his third a heap of bits of glass and pottery, bones and débris. In between each throw of his net, he rails against fortune and passionately laments his state:</p>
                     <p>‘Here virtue cries for misery, and the good-for-nothing disguises himself in his kingdom. The bird that soars high exhausts itself from west to east,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>Master of Jinn</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The famous trickster tale of ‘The Fisherman and the Genie’, at once alarming and funny, so satisfying in its (first) neat resolution when the pauper outwits the colossus, the enemy is hoist on his own petard, and the jinni inveigled back into the bottle, has rightly enjoyed a long and celebrated history (it was successfully restaged in the Disney<italic>Aladdin,</italic>with Robin Williams voicing the genie). But when Sakhr remembers the scene of his rebellion and punishment at the hands of Solomon, his story provides the fundamental background plot for the cosmology of the<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>, in which the wise</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 2</label>
                     <title>The City of Brass</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>54</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Damascus, the Caliph Abd el-Malik wants to know more about the great king Solomon; in response one of his court begins to tell him about the existence of old copper bottles which release, as soon as they are opened, strange forms of smoke. A traveller and treasure-hunter present, called Talib ibn Sahl, picks up the story, describing to the Caliph how his grandfather was once sailing to Sicily but was blown off course and fetched up in a land inhabited by a black people who went about naked, had not yet heard of the true faith, and spoke an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Riding the Wind:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Flying Carpet I</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Shahrazad begins to relate ‘The Tale of the City of Brass’ on the 567th night, past the centre of the vortex of her stories; it is a slow, magnificent, melancholy tale of a quest within a quest, a sober elegy to human littleness and mortality, condensing major themes of the<italic>Nights</italic>. The critic Andras Hamori has called it, a little unkindly, ‘the gloomiest of travelogues’, but its protracted, incantatory melancholy creates a lull – a<italic>berceuse</italic>motif in the midst of a vast symphony.</p>
                     <p>The Caliph Abd el-Malik ruled the immense Umayyad empire from its capital in Damascus from 685</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 3</label>
                     <title>Prince Ahmed and the Fairy Peri Banou</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Three brothers, sons of the Sultan of the Indies, are rivals for the hand of the exquisitely beautiful Princess Nouronnihar, their first cousin and an orphan, who lives in the palace with them. The three princes are dispatched by their father at the beginning of the story: the one who brings back the greatest wonder shall marry her.</p>
                     <p>Prince Houssain, the eldest, travels eastwards in several caravans to a city of fabulous wealth, where a fabulous trade in carpets and jewels is being conducted, rose-sellers throng the streets, and its black inhabitants gleam from the gold, pearls and gems with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>A Tapestry of Great Price:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Flying Carpet II</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The stories of the<italic>Nights</italic>invite the Sultan to deepen his understanding – of wonders, secrets, human behaviour and the unexpected twists of destiny – and we the readers find ourselves listening in and learning alongside him. When human characters, as opposed to Solomon, are given the chance to set off on a flying carpet, the double effects of excitement and disorientation resonate very powerfully indeed.</p>
                     <p>The magic carpet does not attract special attention from the storyteller; it simply features as one of three magical gifts obtained by the brothers. Yet, just as the glass extends the faculty of sight,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 4</label>
                     <title>The Prince of the Black Islands</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fisherman reluctantly agrees to trust the jinni, Sakhr, releases him from the copper flask for a second time, and lets himself be led toward the promised fortune. After long days’ and nights’ walking beyond all known territory, they reach a lake; the jinni has explained nothing, but at his orders the fisherman casts his net and draws up a haul of fishes, marvellously coloured white, red, blue and yellow; he is to take them, the jinni goes on, to the nearby palace and offer them to the vizier for the king of that country, who will find them delicious</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Worst Witch</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The tale of ‘The Prince of the Black Islands’, which is also known in Burton’s translation as ‘The Tale of the Ensorcelled Prince’, and in the most recent French version, simply as ‘The Tale of the Young Man’, closes the first cycle of stories in the<italic>Nights</italic>. With its happy ending (for some), it ties and knots several threads, and proves the power of the ransom tale. The next cycle, ‘The Porter and the Three Ladies of Baghdad’, will drive home harder the salvific function of the storyteller’s art. Every story in both these groups plunges into depths of inexplicable,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Egyptian Attitudes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a packed account of Egypt, a country which he admired and where he had travelled extensively, the Greek historian Herodotus declares: ‘the names of all the gods have been known in Egypt from the beginning of time …’ In a genial, idiosyncratic gossipy style, he inventories a<italic>Wunderkammer</italic>of knowledge, reviewing the origin and habits of the phoenix, the edibility of crocodiles and the processes used in mummification. Through all the fabulous lore, Herodotus stresses the primacy and the originality of the country: ‘It was the Egyptians too,’ he writes,</p>
                     <p>who originated, and taught the Greeks to use ceremonial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 5</label>
                     <title>Hasan of Basra</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A successful merchant of Basra dies before his time, leaving his widow with two sons; one of them is calm and prudent and takes his half of the inheritance to follow in his father’s footsteps and open a shop in the market. But the other, called Hasan, a boy of radiant beauty and charm, is a lazy good-for-nothing. His mother is determined, however, and she’s made sure he knows the Koran and can write an elegant hand and express himself gracefully. Even with these gifts, he won’t apply himself to anything serious but runs around in a gang of feckless</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>Magians and Dervishes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>conjured an enchanted virtual world that could be safely entered and explored, accepted and naturalised by the Enlightenment and modern reader and writer precisely because they often unfold in an elsewhere that is different from the native habitat of Judaeo-Christian demons and eschatological visions. A home-grown practice of, and belief in, magic was set aside to be replaced by foreign magic – stranger magic, much easier to disown, or otherwise hold in intellectual and political quarantine.</p>
                     <p>The stories provide a stimulus to this legitimate – and hypocritical – pleasure. Powerful, fiendish enchanters appear in several of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 6</label>
                     <title>A Fortune Regained</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There’s a lovely old house in Baghdad, built around a shaded and tiled courtyard with a square pool in the centre where a small jet of water pulses. It resembles many others in that old city. Doves fly down from their dovecote in the heat of the day to rinse their dusty wings in the little pool, and the small lemon trees breathe honey; beaded wooden interlacings on the windows of the house, both those overlooking the street and those facing the courtyard, mottle the cool inner rooms. It is not unlike many other houses in that city.</p>
                     <p>But to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Dream Knowledge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>stories are told in the night by a woman in bed with her husband; her inspiration must not stop flowing or she will die. She must continue summoning up stories, or she – and others – will wake up to the reality of her danger. It is as if the dreamer must continue to dream – on our behalf. Our survival depends on the continued processes of her mind.</p>
                     <p>Interestingly, Shahrazad does not make up the stories, as we are told clearly from the start that she is clever and learned and has ‘never forgotten anything she</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>‘Everything You Desire to Know about the East …’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Interactions between the Sublime Porte and the capitals of Western powers did not become very frequent – or indeed any friendlier – but the degree of acquaintance grew. From assuming difference and observing it with curiosity, travellers began to point to the differences in order to keep a distance and exculpate themselves by association, as we saw in relation to the whirling dervishes. When the<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>appeared in French and English, the book was received as a Baedeker, as it were, an encyclopaedia, a social handbook and a costume album. It was seen as a far superior substitute to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Colour plates</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 7</label>
                     <title>The Greek King and Doctor Douban</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fisherman has managed with his cunning ruse to trick the furious – and highly gullible – Sakhr back into the copper bottle and is walking back to the water’s edge to throw him back into the sea when, from within, the jinni pleads for his life. The fisherman sternly refuses, while the jinni promises him every blessing. ‘You are lying,’ says the fisherman. ‘Your promises are empty. You and I are like the vizier of King Yunan and Douban, the doctor. ‘Tell me how we’re like them,’ says the jinni, and so sparks the next story within a story</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>The Thing-World of the Arabian Nights</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the box of stories opened so far in the cycle of ‘The Fisherman and the Genie’ the tales fit one inside the other with internal rhymes and structural patterns, both matching and inverted. Remedies and poisons alternate throughout the tales, instruments of healing with instruments of harming; good deeds are rewarded by ill deeds and the ill deeds are then punished according to the justice of providence (the king dies for his treachery, but Douban also lies dead (Pl. 4), and we hear nothing of the treacherous vizier). But as a ransom tale, told by the fisherman to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 8</label>
                     <title>Abu Mohammed the Lazy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Zubayda, the wife whom Caliph Harun al-Rashid loves most of all, is making a head-dress of splendid jewels, but the central gem is missing and she wants a jewel bigger and brighter than any other. She sends a eunuch to the caliph and he immediately gives the order that the jewel she covets must be found; when he hears there are problems, he cries out in a rage, and is then told that the merchants have revealed that a certain merchant in Basra, nicknamed Abu Mohammed ‘the Lazy’, the son of a mere barber at the public baths, has a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>The Word of the Talisman</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Tale of Abu Mohammed the Lazy combines two traditions: an Egyptian strand of eerie phenomena and powerful instrumental magic, and a story of trade and adventure in the East and the Far East which originates in Iraq. The monkey jinni begins as a poor maltreated creature, but changes into a malignant schemer; the effect is gripping, especially as his plans have been laid with such long-term foresight and have such a specific erotic purpose. By contrast with this wilfulness, our wastrel hero lacks all definition and volition; he is the plaything of chance, with no hint from the storyteller</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 9</label>
                     <title>Marouf the Cobbler</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marouf the Cobbler’s life is made a misery by his wife, a harridan who subjects him to her whims and beats him when he fails to produce what she wants. He finds it hard to earn a living at his trade; nobody seems to have their shoes mended any more. One day, she demands that he bring her back a sweetmeat – shredded wheat drenched in wild honey. No work comes his way that day, but the baker takes pity on him and advances him the money he needs to buy the sweetmeat, nicely cooked in butter but steeped in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>The Voice of the Toy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>240</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fortune is wealth in the story of ‘Marouf the Cobbler,’ and both arise without rhyme or reason and pour down blessings on him: no special qualities of personality single out the hero, except perhaps an unparalleled willingness to blag and go along with the scam once his friend the Egyptian merchant Ali has put it in his head. No unusual marks of favour from destiny, or exceptional piety or ability entitle him. The luck that comes his way when he disturbs the jinni in the ruined warehouse puts paid to any notions that virtues like hard work and diligence and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Money Talks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>252</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1709, an anonymous lampoonist directly echoed the title of the first English translation,<italic>Arabian Nights’ Entertainments</italic>, with the opening instalment of a satire called<italic>The Golden Spy – The Introduction; or the First Nights</italic>[sic]<italic>Entertainment</italic>. The author, Charles Gildon, dedicated his book to ‘The author of<italic>A Tale of a Tub</italic>’ and with scurrilous, Swiftian scorn, adopts the first person of a<italic>louis d’or</italic>, a gold coin from the luxurious spendthrifts across the Channel, to excoriate the abuses of contemporary society.</p>
                     <p>This penny morality about ‘the power and progress of gold’ starts in antiquity: the coin begins as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Magnificent Moustaches:</title>
                     <subtitle>Hamilton’s Fooling, Voltaire’s Impersonations</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The opera<italic>Così fan tutte</italic>, first performed in Vienna in January 1790, was Mozart’s last collaboration with Lorenzo Da Ponte, most sparkling and inventive of librettists. Don Alfonso, the<italic>éminence grise</italic>of the drama, spurs on the two young male protagonists to test the constancy of their fiancées, Dorabella and Fiordiligi, and proposes they use the traditional romance device of a bed trick (as used in in several stories of the<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>and in<italic>All’s Well That Ends Well</italic>and elsewhere). On this occasion it will take the form of an oriental farce, knowingly making fun of the craze</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 10</label>
                     <title>Rosebud and Uns al-Wujud the Darling Boy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>282</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the hero (Uns al-wujud the Darling Boy), at last arrives at the enchanted castle where his beloved, Rosebud (Felkanaman), has been imprisoned by her father, Ibrahim, vizier to the King of Hezan, he’s been through thick and thin to reach her. The castle stands on the summit of the Mountain of the Grief-Stricken Mother, in the middle of the sea of Kenouz, one of the stormiest in the world, impassable. But Uns al-Wujud has been helped in his quest by many, for his sweetness and goodness and beauty inspire confidence in all who meet him, as well as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 11:</label>
                     <title>The Jinniya and the Egyptian Prince</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>284</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A king of Egypt had a son, Chemnis, for whom he wanted every advantage of upbringing and education, and to this end, he installed him in a quiet retreat on an island in the middle of a great lake. There the boy studied, and made great progress. On his eighteenth birthday, however, he told his father he wanted to taste the world; he had acquired deep learning, but no experience of life. The king offered him girls, but the young man asked instead to see the pyramid that his father was building for his tomb after his death. The father</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>‘Symbols of Wonder’:</title>
                     <subtitle>William Beckford’s Arabesque</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>289</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story about Rosebud and Uns al-Wujud the Darling Boy appears in many different editions of the<italic>Nights</italic>, but none, as far as I know, includes the story which the writer William Beckford (1760–1844) interjects, ‘The Jinniya and the Egyptian Prince’. The protagonists often allude to a legend that gave the mountain its sad name, but their accounts make little sense. (Lane has the jinn happily giving birth to ‘hundreds of children’ – and it is their crying that passing sailors hear. But that would hardly add ‘Grief-Stricken Mother’ to the mountain’s name.) Beckford paid attention to these inconsistencies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>Oriental Masquerade:</title>
                     <subtitle>Goethe’s West-Eastern Divan</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Weimar in 1815, around three decades after the first performance of<italic>Così fan tutte</italic>, Johann Wolfgang von Goethe came across translations of the medieval Persian poet Hafiz, by the orientalist Joseph von Hammer-Purgstall, some of the very first into a European language. They captivated him with an intensity that took him, in his mid-sixties, by surprise, and he wrote:</p>
                     <p>And though the whole world sink to ruin, I will emulate you, Hafiz, you alone! Let us, who are twin spirits, share pleasure and sorrow! To love like you, and drink like you, shall be my pride and my life-long</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Colour plates</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 12</label>
                     <title>Camar al-Zaman and Princess Badoura</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Childlessness is a great curse in the<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>and many kings and wealthy merchants suffer bitterly for it. But sharper still than lacking a child is the sorrow a child inflicts when he or she does not want to marry and bring grandchildren into the family.</p>
                     <p>Camar al-Zaman, the prince and heir to the Khalidan islands, is one of these young and angry voices raised up against marriage: he has heard the stories of women’s<italic>makr</italic>, their wiles, lusts, perfidiousness and violence; and he refuses to marry, swearing he’d rather give himself up to die. As he is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>Thought Experiments:</title>
                     <subtitle>Flight before Flight</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>330</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of Camar al-Zaman and Princess Badoura is one of the lovely long romances of the<italic>Nights</italic>, told by Shahrazad over many nights, from the 179th to the 217th night. Its heroine Badoura is strong-willed, ardent, capable and, above all, intensely loyal. She is a prime exhibit in Shahrazad’s pageant of virtuous women: beginning as a stern, proud virgin, a fairytale princess who is wholly bound up with her royal father, she develops into a witty trickster who tests Camar in one of the frankest and most surprising bed tricks from a wide repertoire of variations on the motif:</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVENTEEN</label>
                     <title>Why Aladdin?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 26 October 1831, in the exquisite Regency Theatre at Bury St Edmunds, Suffolk, England, ‘under the patronage of Lieut.-Col. and Mrs Rushbrooke’, the<italic>Grand Spectacular Tale of Enchantment, (interspersed with Music) called Aladdin or, The Wonderful Lamp</italic>was staged as the climax of a varied bill of entertainments. The evening began with a comedy, called<italic>Ups and Downs, or the Ladder of Life</italic>; this was followed by ‘the popular Farce of<italic>My Wife! What Wife!’,</italic>and then ‘A Comic Song, sung by Mr Burton’, as the curtain-raiser to the main attraction. This<italic>Aladdin</italic>was only one in a spate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHTEEN</label>
                     <title>Machine Dreams</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The film-maker William Kennedy Laurie Dickson was Thomas Edison’s assistant and collaborator in the early years of the Kinetograph. To make the first experimental films, he built a set in their offices in Brooklyn. Effectively a camera obscura, this pioneering film lot revolved so that light penetration could be controlled; it was nicknamed ‘the Black Maria’, and in a photograph that survives, it certainly has a grim look, as of a detention centre. But for Dickson, the studio had different connotations: it was itself mobile, tuned to the rhythms of cosmic revolutions as it turned on its axle with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 13</label>
                     <title>The Ebony Horse</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A king has three daughters who are as lovely as the moon at the full in the sky or as a spring garden in flower, and three learned men present themselves as suitors, bearing gifts: one has a brass trumpet which sounds whenever an enemy is approaching; the second offers a gold peacock which tells the time by beating its wings on the hour; the third presents a horse made of ivory and ebony which he promises will carry its rider wherever he wants.</p>
                     <p>The king tests the first two gifts. They work as promised, and the sages ask for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINETEEN</label>
                     <title>The Shadows of Lotte Reiniger</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>390</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The magic automaton from the romance of ‘The Ebony Horse’ gave Lotte Reiniger her point of departure for<italic>Die Abenteuer des Prinzen Achmed</italic>(The Adventures of Prince Achmed), which she made in Berlin in 1923–25; this ‘shadow film’, as she called it, is the first full-length animated feature to survive. The story, an early peripatetic romance interrupted by many unforeseen mishaps (reroutings, hijackings, kidnappings), is also known as ‘The Tale of the Magic Horse’. It is one of the most popular in the<italic>Arabian Nights</italic>. It travelled on the sea of stories before the<italic>1001 Nights</italic>were printed: a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 14</label>
                     <title>Aladdin of the Beautiful Moles</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>403</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the richest and most powerful merchants in Baghdad grieves that he has no children, and a passing magician rallies him by giving him a wonderful mixture of stuff to thicken his sperm. The potion is a placebo – its power lies wholly in the believing, and the merchant does believe. A baby is born. He is the most beautiful boy ever seen, like the summer moon in its fullness on the horizon, with jet black hair and on his fair cheeks some beauty spots –<italic>shamat</italic>– which give him his name, Ala al-Din Abu ’l-Shamat, Aladdin of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWENTY</label>
                     <title>The Couch:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The long and tangled romance, ‘The Tale of Ala al-Din Abu ’l-Shamat’ (Aladdin of the Beautiful Moles), is one of the most extravagant of all the<italic>Nights</italic>in its wayward plotting, far-fetched coincidence, and peculiar, unexplained emotional reversals. Told over nineteen nights, it proves a rigmarole which Shahrazad barely keeps under control; no summary can capture its corkscrew shape. It is, however, ‘the true Aladdin’, as Philip Kennedy has written, and it plies together multiple strands from different romances and different periods, so that ‘a single tale has a complex stratigraphy of distinct kinds of stories that, in their tone,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Story 15</label>
                     <title>Prince Ardashir and Hayat al-Nufus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One king in this story is childless; he rules in Shiraz, in Iran. At last in his old age, the doctors in his entourage mix him the right medicine, and a son is born, Ardashir, a boy as beautiful as the full moon and very good at his lessons, too. The other king in this story rules in Basra, in Iraq. He has a daughter, Hayat al-Nufus, who is equally accomplished and beautiful as Ardashir, if not more so. But she is set against marriage, and indeed declares that she will kill herself if her father tries to make a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>‘All the story of the night told over …’</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>429</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Anyone who reaches the end of the tales of the 1001 Nights will die, the legend says; but the danger is not very serious, since it is not possible to say, as you might about another book, that you can put it down because you have finished it. The reason does not lie in its length, but in its myriad variations and the efflorescence of the structure. On the 602<sup>nd</sup>Night, Sultan Shahriyar finds himself listening to a story … about the son of a king, a young prince with no name, who climbs a tree and then sees a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Glossary</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>437</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>439</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Stories</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>445</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>499</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt2jbtr6.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>517</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
