<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BL51.W763 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Phenomenological theology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy, French</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Words of Life: New Theological Turns in French Phenomenology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BENSON</surname>
               <given-names>BRUCE ELLIS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WIRZBA</surname>
               <given-names>NORMAN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Caputo</surname>
               <given-names>John D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>series editor</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823230723</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823248698</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c5cjph"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Words of Life is the sequel and companion to Phenomenology and the Theological Turn,edited by Dominique Janicaud, Jean-Francois Courtine, Jean-Louis Chrtien, Michel Henry, Jean-Luc Marion, and Paul Ricoeur. In that volume, Janicaud accuses Levinas, Henry, Marion, and Chrtien of veeringfrom phenomenological neutrality to a theologically inflected phenomenology. By contrast, the contributors to this collection interrogate whether phenomenology's proper starting point is agnostic or atheistic. Many hold the view that phenomenology after the theological turn may very well be true both to itself and to the phenomenological things themselves.In one way or another, all of these essays contend with the limits and expectations of phenomenology. As such, they are all concerned with what counts as properphenomenology and even the very structure of phenomenology. None of them, however, is limited to such questions. Indeed, the rich tapestry that they weave tells us much about human experience. Themes such as faith, hope, love, grace, the gift, the sacraments, the words of Christ, suffering, joy, life, the call, touch, listening, wounding, and humility are woven throughout the various meditations in this volume. The contributors use striking examples to illuminate the structure and limits of phenomenology and, in turn, phenomenology serves to clarify those very examples. Thus practice clarifies theory and theory clarifies practice, resulting in new theological turns and new life for phenomenology. The volume showcases the work of both senior and junior scholars, including Jean-Luc Marion, Jean-Yves Lacoste, Kevin Hart, Anthony J. Steinbock, Jeffrey Bloechl, Jeffrey L. Kosky, Clayton Crockett, Brian Treanor, and Christina Gschwandtner-as well as the editors themselves.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BENSON</surname>
                           <given-names>BRUCE ELLIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many who read this introduction will immediately know that the phrase on which the subtitle of this collection of essays is based—the so-called theological turn in French phenomenology—comes from a text of Dominique Janicaud.¹ Indeed, one can read this volume as a companion to<italic>Phenomenology and the “Theological Turn”: The French Debate</italic>, which appears in this same series. In his official report to the French government that details the contours of the development of philosophy in France from 1975 to 1990, Janicaud claims that philosophy (in particular phenomenology, the dominant mode of philosophy in France today) has taken</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Continuing to Look for God in France:</title>
                     <subtitle>On the Relationship Between Phenomenology and Theology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SIMMONS</surname>
                           <given-names>J. AARON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relationship between phenomenology and theology is as complex and troubled as is the relationship between faith and reason. Following the publication of a collection of essays entitled<italic>God in France</italic>in 2005,¹ the debate concerning the “theological turn” that was primarily inaugurated by Dominique Janicaud in 1991 might itself be viewed as having taken a new “turn.”² What connects the nine essays in this important collection is the supposition that, despite Janicaud’s contention, there has not been a theological turn in recent French phenomenology. Instead, in various ways, all of the authors argue that within “new phenomenology” there has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Being Without God</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BLOECHL</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Whether or not we may now speak globally or even retrospectively about a distinctively “French” phenomenology—and both the meaning and the possibility of such an adjective have never been clear to me—we may nonetheless attend with interest to a few basic theses in the work of some contemporary French thinkers who have conduct their research in the wake of Husserl and, more so, Heidegger.<italic>More so, Heidegger</italic>: One may rightly wonder, what does it mean to grant Heideggerian thought all rights and privileges when speaking of phenomenology? And second, what does it mean to suppose that phenomenology as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Appearing and the Irreducible</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LACOSTE</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN-YVES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gschwandtner</surname>
                           <given-names>Christina M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “reduction,” or<italic>epochê</italic>, is officially a latecomer in the phenomenological landscape. Husserl’s first published text to propose the concept is the first book of the<italic>Ideas</italic>, published in 1913.¹ It certainly would not be difficult to show that the reduction is already present in an inchoate fashion in the 1905–1906 lectures on the theory of consciousness,² and we can suspect that the reduction is present<italic>in nuce</italic>from the<italic>Logical Investigations</italic>onward. Yet let us stick with the official version and focus on the<italic>Ideas</italic>. To begin at the beginning, in the beginning was not phenomenology, that is,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“it / is true”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HART</surname>
                           <given-names>KEVIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Phenomenology, as properly practiced, is a response to what is given rather than a single procedure that can be perfected. Responses can take various forms—essays, treatises, paintings, conversations, narratives, plays, and poems—each of which has constraints that, whether respected or transgressed, inflect phenomenological observation in different ways. Literature certainly gives us a range of examples for understanding phenomenology. When reading Italo Calvino’s<italic>Invisible Cities</italic>(1972) we see exactly what “free phantasy” is, and when watching<italic>Othello</italic>we grasp the<italic>eidos</italic>of jealousy far better than in reading a paper about that obsessive state in a psychology journal.¹ Yet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Phenomenality of the Sacrament—Being and Givenness</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARION</surname>
                           <given-names>JEAN-LUC</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>Translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Benson</surname>
                           <given-names>Bruce Ellis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the sacrament—or, more precisely, that of the sacramentality of the sacrament—undoubtedly first arises concerning theology. If one admits, at least as a formal point of departure for it one of its normative definitions, one will say with the<italic>Decree of the Eucharist</italic>of the Council of Trent: “Indeed the holy Eucharist shares in common with the other sacraments that it is a symbol of a sacred thing and the visible form of an invisible grace.”¹ Starting from the Eucharist, one must pose and then formulate the connection between the sacramental symbol and that to which</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Human in Question:</title>
                     <subtitle>Augustinian Dimensions in Jean-Luc Marion</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KOSKY</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most of the English-speaking audience was introduced to the new French phenomenology, the subject of this volume, through the work of Jean-Luc Marion. In particular, the translation of Marion’s<italic>God Without Being</italic>was the first major work of these authors to achieve widespread attention. Because of this, the new French phenomenology is associated with a “theological turn.” No doubt,<italic>God Without Being</italic>justifies being labeled a theological work. Its project was to give revelation or to think a transcendent God absolutely and unconditionally. The divine transcendence could be given by liberating God from those determinations, which, Marion argued, reduced it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Poor Phenomenon:</title>
                     <subtitle>Marion and the Problem of Givenness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STEINBOCK</surname>
                           <given-names>ANTHONY J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Today one can hardly speak of a phenomenology of givenness without approaching or coming to terms with Jean-Luc Marion’s novel conception of the “saturated phenomenon.” The saturated phenomenon is that which subverts, overflows, exceeds, and precedes the intentional sense-giving on the part of the subject.</p>
                     <p>According to Marion, there are four main modes of saturated givenness, what he calls the event, the idol, the flesh, the icon, and, encompassing all of them, revelation.¹ The phenomenological status of the saturated phenomena is relatively clear in Marion’s work, and it has been the topic of many investigations. What remains extremely ambiguous, however,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Michel Henry’s Theory of Disclosive Moods</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HANSON</surname>
                           <given-names>JEFFREY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Michel Henry pursued throughout his career a remarkable, and remarkably consistent, account of disclosive mood. As a phenomenologist of affectivity, it is no surprise that Henry focused his attention on specific tonalities that reveal a privileged truth. Early in his career Henry emphasized despair as the privileged tonality, but later he dispensed with despair and instead preferred to speak of anxiety. Despite the change in vocabulary, however, in each case his interpretation of what the disclosive mood discloses is the same.¹ Beyond the sort of disclosure characteristic of any ordinary feeling, a disclosive mood, according to Henry, reveals the self</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Can We Hear the Voice of God?</title>
                     <subtitle>Michel Henry and the Words of Christ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GSCHWANDTNER</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTINA M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The crackling of flames around the bush looked threatening in the dry desert. Where would he get water to extinguish the blaze? Yet this fire was peculiar: it didn’t seem to spread. The barren branches were brilliantly illumined in the flickering tongues, but like a well-coordinated dance they moved back and forth without damaging the bush itself. A mysterious fire indeed.</italic>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>His step was slow and hesitant; his feet almost stumbled under the weight of his grief. The mountain seemed impossibly high and yet the destination far too close. His son skipped ahead with firewood on his shoulder. How could</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Radical Phenomenology Reveals a Measure of Faith and a Need for a Levinasian Other in Henry’s Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MERCER</surname>
                           <given-names>RONALD L.</given-names>
                           <suffix>JR.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jean-Yves Lacoste reminds us in “The Work and Complement of Appearing” that things exist inasmuch as they invite themselves to us. Were we but able to render an account of this invitation, were we only to perceive that it is not in disguise that things appear to us, and were we, finally, to know the conditions under which consciousness is open, all the work of philosophy would be, by right, achievable.¹ “Were we”—a contrary to fact conditional. If we<italic>were</italic>to have made these accounts, perceptions, and conditions—but we have not—then all of philosophy’s work would be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Truth of Life:</title>
                     <subtitle>Michel Henry on Marx</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CROCKETT</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAYTON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the translation of<italic>I Am the Truth</italic>, Michel Henry has emerged in the English-speaking world as one of the Christian phenomenologists associated with the turn to religion on the part of contemporary continental philosophy. Henry’s previous phenomenological books, such as<italic>The Essence of Manifestation</italic>and<italic>Philosophy and Phenomenology of the Body</italic>, can be read as significant philosophical works in themselves or alternatively as leading toward his later, more explicitly religious writings.¹ Whether in his dense phenomenological reflections or his intense religious meditations, Henry’s language is provocative, and I would like to second Jean-Luc Marion’s initial negative reaction. Referring to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Call of Grace:</title>
                     <subtitle>Henri de Lubac, Jean-Louis Chrétien, and the Theological Conditions of Christian Radical Phenomenology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DAVIS</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSHUA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay investigates the theological issues associated with the so-called theological turn in French phenomenology.¹ The burden of the inquiry is threefold: to question the terms of the debate as elaborated by Dominique Janicaud; to suggest a possible reason for the stalemate in the debate that has developed in response to those terms; and to present a more<italic>theologically</italic>attentive perspective that can overcome this deadlock from within specifically phenomenological strictures. The claim will be advanced that Christian radical phenomenology tacitly and illicitly deploys the theological categories of grace and the supernatural, leading to unwarranted claims about manifestation that occlude</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Between Call and Voice:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Antiphonal Thought of Jean-Louis Chrétien</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BALLAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JOSEPH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>196</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the book itself offers no substantial development of its marvelous title, Paul Claudel’s<italic>The Eye Listens</italic>¹ is often cited by Jean-Louis Chrétien as a pithy formulation of an important phenomenological principle. In addition to the observation of artworks (the topic of Claudel’s book), itself impossible without the silence of listening, the concept of a listening eye applies more generally to the relations of the individual sense faculties to one another in their common, worldly labor. Seeing and hearing, touch and sight, cannot be separated one from the other but, rather, bespeak a “radical unity of sense,”² a oneness constitutive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Chrétien on the Call That Wounds</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BENSON</surname>
                           <given-names>BRUCE ELLIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Only at the very end of Jean-Louis Chrétien’s remarkable essay on prayer do we discover why he thinks of prayer as “wounded”:</p>
                     <p>Why call it “wounded word”? It always has its origin in the wound of joy or distress, it is always a tearing that brings it about that the lips open. And it does so as it is still and otherwise wounded. Wounded by this hearing and this call that have always already preceded it, and that unveil it to itself, in a truth always in suffering, always agonic, struggling like Jacob all night in the dust to wrest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Embodied Ears:</title>
                     <subtitle>Being in the World and Hearing the Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>TREANOR</surname>
                           <given-names>BRIAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>222</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Philosophers thinking in the wake of Emmanuel Levinas—that is to say<italic>all</italic>of us working at the intersection of continental philosophy and theology—tend to construe the relationship of the self to the other in terms of one of two sensory metaphors: the visual or the oral/aural.</p>
                     <p>The mainstream philosophical tradition of the West is characterized by a marked preference for the visual metaphor. Plato, for example, analogizes knowledge and vision explicitly in his attempt to describe the role played by the Good (<italic>agathon</italic>) in intellection (either<italic>noesis</italic>or<italic>dianoia</italic>). “As the good is in the intelligible region with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Witness of Humility</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WIRZBA</surname>
                           <given-names>NORMAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is no task more difficult than to be faithful and true to our creaturely condition. Whether out of fear, blindness, suspicion, arrogance, or rebellion, our abiding temptation is to evade, dissimulate, or distort each other and our place in the world. Rather than patiently and honestly living up to our need before others—by taking full account of, and then honoring, the breadth and depth of the relationships we live through—we deform need into fantasy and remake the world to suit our own desires. Rather than being grateful for the fact that others contribute to our well being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>307</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c5cjph.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
