<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Marxism and Form</book-title>
         <subtitle>20th-Century Dialectical Theories of Literature</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JAMESON</surname>
               <given-names>FREDRIC</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>ADORNO</surname>
               <given-names>T. W.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BENJAMIN</surname>
               <given-names>WALTER</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MARCUSE</surname>
               <given-names>HERBERT</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib5">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BLOCH</surname>
               <given-names>ERNST</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib6">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LUKÁCS</surname>
               <given-names>GEORG</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib7">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SARTRE</surname>
               <given-names>JEAN-PAUL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400884506</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400884500</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1971</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ggjkw6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>For more than thirty years, Fredric Jameson has been one of the most productive, wide-ranging, and distinctive literary theorists in the United States and the Anglophone world. Marxism and Form provided a pioneering account of the work of the major European Marxist theorists--T. W. Adorno, Walter Benjamin, Herbert Marcuse, Ernst Bloch, Georg Lukács, and Jean-Paul Sartre--work that was, at the time, largely neglected in the English-speaking world. Through penetrating readings of each theorist, Jameson developed a critical mode of engagement that has had tremendous in.uence. He provided a framework for analyzing the connection between art and the historical circumstances of its making--in particular, how cultural artifacts distort, repress, or transform their circumstances through the abstractions of aesthetic form.</p>
         <p>Jameson's presentation of the critical thought of this Hegelian Marxism provided a stark alternative to the Anglo-American tradition of empiricism and humanism. It would later provide a compelling alternative to poststructuralism and deconstruction as they became dominant methodologies in aesthetic criticism.</p>
         <p>One year after Marxism and Form, Princeton published Jameson's<italic>The Prison-House of Language</italic>(1972), which provided a thorough historical and philosophical description of formalism and structuralism. Both books remain central to Jameson's main intellectual legacy: describing and extending a tradition of Western Marxism in cultural theory and literary interpretation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="432"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>T. W. ADORNO; OR, HISTORICAL TROPES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To whom can one present a writer whose principal subject is the disappearance of the public? What serious justification can be made for an attempt to summarize, simplify, make more widely accessible a work which insists relentlessly on the need for modern art and thought to be difficult, to guard their truth and freshness by the austere demands they make on the powers of concentration of their participants, by their refusal of all habitual response in their attempt to reawaken numb thinking and deadened perception to a raw, wholly unfamiliar real world?</p>
                     <p>It is as though everything in the life</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>VERSIONS OF A MARXIST HERMENEUTIC</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So the melancholy that speaks from the pages of Benjamin’s essays—private depressions, professional discouragement, the dejection of the outsider, distress in the face of a political and historical nightmare—searches the past for an adequate object, for some emblem or image at which, as in religious meditation, the mind can stare itself out, in which it can find momentary, if only aesthetic, relief. It finds it: in the Germany of the Thirty Years’ War, in the Paris “capital of the nineteenth century.” For they are both—the Baroque and the modern—in their very essence allegorical, and they match</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>THE CASE FOR GEORG LUKÁCS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For Western readers the idea of Georg Lukács has often seemed more interesting than the reality. It is as though, in some world of Platonic forms and methodological archetypes, a place were waiting for the Marxist literary critic which (after Plekhanov) only Lukács has seriously tried to fill. Yet in the long run even his more sympathetic Western critics turn away from him in varying degrees of disillusionment: they came prepared to contemplate the abstract idea, but in practice they find themselves asked to sacrifice too much. They pay lip service to Lukács as a figure, but the texts themselves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>SARTRE AND HISTORY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>206</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The customary description of the<italic>Critique of Dialectical Reason</italic>as an attempt to reconcile existentialism and Marxism has always seemed to me to betray a fundamental naïveté about the relationship of thought in general, and political thought in particular, to our being as a whole, to that total human reality of which it is an expression. Intellectual systems are not here opinions which can be tinkered with, adjusted, manipulated until we somehow manage to fit them together properly; and such an operation is all the more ironic when it takes as its object two philosophical approaches which explicitly deny the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>TOWARDS DIALECTICAL CRITICISM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>306</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A phenomenological description of dialectical criticism? The contradiction is not so great as it might at first glance appear. The peculiar difficulty of dialectical writing lies indeed in its holistic, “totalizing” character: as though you could not say any one thing until you had first said everything; as though with each new idea you were bound to recapitulate the entire system. So it is that the attempt to do justice to the most random observation of Hegel ends up drawing the whole tangled, dripping mass of the Hegelian sequence of forms out into the light with it. So it is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>417</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkw6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
