<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Operation of Grace</book-title>
         <subtitle>Further Essays on Art, Faith, and Mystery</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wolfe</surname>
               <given-names>Gregory</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780718894399</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780718844721</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The Lutterworth Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Gregory Wolfe</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1p5f2hg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Operation of Grace collects a decade’s worth of essays by Gregory Wolfe taken from the pages of Image, the literary journal he founded more than a quarter century ago. As he notes in the preface, his Image editorials, while they cover a wide range of topics, focus on the intersection of “art, faith, and mystery". Wolfe believes that art and religion, while hardly identical, offer illuminating analogies to one another—art deepening faith through the empathetic reach of the imagination and faith anchoring art in a vision beyond the artist’s ego. Several essays dwell on how aesthetic values like ambiguity, tragedy, and beauty enlarge our understanding of the spiritual life. There are also a series of reflections that extend Wolfe’s campaign to renew the neglected and often misunderstood tradition of Christian humanism. Finally, there are sections that contain more personal meditations arising from Wolfe’s involvement in nurturing and promoting the work of emerging writers and artists. The Operation of Grace demonstrates once again why novelist Ron Hansen has spoken of Wolfe as “one of the most incisive and persuasive voices of our generation".</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="220"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Metaphorical God</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Cave and the Cathedral</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1994, three spelunkers were looking for undiscovered caves in the Ardèche region of southeastern France. The region is named after the Ardèche River, which has cut through limestone for millennia and created hundreds of caves. On a summer weekend expedition they came across a place in a cliff wall where they sensed a draft of warm air near a pile of rubble. They dug around it but soon lost interest. Then in December they returned to the same place and felt a stronger draft. They began digging in earnest and entered a vast cave complex filled with dozens of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Wound of Beauty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Strange as it may seem, beauty still needs to be defended. In the history of the West, beauty has played the role of Cinderella to her sisters, goodness and truth. I don’t mean to say that beauty in art or nature hasn’t been appreciated throughout history—though there have been times when beauty has been the subject of frontal assaults—but simply that when we start getting official, when we get theological or philosophical, beauty becomes a hot potato.</p>
                     <p>The ambivalence about beauty at the heart of Western culture begins at the beginning. In Jerusalem, proscriptions against idols and graven</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Tragic Sense of Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When i first arrived at Oxford University in the early 1980s to pursue graduate work, I was all swagger on the outside, but that was to conceal the soft center of terror within. I had gone from being a big man on a small midwestern campus situated between two cornfields to a nobody at an ancient European university whose “New College” had been founded in the fifteenth century. For one thing, there were the social bewilderments attendant upon entering a society where class was a more important and more complex phenomenon than I had ever known it could be. But</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Singularly Ambiguous</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Samuel Johnson, the great eighteenth-century critic, moralist, and wit, once said of the American revolutionaries: “How is it that we hear the loudest yelps for liberty among the drivers of [slaves]?” I don’t know what Johnson’s friend, Edmund Burke—a proponent of American independence—said in response, but I rather hope it was: “Touché.”</p>
                     <p>While I can’t match Johnson’s epigrammatic waggery, I often find myself with similar sentiments these days about those who seek to defend “the West” from its perceived enemies. Whether implicitly or explicitly, these champions of Western civilization believe that in a time of war, terrorism, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Strange Pilgrims</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his masterful book<italic>The Life You Save May Be Your Own</italic>, Paul Elie has crafted a braided narrative about the lives and works of four twentiethcentury American Catholic writers, all now canonical figures: Dorothy Day, Thomas Merton, Flannery O’Connor, and Walker Percy. The first sentence begins casually but ends with a kick: “In the photographs, they don’t look like people who might make you want to change your life.”</p>
                     <p>For those who know anything about this quartet, this statement is puzzling. In their youth, all four had read—and felt liberated by—the French neo-Thomist Jacques Maritain’s<italic>Art and</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Secular Scriptures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any new book about the relationship between the Bible and literature enters a crowded field, one strewn with masterworks by the likes of Robert Alter, Frank Kermode, Northrop Frye, and Gabriel Josipovici. So the bar is set high. Nicholas Boyle’s<italic>Sacred and Secular Scriptures: A Catholic Approach to Literature</italic>clears that bar with room to spare. While the subtitle might put some readers on guard, Boyle proves a hospitable and respectful writer; at points the Catholic tradition takes center stage, but much of the book speaks with equal power and resonance to Jewish and Protestant traditions.</p>
                     <p>There is no disguising</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Shouts and Whispers</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having been a participant in any number of roundtables and panels on the state of religion in America, and in particular the relationship between faith and culture, I’ve grown accustomed to hearing my conservative colleagues argue that contemporary writers of faith are flabby compared to the more muscular writers of the early-and mid-twentieth century.</p>
                     <p>The argument goes like this: writers like C. S. Lewis, W. H. Auden, Evelyn Waugh, and Flannery O’Connor created works that offered Christianity as an alternative to modern secularism. Many of them were public converts to the faith, and wrote works in which conversion is the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fully Human</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Last night i watched—mesmerized, despite its near three-hour length—Andrei Tarkovsky’s film<italic>Stalker</italic>, a minimalist science fiction epic set in a dreary, bombed-out industrial wasteland. The title does not derive from the contemporary connotation of the sexual predator, but goes back to the sort of guide who leads hunters to where game can be found. In fact, the script deliberately associates its stalker with the James Fenimore Cooper character Natty Bumppo, who is known as “Deerstalker.”</p>
                     <p>In the film the stalker leads people into the Zone, a heavily fortified area guarded by machine-gun nests and roving patrols. Some years</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Thirty Seconds Away</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>By all accounts, Saint Irenaeus of Lyons, a bishop of the early church, didn’t have it easy. For one thing, he’d left the thriving, well-established Christian community in Asia Minor for what was, in essence, missionary territory. Lyons was hardly the back of the beyond—it was, in fact, a thriving commercial center in southern Gaul that did a lot of trade with the East, which was why Christianity could slip in so easily. But if the bourgeois cosmopolitanism of the city offered opportunities for the fledgling church, it also posed its own set of challenges.</p>
                     <p>Irenaeus found himself dividing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Religious but Not Spiritual</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For a number of years I’ve been saving up the fiction of Anthony Trollope as a sort of mid-life treat. At least I hoped it would be a treat. Trollope is the kind of author who is often ridiculed as a literary lightweight: a Victorian lacking the range and energy of Dickens; a drawing-room chronicler without Jane Austen’s tart irony or powers of observation. Even as I turned to the first page I was braced for disappointment.</p>
                     <p>So far I can report that Trollope—for all his gentle romantic farce and clerical satire—stands up quite well as a distinctive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Current Event</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>He said he never intended to found anything, and I believe him. But he had a gift for friendship. When his funeral mass was celebrated in Milan last month, 30,000 of his companions were there. The principal celebrant, Cardinal Ratzinger, read a message from another friend, Karol Wojtyla.</p>
                     <p>It may be a truism to say that every saint is a saint for his times, but in the case of Father Luigi Giussani, the match between charism—the particular form of faith he felt called to live—and the spirit of the age was nothing short of extraordinary. In the early</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>East and West in Miniature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The recent controversy over Pope Benedict XVI’s Regensburg lecture—which touched on the nature of human reason, but which also questioned, in passing, the relationship between faith and reason in Islam—may turn out to be more productive than was at first thought. Among other things, it generated a substantive open letter to the pope signed by thirty-eight respected Muslim clerics—a document that itself is carefully reasoned and gracious. At a time when the rising tide of Islamic fundamentalism and terrorism is being met by increasing fear and stereotyping in the West, any form of dialogue is cause for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Picturing the Passion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Now that Mel Gibson’s<italic>The Passion of the Christ</italic>has reached thousands of screens around the world and the frenzy of editorializing, pre-and postrelease, has died down, two of the early questions about the film have been answered. Once the film entered the public domain, most of the fears about whether it was anti-Semitic dissipated, leaving only some concern about the possibility that in certain parts of the globe anti-Semites might use the film to incite violence. The other question—would<italic>The Passion</italic>’s graphic violence keep people away from the theaters—has been answered with a resounding no. The numbers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Why the Inklings Aren’t Enough</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Toward the end of his life, Karl Marx found himself in conversation with an earnest would-be acolyte who was burbling about his plan to found a Marxist club. The older man suddenly rounded on him, declaring:<italic>Je ne suis pas une Marxiste!</italic>(I am not a Marxist). In a few simple words Marx managed not only to reject the status of cult hero but also to insinuate that systematizing his thought would falsify it.</p>
                     <p>In a similar vein, it has often been noted that the two Oxford dons at the center of the famous literary group known as the Inklings</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Culture Wars Revisited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ten years ago in these pages I attempted to explain “ Why I Am a Conscientious Objector in the Culture Wars.” At that time, the dust had only recently settled on the public controversies over National Endowment for the Arts funding of works by Robert Mapplethorpe and Andres Serrano. In addition to the debate over public funding of the arts, the central culture war issues had emerged: abortion, euthanasia, welfare, homosexual rights, and church/state relations. James Davison Hunter had followed up his groundbreaking book<italic>Culture Wars</italic>with the even more ominously titled<italic>Before the Shooting Starts</italic>.</p>
                     <p>It was clear then</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Always Now</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Are you convinced that everything is going to hell in a handbasket? Down the tubes? Or are you possessed of a more sanguine temperament? Do you feel that life is getting better every day in every way? Do you believe in progress or regress? What would the make and model of your handbasket happen to be?</p>
                     <p>The older I get, the more interested I am in people’s convictions about the<italic>directionality</italic>of history.</p>
                     <p>I have been told that there were times when the doctrine of progress was in the ascendant, when millions of people believed that society was moving inexorably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Two-Way Traffic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a recent essay, poet Ira Sadoff issued a sweeping denunciation of what he calls the “spiritualization of American poetry.” Entitled “Trafficking in the Radiant” and published in the<italic>American Poetry Review</italic>, the essay asserts that contemporary poets have been influenced by the resurgence of religiosity in our culture, with disastrous results. “My contention is that using religion as a metaphorical expression of our powerlessness . . . diminishes human agency and makes possible a hierarchical authoritarianism . . . [and] that the Romantic desire to transcend materiality leads to a flight from the social and the sexual.”</p>
                     <p>In short,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Keeping a Private Address</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>95</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Reviewing a recent biography of the writer Eudora Welty, Francine Prose confessed that before reading the book she had imagined the author as “a bit like Emily Dickinson with excellent southern manners, or perhaps a more robust, less God-haunted Flannery O’Connor—one of those stay-at-home prodigies who somehow acquire an intimate knowledge of human experience without venturing far beyond the garden gate.” Despite the biographies detailing her wide travels and far-flung friendships, despite the volumes of her photographs, which demonstrate her eye for the public world, the myth of Welty as recluse has been slow to die.</p>
                     <p>Though a much</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conservative Elegies</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Within just a few weeks of each other, America recently lost two of its finest sons—William F. Buckley Jr. and E. Victor Milione. One was known to millions, while the other preferred obscurity, but both were seminal figures in the modern revival of political and intellectual conservatism. I eulogize them together not only because of their shared convictions, but for a simple reason: they were my first two employers. They literally gave me my start in life.</p>
                     <p>In the summer of 1980, I could be pardoned for feeling like William Wordsworth at the time of the French Revolution: a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Poetic Justice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Before I came down here to deliver this talk on how art and social justice should—and shouldn’t—mix, I posted on Facebook that I was preparing by reading the works of various writers. One commentator singled out Gustave Flaubert from my list and responded with a skeptical “Hmm.” I understood the reaction: after all, Flaubert was known as a writer who cared more for style than social justice (“One never tires of what is well-written, style is life!”). In contrast to the two other great social realists of nineteenth-century French fiction—Honoré de Balzac and Émile Zola—Flaubert rarely</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Looking for a Renaissance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>115</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most educated people, in addition to a set of favorite authors, artists, and composers, develop a fascination for one or more historic cultures: republican Rome, say, or colonial New England or the Ming dynasty. Sometimes these passions are matters of aesthetic or intellectual taste, but often they bear a relationship to the individual’s ideas about what constitutes the good life and how the ideals of a past culture might nurture and strengthen one’s own. Of course, the prevailing world view of a given time period may play a role in guiding what the majority find engaging. After several centuries of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Giotto’s Ratio</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Image</italic>is a journal devoted exclusively to contemporary literature and art—to the present moment—but here we are in the cradle of the Renaissance. We have not come out of mere antiquarian curiosity, but in search of parallels to our own time and the insights we can glean from them. As an organization interested in the cross-fertilization of art and faith, and the ways that these two fundamental human experiences can renew lives and communities, we believe that the Renaissance offers a model of cultural transformation that is highly relevant to the present.</p>
                     <p>Last year, the inaugural year of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Follies Worldly and Divine</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1509, as he lay sick in bed, Desiderius Erasmus decided to pass the time by producing a literary gift for his friend and fellow Christian humanist, Thomas More. Within a week, he completed the<italic>Encomium Moriae</italic>, which can be read as either the “praise of More” or the “praise of folly.”</p>
                     <p>A best seller in its own time,<italic>The Praise of Folly</italic>is little read today. Written before the rise of the novel, it lacks the sort of picaresque narrative structure that makes a book like<italic>Candide</italic>accessible to contemporary readers. The<italic>Folly</italic>is written in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The King’s Great Matter . . . and Ours</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The royal soap opera that is the life and reign of Henry VIII evokes endless fascination both in the realms of scholarship and the popular imagination. Erudite tomes heavy with footnotes, racy novels the size of toaster ovens, and sumptuously staged television miniseries pour forth in a steady stream. And what’s not to like? For most of us, sex, power, intrigue, and those exquisite costumes are irresistible.</p>
                     <p>And yet, in all but the most superficial treatments of the period, there is a sense, whether inchoate or sharply defined, that there is more to this story than whispered betrayals in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Becoming the Other</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the first days of May 1610, the renowned Confucian scholar Li Madou lay dying in his home in Beijing. Hundreds of the leading citizens of the Chinese capital came to pay their respects to the man whose books on ethics, mathematics, friendship, and the mysteries of life and death had been read and circulated throughout the Middle Kingdom. The visitors recalled with great affection the many enlightening conversations and debates they had enjoyed in his residence, over which their host had presided. Even as he was slipping away they remembered his dignity and generosity in welcoming them to his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Humiliation of the Word</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is fitting that at this residency—the last for you who are graduating—we have been reading and studying T. S. Eliot’s poem<italic>Four Quartets</italic>. For many readers,<italic>Four Quartets</italic>is the most powerful and resonant exploration of Christian faith in the annals of twentieth-century poetry. It is also the kind of poem that, once you fully absorb it, tends to follow you around everywhere, interpreting your life—it possesses that sort of metaphysical urgency.</p>
                     <p>This poem has been called Eliot’s<italic>Paradiso</italic>, after the infernal visions of Prufrock and<italic>The Waste Land</italic>and the purgatorial fires of<italic>Ash Wednesday</italic>.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Stalking the Spirit</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This program is blessed to have its intensive, ten-day residencies at two of the most beautiful places on the continent: the high desert of Santa Fe, New Mexico, and the water’s edge on Whidbey Island, Washington, where we look across the Strait of Juan de Fuca at the Olympic Mountains. At the graduation ceremonies held at the conclusion of these residencies there is always a chance that nature will make a dramatic entrance. Here at our Santa Fe graduations it’s monsoon season, when the thunderheads build up over the course of the day and you can see curtains of rain</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Operation of Grace</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I’d like to share a few thoughts with you that I hope are appropriate for the occasion, words derived from two texts we’ve studied together, T. S. Eliot’s<italic>Four Quartets</italic>and Evelyn Waugh’s<italic>Brideshead Revisited</italic>. Both were written in the years just before and during World War II; both sought to find hope amid the encroaching catastrophe—the possibility of grace and renewal in the face of a civilization being destroyed from within as well as from without.</p>
                     <p>The war had the effect of evoking deep personal feeling in both these writers, so much so that Waugh, at least, feared</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Who’s Afraid of Geoffrey Hill?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Oxford University has a new Professor of Poetry. The post is largely ceremonial, though it does require the occupant to deliver an occasional lecture. Still, it is a significant honor, second only in the United Kingdom to that of poet laureate. First established in 1708, the professorship is an exclusive club, one that has numbered among its members Matthew Arnold, Robert Graves, W. H. Auden, and Seamus Heaney.</p>
                     <p>Geoffrey Hill won this year by a landslide. Normally that sort of margin would indicate a broad base of admiration and even affection among Oxford graduates, but in this case the appearance</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Poetry of Exile</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>History is written by the victors, so the saying goes. It would be pleasant to believe that the history of literature (or the arts in general) might prove an exception to this rule, that artistic merit will always be recognized in its own time, regardless of fashion or ideology. But we know that’s not true. Artists who consciously or unconsciously spurn the dominant institutions and trends of their culture always struggle to gain recognition.</p>
                     <p>There are posthumous demotions and rediscoveries, of course, which can bring about a measure of belated justice. But it’s hard not to think from time to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Voice of This Calling</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Four days after I turned three, my sister was born. I was young enough to be confused and anxious about what was going on. My mother had grown large and then abruptly disappeared from our apartment, where I was left with a sitter. This all took place in the days when hypersensitivity about germs and infections kept small children out of hospitals. A couple of days later my father drove me to the back of the hospital in his 1957 Thunderbird convertible, the car my mother would make him relinquish in favor of a sedan that would accommodate two growing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Scenes from an Editorial Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The publication of the fiftieth issue of a journal doesn’t constitute an anniversary, but it does have the feel of a milestone. The impulse, especially for someone who was present at the creation, is to engage in a little fond reminiscence. Yet I find myself resisting that impulse. In fact, as the years have passed, I’ve found myself reflecting less on the role I’ve played in shaping this enterprise than on what it has done to shape me.</p>
                     <p>It goes without saying that a project as all-consuming as a quarterly journal like<italic>Image</italic>is the proverbial gorilla in the room.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Four Cultures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>An old Albert Brooks film has been rattling around in my head of late:<italic>Defending Your Life</italic>. Divorced advertising exec fiddles with the CD player in his brand new BMW and plows into a city bus, only to find himself in Judgment City, where he has to account for himself in a jury trial where the evidence consists of episodes from his life. The worst possible result isn’t exactly hell; it’s being sent back to earth for another attempt, rather than moving forward, to a better planet and a better life.</p>
                     <p>In the version of the film playing in my</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Mugg, Hitch, and Me</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was growing up, I wanted to be Christopher Hitchens. In a manner of speaking. I didn’t, in fact, learn who he was until I was in my thirties, but I can see in retrospect that Hitchens was the epitome of everything I hoped to be as a writer. My passions were political, philosophical, and literary, and it seemed to me that there could be no better life than as a prolific cultural critic who wrote bluntly and even prophetically about the follies of the age. I imagined writing long review essays of contemporary novels and biographies, laced with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Breath</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The summer of 1968, though it mourned the recent assassination of Martin Luther King Jr. and shuddered at the murder of Robert F. Kennedy, was a pastoral idyll for a nine-year-old boy who had just moved from an apartment in Manhattan to the lush north shore of Long Island. My mother, concerned about crime and eager for her two children to be able to run and play in wider, greener places than urban parks, had convinced my father to rent a two-hundred-year-old farmhouse on seven acres in Kings Point.</p>
                     <p>That farmhouse has long since been torn down, and three gleaming</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f2hg.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>208</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
