<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8m3</collection-id>
      <volume>189</volume>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PL2754.T75 Z665 2000</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chou, Tso</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">jen, 1885–1967</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Modernism (Literature)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">China</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Zhou Zuoren and an Alternative Chinese Response to Modernity</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Daruvala</surname>
               <given-names>Susan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2000</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674002388</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781684173396</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1684173396</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Asia Center</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge (Massachusetts); London,</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1tfj8w7"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book explores the issues of nation and modernity in China by focusing on the work of Zhou Zuoren (1885-1967), one of the most controversial of modern Chinese intellectuals and brother of the writer Lu Xun. Zhou was radically at odds with many of his contemporaries and opposed their nation-building and modernization projects. Through his literary and aesthetic practice as an essayist, Zhou espoused a way of constructing the individual and affirming the individual’s importance in opposition to the normative national subject of most May Fourth reformers. Zhou’s work presents an alternative vision of the nation and questions the monolithic claims of modernity by promoting traditional aesthetic categories, the locality rather than the nation, and a literary history that values openness and individualism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="386"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>XI</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Modernity and the Rupture with the Past</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a study of the modern Chinese writer Zhou Zuoren (1885-1967) and of alternative responses to nationalism and modernity. Zhou was an important early contributor to the watershed May Fourth New Culture movement (1917-23), which set the direction for the subsequent development of modern Chinese literature.¹ Zhou represented the humanistic strand of thinking concerned with defining an ideal life. A founding member of the Literary Association of China (Wenxue yanjiu hui), set up in 1920, he initially advocated the creation of literature to foster humanitarian values? However, two years later he broke with the idea that literature had a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Constructions of Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>59</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On a late autumn evening in 1906, when dusk had already fallen over the city, Zhou Zuoren arrived at a modest boarding house in the hilly Yushima ni-chome section of Hongo district in Tokyo. Lu Xun had moved to Tokyo six months earlier, after deciding to abandon his medical studies and pursue a career in literature. He was now returning, this time with his brother, from a two-month trip home to Shaoxing. Zhou Zuoren, for whom everything was new, felt a mounting sense of anticipation as they entered the building. Like others of his generation he was attracted by Japan’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>The Aesthetics of place and Self</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Zhou Zuoren’s central contribution to modern Chinese literature-and the foundation of his reputation-was first spelled out in March 1922 by Hu Shi, as he was taking stock of the success of the new literature in the vernacular. Hu distinguished two types of vernacular essay<italic>(baihua sanwen)</italic>, of which the long, argumentative essay<italic>(yilunwen)</italic>was one. The success of this form was obvious, Hu said, and he then proceeded to discuss what we may call the essay proper<italic>(sanwen)</italic>:</p>
                     <p>In recent years, the most noticeable development as far as the essay<italic>(sanwen)</italic>is concerned has been the short essay<italic>(xiaopin sanwen)</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Zhou Zuoren’s Humanism, the Self and the Essay Form</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Zhou Zuoren’s aesthetics of<italic>quwei and bense were</italic>grounded in a concept of the self traceable to the radical Neo-Confucianism of the late Ming. Zhou’s innovation was to capitalize on its respect for the self as an autonomous moral agent but to secularize these aesthetics by disconnecting them from any religious or political dogma, while leaving them open-ended so that they could reflect the ineffable in the hands of those writers who wished them to do so.</p>
                     <p>Feng Wenbing, a close associate of Zhou and a practitioner of Chan meditation, is a good example. Zhou’s preface to Fengs<italic>The Tale</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Construction of the Nation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The mistrust of didacticism that runs through Zhou’s writing can be read as a commentary on the ideological construction of the modern nation-state. Zhou’s attack on Han Yu and the<italic>daotong system</italic>takes us to the heart of his criticism, for Han Yu was a pivotal figure in the attempt to construct a single foundation for sociopolitical action and individual cultural production in the wake of the An Lushan (d. 757) rebellion.¹ Han Yu’s radical innovations in guwen as a literary form redefined learning in terms of the Confucian “way of the sage,” and he particularly attacked Daoist and Buddhist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Character List</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1tfj8w7.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
