<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Archaeology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>An Archaeology of Prehistoric Bodies and Embodied Identities in the Eastern Mediterranean</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>MINA</surname>
               <given-names>MARIA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>TRIANTAPHYLLOU</surname>
               <given-names>SEVI</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>PAPADATOS</surname>
               <given-names>YIANNIS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>31</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781785702914</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781785702945</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Oxbow Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Oxford; Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Oxbow Books</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>the individual authors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1ggjkqm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In the long tradition of the archaeology of the eastern Mediterranean bodies have held a prominent role in the form of figurines, frescos, or skeletal remains, and have even been responsible for sparking captivating portrayals of the Mother-Goddess cult, the elegant women of Minoan Crete or the deeds of heroic men. Growing literature on the archaeology and anthropology of the body has raised awareness about the dynamic and multifaceted role of the body in experiencing the world and in the construction, performance and negotiation of social identity. In these 28 thematically arranged papers, specialists in the archaeology of the eastern Mediterranean confront the perceived invisibility of past bodies and ask new research questions. Contributors discuss new and old evidence; they examine how bodies intersect with the material world, and explore the role of body-situated experiences in creating distinct social and other identities. Papers range chronologically from the Palaeolithic to the Early Iron Age and cover the geographical regions of the Aegean, Cyprus and the Near East. They highlight the new possibilities that emerge for the interpretation of the prehistoric eastern Mediterranean through a combined use of body-focused methodological and theoretical perspectives that are nevertheless grounded in the archaeological record.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface and Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mina</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Triantaphyllou</surname>
                           <given-names>Sevi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Papadatos</surname>
                           <given-names>Yiannis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction.</title>
                     <subtitle>The Archaeology of Bodies and the Eastern Mediterranean</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Robb</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most amazing objects in any European museum is a painted clay statue on display in Nicosia which shows a woman with a baby emerging upside down from her vagina. It is probably the only representation in all of European prehistory which shows a woman actually giving birth — a mind-boggling fact when one considers, as Mark Twain remarked, that being born is one of the few universal human experiences. And this thought-provoking find is not alone. From the golden face masks of Mycenae to the unparalleled youths and processing women in the Akrotiri frescoes — so unlike anything in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Polydactyly in Chalcolithic Figurines from Cyprus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gamble</surname>
                           <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Winkelmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Christine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fox</surname>
                           <given-names>Sherry C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Mimesis</italic>is the imitation of nature and life in art or literature. According to Plato, all art is mimetic of life and therefore a reflection of reality. This theory has spawned an entire philosophy and study of art and the nature of reality and identity (<italic>i.e.</italic>Potolsky 2006, Halliwell 2009 — for a prehistoric example see Borić 2007). If art does indeed reflect reality, then this could present a window into the past, representing either ideal images for a particular period or specific individuals. In some cases, it is possible to observe the integration of a specific biological phenomenon into artistic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Figurines, Paint and the Perception of the Body in the Early Bronze Age Southern Aegean</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Papadatos</surname>
                           <given-names>Yiannis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most studies on anthropomorphic figurines of the Early Bronze Age (hereafter EBA) in the southern Aegean tend to emphasise the strong similarities concerning their type, form and context of findspot (Renfrew 1969; 1991; Branigan 1972; Getz-Preziosi 1987; Doumas 2002). This is largely because Cycladic three-dimensional iconography, particularly the female figurines with folded arms, profoundly influenced the neighbouring areas. Imports from the Cyclades, hybrid types and local imitations of Cycladic-type figurines were found in many sites across the littoral southern Aegean and Crete (Branigan 1972; Sakellarakis 1987; Mina 2008). The typological homogeneity of these figurines was used as evidence for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Thoughts on the Funerary Use of the Early Bronze Age (EBA) Cycladic Figurines:</title>
                     <subtitle>Iconography, Form, Context and Embodied Lives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goula</surname>
                           <given-names>Dimitra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Painted motifs on Cycladic folded-arm figurines (FAFs hereafter) have been considered as representations of body ornamentation that reflected social identity and status (Broodbank 1992, 543–5; 2000, 247–75; Carter 2008, 120–1; Sherratt 2000, 134; Hoffman 2002, 532–4). This paper aims to formulate some thoughts concerning possible meanings of the FAFs deposited in burial contexts. The study of embodied through consideration of painted patterns on the figurines’ surface in most cases make no reference to gender or to the association of specific iconography with the burial context.</p>
                     <p>Initially, earlier interpretations of the statuettes and approaches to the individual</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Composite, Partial, Created and Floating Bodies:</title>
                     <subtitle>a Re-Assessment of the Knossos Temple Repositories Assemblage</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stevens</surname>
                           <given-names>Fay</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Simandiraki-Grimshaw</surname>
                           <given-names>Anna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper operates within the framework of the Cretan Bronze Age (<italic>c.</italic>3000–1100 BC) and focuses on a category of complex buildings dating mainly<italic>c.</italic>1900–1430 BC. We use the term “Palaces” for the sake of continuity, although we are mindful that it does not automatically imply (only) a royal residence (cf. Hood 1995; Day and Relaki 2002; Schoep 2010). We also use the term “Minoan” to refer to the Cretan Bronze Age, again for the sake of consistency, although we are aware that this also invites analysis/deconstruction (cf. Karadimas and Momigliano 2004; Whitley 2006). We are particularly</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Figurines and Complex Identities in Late Bronze Age Cyprus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Knox</surname>
                           <given-names>Daisy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Figurines provide enticing images through which to imagine otherwise remote and faceless prehistoric communities. Early examples from Cyprus feature recurrently on the covers of monographs, excavation reports and conference posters (<italic>e.g.</italic>Coleman<italic>et al.</italic>1996; Tatton-Brown 1997; Knapp 2008); a Chalcolithic figurine was even deemed an apposite image for the one euro coin. Although for modern audiences, figurines have become convenient symbols, embodying and displaying Cyprus’s past identities, researchers are well aware that these complex objects encompass far more than simply passive reflections of past realities. Prehistoric figurines were symbolically-charged objects with clear, active roles in shaping the socio-political landscape</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Handlers and Viewers:</title>
                     <subtitle>Some Remarks on the Process of Perception of Terracotta Figurines on the Example of Cypriot “Goddesses with Upraised Arms”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zeman-Wiśniewska</surname>
                           <given-names>Katarzyna</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Coroplastic studies concerning figures and figurines have developed as a distinct, very vibrant and dynamic field of archaeological research.¹ Terracotta figures and figurines, especially anthropomorphic ones, are fascinating in the way they bring us<italic>face to face</italic>with the past, and have provoked numerous discussions concerning social structures, ancient religions, and even prehistoric models of beauty. Scholars have suggested that artefacts, including figures and figurines, should not be studied, as they are still often presented in museums, standing alone, extracted from their environment, visible only en-face and untouchable (Brumfiel 1996; Hamilton<italic>et al.</italic>1996; Bailey 2005; Zonou-Herbst 2009). We can</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Re-Making the Self:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bodies, Identities and Materialities in Chalcolithic Cyprus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bolger</surname>
                           <given-names>Diane</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this paper I explore some of the ways that changes in multiple aspects of bodily practice during the Chalcolithic period of Cyprus — human burials, figurative art, personal ornamentation and other forms of material culture — can be linked to one another through the concept of the “fractal self”, a term first used by social anthropologists in the early 1990s but applied more recently in archaeological studies by Lucas (1996), Tilley (1996), Chapman (2000), Fowler (2002; 2004; 2008) and Brück (2006) (see also Borić and Robb 2008). I argue that a fundamental transformation of personal and social identity was brought about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Pots and People:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Investigation of Individual and Collective Identities in Early Bronze Age Cyprus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Webb</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Archaeologists routinely consider artefacts in relation to other artefacts and use relationships of similarity and difference to create typologies and organise material culture into chronological or geographical entities (Jones 2007, 143). In this paper I propose instead to focus on the relationship between artefacts and people and ask whether different material assemblages reflect differently embodied lives in Early Bronze Age Cyprus (EBA hereafter) (on the existence of embodied individuals in prehistory and a review of the literature, see Knapp and van Dommelen 2008 and Knapp 2010).</p>
                     <p>Fundamental to this exercise is the premise that the way in which objects are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Dressed to Impress:</title>
                     <subtitle>Metal Objects and Embodied Identities in Early and Middle Bronze Age Cyprus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mina</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following the premise of embodiment theory that “bodily experience is understood to be the existential ground of culture and self” (Csordas 1994, 269), this paper discusses the embodied identities that were generated in connection with the use of metal accoutrements and jewellery in prehistoric Cyprus. Proponents of an embodiment approach in archaeology have generally argued that the study of past identities should focus on the recovery of individuals and their diverse and subjective bodily experiences that cannot be accounted for by broad collectives (Knapp and Meskell 1997, 186; Meskell 2000, 13, 21; Knapp and van Dommelen 2008, 23–4). This</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Placed with Care:</title>
                     <subtitle>Interaction with Decorated Mycenaean Metal Vessels</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Aulsebrook</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephanie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Vessels manufactured from metal appear in a geographically-wide distribution of Late Bronze Age deposits across the southern Greek mainland,<italic>c.</italic>1700–1200 BC, although they remain relatively rare in the archaeological record. Their decoration required additional crafting time, labour and skill, altering their appearance and changing the interactions between the individual user, the vessel, and other participants within their context of use. Much emphasis has been placed within the discipline of archaeology on the communicative aspects of material culture (cf. Shanks and Tilley 1987, 97, 117; Kenoyer 2000, 91; for a more nuanced approach Meskell 2005, 2), but less attention</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>The Performative Body and Social Identity in the Room of the Fresco at Mycenae</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Chapin</surname>
                           <given-names>Anne P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Excavations undertaken in 1968–9 revealed an exceptional fresco<italic>in situ</italic>in the southeast corner of Room 31, a shrine known as the “Room of the Fresco” in the Cult Center at Mycenae (Fig. 11.1). The fresco preserves parts of three female figures, each painted with distinctive costume and attributes: above is the “Sword Bearer,” cloaked and holding a sword pointed tip down; and a “Spear Bearer,” who wears a flounced skirt and grasps a spear or staff (tip up, but missing). The third figure, the “Adorant”, stands on a lower level and raises objects of uncertain identity in votive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>“It’s War, not a Dance”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Polarising Embodied Identities in the Aegean and the Eastern Mediterranean from the End of the Bronze Age to the Early Iron Age, 1200–700 BC</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mikrakis</surname>
                           <given-names>Manolis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After the epochal collapse of state-level societies at the end of the Bronze Age, most of the eastern Mediterranean experienced new forms of statehood for which new social identities were essential. The old system’s failure to prevent disaster would have discredited earlier ideologies defining personal achievement and social status through reference to the supernatural (for the Aegean, see Mikrakis 2013, 229–30, with references). Practices revolving around the human body, the handiest tool for survival in periods of hardship such as in the so-called Dark Age that followed the collapse, would have increased sharply, causing tensions and conflicts.</p>
                     <p>In the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Nuptial Vases in Female Tombs?</title>
                     <subtitle>Aspects of Funerary Behaviour during the Late Geometric Period in Attica</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vlachou</surname>
                           <given-names>Vicky</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The pitcher, a pouring vessel with one vertical handle (“bell-mouthed oinochoe”, after Cook 1997, 22; “pitcherolpe”, after Davison 1961, 10) was introduced in the Athenian repertoire before the middle of the 8th century BC presumably by the Dipylon Painter (Coldstream 1968, 34). The shape has been seen as the descendant of the shoulder-handled amphora that hardly survives into the Late Geometric (LG) I period (Coldstream 1968, 34), while an origin to the late Phrygian painted and monochrome one-handled round-mouthed jug of the late 8th century BC has also been suggested (Langdon 1993, 205; Mitten 1995, 379–80).</p>
                     <p>The number of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Turning into Stone:</title>
                     <subtitle>Rock Art and the Construction of Identities in Ancient Thrace</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pilavaki</surname>
                           <given-names>Stella</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Little is known about the social organisation and culture of the indigenous tribes that had lived since prehistory in Aegean Thrace. I quote a passage of Herodotus, which constitutes a rare incidence among the sporadic references to the Thracians in the Greek literature that gives a glimpse into the values according to which these societies were structured: “To be tattooed is a sign of noble birth; to bear no such marks is for the baser sort. The idler is most honoured, the tiller of the soil most contemned; he is held in highest honour who lives by war and foray”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Lithics and Identity at the Middle Palaeolithic site of Lakonis Cave I, Southern Peloponnese, Greece</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Elefanti</surname>
                           <given-names>Paraskevi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Panagopoulou</surname>
                           <given-names>Eleni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Recent developments in the study of Palaeolithic society have emphasised the need to adopt a more comprehensive approach to the interpretation of human behaviour by taking into consideration various scales of analysis, encompassing both time and space. These scales of analysis can include individuals interacting for only a few hours in the course of a brief encounter, to larger groups and for longer periods, in the context of complex social networks within extended spatial units (Gamble 1999, 67–8). The study of individuals in particular, has generally been regarded as beyond the resolution of the Palaeolithic record (Clark 1992, 107),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Picrolite and Other Stone Beads and Pendants:</title>
                     <subtitle>New Forms in an Old Material during the Transition from the Chalcolithic to the Cypriot Bronze Age</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Georgiou</surname>
                           <given-names>Giorgos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper focuses on the fact that picrolite, an indigenous stone that was extensively used during the Chalcolithic period (4000/3900–2500/2400 BC) for the manufacture of small figurines and other symbolic artefacts, was used in the Early and Middle Cypriot periods (2400–1700 BC) for the production of pendants in new forms. Although the relatively limited number and contextual information available for Bronze Age objects leaves little opportunity to consider in detail how they were perceived by their makers and wearers, they can nevertheless be used to give insights into their significance and the way in which they embodied identity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>The Embodiment of Land Ownership in the Aegean Early Bronze Age</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kouka</surname>
                           <given-names>Ourania</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Following the aforementioned definition, which corresponds also to theoretical approaches of embodiment and its perception (Merleau-Ponty 1964, 159–90; Lesure 2005), it is argued that the built environment demonstrates from prehistoric times an anthropogenic system of closed and open spaces for hosting every-day life, economic, social and symbolic activities. It represents, therefore, an agent through which the needs, abilities and habits of humans are embodied, but also the field for economic and social interaction. Moreover, built environment — domestic, funeral, and sacred — displays the existential ground of culture that allows the identification of its cognitive creator and owner.</p>
                     <p>Ownership is a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>From Potter’s Mark to the Potter Who Marks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Christakis</surname>
                           <given-names>Kostis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The application of marks on pottery during the manufacture and before the firing of a pot is a widespread practice in both the archaeological and ethnographic records of a range of different cultural milieus. Given that the mark was applied before the firing process, it is generally agreed that it is the potter who was responsible for marking the pot. Discussions so far have focused exclusively on the function and meaning of these marks. Most scholars relate them to potters and/or workshops (<italic>e.g.</italic>Bikaki 1984, 9, 22, 42; Papadopoulos 1994; Hirschfeld 1999, 33; Lindblom 2001, 132–3; Ditze 2007, 279</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Grasping Identity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Theoretically informed Human Bioarchaeology in or for the Eastern Mediterranean?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lorentz</surname>
                           <given-names>Kirsi O.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Archaeologists have attempted to study identity through several different avenues and varied archaeological remains (see<italic>e.g.</italic>Insoll 2007), including employing data derived from analyses of human remains. More recently, some bioarchaeologists have begun to attempt social interpretations of the physical anthropological and palaeopathological data they produce (Agarwal and Glencross 2011; Gowland and Knüsel 2006), focusing on identity issues. Grasping for identity through archaeological human remains is a challenging endeavour as, for example, papers in the edited volume by Gowland and Knüsel illustrate (2006, see specifically Le Huray<italic>et al.</italic>2006; Montgomery and Evans 2006). Only some differential practices relating to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>Headshaping and Identity at Tell Nader</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kopanias</surname>
                           <given-names>Konstantinos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fox</surname>
                           <given-names>Sherry C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Human skeletal data are presented in this chapter within the context of the archaeological data from the site of Tell Nader in the Kurdistan Region of Iraq to help elucidate long-standing questions of cultural dynamics. In particular, a form of circumferential headshaping has been found in the skeleton of an adult female recovered from the Ubaid site. It is suggested from the integrated results of the study of the human remains in their cultural context that the intentionally produced modification of the cranium recovered from the archaeological site of Tell Nader is linked to group identity in the Ubaid.</p>
                     <p>Tell</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>Constructing Identities by Ageing the Body in the Prehistoric Aegean:</title>
                     <subtitle>the View through the Human Remains</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Triantaphyllou</surname>
                           <given-names>Sevi</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Until recently the perception of age had drawn minimal attention in archaeological research which has been dominated by studies concerning the importance of gender. Work, however, undertaken from the ’90s onwards (Gero and Conkey 1991; Moore and Scott 1997; Montserrat 1998; Hamilakis<italic>et al.</italic>2001; Díaz-Andreu<italic>et al.</italic>2005; Joyce 2005; Gowland and Knüsel 2006; Lucy 2005; Sofaer 2006; Insoll 2007; Borić and Robb 2008; Rebay-Salisbury<italic>et al.</italic>2010; Robb<italic>et al.</italic>2013) on the archaeology of the body has put forward new arguments as regards the construction of age but also, more lately, the link of gender with age</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>Secondary Burials and the Construction of Group Identities in Crete between the Second Half of the 4th and 2nd Millennia BC</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Girella</surname>
                           <given-names>Luca</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Todaro</surname>
                           <given-names>Simona</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Secondary mortuary practices entail the primary inhumation of the individual and the subsequent manipulation of its skeletal remains with actions of disarticulation, collection and relocation of selected bones from one location to another. It is, therefore, not easily identifiable in communal tombs,<italic>i.e.</italic>in those funerary structures that were used for successive multiple burials that required the partial or total relocation of the previous inhumations in order to allow the re-use of the burial ground. It is therefore hardly surprising that secondary mortuary practices have only recently been recognised in the communal tombs of the central and western Mediterranean from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>Bodies in a Pickle:</title>
                     <subtitle>Burial Jars, Individualism and Group Identities in Middle Minoan Crete</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Herrero</surname>
                           <given-names>Borja Legarra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gustave Glotz suggested back in the 1920s that the appearance of burial containers in Middle Bronze Age (MBA) I (Middle Minoan or MM I) Crete signalled the break-down of large social groups in Minoan society into smaller families (Glotz 1925, 138). He never really qualified this statement and probably never realised that it would become a pillar for our understanding of change in the period.</p>
                     <p>The idea proved instantly popular (Wiesner 1938, 181–2) and was taken up in the 1960s as part of the new milieu of socio-political approaches to the study of state formation (Pini 1968, 34; Rutkowski</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>Fire, Fragmentation and the Body in the Late Bronze Age Aegean</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Galanakis</surname>
                           <given-names>Yannis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although mortuary data is one of the primary sources for studying the Late Bronze Age (LBA) in the Aegean, it is often studied in isolation from the complex, multi-staged processes and performances that made up the funeral and everything that followed it. The depositional sequence of these actions is most frequently overlooked, not least because of practical difficulties in reconstructing these events and the ephemeral and often ambiguous nature of the evidence. Despite these limitations, however, there are many clues, both direct — in the form of residual remains — and indirect — in the form of purposefully destroyed things¹ — that hint at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>Spatial and Temporal Variability in Identity and Representation within the Bronze Age Cemeteries of Knossos, Crete</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hatzaki</surname>
                           <given-names>Eleni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Late Bronze Age (LBA) Crete underwent a series of sequential and abrupt political changes when shifting from a multi-palatial setup of the Neopalatial at the end of LM IB, to a monopalatial setup of the Final Palatial centred at Knossos and starting in LM II, followed by its collapse in Late Minoan (LM) IIIA2, and the subsequent rise of independent regional centres during the Postpalatial LM IIIA2–LM IIIB early. These dramatic changes have yet to be linked to burial customs as a means to access continuity and change in social structures at site as well as island level. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26</label>
                     <title>Collective Selves and Funerary Rituals.</title>
                     <subtitle>Early Mycenaean Dromoi as Spaces of Negotiation and Embodiment of Social Identities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Papadimitriou</surname>
                           <given-names>Nikolas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present paper aims at investigating — both theoretically and in the context of the Early Mycenaean period in mainland Greece (Table 26.1) — the relation of funerary rituals with processes of shaping, negotiating and transmitting collective identities. In particular, I wish to explore the role of specially designated ritual spaces (in this case, the<italic>dromoi</italic>of Mycenaean tombs) as frameworks for the creation of embodied experiences of shared remembering and identification. In this effort, I will draw extensively on anthropological literature examining rituals as public performances. Anthropologists recognise widely the ability of rituals to instil social values, worldviews and power relations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>27</label>
                     <title>Burning People, Breaking Things:</title>
                     <subtitle>Material Entanglements, the Bronze Age/Iron Age Transition and the Homeric Dividual</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Whitley</surname>
                           <given-names>James</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an interview with the<italic>Guardian</italic>newspaper in 2011, Mr Boris Johnson, the classically-educated Mayor of London, was asked whether he had found the job at all difficult. He replied with a quotation that obviously baffled the reporter:‘τέτλαθι δή, κραδίη; καὶ κύντερον ἄλλο ποτ’ ἔτλης,’ (Homer,<italic>Odyssey</italic>, 20.18).</p>
                     <p>The context is the<italic>Odyssey</italic>, where Odysseus is disguised as a beggar in his own palace in Ithaka, and recalls a worse time, when he was in Polyphemos’ cave. Johnson was indicating that he had indeed found the job of mayor trying — but that he had seen worse [κύντερον] — and he mustn’t</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1ggjkqm.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>28</label>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bodies in the Eastern Mediterranean</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kotsakis</surname>
                           <given-names>Kostas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an early paper on embodiment, Lynn Meskell (1996) ended her argument wondering whether<italic>the body</italic>will eventually remain a central analytic subject in archaeology or will dissolve into yet another intellectual fad. True, archaeology has come rather late in this field, which had already dominated the social sciences, anthropology, and feminist studies (Csordas 1994a){Csordas, 1994 #8978}{Csordas, 1994 #9578}{Csordas, 1994 #9578}. Almost two decades later, the proliferation of the relevant archaeological literature shows beyond doubt that the concept is now well-established and directs, one way or another, much of the ongoing archaeological analysis. Indeed, the conference presented in this volume</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
