<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1979.S5K44 1987</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Wayang</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Shadow pantomimes and plays</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Indonesia</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Java</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethnology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Indonesia</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Java</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Java (Indonesia)</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social life and customs</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Performing Arts</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Javanese Shadow Plays, Javanese Selves</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Keeler</surname>
               <given-names>Ward</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400886722</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400886724</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1987</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1m3221q"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>As with many performing arts in Asia, neither the highly stylized images of the Javanese shadow play nor its musical complexity detracts from its wide popularity. By a context-sensitive analysis of shadow-play performances, Ward Keeler shows that they fascinate so many people in Java because they dramatize consistent Javanese concerns about potency, status, and speech.</p>
         <p>Originally published in .</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback and hardcover editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="308"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Illustrations]</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>ON INTERPRETING A JAVANESE ART FORM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>N<italic>dhrog-dhog-dhog</italic>. The puppeteer rapped a heavy wooden mallet against the side of the puppet box to his left, starting a performance of the Javanese shadow play (<italic>wayang kulit</italic>). The great gong sounded and the Javanese orchestra arranged behind him began to play. A man in his early sixties, with the wide-set eyes and wide jaw characteristic of lowland Javanese, the puppeteer (<italic>dhalang</italic>) sat cross-legged in front of a long white screen with a red border, a bright light suspended above his head. Banana-tree trunks, held by supports about a foot off the ground, ran along the base of the screen.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>LANGUAGE, POWER, AND ASCETICISM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Formal Javanese encounter is remarkable. Among people who are not close kin or longtime associates, and to an extent even among them, face-to-face encounter requires that everyone take great care to behave in a manner appropriate to his or her relative social status, no matter what the business at hand. Vocabulary, sentiment, gesture, timing—all must be adjusted carefully in view of the responses they are liable to arouse among the people present, and in view of one’s own social status relative to theirs. Such issues matter in encounter everywhere, certainly, but in Java the degree to which they have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>FAMILY RELATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>51</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Assumptions about the self, power, and interaction inform two kinds of action—interpersonal encounter and ascetic practices—that stand as complementary opposites in Java These assumptions do not simply suffuse the atmosphere, however, they must be learned and acted upon. They are never systematically taught, nor are they often explicitly articulated. Instead, they are learned and applied in specific contexts, and in diverse ways My purpose in this chapter is to show how young Javanese become familiar with these assumptions in the workings of Javanese families In the following three chapters, I will consider how people draw upon such understandings</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>[Illustrations]</title>
                  </title-group>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>VILLAGE POLITICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>If in Javanese families potency should concentrate in the person of the father, in larger realms, such as the village and the state, potency should concentrate in males of similarly elevated status. Efforts to protect and magnify impressions of a leader’s potency, efforts to benefit by it, and efforts to escape any control it might imply mark political relations in these domains much as they do in the family. As a result, m all these political relations, the paradoxical concept of quiescent power influences everyone’s behavior.</p>
                     <p>That there is a politics implicit in the relations between a dhalang, his sponsors,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>POTENCY, POSSESSION, AND SPEECH</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A powerful figure in Java suggests the possibility of protection, wellbeing, and prosperity. He thereby invites voluntary submission. In return for the style and, to some degree, the services indicative of deference, an individual wins some assurance of the powerful person’s material and/or mystical support. However, ideological precepts and practical patterns of avoidance show distrust of the impulse to compromise one’s own sovereignty m dependence upon or submission to a powerful figure. At the same time, such figures may resist people’s attempts to put claims upon them. I have discussed the nature and workings of such ambivalence in relations between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>RITUAL CELEBRATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dissimulation of exertion at the center, whether of kingdoms, of villages, or even of families, is necessary to maintain impressions of a respected figure’s potency and prestige. It is in terms of this conception (of what might be called the dissembled center), that I wish to discuss the roles of the sponsors and the dhalang at a ritual celebration. The important and problematic fact about these events is that they are occasions in which “the center” is occupied by two such different kinds of central figures: the ritual’s sponsors and the dhalang. Their simultaneous presence is made possible by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>THE STATUS OF DHALANG AND RITUAL SPONSORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When sponsors invite a dhalang and his troupe to perform at a ritual celebration, the guests’ attention is further distracted away from the sponsors. The performance once again dissembles and enhances the sponsors’ aura of authority, as the sponsors seek to make the dhalang’s voice an extension of their own. In particular, they hope his voice will win the guests’ voluntary, yet total, submission. Relations between the sponsors of a wayang and the dhalang who performs it, however, are complicated. Is their authority shared, or are they instead locked in competition? The status of dhalang in Javanese society has long</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>THE DHALANG, THE TROUPE, AND THE TRADITION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The dhalang becomes the central figure at a ritual celebration from the time he starts performing until he stops eight or nine hours later. During this time, the sponsors recede discreetly into the background as an unseen though crucial force. Yet if the dhalang appears in some respects obvious, even flamboyant, in his performance, the active agent of an evasive authority, much about the dhalang himself repeats the play of power both constraining and restrained, pervasive yet dissembled. Actually, more diversely and dynamically than in relations between dhalang and sponsors, the links between the dhalang and his troupe, the dhalang</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>THE PLEASURES OF THE PERFORMANCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Javanese accounts of submission to a king exaggerate the notion of his beneficent berkah to the point of seeing m it a deeply satisfying influence. It is still threatening, however, in fact all the more so, and both the pleasure and the threat can be described as a kind of forgetfulness. Pak Cerma related that his father, Mbah Mardi, was offered the opportunity to become a dhalang at the court (abdi-dalem dhalang) at the Susuhunan in Solo.</p>
                     <p>The pay was poor, but it’s easy for a servant of the court [abdidalem] to make money on the side because of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>ON JAVANESE INTERPRETATION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>People’s relations with signs in Java, the degree to which they are master of or subject to them, at once indicate and determine their potency. This assumption about the relationship between self and Signs has important consequences for Javanese epistemology. Exegesis of wayang exemplifies these consequences, and I will take it as a starting point for a more general discussion of Javanese interpretation. My point is that, like speech, the signs that are an art form, a tract of ngèlmu, or a dream, all pose a challenge to a person’s autonomy, a challenge to which modes of interpretation are the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In contemporary anthropology, much is made of the ways in which meaning is constructed by a culture’s members. The interpretive act by which sense is asserted, such as in the interpretation of art or dreams or language, is a moment m which such constructions of meaning become particularly clear. It seems therefore a particularly vital point at which to observe a culture’s workings. The meeting of individuals and events that interpretation implies is a reapplication of principles, occasionally a revision, rarely, in Java at least, a radical reconsideration of them. But in interpreting phenomena of whatever sort, people act upon</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>GLOSSARY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1m3221q.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
