<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183gx2w</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Border Watch</book-title>
         <subtitle>Cultures of Immigration, Detention and Control</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hall</surname>
               <given-names>Alexandra</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="series-editor">Series Editors:</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Amit</surname>
               <given-names>Vered</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mitchell</surname>
               <given-names>Jon P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745327235</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781849647168</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Alexandra Hall</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183p2n9"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Questions over immigration and asylum face almost all Western countries. Should only economically useful immigrants be allowed? What should be done with unwanted or 'illegal' immigrants? In this bold and original intervention, Alexandra Hall shows that immigration detention centres offer a window onto society's broader attitudes towards immigrants. Despite periodic media scandals, remarkably little has been written about the everyday workings of the grassroots immigration system, or about the people charged with enacting immigration policy at local levels. Detention, particularly, is a hidden side of border politics, despite its growing international importance as a tool of control and security. This book fills the gap admirably, analysing the everyday encounters between officers and immigrants in detention to explore broad social trends and theoretical concerns. This highly topical book provides rare insights into the treatment of the 'other' and will be essential for policy makers and students studying anthropology and sociology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="216"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Amit</surname>
                           <given-names>Vered</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Going Inside</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Locksdon immigration removal centre accommodates men who have been detained under UK immigration law. The centre is a cluster of buildings set behind an imposing perimeter wall topped with razor wire. For Locksdon officers, staff and visitors, entry to the establishment is through a small door in the wall that leads into the gate area. For people who find themselves detained at Locksdon, entry is in the back of an escort contractor’s van, often at the end of a long and exhausting journey. Inside the centre walls, detainees getting out of the escort van, like staff coming through the gate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Visual Practice and the Secure Regime</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ed Davies was a long-serving officer at Locksdon. He had joined the Prison Service after serving in the army, like many of his colleagues, and he had been content to stay as a normal grade officer rather than ‘going for promotion’ and ‘joining management’, despite his experience. Ed was popular with his colleagues but he was known to be temperamental: sometimes he was talkative and humorous, sometimes he was remote and unapproachable. There were rumours of problems at home, depression perhaps. Ed appeared to be particularly affected by the working environment at Locksdon, which he summed up as having ‘everyone</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Being There:</title>
                     <subtitle>Social Life in the Centre</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>My first week [in a prison] I was shitting myself. Everyone told me it’d take six months before I felt on top of it. It takes ages to learn all the rules. I mean, some rules are hard and fast, they never change, like security rules, but learning how to … I mean there’s no hard and set line, like in some jobs, where the answer can be yes or no. In the Prison Service, life is like that: wiggly [motions hand in an uneven line]. When you first start, you’ll be on the landing and suddenly all these guys</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Compliance and Defiance:</title>
                     <subtitle>Contesting the Regime</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is just after lunch in the centre office. Sam, an SO, is duty officer for the afternoon and is responsible for the overall running of the regime. He is also centre officer and must deal with detainee queries in the afternoon period – requests to send faxes to solicitors, appointments to see Locksdon’s manager. As Sam settles behind the desk, a few detainees enter the office. One man comes in holding his detainee card. ‘I want to make a hole in my card,’ he announces (many detainees kept their cards on strings or chains round their neck). Sam eyes</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Drawing the Line:</title>
                     <subtitle>Discretion and Power</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Locksdon alarm bell could sound at any moment of the day or night. Its loud ringing indicated a crisis in the regime: a detainee or staff member in danger, a medical emergency, or a fire. Alarm buzzers were positioned around the establishment so that officers or detainees could call for help from every zone. For officers, the alarm bell signalled an emergency where life itself could be at stake. When it rang, the establishment appeared to freeze for a second before bursting into action. Available officers would drop what they were doing and run to the illuminated plan near</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Ethics and Encounters</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One crisp morning in autumn 2002, I am in a classroom in the Locksdon education department. An Algerian student has written a story about a prisoner in a war camp in the English class. He describes his protagonist feeling like a shipwrecked vessel dashed upon rocks, alone. I ask him how long he has been at Locksdon, and he replies bitterly that he has been detained for many months ‘for nothing …’ At that moment, Susan, Locksdon’s diversity officer, enters with an announcement: she is organising a ‘Festival of Faiths’ at Locksdon. She tells the detainees that it will be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 8 April 2009, news broke that the UK police and security agencies had foiled a major planned terrorist bomb plot and had arrested twelve men in Manchester under the UK Terrorism Act 2000. The men, all but one of them Pakistani, had been under surveillance since their arrival in Britain on student visas. One of the arrested men was released shortly after, but the remaining eleven men were held for two weeks under the Terrorism Act as the police investigated the plot and the men’s alleged terrorist activities. By 22 April, however, Operation Pathway was causing controversy when it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p2n9.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
