<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Education</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Whose History?</book-title>
         <subtitle>Engaging History Students through Historical Fiction</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Rodwell</surname>
               <given-names>Grant</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781922064516</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781922064509</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Adelaide Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>South Australia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Grant Rodwell</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.20851/j.ctt1t304sf"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book aims to illustrate how historical novels and their related genres may be used as an engaging teacher/learning strategy for student teachers in pre-service teacher education courses. It does not argue all teaching of History curriculum in pre-service units should be based on the use of historical novels as a stimulus, nor does it argue for a particular percentage of the use of historical novels in such courses. It simply seeks to argue the case for this particular approach, leaving the extent of the use of historical novels used in History curriculum units to the professional expertise of the lecturers responsible for the units.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="280"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations and Acronyms</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I once was taking a unit of work on Napoleon in Moscow with my university History Curriculum and Methodology students. What sources could we use? A group of students wanted Tolstoy’s<italic>War and Peace</italic>(1869/2010), an iconic historical novel. What about Adam Zamoyski’s 1812:<italic>Napoleon’s Fatal March on Moscow</italic>(2005), one of the best nonfiction sources on the topic? The class group then debated the relative merits of historical novels versus nonfiction as teaching/learning sources in schools and colleges — a huge and multi-layered topic.</p>
                     <p>Motivation, however, to write this book came from other sources. First, there was the continued demonstrated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Compulsory History:</title>
                     <subtitle>the Issues Confronting Teachers</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Australian Curriculum Assessment and Reporting Authority (ACARA), through a rolling program, has been mandating the teaching of History in Australian schools. However, this comes at a time when students’ interest in studying History in schools is at a low ebb. While I will pursue these topics later in this chapter, here I address the issues associated with having Australian History students engage with historical novels.</p>
                     <p>The internationally acclaimed Australian children’s novelist, Jackie French, titled her presentation to the 2010 History Teachers’ Association of Australia (HTAA) Conference in Sydney ‘Turning History into Stories and Stories into History — Subtitle: What We</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Student Engagement through Historical Narratives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the teaching of History in Australia undergoes substantial changes through the implementation of the national History curriculum, undergraduate student teachers and teachers in classrooms are being required to re-think their teaching/learning strategies for the teaching of History. With the developments in SOSE/HSIE since the 1970s, curricula researchers have found that during the last few decades the teaching of History has drifted almost into oblivion in many Australian schools. More recently, with the implementation of the National History curriculum undergraduate teachers and teachers in classrooms have been asked to re-engage with the subject (Rodwell, 2010). In this chapter, I argue</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Pedagogical Dimensions of Historical Novels and Historical Literacy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As many teachers and educators seriously question the role of textbooks in the History lesson, teachers and educators are looking increasingly to alternative and more engaging teaching/learning strategies (Villano, 2005). Recognising the significant pedagogical advantages of using historical fiction in their classrooms, some teachers have long used historical fiction as a central teaching/learning strategy in the History classroom. Now, however, student teachers and teachers are advantaged — and consequently, should be reassured — by an emerging amount of research showing how the teaching of historical literacy through historical novels can be achieved. There is, I argue, ample evidence of the many pedagogical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Defining the Historical Novel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The genre of historical fiction is continually expanding, adapting to new demands from readers and the creativity of authors. First, let us examine this phenomenon from its international perspectives.</p>
                     <p>What is historical fiction? The United States-based Historical Novel Society acknowledges the complexity and proposes the following definition:</p>
                     <p>There will never be a satisfactory answer to these questions, but these are the arbitrary decisions we’ve made.</p>
                     <p>To be deemed historical (in our sense), a novel must have been written at least fifty years after the events described, or have been written by someone who was not alive at the time of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Increase of History as a Subject for Novels:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory and the Context of Interpretation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>History teachers have available to them a rising tide of popularity in the reading of historical novels. There is no sign of this popularity waning. As this chapter will demonstrate, the historical novel continues to develop as a literary genre as increasing numbers of authors are attracted to it.</p>
                     <p>In 2008 Richard Nile wrote an impressionistic article in<italic>The Australian</italic>: ‘today, historical novels massively outsell even the finest [nonfiction] history, and readers continue to learn from their imaginative journeys into Australia’s past’ (Nile, 2008). Thus, for Nile, historical fiction serves to educate readers about our past in a manner that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>‘The plot against the plot’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Page-turners for Students</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When teachers or academics recommend a particular historical novel as a teaching/learning strategy for an undergraduate unit or classroom activity, they enter into a very problematic and contested domain. But most teachers or academics would agree that the first consideration should be meeting their students at their point of need. It is likely that many students will have been exposed to, or will have read, historical novels generally and/or Australian historical novels. Some may be aware of the changes that have come over the historical novel, and the Australian historical novel specifically, since the onset of the postmodernist and postcolonial</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Counterfactual Histories and the Nature of History</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consider this historical account: the setting is the Cocos Islands in the Indian Ocean; the date is 7 November 1914; the author is Stuart Macintyre, the Ernest Scott Professor of History at the University of Melbourne, and, since 2002 a Laureate Professor of the University of Melbourne. He writes:</p>
                     <p>The German raiders stood off till nightfall. Under the cover of darkness the Scharnhorst came alongside the Melbourne on the port station and opened fire. The sudden bombardment at close range crippled the Australian ship. Meanwhile the two German light cruisers engaged the Sydney on the starboard station and soon put</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Alternate Histories in the Classroom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout Australian States and territories, History students often study the 1954 Petrov affair in Australian history, as they do the 1975 Whitlam dismissal. How might teachers add some historiographical zest to these studies? How can alternate history, or allohistorical narratives, assist?</p>
                     <p>The recent publication of Nicholas Hasluck’s<italic>Dismissal</italic>(2011) is timely in these regards. Alternate histories are usually set amidst the great events of world history — Napoleon, Hitler and Nazism, and so on. Indeed, as Croome (2011) has stated, in what might amount to a throwaway line, alternate history is ‘a genre often undermined in Australia by the sense that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>‘Caught in time’s cruel machinery’:</title>
                     <subtitle>Time-slip Novels in the History Lesson</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jake and his mate, Al, have just stepped from a storeroom in Al’s diner in the year 2011 back to the 1950s. Al has set Jake the great challenge of saving JFK from the sniper’s rifle, and thus altering the course of history. Stephen King’s time-slip novel 22.11.63 makes fascinating reading, and from my experience, many secondary History students find it extremely appealing.</p>
                     <p>As Chapter 4 showed, the UK-based Historical Novel Society (n.d.) defined historical novels to include time-slip novels. Apart from being arguably a legitimate member of the genre, there are excellent commercial reasons for this. Walk through many</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Whose History?</title>
                     <subtitle>Historical Fiction and the Discipline of History in the Classroom: Varying Views of the Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alert students will often tell teachers and university lecturers that there is sometimes a significant discrepancy between the same historical characters, settings or incidents in historical fiction and nonfiction. An illustration of this point arises with hugely successful author Bryce Courtenay’s work of historical fiction,<italic>The Potato Factory</italic>(1995), and a subsequent work of nonfiction, which sought to put the record straight on Isaac (Ikey) Solomon, one of the principal characters in Courtenay’s novel. Judith Sackville-O’Donnell, a Melbourne author, challenged Courtenay’s depiction of Ikey Solomon, who was also believed to be the model for Charles Dickens’s fictional villain Fagin.</p>
                     <p>Sackville-O’Donnell’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Understanding the Past through Historical Fiction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Many students undertaking teacher-preparation courses in Australian universities, and/or teachers are likely to be avid readers of Australian historical novels. This chapter is written with the object of deepening their appreciation of the rich tapestry of the Australian historical novel. It does so in order that they might increase their understanding of the way that historical novels can fully engage students in an appreciation and understanding of Australian history, particularly the different ways in which generations of Australian historians as compared to writers of historical fiction have perceived the past.</p>
                     <p>Although textbooks have not always been used in significant numbers</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Unpacking Historical Novels for their Historicity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Historical Facts and Historical Agency</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>171</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historical novels can tell us much about not only our past, but also what we collectively hold to be important about our past. Usually, they provide an insight into the past in many and varied ways, including ways that are, I suggest, simply impossible to present to students of history through textbooks. This chapter will show how the development of an appreciation of historical facts and historical agency can be achieved most fruitfully through the use of historical novels in the classroom.</p>
                     <p>Historical figures have become historical characters in this type of novel. But is their characterisation partly imaginary? Often</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Key themes in Australian History and their Reflection in Historical Novels</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Australian historical fiction tends to fall into some dominant categories, reflecting perennial themes that are forever being reinterpreted: first settlement, European inland exploration, pastoralism, conflict with Indigenous Australians, patriotism and war are common themes of Australian historical fiction. In writing these novels and responding to these themes, among other things, novelists inform readers much about how Australians think of themselves and of how they perceive the Australian nation. Novels often challenge conventional values in these respects. Certainly, they offer engaging insights for students into Australian history.</p>
                     <p>For the most part, Australia’s history is founded on the convict past. Only South</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Taken as a part or as a whole, once teachers have used historical novels and their sub-genres as a teaching/learning strategy in their History lessons, they come to appreciate the huge contribution they can make to their students’ appreciation of history. Many students immediately engage with their historical novels, and this is, I suggest, not surprising.</p>
                     <p>Historical novels currently enjoy huge popularity amongst the readership of the Australian public, as does children’s historical fiction through the writings of such fine authors as Jackie French. While some commentators may lament this rising tide of popularity for historical fiction, with the onset</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1t304sf.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>266</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
