<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P90.C66 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mass media</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1789–1900</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Constructing Charisma</book-title>
         <subtitle>Celebrity, Fame, and Power in Nineteenth-Century Europe</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BERENSON</surname>
               <given-names>EDWARD</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>GILOI</surname>
               <given-names>EVA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780857458155</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781845459772</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1845459776</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Berghahn Books</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; Oxford</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition, 1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Edward Berenson</copyright-holder>
         <copyright-holder>Eva Giloi</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qckwq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Railroads, telegraphs, lithographs, photographs, and mass periodicals-the major technological advances of the 19th century seemed to diminish the space separating people from one another, creating new and apparently closer, albeit highly mediated, social relationships. Nowhere was this phenomenon more evident than in the relationship between celebrity and fan, leader and follower, the famous and the unknown. By mid-century, heroes and celebrities constituted a new and powerful social force, as innovations in print and visual media made it possible for ordinary people to identify with the famous; to feel they knew the hero, leader, or "star"; to imagine that public figures belonged to their private lives. This volume examines the origins and nature of modern mass media and the culture of celebrity and fame they helped to create. Crossing disciplines and national boundaries, the book focuses on arts celebrities (Sarah Bernhardt, Byron and Liszt); charismatic political figures (Napoleon and Wilhelm II); famous explorers (Stanley and Brazza); and celebrated fictional characters (Cyrano de Bergerac).</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="244"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Illustrations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERENSON</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GILOI</surname>
                           <given-names>EVA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fame, charisma, celebrity—we use these three words commonly nowadays and often interchangeably. We grant celebrity status to prominent actors and actresses, sports figures, television personalities, and political leaders, some of whom we call famous and charismatic as well. As a former president of the United States, Bill Clinton is famous. He also enjoys celebrity status thanks to myriad magazine covers sporting his easily recognized face. And those with fond memories of his presidency tend to consider him charismatic as well. Princess Diana shared these attributes, only much more so, her apparent charisma enhanced by the whiff of royalty, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Charisma and the Making of Imperial Heroes in Britain and France, 1880–1914</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERENSON</surname>
                           <given-names>EDWARD</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1874, an unknown French naval ensign, Pierre Savorgnan de Brazza, went to Africa to seek a water route from the Atlantic Ocean to the smooth lakelike reaches of the Upper Congo River. He hoped to bypass the 32 cataracts that forbid all navigation on the lower Congo up to what became known as Stanley Pool. In exploring the banks of the Congo, Brazza claimed a huge swathe of Equatorial Africa for France. It mattered little that this territory lacked economic or strategic value. Brazza’s extraordinary bravery, his apparent willingness to suffer to achieve a nearly impossible goal, made him</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>“So Writes the Hand that Swings the Sword”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Autograph Hunting and Royal Charisma in the German Empire, 1861–1888</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GILOI</surname>
                           <given-names>EVA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1876, high school student Nicolaas von Cammenga approached Emperor Wilhelm I with a personal request:</p>
                     <p>Most Serene, High and Mighty Emperor!</p>
                     <p>May Your Majesty graciously allow me to direct these lines to Your Majesty, lines meant only to prove my deepest reverence and greatest veneration for Your Majesty. I have a request for Your Majesty, which, if Your Majesty graciously deigns to take notice of it, Your Majesty can easily fulfill. It consists, namely, in having Your Majesty send me a picture of Your Majesty, my dearly beloved Emperor and King. Until now, I have had a photograph of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>The Workings of Royal Celebrity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wilhelm II as Media Emperor</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KOHLRAUSCH</surname>
                           <given-names>MARTIN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Only rarely has Wilhelm II, the last Prussian King and German Emperor, been portrayed as a charismatic ruler.¹ This may not be surprising, as nineteenth-century monarchs are usually regarded, according to Max Weber’s ideal-types, as examples of traditional authority. Nevertheless, the reluctance to think about charisma and the Kaiser is regrettable, not least because Weber developed his concepts of authority against the backdrop of Wilhelm II’s rule.²</p>
                     <p>At the time Weber pondered his ideas on charismatic rule, a dramatic transformation of the monarchy was underway, owing to the emergence of mass media in Germany. In what Walther Rathenau aptly branded</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>From the Top:</title>
                     <subtitle>Liszt’s Aristocratic Airs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GOOLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>DANA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Franz Liszt died in 1886, he was so famous that Eduard Hanslick, an influential Viennese music critic, claimed there was “no better known face in Europe.”² Hanslick was a master of the double-edged compliment, and he chose his words carefully. He did not say that Liszt was the best-known<italic>composer</italic>or even the best-known<italic>pianist</italic>—these, in Hanslick’s view, had already faded from public memory. It was literally the<italic>face</italic>, reproduced ad infinitum in journals, lithograph portraits, and other ephemera, that had created and sustained Liszt’s pan-European celebrity. Hanslick’s comment voices a suspicion that has dogged celebrated public figures</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>Celebrity Gifting:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mallarmé and the Poetics of Fame</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>APTER</surname>
                           <given-names>EMILY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are myriad approaches to investigating how celebrity is constituted and conferred. The symbolist writer Stéphane Mallarmé (1842–1898) offers a good case for testing approaches to the historiography of fame in nineteenth-century France. Mallarmé can be seen as the prototype of a contemporary “I am not there” model of celebrity. A nobody in full view (photographed by Nadar, the subject of portraiture by Edouard Manet, Edvard Munch, and Paul Gauguin), he demonstrated an idiosyncratic form of media savvy that involves making a name for oneself through self-annexation to an international cast of creative, talented, beautiful people—writers, thinkers, artists,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Rethinking Female Celebrity:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Eccentric Star of Nineteenth-Century France</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBERTS</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY LOUISE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Does female celebrity in the nineteenth century warrant our particular attention? Does it differ significantly from male celebrity or can it be deemed impervious to gender norms? In<italic>The Frenzy of Renown</italic>, Leo Braudy left such questions aside, focusing his history of fame mostly on men. Though he never denies that societies could celebrate women, he does not examine what happens when they do. It is this question that interests the historian Lenard Berlanstein, who argues that celebrated women, and actresses in particular, evoked more attention than did their male counterparts. Because celebrity in the nineteenth century was defined as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Byron, Death, and the Afterlife</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MINTA</surname>
                           <given-names>STEPHEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“<italic>Quand on nous a annoncé la mort de Byron, il nous a semblé qu’on nous enlevait une part de notre avenir</italic>.”¹ Victor Hugo’s anguished response to the death of Byron was echoed across Europe. Jane Welsh, the future wife of Thomas Carlyle, wrote of her own reaction: “My God, if they had said that the sun or the moon had gone out of the heavens, it could not have struck me with the idea of a more awful and dreary blank in the creation than the words ‘Byron is dead!’” While Carlyle himself felt “as if I had lost a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>The Historical Actor</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FRITZSCHE</surname>
                           <given-names>PETER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After the Battle of Waterloo on 18 June 1815, visitors from across Europe thronged to the field of battle outside the city of Brussels. In the very first weeks, the site was still littered with the debris of decamped soldiers and the remains of the dead. In<italic>A Visit to Flanders in July 1815</italic>, the Englishman James Simpson reported that all around him “lay the melancholy remains of the clothes, accoutrements, books, and letters of the dead.” Indeed, written materials “were spread over the field like the rubbish of a stationer’s shop.” Charlotte Eaton was also struck by “the quantities</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Celebrity, Patriotism, and Sarah Bernhardt</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SILVER</surname>
                           <given-names>KENNETH E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>After Queen Victoria, Sarah Bernhardt (1844–1923) was probably the most celebrated woman of the nineteenth century and certainly the most famous Frenchwoman. Apart from the drawing power of her obvious talent (the opinions of her theatrical detractors notwithstanding), Bernhardt’s colossal celebrity was dependent upon and inextricably bound up with French prestige: its ancient and recent history, its real and imagined travails. The extent to which Bernhardt and France were the Gemini twins of the<italic>fin-de-siècle</italic>theatrical firmament became clear to me when Carol Ockman and I organized the exhibition, “Sarah Bernhardt: The Art of High Drama,” for New York’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Heroes, Celebrity, and the Theater in Fin-de-Siècle France:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cyrano de Bergerac</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DATTA</surname>
                           <given-names>VENITA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The author of these hyperbolic words is Rosemonde Rostand, describing the reactions to the dress rehearsal of her husband’s play<italic>Cyrano de Bergerac</italic>.¹ First presented on the Parisian stage on 27 December 1897, just two weeks prior to the publication of Émile Zola’s<italic>J’Accuse</italic>, Edmond Rostand’s<italic>Cyrano de Bergerac</italic>has become one of the most beloved and most often staged plays in the history of the French theater.² Not only did the play mark the birth of Cyrano as a national figure, it also announced the arrival of Rostand as a worldwide celebrity. Almost immediately, Rostand received the Legion of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Secular Anointings: Fame, Celebrity, and Charisma in the First Century of Mass Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BRAUDY</surname>
                           <given-names>LEO</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was somewhere in the middle of writing<italic>The Frenzy of Renown</italic>— which turned out to be a twelve-year project—my agent started getting anxious. “You’d better hurry up and finish,” she said. “Soon, no one’s going to be interested in fame any more.” Yet today, more than twenty years later, US culture as well as global culture generally seems more flooded than ever before with the dissemination and merchandising of names and faces that are the hallmarks of modern fame.</p>
                     <p>To give her comment some credit, though, I must admit that fame is a somewhat odd subject to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SELECTED BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qckwq.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
