<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Catholicism and Crisis in Modern France</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BOSWORTH</surname>
               <given-names>WILLIAM</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691625546</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691625549</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400876853</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400876850</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1962</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183pp1p"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The book description for "Catholicism and Crisis in Modern France" is currently unavailable.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="422"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Catholicism and French Society:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Introductory Note</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The Nation,” says Jacques Maritain, “is one of the most important, perhaps the most complex and complete community engendered by civilized life.”² For certain purposes a modern nation, this lofty example of human development, can usefully be considered as one single entity. But often national activities can best be understood if some of the constituent elements of the nation are examined first. This is particularly true in the case of France, where the fabric of historical evolution is rich with the multicolored threads of divergent groups and ideologies.</p>
                     <p>As a “complex and complete community,” the nation resembles lower level communities—</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Historical Sketch:</title>
                     <subtitle>Catholic Institutions and the Laic Republic</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In France, at least among a certain educated elite, the legacy of the past largely determines present actions. For example, today’s quarrels between<italic>laïques</italic>and<italic>cléricaux</italic>over the school question cannot be fully understood without referring to the events of the early 1900’s.¹ Thus, without pretending to give a complete panorama of Catholicism in French history, this historical sketch will provide some of the background necessary for unlocking the mysteries of present-day Catholic behavior.</p>
                     <p>During two periods of recent French history the relations between Church and state were profoundly changed. Just after the turn of the century the Republic officially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>The Ecclesiastical Nucleus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>44</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In certain respects French Catholic institutions resemble our solar system. Lay Catholic groups gravitate around a central element or “sun,” some being quite close to it while others are in orbits farther removed. The “sun” in this case comprises the totality of ecclesiastical institutions—in Rome as well as in France itself.</p>
                     <p>Because this cosmological image must be considered in a political sense, it is greatly complicated and thereby loses much of its orderliness. In the first place, the ecclesiastical nucleus of French Catholicism has no single, unified political behavior pattern. Secondly, political activity seems to increase as one moves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Catholic Action:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Auxiliary to the Hierarchy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Catholic Action comprises all laymen’s groups which are formally mandated by the Hierarchy to aid it in its apostolic function. Not all Catholic groups are in Catholic Action, since not all of them receive the formal mandate. Catholic Action groups are all organized on national and diocese levels, following the Hierarchy which controls them, while other Catholic groups may have quite different organizational bases. These differences plus divergent political perspectives justify treating Catholic Action in a chapter by itself.</p>
                     <p>Catholic Action is mandated to carry on one basic purpose only: to further the apostolic work of the Church. In France,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Catholic Social Action Organizations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>156</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the French Church, always full of subtle shadings, a tacit distinction has arisen between Catholic Action groups, mandated by the Church, and other organizations reflecting Catholic principles. Groups which are mandated exist primarily because of their religious functions. They are integral parts of the Church, instruments of a particular form of evangelization. Their civic and political activities can be limited by the Hierarchy itself. They are always willing to follow, in temporal as in spiritual affairs, the advice of their ecclesiastical counsellors. On the other hand, the organizations outside of Catholic Action, though they might have “Church approval,” exist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Catholic Press</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The preceding chapters have distinguished among Catholic laymen’s groups according to their distance from the ecclesiastical nucleus. The complexity of the Catholic press makes it necessary to include the major Catholic publications in one chapter, regardless of the distance a given publication may be from the core of the Church.¹</p>
                     <p>The Catholic press comprises those publications which are approved by the Hierarchy. The ACA may approve a paper’s editorial board. Or there may be recommendations by all bishops to subscribe (<italic>La Croix</italic>benefits from such recommendations), or sponsorship by individual prelates (this is the case with<italic>Verbe</italic>, for example). “Approval”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Organizations of Catholic Inspiration</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Groups of Catholic inspiration, the last major type of organization contributing to the political impact of French Catholicism, form the “outer ring” of the French Catholic structure. They are farther from the ecclesiastical nucleus than Catholic Action groups, social action groups, and most of the Catholic press. Among the many groups of Catholic inspiration, attention will be focused on the two giants, the<italic>Mouvement Républican Populaire</italic>and the<italic>Confédération Française des Travailleurs Chrétiens</italic>. Other structures will be considered insofar as they contribute to the basic purpose of this study.</p>
                     <p>Two factors distinguish Catholic inspiration organizations from groups closer to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>The School Question and Specialized Catholic Institutions</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>279</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relationship between public and private schools in France during the past century has been a persistent political dilemma of great complexity. Whether fighting for the legal existence of Church schools or pressing for state aid, the Church has been involved in this question as in no other political matter. The place which the school question occupies for the Church Hierarchy, the Catholic press, and Catholic Action groups has already been noted: it is the one political question on which all Catholic groups can take sides.</p>
                     <p>There are also specialized Catholic groups dealing exclusively with the school question. These groups</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Concluding Remarks</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>309</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Outside of a narrow range of dogma, Catholics disagree among themselves on practically everything relating to social and temporal life. Yet there are certain social principles which have very widespread acceptance among the vast majority of Catholics in France. Usually most members of the Hierarchy endorse these principles, though they are not considered as Church dogma. In fact, they have become so generally identified with Catholicism that Catholics with different views must usually explain their reasons for going against the crowd.</p>
                     <p>The purpose of this section is to set forth the main social doctrines which are widely considered as being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix</title>
                     <subtitle>Maps Illustrating the Regional Strength of Catholic Groups</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliographical Essay</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183pp1p.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>397</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
