<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn32mh</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Material Inscriptions</book-title>
         <subtitle>Rhetorical Reading in Practice and Theory</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Warminski</surname>
               <given-names>Andrzej</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780748681228</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0748681221</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780748681235</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">074868123X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Andrzej Warminski</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt5hh2hp"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This monograph provides readings of literary and philosophical texts that work through the rhetoric of tropes to the material inscription at the origin of these texts. The book focuses on the practice and pedagogical value of rhetorical reading. Its readings follow an itinerary from poetic texts (such as those by Wordsworth and Keats) through theoretical or philosophical texts (by Descartes and Nietzsche) to narrative fiction (by Henry James). The book also contains two essays on Paul de Man and literary theory and an interview on the topic of "Deconstruction at Yale." All three of these latter texts are explicitly about the inescapable function and importance of the rhetoric of tropes for any critical reading or literary study worthy of the name. As Andrzej Warminski demonstrates, ‘rhetorical reading’ is a species of ‘deconstructive reading’—in the full ‘de Manian’ sense—but one that, rather than harkening back to a past over and done with, would open the texts to a different future. Key Features: New readings of texts by Wordsworth, Keats, Descartes, Nietzsche, and Henry James Essays and an interview on Paul de Man and ‘Deconstruction at Yale’ Reflects on and exemplifies the pedagogical value of ‘de Manian’ rhetorical reading Attempts to open a future for 'deconstructive' or 'de Manian' reading</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="248"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Series Editor’s Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McQuillan</surname>
                           <given-names>Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Author’s Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 1</label>
                     <title>Facing Language:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wordsworthʹs First Poetic Spirits (ʺBlest Babe,ʺ ʺDrowned Man,ʺ ʺBlind Beggarʺ)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Among the institutionalized ways of<italic>not</italic>facing Wordsworth perhaps none continues to stand upright quite as solidly and fixedly – “as if sustained by its own spirit” (II, 280–1)¹ – as the interpretation of the relationship between man and Nature, Imagination and Nature, in terms of a dialectic of immediacy and mediation, consciousness and self-consciousness. A most suggestive global statement of this interpretation is offered by Geoffrey Hartman in “Romanticism and ‘Anti-Self-Consciousness’” when he reminds us “that Romantic art has a function analogous to that of religion. The traditional scheme of Eden, fall, and redemption merges with the new</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 2</label>
                     <title>Aesthetic Ideology and Material Inscription:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Hegelʹs Aesthetics and Keatsʹs Urn</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hegel’s double, ambiguous and ambivalent if not downright duplicitous, attitude toward art is legible in his<italic>Aesthetics</italic>from one end to the other, from the beginning and to the ends. All we need to know about both the philosophy and the history of art (according to Hegel) is there to be read already in the Introduction. As Hegel goes through the three main types or forms of art according to the different relations between sensuous form and spiritual content proper to each –<italic>from</italic>the (“symbolic”) pre-art of the East and the Egyptians in which there is an inadequation between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 3</label>
                     <title>Spectre Shapes:</title>
                     <subtitle>ʺThe Body of Descartes?ʺ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter’s subtitle – “The Body of Descartes?” – quite rightly dresses the body of Descartes with a question mark.¹ The question mark is most fitting, for, indeed, what we might want to identify under its garments as the body of Descartes could turn out to be a ghost or an automaton – like those hats and cloaks at the end of the Second Meditation that we judge (by the “pure inspection of the mind”) to clothe<italic>men</italic>but which may turn out to cover only “spectres or feigned men” (<italic>des spectres ou des hommes feints</italic>).² But these shapes become</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 4</label>
                     <title>Reading for Example:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Metaphor in Nietzscheʹs Birth of Tragedy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The opening paragraph of section 9 of<italic>The Birth of Tragedy</italic>in a modified version of Walter Kaufmann’s translation reads: “Everything that comes to the surface in the Apollinian part of Greek tragedy, in the dialogue, looks simple, transparent, and beautiful. In this sense, the dialogue is an image of the Hellene whose nature is revealed in the dance because in the dance the greatest strength is only potential but betrays itself in the suppleness and wealth of movement. Thus the language of Sophocles’ heroes surprises us by its Apollinian precision and lucidity, so that we immediately have the feeling</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 5</label>
                     <title>Towards a Fabulous Reading:</title>
                     <subtitle>Nietzscheʹs ʺOn Truth and Lie in the Extramoral Senseʺ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>101</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For all the attention it has received and all the times its most famous (or infamous) lines have been quoted, Nietzsche’s brief “On Truth and Lie in the Extramoral Sense” remains something of an enigma – a “riddling X,” as the text itself refers to the inaccessible and undefinable thing-in-itself (<italic>das rätselhafte X des Dings an sich</italic>). In large measure, the enigmatic status of the text is due to the uncanny way it manages to predict and inscribe within its own borders, in its own terms, any attempt that would gain access to it by solving its riddle and identifying</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 6</label>
                     <title>Reading Over Endless Histories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Henry Jamesʹs ʺThe Altar of the Deadʺ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A reading of a Henry James story in an issue on French symbolism may seem an odd juxtaposition.¹ Certain thematic links are, of course, possible: although James wrote very little on authors whom one could count among the French symbolists, he did write a great deal on what has been called “symbolism” in the American literary tradition (a tradition in which his own work takes a place).² But the possibility of such loose linking already points up a certain symptomatic instability in the very term symbolism itself. That is, the term symbolism would want to serve as a convenient label</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 7</label>
                     <title>Ending Up/Taking Back (with Two Postscripts on Paul de Manʹs Historical Materialism)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Paul de Man’s work – his writing, his teaching – had and continues to have a way of getting under people’s skin.² (Indeed, as de Man himself said at one lecture occasion, this is the moment when things become interesting: “when one gets under people’s skin, when some resistance develops …”) Among the many statements and pronouncements that have succeeded in provoking this kind of response, perhaps one of the most notorious, one that seems to have rankled more intensely and for longer, is the well-known sentence toward the end of “Semiology and Rhetoric”: “This will in fact be the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter 8</label>
                     <title>The Future Past of Literary Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to fulfill the didactic assignment and talk about the future of literary theory,¹ one might as well begin with the question of the<italic>present</italic>of literary theory: what is, what would or could be, “literary theory” today? If one can judge by the signs of the times, then the most direct answer to the question would be: “Not much.” Not much these days could qualify as “literary theory,” not much today<italic>is</italic>literary theory – at least in comparison to the fabled heyday of literary theory during the (late) 1960s and 1970s. In comparison to the various projects</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Appendix:</title>
                     <subtitle>Interview: “Deconstruction at Yale”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barnett</surname>
                           <given-names>Stuart</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Warminski</surname>
                           <given-names>Andrzej</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt5hh2hp.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
