<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.cttn31v7</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Narrative and Becoming</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Askin</surname>
               <given-names>Ridvan</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474414562</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474414579</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Ridvan Askin</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1g09ttm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Ridvan Askin brings together aesthetics, contemporary North American fiction, Gilles Deleuze, narrative theory and the recent speculative turn to answer the question, 'what is narrative?'</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Differential Narratology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book proposes a differential theory of narrative. In doing so, it goes against the most basic fundamentals of narratology. These fundamentals seem so self-evident that they are generally assumed as granted and only rarely voiced explicitly. They are exemplarily set out in this covert manner in the following programmatic statement from Roland Barthes’s ‘Introduction to the Structural Analysis of Narratives’:</p>
                     <p>It may be that men ceaselessly re-inject into narrative what they have known, what they have experienced; but if they do, it is at least in a form which has vanquished repetition and instituted the model of a process</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Intensive Narration:</title>
                     <subtitle>Ana Castillo’s The Mixquiahuala Letters</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ana Castillo’s œuvre is generally taken to be descriptive of Chicana culture and thus predominantly received in terms of ethnicity, feminism, and politics. As a result and as befits Chicana literary studies’ received tradition, Castillo scholarship is strongly thematic, with the themes of ethnic, sexual, and cultural identity taking centre-stage. Accordingly, the conceptual tools used for these thematic explorations are predominantly derived from postcolonial, feminist, and cultural studies with those of hybridity – or<italic>mestizaje</italic>as its specific Chicano/a variant – and difference ranging foremost among them. In this vein, and in accordance with the general bent of Chicana literary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Narrating Sensation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Michael Ondaatje’s The Collected Works of Billy the Kid</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first page of Michael Ondaatje’s<italic>The Collected Works of Billy the Kid</italic>features famous frontier photographer L. A. Huffman’s caption to a picture of Billy he allegedly took. Where the picture should be, however, there is nothing but an empty frame. The text thus starts with a forceful problematisation of representation as, contrary to Huffman’s statement, Billy is<italic>not</italic>depicted. In addition, the Huffman caption is fictional.<italic>The Collected Works of Billy the Kid</italic>thus immediately signals that the status of the image, that representation will be an issue both formally and in terms of content. This problematic status</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Sensational Realism:</title>
                     <subtitle>Colson Whitehead’s The Intuitionist</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In its emphasis on verisimilitude and its depiction of social relations, Colson Whitehead’s<italic>The Intuitionist</italic>is a realist novel and thus deviates substantially from the more experimental set-ups of Castillo’s and Ondaatje’s narratives discussed in Chapters 1 and 2. While<italic>The Mixquiahuala Letters</italic>’ and<italic>The Collected Works of Billy the Kid</italic>’s respective forms emphasise and enact incompleteness, processuality, and divergence (a series of disconnected narrative and poetic vignettes in Ondaatje’s case; a set of letters that present the reader with three divergent story variants in Castillo’s), nothing like that holds for Whitehead’s novel.<italic>The Intuitionist</italic>can be described as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Real Folds:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mark Z. Danielewski’s House of Leaves</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To date,<italic>House of Leaves</italic>has overwhelmingly been read in light of its mediality, the question of technology, and digital culture at large. Apart from the oft-quoted pioneering articles by Brian W. Chanen, Mark B. N. Hansen, N. Katherine Hayles, and Jessica Pressman (Chanen 2007; Hansen 2004; Hayles 2002a; Pressman 2006), three out of five essays dealing with<italic>House of Leaves</italic>in the first book project exclusively devoted to the works of Danielewski read the novel through this lens (McCormick 2011; Evans 2011; Thomas 2011). Add to that another two essays from<italic>Revolutionary Leaves</italic>(Aghoro 2012; Bilsky 2012), the second</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>From the Becoming of Narrative to the Narrativity of Becoming</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To rehearse: what has been established under the heading of differential narratology is becoming as it pertains to narrative, narrativity in constant variation generating ever new variants of narrative; the virtual dance of narrative differentials producing actual, numerically differentiated narratives; the intensive sensations and forces of transcendental Narrative (affects, percepts, forces) bringing about the extensive states of affairs and networks of empirical narratives (events, existents, plots). In short, becoming, the dynamic and continuous process of selecting and gathering heterogeneous elements to be expressed, has been revealed as the ontologically primary virtual realm of any given actual narrative. But this has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g09ttm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
