<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">DC226.3.E54 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Napoleonic Wars, 1800–1815</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Chance</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Coincidence</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Europe</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">1789–1815</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Military art and science</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">19th century</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Empire of Chance</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Engberg-Pedersen</surname>
               <given-names>Anders</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>03</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780674967649</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780674425415</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts; London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the President and Fellows of Harvard College</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c99bhs"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Anders Engberg-Pedersen shows how the Napoleonic Wars inspired a new discourse on knowledge in the West. Soldiers returning from battle were forced to reconsider what it is possible to know and how decisions are made in a fog of imperfect knowledge. Chance no longer appeared exceptional but normative—a prism for understanding the modern world.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="336"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Prism of War</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us accompany the recruit onto the battlefield,” writes Carl von Clausewitz in his unfinished magnum opus<italic>On War</italic>. “As we approach,” he continues,</p>
                     <p>the increasingly loud thunder of the cannon is followed by the howling of bullets, which attracts the attention of the inexperienced. Bullets begin to strike the ground close to us, before and behind. We run toward the hill where the commanding officer is positioned with his large retinue. Here the impact of the cannonballs and the explosion of shells become so frequent that the seriousness of life shatters the adolescent fantasy. Suddenly a friend falls to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Geometry of War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Siege Architecture and Narrative Form</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It begins with an accident in the archive. On a small table piled with heaps of papers and stacks of books is a comprehensive library of war: treatises on fortification by Cataneo and Ramelli are crowded by the works of Stevin and Coehoorn, Sheeter and Pagan, Blondel and Vauban. Additional volumes on the theory of ballistics by Tartaglia, Torricelli, and Galileo are scattered among them. Together they form a small but comprehensive library of military thought from its early Italian origins in the fifteenth century through its Dutch and French developments in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries—an archive of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>State of War 1800:</title>
                     <subtitle>Topography and Chance</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1812 the Russian emperor summoned Carl von Clausewitz to a war council. A report about unforeseen enemy movements had just come in, and its effect on their military plans needed to be gauged. The three members of the council gathered around a map lying on the table and began discussing the different scenarios:</p>
                     <p>Colonel Toll, Count Orlof and the author gathered around the table to investigate the matter on the map. Count Orlof, being a young officer who had never been involved in the larger movements of war but otherwise possessed a lively mind, quickly came up with the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Modus Operandi:</title>
                     <subtitle>On Touch, Tact, and Tactics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the collection of Napoleonic bon mots that Balzac collected and published in 1838, the French emperor at one point states, “War is above all a matter of tact.”¹ The pithy formulation compresses a whole discourse in philosophy, military theory, pedagogy, and literature into a single concept. What for Napoleon, or at least for Balzac’s Napoleon, is presented as a self-evident truth in need of no further explanation was the subject of a more detailed analysis in various fields that attempted to develop a kind of knowledge that could guide action. Clausewitz instituted probability as a conceptual paradigm for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Exercising Judgment:</title>
                     <subtitle>Technologies of Experience</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The interest in operational knowledge was not limited to the fields of philosophy, military theory, and literature. As the logical extension of the attempts to delineate its basic features the question arose: How does one acquire operational knowledge, and, conversely, how does one teach it? Practical knowledge entered the curriculum of educational theory. Military pedagogy, however, differed from the contemporary developments in educational theory during the second half of the eighteenth century in that it was specifically tailored to the state of war. This created a fundamental problem, for how does one train a recruit without exposing him to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Paper Empires:</title>
                     <subtitle>Military Cartography and the Management of Space</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1813 one of Napoleon’s armies arrives in Silesia after two victorious battles and a number of smaller skirmishes. The advance into new territory puts the army in a predicament. Bacler d’Albe, Napoleon’s chief cartographer, writes back to Paris from the front: “We have now arrived in Silesia. I am truly in a difficult situation; no supply wagons, no maps! I understand nothing of this maneuver. This damned supply wagon, it will arrive after the war is over! Send me with the greatest speed a part of the area between Dresden and the Niemen river. [. . . ] I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Poetics of War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Cartography and the Realist Novel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Everything happens on a battlefield in a way that totally transcends our imagination and our powers of description.”¹ Articulated by Nikolay Rostov in Tolstoy’s<italic>War and Peace,</italic>this claim presents one of the main challenges to the nineteenth-century novel, namely the representability of warfare. The Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars, which had left such a profound imprint on Europe an history, seemed at the same time to evade description, to mark a hole in the textual fabric of history. In the attempt to conceptualize the wars, the literary imagination was faced not with a simple object but with an entire matrix</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Disorder of Things</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The state of war is articulated in a diverse range of forms, materials, and genres that all, with shifting emphases, respond to the disappearance of a secure foundation of knowledge. Out of the flat geometrical order, war emerges as a fully formed three-dimensional world governed by an operational dynamic that allows only hypothetical scenarios, average truths, a spectrum of probabilities. In its tremendous complexity, war is a blurry object in which a pervasive disorder obtains. But even as some seek to exclude the state of war from the realm of epistemology—be it in philosophical and military treatises or in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>253</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c99bhs.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
