<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN33.E76 2008</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Art and anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Literature and anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Ethnographica Moralia</book-title>
         <subtitle>Experiments in Interpretive Anthropology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Panourgiá</surname>
               <given-names>Neni</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Marcus</surname>
               <given-names>George E.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>16</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823228867</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823280797</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1x76fs8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Panourgia and Marcus bring together anthropologists working in various parts of the world (Greece, Bali, Taiwan, the United States) with classicists, historians, and scholars in cultural studies. The volume takes into account global realities such as 9/11 and the opening of the Cypriot Green Line and explores the different ways in which Geertz’s anthropology has shaped the pedagogy of their disciplines and enabled discussions among them. Focusing on place and time, locations and temporalities, the essays in this volume interrogate the fixity of interpretation and open new spaces of inquiry. The volume addresses a wide audience from the humanities and the social sciences—anyone interested in the development of a new humanism that will relocate the human as a subject of social action.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Panourgiá</surname>
                           <given-names>Neni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marcus</surname>
                           <given-names>George E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the spring of 1999, before 9/11—or the possibility of it—entered the public, political, and intellectual discourses, we, Neni Panourgiá and George Marcus, sat talking about what had happened to the critique of anthropology, what critical thought had brought to the project of anthropology and ethnography, and what the theoretically systematic approaches to anthropology had produced in the last twenty years. It seemed to us that what we had come to understand as interpretive anthropology had engendered new, engaged, and sustaining modalities of making the translation process of cultural experience to textual representation possible. With its beginnings in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Interview with Clifford Geertz</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Geertz</surname>
                           <given-names>Clifford</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Panourgiá</surname>
                           <given-names>Neni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kavouras</surname>
                           <given-names>Pavlos</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The interview with Clifford Geertz has a long history. It was originally conceived as part of a profile on Geertz for the Greek independent television program<italic>On the Paths of Thought</italic>, which has hosted such profiles of world-eminent thinkers and artists in various disciplines. To that end, a first interview was given by Geertz to Professors Konstantinos Tsoukalas and Neni Panourgiá in February 1999 at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton. A second interview was graciously granted by Geertz to Panourgiá and Professor Pavlos Kavouras during the 1999 seminar in Hermoupolis. (See also the article “Conversations in Hermeneutic Anthropology,”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contemporary Fieldwork Aesthetics in Art and Anthropology:</title>
                     <subtitle>Experiments in Collaboration and Intervention</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Marcus</surname>
                           <given-names>George E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, Douglas Holmes and I have been working toward an articulation, and a refunctioning even, of ethnographic research practices so basic to the identity of anthropology.¹ It is remarkable to reflect on how much research in social and cultural anthropology, especially in the United States, has consisted of variations on a particular aesthetic of practice that can be condensed to a near-mythic scene of encounter—a Malinowskian one, or latterly, a Geertzian one (e.g., the famous opening of Geertz’s “Deep Play” essay²). Recall, for instance, these oft-quoted lines from the beginning of the<italic>Argonauts of the Western Pacific</italic>,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Myth, Performance, Poetics—the Gaze from Classics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Almost thirty years ago, Sally Humphreys, then a member of the Departments of Anthropology and History at University College London, wrote that</p>
                     <p>the relation between Classics and Anthropology must be a relation of active debate. It is difficult, if not impossible, to gain an understanding of the methods and critical standards in argument of another discipline without personal contact and discussion. Up to the FirstWorldWar both classicists and anthropologists took it for granted that their relationship should be one of exchange of ideas and collaboration in developing theory; we have to try to recreate this situation.”¹</p>
                     <p>Since then, much water</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Birth of Anthropology out of a Pause on Pausanias:</title>
                     <subtitle>Frazer’s Travel-Translations Reinterrupted and Resumed</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Boon</surname>
                           <given-names>James A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Alas, poor Frazer: deceased since 1941, yet never at rest. Yes, Sir James George Frazer: repeatedly<italic>revenant</italic>. AfterWorld War II, Theodor Gaster eventually pruned<italic>The New Golden Bough</italic>; later Stanley Edgar Hyman gauged Frazer’s legacy, along with Darwin, Marx, and Freud; and John B. Vickery saluted Frazer’s influence among literary modernists: T. S. Eliot, James Joyce, and others.¹ Meanwhile in 1969, I. C. Jarvie had assessed disciplinary “othering” of Frazer’s approach versus Bronislaw Malinowski’s functionalism—by then also “historical.”² Subsequently, I recommended amalgamating anthropological and literary rereadings of Frazer<italic>and</italic>Malinowski (among others), aiming to avoid reductive polarizations that keep</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anamneses of a Pestilent Infant:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Enigma of Monstrosity, or Beyond Oedipus</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Athanasiou</surname>
                           <given-names>Athena</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The brash skeptic and the defunct hero, the abandoned infant and the triumphant sovereign, the autonomous and the dispossessed, the Hegelian inaugural philosopher, Nietzsche’s last human, the Freudian emblematic figure. How do the multiple figures of Oedipus enact and inflect the philosophical, anthropological, and psychoanalytic aporias of modern Western episteme? In this essay, I attempt to tackle this question by thinking through the cleavages of heteronomy and autonomy, belonging and errancy, sovereignty and liminality, the body of the sovereign and the future of the body politic. I suggest a (literally) symptomatic reading of Oedipus’s body, one that illustrates a corporeal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Fragments of Oedipus:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anthropology at the Edges of History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Panourgiá</surname>
                           <given-names>Neni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper was originally written differently, argued differently, and presented differently, before the clouds and drums of the unspoken and undeclared war and occupation that surround us now. However, this same war, whose absence produced a different discourse, makes imperative the reflection on what follows. The events of 9/11 forced upon us the radical reevaluation of the ways in which we engage in critical discourses. Not that we need to invent new ways of addressing the events around us, because, as Schiller already noted in his letter to Goethe, “everything is already there, so it needs only to be extricated.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Carnal Hermeneutics:</title>
                     <subtitle>From “Concepts” and “Circles” to “Dispositions” and “Suspense”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Papagaroufali</surname>
                           <given-names>Eleni</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To give my students a sense of the incomplete and elusive character of interpretive anthropology, I use two images drawn from Clifford Geertz’s<italic>The Interpretation of Cultures</italic>.¹ One is the “Indian story,” which is “about an Englishman who, having been told that the world rested on a platform which rested on the back of an elephant which rested in turn on the back of a turtle, asked … what did the turtle rest on? Another turtle. And that turtle? ‘Ah, Sahib, after that is turtles all the way down.’”² The other comes from Geertz’s assertion that “the culture of a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Real Anthropology” and Other Nostalgias</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weston</surname>
                           <given-names>Kath</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Imagine it. You are there, in the Department of Anthropology on any one of a number of college campuses in the United States, circa 1974. Clifford Geertz’s recently published<italic>The Interpretation of Cultures</italic>has made it past the standard-bearers of political economy, past the guardians of waning structuralist truths, and into a graduate-student reading group.¹ No one knows yet whether the discipline will turn in the direction of meaningful explication or veer off in search of more easily replicable projects.</p>
                     <p>Students emerge from the reading group intellectually invigorated, duly impressed, but as nervous about their career options as you have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Canonical and Anticanonical Histories</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liakos</surname>
                           <given-names>Antonis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of this paper is to propose an interpretation of national historiography(-ies) as a specific way of making sense of the past, within a framework of tensions in the making of a global sphere of production of history. The term<italic>history</italic>is a linguistic and cultural indicator of diverse ways of understanding social temporality. These ways of understanding are different in time and space. In some cultures, the concept of history and more generally the understanding of chronology were entirely different from the meaning of history in Western tradition. In Polynesia, for instance, historicity unfolds as an eternal return,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Anthropology at the French National Assembly:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Semiotic Aspects of a Political Institution</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Abélès</surname>
                           <given-names>Marc</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the conclusion of his book<italic>Negara: The Theatre State in Nineteenth-Century Bali</italic>, Clifford Geertz writes: “What our concept of politic power obscures, that of the Balinese exposes; and vice versa. And so far as a political theory is concerned, it is there in exposing the symbolic dimensions of state-power.”¹ Commenting, a few pages later, on the classical conceptions of the state, Geertz notes also that “in these views the semiotic aspects of the state remain so much a mummery.”² What seems to me very stimulating in these reflections, as in the whole analysis of<italic>Negara</italic>, is that it opens</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Life Is Dead Here”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Sensing the Political in “No Man’s Land”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Navaro-Yashin</surname>
                           <given-names>Yael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Triggered by references to “death within life” by informants in Northern Cyprus, this paper is an attempt to write against the grain of what I would like to call normalizing representations of “the political” in anthropology. If I have picked what could be called an “abnormal” context for ethnographic research, the territory of Northern Cyprus carved out of international recognition, I intend this “facing [of] the extreme,” in Tzvetan Todorov’s terms,¹ of an exaggerated context, to accentuate the “abnormal” in contexts that are usually considered politically “normal.” The purpose is not to normalize, by default, the abnormal (i.e., the illegal</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Text and Transnational Subjectification:</title>
                     <subtitle>Media’s Challenge to Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schein</surname>
                           <given-names>Louisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the brief space of this essay, I want to stage three relationships and delve into their implications for anthropological ethnography. The first concerns the paradigm agonisms precipitated by the encounter of anthropology with cultural studies. These “culture wars” have been a source of much heat in recent years, of acrimonious vilifications and reciprocal otherings, and I want here to query where the fires are coming from.</p>
                     <p>The second relationship is that of the much-discussed interconnection between media and transnationalism. On the one hand, I hold that media produce a kind of transnational subjectification. That is, in the consumption of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFTERWORD:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Ethnographer’s “Gaze”: Some Notes on Visuality and Its Relation to the Reflexive Metalanguage of Anthropology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kakavoulia</surname>
                           <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since commentary seems to be both a questions-raising and an interpretive practice, I would like to bring into discussion an issue that I think relates in an immediate way to the preceding papers in this volume. We already have an overabundance of theoretical metalanguages informed by powerful interdisciplinary movements (semiotics, linguistics, textual theory, postcolonialism, etc.) that attempt to master issues concerning representational modes. Here, for reasons of terminological economy, I would like to bring into the discussion the verbal-visual distinction and its importance in cross-cultural research. Reminding us of Michel Foucault’s distinction between the seeable and the sayable, this semiotic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1x76fs8.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>277</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
