<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Blaming the Victim</book-title>
         <subtitle>How Global Journalism Fails Those in Poverty</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Lugo-Ocando</surname>
               <given-names>Jairo</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780745334417</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781783712267</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Pluto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Jairo Lugo-Ocando</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt183p3tc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Poverty, it seems, is a constant in today's news, usually the result of famine, exclusion or conflict. In Blaming the Victim, Jairo Lugo-Ocando sets out to deconstruct and reconsider the variety of ways in which the global news media misrepresent and decontextualise the causes and consequences of poverty worldwide. The result is that the fundamental determinant of poverty - inequality - is removed from their accounts. The books asks many biting questions. When - and how - does poverty become newsworthy? How does ideology come into play when determining the ways in which 'poverty' is constructed in newsrooms - and how do the resulting narratives frame the issue? And why do so many journalists and news editors tend to obscure the structural causes of poverty? In analysing the processes of news production and presentation around the world, Lugo-Ocando reveals that the news-makers' agendas are often as problematic as the geopolitics they seek to represent. This groundbreaking study reframes the ways in which we can think and write about the enduring global injustice of poverty.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Tables</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Back in the early twentieth century, one of America’s finest journalists and authors, Upton Sinclair, wrote<italic>The Brass Check</italic>, one of the first comprehensive studies about journalism practices and media ownership. In<italic>The Brass Check</italic>, Sinclair warned that the United States had ‘a class-owned press, representing class interests, protecting class-interests with entire unscrupulousness, and having no conception of the meaning of public welfare’ (1919: 318). Others such as Hamilton Holt saw journalists as ‘tools or vassals of the rich men behind the scenes’ (1909: 4). In both cases, it was perhaps a harsh assessment of the overall state of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The Subjectivity of Poverty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Poverty is arguably the most important single issue in the global news agenda, but at the same time one of the most neglected ones. According to the United Nations’ report<italic>Rethinking Poverty</italic>.<italic>Report on the World Social Situation 2010</italic>, ‘global levels of poverty have changed very little over the past two decades’ (2009: 31), while most experts doubt that more than a handful of countries will achieve the targets set in the Millennium Development Goals (Elliot 2011: 43). Despite this, most of the mainstream news media in the West either ignore the subject altogether or seem wedded to the positivist</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Poverty of Ideas in the Newsroom</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lugo-Ocando</surname>
                           <given-names>Jairo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harkins</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite journalistic normative claims that news accounts on poverty are driven by a quest for social justice, the way poverty is articulated today by the global news media is instead a convergent by-product of more down-to-earth organisational dynamics and interests that happen within the newsrooms. First, we can point to the media’s editorial and news policies, which are shaped by a multiplicity of interests and objectives; second, we have the ideological interventions and approaches of journalists and editors in the process of news gathering and dissemination; and, third, the framing provided by news sources and news shapers in the construction</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>What Lies Beneath?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>60</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When reporting on poverty or related issues such as social exclusion, unemployment, or famine, journalists around the world tend to present their articles mostly as hard news stories. Overall, news about poverty in the global media is more often than not reported following the traditional narrative style and structures often referred to as the ‘5WH’ and the ‘inverted pyramid’, even when the article adopts the feature style. The first technique refers to the ability to answer the basic questions: Who is it about? What happened? Where did it take place? When did it take place? Why did it happen? How</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Africa, That Scar on Our Face</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lugo-Ocando</surname>
                           <given-names>Jairo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Malaolu</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrick O.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his speech to the annual Labour Party conference on 2 October 2001, the then British Prime Minister Tony Blair said to the audience: ‘The state of Africa is a scar on the conscience of the world. But if the world as a community focused on it, we could heal it. And if we don’t, it will become deeper and angrier.’</p>
                     <p>By reducing Africa to a scar, Blair was effectively following a long tradition of colonial rhetoric that has reduced that continent to a simplistic caricature in the western imagination. One hundred and twenty-eight years before and not very far</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Visual Journalism and Global Poverty</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lugo-Ocando</surname>
                           <given-names>Jairo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Eldridge</surname>
                           <given-names>Scott</given-names>
                           <suffix>II</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Kevin Carter’s photograph of a starving child in Sudan, with a vulture lurking in the background, is one of the most iconic visual depictions of poverty ever made. Published in the<italic>New York Times</italic>in 1993, Carter received the Pulitzer Prize for this photo only months before he committed suicide at the age of 33. The image has become a ubiquitous signifier of famine, that has informed other portrayals of poverty ever since. This particular photo has become referential because certain images, whether stereotypical or unique, carry an ability to express emotions and knowledge (Hariman and Lucaites 2007: 10) in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Spinning Poverty!</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On 4 January 1890, the<italic>Leeds Mercury</italic>newspaper in England published an article calling for donations with the headline ‘The China Famine of 1888–89’ (Issue 16,145). It was a news story based on what, by modern standards, would have been a press release sent to the paper by the North China Famine Relief Committee. It quoted a letter from W.V. Drummond, chairman of the committee, in which he explained how bad the situation was in that country and how much difference the help already given had made to the people experiencing the famine. The article then quoted another letter from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>The Emergence of Alternative Voices</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the publication of UNESCO’s report<italic>One World, Many Voices</italic>(MacBride 1980), there has been a growing consensus among scholars, news people and the international community in general about the need for developing nations to have their own voice on the world media stage. This consensus has been reached in part because of a growing awareness about the requirement to empower those in poverty so they can articulate their own responses, in their own terms, to the challenges they face.</p>
                     <p>Where there is not so much agreement is in defining the form and nature of the media provisions these countries</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Beyond the Unsustainable News Agenda</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the past decade, the world has seen major tragedies around the globe, among them the disastrous 2004 Indian Ocean earthquake and tsunami, the fatal floods provoked by Hurricane Katrina in the US in 2005, and the 2011 massive earthquake and tsunami leading to nuclear disaster in Fukushima, Japan. We saw the US, the remaining superpower, almost incapable of dealing with a major natural disaster (Townsend 2006) and Japan become one of the major recipients of aid, after being one of the main donors, as aid to poor countries was being severely cut, despite record profits from Japan’s main corporations</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt183p3tc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
