<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt8f9frs</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR2976.K57 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Shakespeare, William, 1564–1616</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Semiotics and literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Shakespeare</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Theater and the Book</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>KNAPP</surname>
               <given-names>ROBERT S.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400859962</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1400859964</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON, NEW JERSEY</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1989</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Princeton University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7zv1rc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This book explores the reasons for the lasting freshness and modernity of Shakespeare's plays, while revising the standard history of English medieval and Renaissance drama. Robert Knapp argues that changes in the authority of English monarchs, in the differentiation and integration of English society, in the realization of human figures on stage, and in the understanding of signs helped produce scripts that still compel us to the act of interpretation</p>
         <p>Originally published in 1989.</p>
         <p>ThePrinceton Legacy Libraryuses the latest print-on-demand technology to again make available previously out-of-print books from the distinguished backlist of Princeton University Press. These paperback editions preserve the original texts of these important books while presenting them in durable paperback editions. The goal of the Princeton Legacy Library is to vastly increase access to the rich scholarly heritage found in the thousands of books published by Princeton University Press since its founding in 1905.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTE ON TEXTS AND ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xiii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>The Literariness of Shakespeare</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No one in 1623 would have said that Shakespeare’s work marked and embodied some general change in European self-understanding. We often say so now. Portentous and wistful by turns, our talk about Shakespeare habitually sets him between times, last witness for the old, first prophet of the new, a genius of the divided vision and a symbol of our own life on the margins of tradition. Commonplaces can be false, of course, but the proof of this one is repetition, not only iteration of such judgments about Shakespeare’s place in history, but our constant recurrence to his texts, which have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>The Body of the Sign</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>All shifts in modern sympathies notwithstanding, the perplexing thing about late medieval theater is still its radical union of drama with doctrine. I do not mean that there is trouble believing in the orthodoxy of the nonliturgical religious stage: despite a resurgence of Marxist criticism, and our increasing awareness of the dialogic character of all texts, I would not want to claim that the plays embody a dialectical tension between official teaching and popular expression or entertainment.¹ The difficulty, rather, is the absence of such a contradiction, and of any other obvious opposition in these texts between earnest and game,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>The Idea of the Play</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Two related myths of closure inscribe themselves within most modern attempts to understand the literary past. Both are myths of community. The first evokes an unfallen, preindustrial age without moral uncertainty, personal anomie, or economic alienation: this is the era inhabited by Benjamin’s storyteller or D. W. Robertson’s Chaucer, an era in which everyone’s experience was more or less public and shareable, as were the norms by which to judge it. Though hardly a world without sin and error, it at least permitted sin to be identified and at best was a world in which poetry mattered, not as unacknowledged</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>The Moving Image</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I want now to sum my argument so far, develop a few of its implications, and show more precisely how the genealogy I have described sets the stage—in a quite literal sense—for the theatrical and dramatic innovations of the 1580s. Reduced to the limits of a precis, the story I have been trying to tell is this. There is, most of us would agree, a certain tension in Shakespeare—call it ambiguity, complementarity, dialectics, or indecidability—which keeps him readable. That tension, I have been claiming, does not grow out of some radical split in Shakespeare between two</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Shakespearean Authority</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A crucial part of the creation of literary drama in England involved the differentiation of mungrel tragicomedy into a system of structured and more or less determinate generic shapes.¹ Without such a sorting into coded emphases upon the individual image and its sexual or textual deflection, English drama could not have set its own frame, could not have transcended the determinants of civic ritual and ideological occasion. Yet part of the peculiarity of Elizabethan theater also has to do with its reaching beyond the classically certified set of dramatic genres, thereby complicating the opposition between tragedy and comedy with mutants</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zv1rc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
