<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS3537.T4753Z666 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Stevens, Wallace, 1879–1955</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Subjectivity in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dissenters in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Deleuze, Gilles</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Wallace Stevens among Others</book-title>
         <subtitle>Diva-Dames, Deleuze, and American Culture</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>JARRAWAY</surname>
               <given-names>DAVID R.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780773546028</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780773597761</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">077359776X</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>MQUP</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Montreal; Kingston; London; Ithaca</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>McGill-Queen’s University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cd0kr0"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In Wallace Stevens among Others David Jarraway explores the extraordinary achievement of Wallace Stevens, but in contexts that are not usually thought about in connection with Stevens's work - gay literature, contemporary fiction, Hollywood film, and avant-garde architecture, among others. By viewing the poet among these "other" contexts, Jarraway considers the nature of self-reflection and pays special attention to the discrediting of self-presence as the principle of identity in American writing - a theme that reflects American authors’ abiding concern for subjectivities that engage the world from spaces of distance and difference. By returning to the work of Stevens, Jarraway seeks to refurbish this preoccupation by linking it to the literary theory of French philosopher Gilles Deleuze, whose work applies to American writers from Melville and Whitman to Fitzgerald and Cummings. Jarraway forges the link between Deleuze and Stevens by drawing out the female subjectivity found in each writer’s work to rethink the more static masculinist premises of being. Informed by a deep knowledge of and fluency with the work of Stevens and Deleuze, Jarraway uses these writers as a means of entry into American literature and culture, Wallace Stevens among Others is a sophisticated analysis that will open new directions for future scholarship.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="312"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Figures</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To a certain extent,<italic>Wallace Stevens among Others: Diva-Dames, Deleuze, and American Culture</italic>is anticipated by my two previous books: the first devoted to a complete reading of the poet himself (1993), and the second to readings of a number of other poets implicated in Stevens’s work by means of what I refer to as a theory of “dissident subjectivity” in American culture (2003). What is entirely new with the present monograph is my endeavour, over six separate chapters, to explore further the extraordinary achievement of American poet Wallace Stevens in the annals of modern American literature among other literary</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>“The Theory of Life”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wallace Stevens, Gilles Deleuze, and the Difference They Make</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>13</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the following collection of readings largely inspired by the work of Wallace Stevens, I endeavour to situate his poetry, sometimes directly and in other cases quite speculatively, among contexts not often associated with its extraordinary achievement in the annals of modern American culture: the gay alongside the straight fictional narrative (as in chapters 2 and 3), the classic American film (chapter 4), the postwar poetic “school” (chapter 5), and even contemporary architecture (chapter 6). Among these “other” contexts thanks to Stevens, I continue further to advance the claim elaborated previously (in<italic>Going the Distance: Dissident Subjectivity and Modernist American</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>“The Novel That Took the Place of a Poem”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stevens and Queer Discourse</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The collocation of Wallace Stevens and queer discourse, for some, is likely to be somewhat of a stretch. I say this not with an eye to the second element of my chapter’s subtitle, but principally to the poet designated in the first. “Queer is hot,” after all (Berlant and Warner 343). Stevens is not. Nor, I would hazard, has he ever been. To the contrary, Wallace Stevens, through the years, has garnered the canonical reputation, as Joseph Harrington observes, of “a retiring aesthete writing verses,” one who “loathed reading in public” and who was prone “to block out or keep</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>“No Place like Home”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stevens and Contemporary American Fiction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout his long and prodigious career, American writer John Updike has been fascinated by human identity in modern culture – a preoccupation that perhaps became crystallized for him upon completion of his third book of poetry entitled<italic>Midpoint</italic>(1969). Ruminating fondly about that volume some ten years later, Updike observes: “I remain pleased with<italic>Midpoint</italic>. It’s about the mystery of being alive – of being<italic>you</italic>as opposed to being somebody else. Perhaps that’s the abiding mystery in my metaphysical universe” (“Conversation [Reilly]” 145). Ten years further on, the mystery continues in a book of memoirs entitled<italic>Self-Consciousness</italic>(1989). “In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>“Both Sides and Neither”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stevens, Masculinity, and American Film</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The fact that a number of contemporary American gay writers continue to return to the poetry of Wallace Stevens – the work of Mark Doty and Michael Cunningham are the signal instances in previous chapters of this study – will probably suggest the limit case for Stevens’s “masculinity” in his own poetry, and the “erotic poetics” hypothetically subtending it. But in view of the extensive correspondence between José Rodríguez Feo and Stevens gathered together in<italic>Secretaries of the Moon</italic>(1986), and of the considerable interest recounted there by the letter writers in a number of other homosexual authors familiar to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Stevens and New York School Poetry in the Distance</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>158</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a searching meditation on “New York School” poets Frank O’Hara, John Ashbery, and “The Paradoxes of Friendship,” Andrew Epstein pauses over “an intriguing wrinkle” of their early relationship in the final chapter of his magisterial<italic>Beautiful Enemies</italic>: namely, “O’Hara, always assumed by critics to be so distant from Stevens and his influence, actually began his friendship with Ashbery with a shared mutual passion for the poet” (237). “Stevens was a more important poet to them than Eliot,” O’Hara and Ashbery would apparently divulge to novelist Harold Brodkey while at Harvard together with them in the late 1940s – “a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>“The Play between the Spaces”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Stevens and Psychoanalysis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thanks to Wallace Stevens, our focus in the last chapter on the “irrational element” in poetry by means of its speculative relationship to Freudian and post-Freudian psychoanalysis from the 1950s and onward perhaps requires us to explore further Stevens’s own specific debt to the psychoanalytic enterprise itself. I therefore designate psychoanalysis as an “other,” and here a terminal context among others in this study, all the while exercising some caution, as in the last chapter when the subject was broached in relation to Schuyler by means of (and with respect to) Deleuze. This hesitation in Stevens’s case arises because commentators</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Diva-Dames in the Dark</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the heyday of formalist (or structuralist, or archetypal) criticism, the great Canadian literary critic Northrop Frye once ventured a very shrewd insight in concluding a breathlessly synoptic overview of Stevens’s entire oeuvre that I think still holds up today. In the essay entitled “The Realistic Oriole: A Study of Wallace Stevens” from 1957, Frye makes clear why Stevens’s poetry perhaps situates itself so well among the other contexts explored throughout this study for gauging the extraordinary achievement of his work in the century past. Specifically, Frye remarks on the “anti-‘poetic’ quality” of Stevens in contrast, say, to T.S. Eliot</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cd0kr0.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>283</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
