<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Fate of Saul's Progeny in the Reign of David</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Tushima</surname>
               <given-names>Cephas T. A.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>Foreword by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Longman</surname>
               <given-names>Tremper</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227680360</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227900680</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Cephas T.A. Tushima</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cgf3qc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Cephas Tushima provides a thorough analysis of the fate of Saul's heirs, focussing on whether their tragedies were due to continuing divine retribution, coincidence, or Davidic orchestration. He concludes that David was unjust and calculating in his dealings with the Saulides and, like other Near Eastern usurpers, perpetrated heinous injustices against the vanquished house of Saul. Traditionally readers saw Saul as evil and David as a hero; but more recently scholars have written about Saul as a tragic character and David as a villain, turning the book of Samuel into deeply contested interpretive territory. Tushima provides analysis of the critical literature surrounding this contentious issue and contributes his own study that will prove important to the continuing debate. He assesses David's character by analysing how he treats the surviving children of his predecessor, drawing upon the provisions for justice in the covenant community in the book of Deuteronomy. He demonstrates a connection between Samuel and the Torah through themes and motifs, and develops theological conclusions from them on such issues as the impact of human conduct on the environment, marriage, monarchy and Zion theology.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="364"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>iii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Tables</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>viii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Foreword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Longman</surname>
                           <given-names>Tremper</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gundry</surname>
                           <given-names>Robert H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The story of Saul and David is vivid and compelling drawing the reader into a narrative of gripping action and complex characters. Typical of the best hebrew narrative, the narrator of the Saul and David story rarely reveals the motivations of characters and even more sparingly provides moral evaluation of its characters’ actions, preferring a strategy of showing rather than telling the story. Readers are expected to enter into the story with their imagination and to do their own evaluations.</p>
                     <p>The masterfully written account of Saul and David leaves plenty to the readerly imagination. Some readers have a tendency to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tushima</surname>
                           <given-names>Cephas T. A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>xvii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xx</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The threefold divine promise to Abraham (of blessing, progeny, and land) remained of vital importance to israelite life (both at the national and individual levels) through the centuries.¹ Progeny is the evidence of yahweh’s blessings (cf. gen 15: 1–2). one way this blessedness manifests is in the care children provided for their aged parents. Besides, children also saw to the proper burial of their parents. A fitting burial meant ultimately “being gathered” to the ancestral tomb so that the family continued to be together even after death.² More importantly, children served as security for the family and ensured the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>A Survey of the interpretive history of 1–2 Samuel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Chapter 1 laid out the primary concern of this work, the investigation of the fates of Saul’s heirs in David’s reign. It also situated the books of Samuel in the context of the DtrH, highlighting the connection between the Torah and its important motifs and themes, not the least of which is justice—the undergirding criterion for evaluating David’s dealings with the Saulides in the book.</p>
                     <p>The present chapter is an overview of the history of the critical study of the books of Samuel, beginning from the early nineteenth century. It also highlights pivotal points in Samuel scholarship in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Narrative Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The previous chapter reviewed the history of scholarship in Samuel, beginning from the early nineteenth century to the present (at the dawn of the twenty-first century). The review considered the various methodological approaches used in studying Samuel: historicalcriticism, the new criticism, contemporary literary criticism, and the emergent new historicism. Besides methodological questions, the chapter also appraised studies that deal directly with David and Saul. This analysis furnished the needed context for the current endeavor.</p>
                     <p>The present chapter discusses the methodological approach of the present work—narrative criticism. It explores both the rise of narrative criticism, its elements, how the method</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Contest for the Succession to the Throne of Saul (2 Samuel 2–4)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In chapter 3, I outlined the methodology of the present study, namely, narrative criticism. In discussing the narrative critical method, I pointed out the centrality of the final form of the text in its analysis, not the text’s prehistory. Additionally, I noted the<italic>historary</italic>¹ nature of biblical narrative, which ontologically arises from the ground of history, existentially inhabits a literary sphere, and teleologically drives towards a theological goal; and I also noted how all of these trajectories have to be kept in tension for a proper explication of the world of the biblical narrative text. I also explored the various</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>David and Michal</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The focus of this endeavor as a whole is to investigate the fortunes of King Saul’s progeny during David’s reign. My goal is to ascertain, if possible, the factors that account for the great ills that visited the Saulides after the demise of their father, and especially to determine if there had been any Davidic complicity in any of these misfortunes. In the previous chapter, the analysis of the civil war years, reached a few tentative conclusions. First, with respect to the murder of Abner by Joab, David, by his actions and especially his inactions, was at the least blameworthy,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>David and Mephibosheth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>224</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In our continuing study of David’s relationships with Saul’s descendants, we have examined his relationship with Michal in the last chapter. We saw that Michal loved David from the start and sacrificed to secure his safety when his life was threatened. David, however, never showed affection for her. During the long years of their separation, he made no effort to retrieve her from Saul’s sphere but found time to meet with Jonathan more than once. When it was convenient for David to reassert his status as son-in-law of the deceased monarch, in order to smoothen his path to israel’s throne,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>An Integrative Reading of Research Findings</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have explored the relationships between David and Saulides, with a narrative critical approach, in the last three chapters. In chapter four, which deals with the civil war years, two prominent Saulides, Abner and ishbosheth were brutally murdered in cold blood. While there were no sufficient grounds for directly linking David with ishbosheth’s murder, there was significant circumstantial evidence implicating him in Abner’s murder. David’s dealing with Michal and her kin was the subject of study in chapter 5. David not only abandoned Michal when he fled Saul’s palace, but upon his return to israel had her removed, without concern</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Truths from David’s Dealings with the Saulides</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>314</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book set out to address comprehensively and holistically the fate of Saul’s progeny after Saul’s demise. Since there is no separate narrative of Saul’s descendants in the Bible, it traced the story of David and how that story interconnected with the fate of the Saulides to determine whether the ills that befell the Saulides were due to continuing divine retribution, pure happenstance, or Davidic orchestration. The specific passages analyzed for this purpose are 1 Sam 18:17—19:17; 25:39–44; 2 Sam 2–4, 6, 9, 16:1–4; 19:25–31 [ET 19:24–30]; 21:1–14. The investigation revealed David’s complicity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cgf3qc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>341</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
