<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN1009.A1K48 2011</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Children’s literature</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Terminology</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Keywords for Childrens Literature</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Nel</surname>
               <given-names>Philip</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Paul</surname>
               <given-names>Lissa</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>13</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780814758540</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0814758541</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780814758892</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0814758894</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>NYU Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>New York University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt9qg46g"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The study of children's literature and culture has been experiencing a renaissance, with vital new work proliferating across many areas of interest. Mapping this vibrant scholarship, Keywords for Children's Literature presents 49 original essays on the essential terms and concepts of the field. From Aesthetics to Young Adult, an impressive, multidisciplinary cast of scholars explores the vocabulary central to the study of children's literature. Following the growth of his or her word, each author traces its branching uses and meanings, often into unfamiliar disciplinary territories: Award-winning novelist Philip Pullman writes about Intentionality, Education expert Margaret Meek Spencer addresses Reading, literary scholar Peter Hunt historicizes Children's Literature, Psychologist Hugh Crago examines Story, librarian and founder of the influential Child_Lit litserv Michael Joseph investigates Liminality. The scope, clarity, and interdisciplinary play between concepts make this collection essential reading for all scholars in the field. In the spirit of Raymond Williams' seminal Keywords, this book is a snapshot of a vocabulary of children's literature that is changing, expanding, and ever unfinished.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="293"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nel</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Paul</surname>
                           <given-names>Lissa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since about 1970, scholarship in children’s literature has brought together people from the fields of literature, education, library and information science, cultural studies, and media studies. “Children’s literature” itself has become a kind of umbrella term encompassing a wide range of disciplines, genres, and media. of the challenges of children’s literature studies that scholars from disparate disciplines use the same terms in different ways. As a result, meanings can be blurred and cross-disciplinary conversations confused. Drawing on the expertise of scholars in many fields,<italic>Keywords for Children’s Literature</italic>responds to the need a shared vocabulary by mapping the history of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Aesthetics</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thomas</surname>
                           <given-names>Joseph T.</given-names>
                           <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There is perhaps no more vexing, fraught, and neglected concept in the study of children’s literature than<italic>aesthetics</italic>. No doubt the neglect of a serious, theoretical inquiry into the aesthetics of children’s literature stems from our contemporary understandings of the discipline of children’s literature itself. The study of children’s literature has, historically, been the work of librarians and educators of children. Children’s literature came to be seen as an appropriate site of purely literary study only after the rise and fall of mid-twentieth century New Critical and formalist modes of criticism, a state of affairs made possible by the inchoate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>African American</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martin</surname>
                           <given-names>Michelle</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From the beginnings of African American children’s around the turn of the twentieth century, parameters of what should be included has been much of a source of conflict as the terminology used this group of people. Commenting on the contested nature of this genre, Dianne Johnson (1990) asserts in<italic>Telling Tales: the Pedagogy and Promise of African Literature for Youth</italic>:</p>
                     <p>Like children’s literature, as a broad category,</p>
                     <p>African American children’s literature is a label</p>
                     <p>which refers to the intended audience. On the</p>
                     <p>other hand, like Afro-American literature, Black</p>
                     <p>children’s literature refers to the ethnic and racial</p>
                     <p>identities of the authors.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Audience</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clark</surname>
                           <given-names>Beverly Lyon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term “audience” has only relatively recently come to acquire its dominant modern meaning, referring to the viewers of an entertainment or readers of a book. The earliest such usage listed in the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) dates to 1855 . Earlier meanings include “[t]he action of hearing” (dating from c. 1374) and a “[f]ormal hearing,” often with royalty or with a judge (from 1377 ). Derived from the Latin<italic>audire</italic>, to hear, the term has a special resonance for children’s literature, for the youngest children are not readers but rather auditors of literature, truly an audience. Indeed the broad</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Body</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hager</surname>
                           <given-names>Kelly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Oxford English Dictionary’s</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) definition of “body”—”the material frame of man (and animals)”—immediately sets before us one of the term’s principal controversies in children’s literature. That is, what Peter Hunt (1984) would call the adultist, not to mention the sexist, nature of the<italic>OED</italic>’s language reminds us that the matter of the corporeal is often not deemed proper for the consideration of children and is frequently bound up with questions of gender and the adult body. But when we consider the<italic>OED</italic>’s elaboration on this definition—“the material body and its properties”—the physical nature of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Boyhood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tribunella</surname>
                           <given-names>Eric L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Along with childhood and girlhood, boyhood is central to the definition of children’s literature. John Newbery’s<italic>A Little Pretty Pocket-Book</italic>(1744), frequently credited with igniting the children’s literature industry, addressed boys and girls separately as distinct audiences: The book was available for purchase with a ball for boys and a pincushion for girls. Filled with descriptions of games specifically for boys and referring to boy players, the 1787 edition published by Isaiah Thomas in the United States paid additional attention to boys by including a prefatory address to adults about how to raise a healthy, virtuous, and wise<italic>son</italic>, thereby</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Censorship</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Booth</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>26</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The earliest reference to “censor” appears as “one of two magistrates of ancient Rome” (<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>[<italic>OED</italic>]), who in addition to taking the census (that is, the registration of citizens, originally for tax purposes), supervised public morals and censured the population (<italic>Columbia Encyclopedia</italic>2008). The English words “censor” and “census” are from the Latin<italic>censere</italic>, which means to appraise, value, judge, consider or assess; “censure” is from the Latin<italic>censura</italic>, meaning judgment. During the era in which these terms originated, Cato the Elder (234–149 B.C.E.) undertook a vigorous campaign to stem the infiltration of Greek culture (Knowles 2006)</p>
                     <p>According</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Character</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mechling</surname>
                           <given-names>Jay</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The concept of character has two uses in children’s literature discourse. One use belongs to literary criticism, as the critic and reader observe the people in a story or novel as “characters,” that is, as agents or actors (Burke 1973 ) whose actions move a story through time. The other use refers to the moral qualities of a person. These uses of “character” are related, as the root of the English word lies in a Greek word for a tool used to mark or engrave a material (<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>[<italic>OED</italic>]).</p>
                     <p>By the seventeenth century, the English word came to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Childhood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sánchez-Eppler</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Childhood” is an ancient word in English, not a young one. The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>takes as its earliest example for “cildhad” an English gloss inserted during the tenth century between the lines of the Lindisfarne Gospels. The meaning expressed there appears consistent with the most literal strand of our contemporary usage: this passage from the Gospel of Mark (“soð he cuoeð from cildhad”; 9:21) employs childhood as a temporal marker: a father explains to Jesus that his son had been wracked by fits since the earliest years of his life. The miraculous cure Jesus performs stands as a test</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Children’s Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hunt</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Children’s literature” is a term used to describe both a set of texts and an academic discipline—and it is often regarded as an oxymoron. If “children” commonly connotes immaturity, and “literature” commonly connotes sophistication in texts and reading, then the two terms may seem to be incompatible. Henry James, in “The Future of the Novel” (1900b), observed that “the literature, as it may be called for convenience, of children, is an industry,” but not one to be taken seriously: “the sort of taste that used to be called ‘good’ has nothing to do with the matter; we are demonstrably</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Class</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bullen</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word “class” comes to English from the Latin<italic>classis</italic>via the French<italic>classe</italic>. It first appears in Thomas Blount’s<italic>Glossographia</italic>(1656), where he defined it in the language of the times as “an order or distribution of people according to their several Degrees.” Citing Blount, the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) traces the term’s origins to its use by Servius Tullius who, seeking to raise funds for the Roman military, conducted a census for the purpose of taxing citizens according to their means. He created six categories or classes, based on property or net wealth (Kostick 2005). In spite of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Classic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kidd</surname>
                           <given-names>Kenneth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her study of comparative children’s literature, Emer O’Sullivan (2001) notes that children’s classics come from three sources: (1) appropriations of adult works; (2) adaptations from traditional (usually oral) narratives; and (3) works written specifically for children. A classic, then, could be a text adopted by children as well as a work written for them. But, as O’Sullivan’s study also makes clear, things are not so simple. “Classic” is an overdetermined and elastic term, one encompassing very different ideas and attitudes. The notion of a children’s classic amplifies the contradictions of the term, especially to the degree that children’s literature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>Crossover Literature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beckett</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra L.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In children’s literature scholarship, “crossover” refers to literature that crosses from child to adult or adult to child audiences. While crossover literature is not a new phenomenon, the term itself was not adopted until J. K. Rowling’s Harry Potter books gave this literature a high profile. Although the term was in use in the late 1990 s, it did not emerge as a common expression until the early years of the new millennium. While the crossover phenomenon actually began earlier in the visual media, with television shows (<italic>Star Trek</italic>,<italic>The Simpsons</italic>), films (<italic>E.T.</italic>,<italic>Toy Story</italic>), comics (<italic>Charlie Brown</italic>), and video</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Culture</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Flynn</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Culture,” writes Raymond Williams (1983a), “is one of the two or three most complicated words in the English language.” When it is applied to the study of children and their literature, it is certainly one of the most contested as well. The Latin<italic>cultura</italic>is derived from the past participial stem of the root word<italic>colere</italic>: to cultivate, to worship. According to the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>, later meanings are divided into three branches:</p>
                     <p>I. The cultivation of land, and derived senses.</p>
                     <p>II. Worship.</p>
                     <p>III. Extended uses (from branch I.).</p>
                     <p>While the second branch meaning is obsolete and rare, many of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Domestic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nelson</surname>
                           <given-names>Claudia</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term “domestic” derives from the Latin<italic>domus</italic>(house), through the Middle French<italic>domestique</italic>. The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>’s (<italic>OED</italic>) earliest usages are early sixteenth century, by which time the word already had multiple meanings: the achievement of quasi-familial intimacy, as in the 1521 supplication “make hym domestique /Within the heuyns,” but also homegrown rather than foreign. While “domestic” always implied closeness, the extent of the sphere of proximity varied. That sphere might be the individual (John Norris’s 1707<italic>Treatise on Humility</italic>defines “domestic ignorance” as “the ignorance of . . . what passes within our own breast,” notes the<italic>OED</italic>);</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Education</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gruner</surname>
                           <given-names>Elisabeth Rose</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In both<italic>Keywords</italic>(Williams 1983a) and<italic>New Keywords</italic>Bennett, Grossberg, and Morris 2005), “education”<italic>Keywords</italic>has “educate”) is primarily an institutional practice, which, after the late eighteenth century, is increasingly formalized and universalized in Western countries. Bearing the twin senses of “to lead forth” from the Latin<italic>educere</italic>) and “to bring up” (from the Latin<italic>educare</italic>), “education” appears chiefly as an action practiced by adults on children. The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>thus defines the term as “the systematic instruction, schooling, or training given to the young in preparation for the work of life.”</p>
                     <p>Education may be primarily vocational, leading children</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Empire</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wallace</surname>
                           <given-names>Jo-Ann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Slemon</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>75</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A barrage of associated terminology attends the advance of empire, and none of it fires with exactitude.“Imperialism” usually refers to “the practice, the theory, and the attitudes of a dominating metropolitan centre ruling a distant territory” (Said 1993)—that is to say, the politics, the economics, and the enabling ideology behind the promulgation of empires. “Colonialism” is generally understood as the assemblage of ways by which one nation or people imposes direct rule over another nation or people. “Colonization” refers specifically to the establishment of settler colonies in foreign lands. “Neo-colonialism,” a term coined by kwame Nkrumah (the first president of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Fantasy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Baker</surname>
                           <given-names>Deirdre</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of fantasy in the realm of children’s literature has been one of forceful contradictions: on the one hand, fantasy is criticized as being fraudulent, irrational, and overly imaginative; on the other, it is criticized for being formulaic, escapist, and not imaginative enough. The seeds of this debate lie in early uses of the word, which seem to have little to do with literature per se, but nevertheless powerfully influenced the activity of imagination over centuries. Fantasy’s potency in relation to children’s literature reflects its potency in relation to literature in general: it takes us into the heart of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Gender</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hateley</surname>
                           <given-names>Erica</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>86</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) informs us that “gender” has at its root the Latin<italic>genus</italic>, meaning “race, kind,” and emerges as early as the fifth century as a term for differentiating between types—especially those of people and words. In the ensuing 1,500 years, “gender” appears in linguistic and biological contexts to distinguish types of words and bodies from one another, as when words in Indo-European languages were identified as masculine, feminine, or neuter, and humans were identified as male or female. It is telling that gender has historically (whether overtly or covertly) been a tool of negotiation between</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Girlhood</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reid-Walsh</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacqueline</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>92</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>), “girlhood” has been in use from the mid-eighteenth century until the present day as both a singular and a plural noun. From the first cited use—notably, in Samuel Richardson’s<italic>Clarissa</italic>(1747–48), a novel concerning the paragon of virtuous adolescent girlhood—the term “girlhood” has had a history as an ideologically loaded term in Western culture. As the following brief definitions indicate, several meanings overlap: “The state of being a girl; the time of life during which one is a girl. Also: girls collectively.” Its different denotations and connotations make for a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>Golden Age</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sorby</surname>
                           <given-names>Angela</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>96</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The “Golden Age” is a Greco-Roman concept, introduced in Hesiod’s<italic>Works and Days,</italic>which pictures a race of men who “lived like gods without sorrow of heart, remote and free from toil and grief: miserable age rested not on them; but with legs and arms never failing they made merry with feasting beyond the reach of all evils” (2007). In children’s literature, the term was first proposed by the mid-twentieth century British biographer (and Inkling) Roger Lancelyn Green, whose use of it was ideologically freighted but historically useful. Since Green, however, the term has spread and morphed to become a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>Graphic Novel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hatfield</surname>
                           <given-names>Charles</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>100</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nowhere has the fissure between adult-sanctioned and self-selected children’s reading been more boldly marked than in regard to comics, an internationally popular form that has often been seen as the province of amoral profiteers rather than a domain of children’s literature. If comics have at last “arrived” as a children’s genre, then this new acceptance has been spurred by enthusiasm for the graphic novel, the bulwark of comics’ recent claims to literariness.</p>
                     <p>The term “graphic novel” has fuzzy borders and origins. The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) defines “graphic” as “of or pertaining to drawing or painting,” and “novel” as “a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22</label>
                     <title>Home</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reimer</surname>
                           <given-names>Mavis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word “home” comes into English through the Teutonic languages of northern Europe, carrying with it the multiple meanings of world, village, homestead, dwelling, and safe dwelling, as well as indicating a direction, as it continues to do in a phrase such as “go home.” The primary meaning in contemporary usages of the word is “the seat of domestic life and interests.” In this sense, the word is close to the Latin<italic>domus</italic>, from which the adjective “domestic” is derived. As well as referring to a building or place, however, “home” also refers to the quality of feelings associated with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23</label>
                     <title>Identity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Coats</surname>
                           <given-names>Karen</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the various branches of the natural, mathematical, and human sciences, “identity” has a range of uses related to the property of sameness or consistency of an element regardless of the influence of other variables. “Personal identity,” the subset most relevant to studies children’s literature, is defined in the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) as “the sameness of a person or thing all times and in all circumstances; the condition or fact that a person or thing is itself and not something else.” This definition has a rigidity that most contemporary scholars of children’s literature will find objectionable. Rather than being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24</label>
                     <title>Ideology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parsons</surname>
                           <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Based on the classical Greek words<italic>ideo</italic>, meaning idea, and<italic>ology</italic>, referring to a branch of knowledge, a systemic set of ideas, or a form of discourse, the concatenated word “ideology” derives from the French<italic>ideologie</italic>. The concept arose as part of a French philosophical movement in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth century period of Enlightenment, and its original meaning was to denote a science of ideas. In the nineteenth century, the term was taken up by Karl Marx to label the unconscious system of beliefs in a social group, and specifically socioeconomic class structures (Bennett, Grossberg, and Morris</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25</label>
                     <title>Image</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>de Beeck</surname>
                           <given-names>Nathalie op</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Depending on the speaker (children’s author, literary critic, art historian, advertising designer, painter) and the venue (bookstore, literature conference, gallery, marketing meeting), the term “image” implies an array of connotations, purposes, and audiences (Mitchell 1986). In the hybrid contexts of the twenty-first century—where visual culture, visual studies, and visual literacy are related but contested terms—“image” crosses disciplinary boundaries and characterizes multimodal activities in classrooms and communication. For children’s literature, an interdisciplinary field drawing upon many scholarly discourses, pedagogical approaches, and modes of creative expression, “image” is a complex and provisional term, always at play and in flux.</p>
                     <p>Appropriately,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26</label>
                     <title>Innocence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gubar</surname>
                           <given-names>Marah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Pondering the immense popularity of young starlets such as Deanna Durbin and Shirley Temple, Grahame Greene (1993) declared in 1939, “Innocence is a tricky subject: its appeal is not always so clean as a whistle.” While Temple’s charm ostensibly lay in her perfect purity, he argued, in fact she functioned as a highly eroticized figure. Indeed, Temple’s first films were a series of shorts known as “Baby Burlesks” that placed tiny children in compromising positions. “Boy, she’s hot stuff!” remarks one of Temple’s male admirers in one of these shorts (<italic>War Babies</italic>[Lamont 1932]), and her later films likewise situate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>27</label>
                     <title>Intention</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pullman</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“What was your intention when writing this book?” “What did you mean by the passage on page 108 ?” “What did you want the reader to feel at the end?” “What message did you intend the book to deliver?”</p>
                     <p>Authors of novels, especially novels for children, know that questions such as these are not uncommon. This might be surprising, in view of the fact that more than sixty years have gone by since William K. Wimsatt and Monroe C. Beardsley published their famous essay “The Intentional Fallacy” (1946 ), except that somehow it isn’t surprising at all to find that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>28</label>
                     <title>Latino/a</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Serrato</surname>
                           <given-names>Phillip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a proper noun, “Latino” designates a resident of United States who is of Latin American descent. an adjective, it renders the noun that it modifies somehow pertinent to or associated with such individuals. While the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>traces the use of the label back to the 1940s, it did not gain widespread currency until the 1980s. As Suzanne Oboler (1995) observes, “Latino” emerged as a counter to Hispanic,” an umbrella term resented by many who into its fold as “an artifact created and imposed by state administrative agencies.” Among other things, “Hispanic” implicitly cleaned up the genealogy of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>29</label>
                     <title>Liminality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Joseph</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the phenomenon of liminality appears in the earliest children’s texts, it doesn’t appear in children’s literature scholarship until the beginning of the twenty-first century, chiefly in the adjective form, “liminal,” a polyseme whose other meanings relate to psychology and mysticism. “Liminality” is a coinage from the Scottish anthropologist Victor Turner (1969 ), who drew on “liminaire,” a term used by Arnold Van Gennep (1909) in his ethnographical writings on preindustrial societies to designate the middle, transitional stage of a three-stage paradigmatic rite of passage (“rites which accompany every change of place, state, social position and age”). Joseph Campbell adapted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>30</label>
                     <title>Literacy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Paul</surname>
                           <given-names>Lissa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>Keywords</italic>, the term “literacy” does not have an entry of its own. Instead, Raymond Williams (1976) traces its evolution from its fourteenth-century root, “literature.” For the first three hundred years of its life, “literature” was an all-purpose word referring sometimes to “being well-read,” and at other times to “the books in which a man is well-read” (Williams 1976). Gradually, this common-ancestor word divided into several distinct species: the root-word, “literature,” strengthened its links to nationhood (as in English literature or French literature); “literate” came to describe being well-read; “literary” became associated with the “profession of authorship”; and “literacy” arose</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>31</label>
                     <title>Marketing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cummins</surname>
                           <given-names>June</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>146</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>At its most basic level, the word “marketing” refers to the “action of buying or selling” (<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>[<italic>OED</italic>]) and always implies some sort of exchange, usually involving goods, services, or ideas—and money. A common usage of “marketing” that directly affects children’s literature is “the action, business, or process of promoting and selling a product” (<italic>OED</italic>). Since the advent of the printing press, literature has been intimately related to marketing. It is self-evident that developing technologies made widespread literacy possible; what may take some explaining is that marketing is as essential to the development and dissemination of children’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>32</label>
                     <title>Modernism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Reynolds</surname>
                           <given-names>Kimberley</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Arguably no word maps the kind of cultural shifts in language that Raymond Williams (1976) was documenting better than “modernism.” At its simplest this is because of its roots in the word “modern.” Inevitably, what is modern at one time eventually becomes dated and of its time, and so from the first recorded use of that root word in 1500, through the appearance of the word “modernism” itself in 1737, to the fin de siècle, it was a shifting signifier, referring to the present of any given period, rather than a specific historical moment or movement (<italic>Shorter Oxford English Dictionary</italic>),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>33</label>
                     <title>Multicultural</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Dudek</surname>
                           <given-names>Debra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term “multicultural” and its associated “-ism” have been the focus of many debates in literary, educational, political, and sociological circles since the terms were coined. “Multicultural” first appeared in the<italic>New York Herald Tribune</italic>in 1941: “A fervent sermon against nationalism, national prejudice and behavior in favor of a ‘multicultural’ way of life” (<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>[<italic>OED</italic>]). The second usage, in 1959 by the<italic>New York Times</italic>, both narrows and broadens the definition by connecting a culturally diverse city to cosmopolitanism. In 1965, the adjective “multicultural” expanded into the noun “multiculturalism” in the<italic>Preliminary Report of the Royal Commission</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>34</label>
                     <title>Nature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hollindale</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For the environmentalist and literary critic alike, “nature” has multiple meanings. The zoologist Colin Tudge (2005) observes that “<italic>all</italic>definitions of nature are simply for convenience, helping us to focus on the particular aspect that we happen to be thinking about at the time.” Of the General Prologue to Chaucer’s<italic>Canterbury Tales</italic>(1387), the literary critic John F. Danby (1961) notes that for Chaucer, the word has three dimensions: Nature is a kind of goddess, the collective force of animate life; it is the material world of organic growth and change; and it is the responsive disposition in the hearts</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>35</label>
                     <title>Nonsense</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Heyman</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Shortsleeve</surname>
                           <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his introduction to<italic>The Chatto Book of Nonsense</italic>, Hugh Haughton (1988) comments that “nonsense is a bit of a problem.” Haughton is alluding to a set of semantic and literary “difficulties” that have surrounded “nonsense” since the term came into common usage in the seventeenth century. At first the word was used mostly in its literal sense, meaning that which makes no sense, or that which is useless, but a new meaning emerged over the next two hundred years, referring to a particular literary phenomenon. The interactions between these senses of the word are at the heart of some</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>36</label>
                     <title>Picture Book</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moebius</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>No keyword in children’s literature could be quite as fluid in its application as the one word “picturebook” the two-word “picture book.” The cultural medium which this locution refers is itself quite malleable and can be stretched to include: nonprint pictorial media for children or adults on the internet; picture-book format” or, following the German cognate,<italic>Bilderbuch</italic>, “a type of visual encyclopedia”; humorous simulacra adults such as the recent<italic>Goodnight Bush</italic>(Origen and Golan 2008); or the once risqué<italic>Home Sweet Zoo</italic>(Barnes 1950). Or it can simply be a book with pictures in it; Henry James in 1900 called</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>37</label>
                     <title>Popular</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cassidy</surname>
                           <given-names>Julie A. S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While the definition of the term “popular” has remained relatively unchanged for over four hundred years, its connotation certainly takes on new meaning when applied to children’s literature. In<italic>Keywords</italic>, Raymond Williams (1983a) reports that the term “popular” was “originally a legal and political term” that first came into the English language in the late fifteenth century. Within the domain of the legal system, an “action popular” was any suit that was open to or brought forth by anyone who was part of the general public. According to the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>), in the early sixteenth century the term</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>38</label>
                     <title>Postcolonial</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bradford</surname>
                           <given-names>Clare</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word “postcolonial” refers (I) to a period or state following (that is, “post”) colonialism, and (2) to the effects of colonization upon cultures, peoples, places, textuality. The terms most often associated with “postcolonial” are “imperialism,” which denotes the formation of an empire, and “ colonialism,” which refers to the establishment of colonies by an imperial power that maintains control over them. The first usage of “postcolonial” (or “post-colonial”) identified in<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) occurs in 1883 in the<italic>Century Illustrated Monthly Magazine</italic>(White 1883), where it denotes “occurring or existing after the end colonial rule.” This association of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>39</label>
                     <title>Postmodernism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nel</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Postmodernism” denotes an historical period, a style, or a cultural logic. If an historical period, then the word means<italic>after modernism</italic>—although when, precisely, modernism ended is debatable: 1939, 1945, and 1950 are common dates, but the term “postmodernism” crops up well before then. The<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>) finds J. M. Thompson in 1914 using “Post-Modernism” to describe a shift in Christian thinking that would “escape from the double-mindedness of Modernism.” A still earlier example eluded the<italic>OED</italic>: circa 1870, the English painter John Watkins Chapman spoke of “postmodern painting,” which he alleged was more avant-garde than French impressionism</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>40</label>
                     <title>Queer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mallan</surname>
                           <given-names>Kerry</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>186</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word “queer” is a slippery one; its etymology is uncertain, and academic and popular usage attributes conflicting meanings to the word. By the mid-nineteenth century, “queer” was used as a pejorative term for a (male) homosexual. This negative connotation continues when it becomes a term for homophobic abuse. In recent years, “queer” has taken on additional uses: as an all-encompassing term for culturally marginalized sexualities—gay, lesbian, bi, trans, and intersex (GLBTI)—and as a theoretical strategy for deconstructing the binary oppositions that govern identity formation. Tracing its history, the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>notes that the earliest references to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>41</label>
                     <title>Race</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Smith</surname>
                           <given-names>Katharine Capshaw</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A term with a variety of charged meanings and purposes, “race” arose in English in the sixteenth century from the French “race” and the Italian “razza” and has been employed as a means of grouping individuals by ethnic, social, or national background. While the term has been applied generally to a range of collective identities— including the “human race” (Williams 1976) or the “German race” (Murji 2005)—at present the term invokes categorization attached to imagined physical similarities or to a group’s own sense of collective ideals and history. “Race” as a term points both backward toward injurious histories of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>42</label>
                     <title>Reading</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spencer</surname>
                           <given-names>Margaret Meek</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As recent classical scholarship makes plain, reading is a human, deictic invention. Evidence comes from the evolution of ancient alphabetic writing systems: Sumerian (cuneiform), Akkadian (<italic>Gilgamesh</italic>), Ugaritic (a fine, delicate script), and Egyptian hieroglyphs. Texts on stone and papyrus proved to be more lasting ways of recalling past events than human memory. Long, long before twentieth-century educators would debate whether reading should be taught by phonics or meaning-based methods, the Sumerians showed their young writers how to make word lists on clay tablets by incorporating elements of both of these pedagogies in their instruction. The later, successful Greek alphabet was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.47</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>43</label>
                     <title>Realism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mercier</surname>
                           <given-names>Cathryn M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Unlike the term “fantasy,” “realism” (or “realistic fiction”) doesn’t always appear as a distinct category in reference books about children’s literature. The<italic>Norton Anthology of Children’s Literature</italic>(Zipes et al. 2005) includes sections on legends, myth, fairy tales, fantasy, and science fiction, but no single entry on realistic fiction. The<italic>Norton Anthology</italic>does devote sections to adventures, school stories, and domestic fiction, and excerpts from seminal titles that have realistic qualities, such as<italic>From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler</italic>(Konigsburg 1967). Similarly, Perry Nodelman and Mavis Reimer’s<italic>The Pleasures of Children’s Literature</italic>(2003) includes sections on poetry,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.48</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>44</label>
                     <title>Science Fiction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hastings</surname>
                           <given-names>A. Waller</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>202</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The term “science fiction” denotes a genre of imaginative literature distinguished from realism by its speculation about things that cannot happen in the world as we know it, and from fantasy by abjuring the use of magic or supernatural. In science fiction, all phenomena and events described are theoretically possible under the laws of physics, even though they may not at present be achievable. Stated in this way, it would appear that works belonging to the genre would be easily identifiable. However, critics of science fiction have struggled to find an adequate definition almost since the term was coined and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.49</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>45</label>
                     <title>Story</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Crago</surname>
                           <given-names>Hugh</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historically, “story” is probably one of the most frequently employed words in relation to children’s literature. Yet despite its constant use by reviewers and critics over much of the history of fiction written specifically for young people, it has rarely been defined or analyzed. In its apparent simplicity, taken-for-grantedness, and resistance to deconstruction, the term establishes itself as something unquestioned, like the nature of “childhood” or “the child” itself. “Story” is missing from the index of numerous works where one might reasonably expect to find it—such as Katherine Nelson’s<italic>Narratives from the Crib</italic>(1989), a psycholinguistic study of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.50</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>46</label>
                     <title>Theory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rudd</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The word “theory” appears in Raymond Williams’s original<italic>Keywords</italic>(1976). He traces its origins back to the Greek<italic>theoros</italic>, meaning “spectator,” with its root in<italic>thea</italic>, for “sight,” which also gave us “theater.” As more recent commentators put it, “[T]he literal sense of looking has then been metaphorized to that of contemplating or speculating” (Wolfreys et al. 2006). The term became increasingly opposed to “practice,” not only as something removed from the everyday, but also as something involved in attempts to explain and model the everyday. Although the title of Williams’s work—<italic>Keywords</italic>—implicitly underwrites the importance of language, his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.51</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>47</label>
                     <title>Tomboy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Abate</surname>
                           <given-names>Michelle Ann</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>220</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the rise of feminism and the advent of queer theory make tomboyism seem like a relatively contemporary phenomenon, the concept originated in the sixteenth century. Interestingly, the term “tomboy” initially referred to rowdy gentlemen courtiers rather than boisterous young women. The first listing in the<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>(<italic>OED</italic>), from 1533, defines “tomboy” as a “rude, boisterous or forward boy.” Several decades later, in the 1570s, the term shifted from characterizing a spirited young man to a like-minded young woman. In so doing, it also acquired newfound sexual associations and age coordinates. “Tomboy” lost the innocently playful connotations it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.52</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>48</label>
                     <title>Voice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cadden</surname>
                           <given-names>Mike</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The first mention of “voice” as metaphor appeared in 1587 when Golding De Mornay wrote that “there is . . . a dubble Speech; the one in the mynd, . . . the other the sounding image thereof, . . . vttered by our mouth” (<italic>Oxford English Dictionary</italic>). Four centuries later, doubleness had become multiplicity. As Charlotte Otten and Gary Schmidt (1989) note, the “word<italic>voice</italic>itself is undergoing changes: it has moved from being a strictly descriptive term into the realm of metaphor that now includes more than point of view and that encompasses all that identity itself connotes.”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.53</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>49</label>
                     <title>Young Adult</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Talley</surname>
                           <given-names>Lee A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Talley phrase “young adult” reflects the history of changing perceptions of childhood, adolescence, and adulthood and how these ideas have shaped parenting, education, libraries, publishing, and marketing (Cart 1996 ; Eccleshare 1996 ; Campbell 2009). The Young Adult Services Association (YALSA) denotes ages to eighteen as composing “ young adult” readers YALSA 1994). Given the dominant conception that period of growth is particularly important, understandings of what constitutes “good” young adult literature vary extensively, for there is a great deal at stake.</p>
                     <p>Readers often imagine young adult (YA) literature texts that challenge the status quo. They believe while children’s literature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.54</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.55</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt9qg46g.56</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
