<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GN33.J34 2013</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Ethics</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Anthropological aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Well-being</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Immigrants</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Cross-cultural studies</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Wherewithal of Life</book-title>
         <subtitle>Ethics, Migration, and the Question of Well-Being</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Jackson</surname>
               <given-names>Michael</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="author">In conversation with</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Emmanuel</surname>
               <given-names>Mulamila</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Franco</surname>
               <given-names>Roberto M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ouédraogo</surname>
               <given-names>Ibrahim</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>03</day>
         <month>08</month>
         <year>2013</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780520276727</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780520956810</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0520956818</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>BERKELEY; LOS ANGELES; LONDON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Regents of the University of California</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt7zw54w"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>The Wherewithal of Life</italic>engages with current developments in the anthropology of ethics and migration studies to explore in empirical depth and detail the life experiences of three young men - a Ugandan migrant in Copenhagen, a Burkina Faso migrant in Amsterdam, and a Mexican migrant in Boston - in ways that significantly broaden our understanding of the existential situations and ethical dilemmas of those migrating from the global south. Michael Jackson offers the first biographically based phenomenological account of migration and mobility, providing new insights into the various motives, tactics, dilemmas, dreams, and disappointments that characterize contemporary migration. It is argued that the quandaries of African or Mexican migrants are not unique to people moving between 'traditional' and 'modern' worlds. While more intensely felt by the young, seeking to find a way out of a world of limited opportunity and circumscribed values, the experiences of transition are familiar to us all, whatever our age, gender, ethnicity or social status - namely, the impossibility of calculating what one may lose in leaving a settled life or home place; what one may gain by risking oneself in an alien environment; the difficulty of striking a balance between personal fulfillment and the moral claims of kinship; and the struggle to know the difference between 'concrete' and 'abstract' utopias (the first reasonable and worth pursuing; the second hopelessly unattainable).</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preamble</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN THE SUMMER OF 2005, en route from Denmark to the United States to take up yet another visiting academic position, I decided to break my journey in London to look up Sierra Leonean friends and document some of their experiences of living betwixt and between. One cloudless morning, I accompanied Sewa Koroma on a circuitous tour of the West End, revisiting the sites of critical events during his first year in the city. At one point, we stopped on Westminster Bridge to take in the view. Tourist boats were moving up and down the river, whose muddy banks had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Emmanuel</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I LIVED AND WORKED IN COPENHAGEN, Denmark, for six years. After moving to the United States in 2005, I returned to Denmark every year to give talks, see old friends, and attend the PhD defenses of my former students.</p>
                     <p>When Susanne Bregnbaek successfully defended her doctoral thesis in the fall of 2010, I was invited to her apartment in Christianshavn to celebrate the rite of passage with family and friends. Curiously enough, Susanne’s thesis, though based on fieldwork in Beijing, resonated with a conversation I would have later that evening with Emmanuel Mulamila, a Ugandan who was married to one</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Roberto</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A COUPLE OF MONTHS AFTER my conversations in Copenhagen with Emmanuel, I was sitting in an espresso bar in Boston’s North End, killing time before attending a ceremony at Faneuil Hall, where I would take an oath of allegiance, receive my certificate of naturalization, and “enjoy my new life as a United States citizen.” My mind, however, was not on the day ahead, but on Emmanuel’s story and the opening lines of Woody Guthrie’s “Talking Columbia,” where he describes watching the boats entering and leaving Bonneville lock and</p>
                     <p>thought ’bout the river goin’ to waste,</p>
                     <p>thought ’bout the dust, thought</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Ibrahim</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN 2007 MY COUSIN LOUISA JACKSON and her friend Evelien Kuipers were working as volunteers for an NGO in Ghana. Louisa was helping out in an orphanage; Evelien was teaching English in an elementary school five hundred miles away. When they first met, Evelien responded instantly to Louisa’s unconventional personality, and both quickly discovered a shared commitment to protecting the environment and helping the poor. Th e two young women (Evelien was thirty, Louisa twenty-three) kept in touch by telephone and began planning a seven-week tour of Togo, Benin, and Burkina Faso when their contracts in Ghana ended. Evelien had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Postscript</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>197</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>JOAN DIDION ONCE WROTE, “We tell ourselves stories in order to live.”¹ Our stories provide us with parsimonious, coherent, and uncomplicated versions of events that have overwhelmed us. They offer the consoling illusion that even if we do not always have a hand in determining the course of our lives, a hidden hand is guiding our destiny from behind the scenes. In the opening of his autobiographical novel<italic>Look Homeward, Angel,</italic>Thomas Wolfe imagines a thread of fated connections that transcend time and memory: “Each of us is all the sums he has not counted: subtract us into nakedness and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX:</title>
                     <subtitle>EXISTENTIAL MOBILITY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>231</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7zw54w.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
