<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">RG556.N38 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Pregnancy</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Childbirth</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Parenting</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Popular culture</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Natal Signs</book-title>
         <subtitle>Cultural Representations of Pregnancy, Birth and Parenting</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>EDITED BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>BURTON</surname>
               <given-names>NADYA</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>04</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781772580341</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1772580341</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Demeter Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bradford, ON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Demeter Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1rrd8tc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Natal Signs: Cultural Representations of Pregnancy, Birth and Parenting explores some of the ways in which reproductive experiences are taken up in the rich arena of cultural production. The chapters in this collection pose questions, unsettle assumptions, and generate broad imaginative spaces for thinking about representation of pregnancy, birth, and parenting. They demonstrate the ways in which practices of consuming and using representations carry within them the productive forces of creation. Bringing together an eclectic and vibrant range of perspectives, this collection offers readers the possibility to rethink and reimagine the diverse meanings and practices of representations of these significant life events. Engaging theoretical reflection and creative image making, the contributors explore a broad range of cultural signs with a focus on challenging authoritative representations in a manner that seeks to reveal rather than conceal the insistently problematic and contestable nature of image culture. Natal Signs gathers an exciting set of critically engaged voices to reflect on some of life’s most meaningful moments in ways that affirm natality as the renewed promise of possibility.Natal Signs: Cultural Representations of Pregnancy, Birth and Parenting explores some of the ways in which reproductive experiences are taken up in the rich arena of cultural production. The chapters in this collection pose questions, unsettle assumptions, and generate broad imaginative spaces for thinking about representation of pregnancy, birth, and parenting. They demonstrate the ways in which practices of consuming and using representations carry within them the productive forces of creation. Bringing together an eclectic and vibrant range of perspectives, this collection offers readers the possibility to rethink and reimagine the diverse meanings and practices of representations of these significant life events. Engaging theoretical reflection and creative image making, the contributors explore a broad range of cultural signs with a focus on challenging authoritative representations in a manner that seeks to reveal rather than conceal the insistently problematic and contestable nature of image culture. Natal Signs gathers an exciting set of critically engaged voices to reflect on some of life’s most meaningful moments in ways that affirm natality as the renewed promise of possibility.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BURTON</surname>
                           <given-names>NADYA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thinking about representations of pregnancy, childbirth, and parenting is an exciting project in the contemporary context. Positioned in an era when traditional and historical constraints on representations of these life events have been unsettled, we find ourselves facing a shifting landscape. We are, furthermore, also confronted by evolving economies of cultural production and consumption; not only are we encountering new images, but we are continuing to witness changes in the systems of generation and circulation by which they are produced and consumed.</p>
                     <p>Although most readily accessible popular representations remain conventional and banal, just as notably we find ourselves increasingly confronted</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What to Expect When Your Avatar is Expecting:</title>
                     <subtitle>Representations of Pregnancy and Birth in Video Games</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CRUIKSHANK</surname>
                           <given-names>LAUREN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When it comes to video games, much attention is paid to representations of death. Game developers spill considerable digital blood crafting elaborate spectacles of violent demise in death-oriented games, while academics and the popular media spill equally as much ink debating the implications of those virtual fatalities. Avatars, visual representations of human players in these digital spaces, die repeatedly in games, such that experiences of dying become “part of the everyday life in the world” (Klastrup 144). However, in the context of this discussion and a medium in which death has so often been the focus, what about birth?</p>
                     <p>How</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Masculine Pregnancy:</title>
                     <subtitle>Butch Lesbians’, Trans Men’s &amp; Genderqueer Individuals’ Experiences</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WALKS</surname>
                           <given-names>MICHELLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Between february 2011 and april 2012, I conducted research in British Columbia focused on butch lesbians’, trans men’s, and genderqueer 3 individuals’ experiences with pregnancy and infertility. I came to this research topic as a queer femme who had heard first-hand from butch, trans, and genderqueer-identifying friends of their diagnoses of infertility, and also (from both different and the same friends) of their desires to experience pregnancy. I was aware that in Canada, when a baby is born and seen as having a vulva, the child is labelled as “female,” and there is a cultural expectation for that baby to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>That Fat Man is Giving Birth:</title>
                     <subtitle>Gender Identity, Reproduction and the Pregnant Body</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SURKAN</surname>
                           <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Did you always want to be pregnant?” The social worker peered across the room at the two of us, but the question is directed to me, since I am the patient. My partner and I are sitting in an office in a prestigious urban teaching hospital, on a floor dedicated to reproductive medicine. On any given day in this location, scores of women emerge from the elevator, sit in waiting rooms, have vital signs checked, undergo blood tests, ultrasounds, and internal exams, and consult with doctors, nurses, social workers, and patient coordinators—all in the attempt to have a baby.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Gay Men’s Narratives of Pregnancy in the Context of Commercial Surrogacy</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RIGGS</surname>
                           <given-names>DAMIEN W.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DEMPSEY</surname>
                           <given-names>DEBORAH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Historically, gay men have primarily become fathers in the context of heterosexual relationships, or for some men through foster care, adoption, or co-parenting arrangements as sperm donors (Riggs and Due). Since the beginning of the twenty-first century, however, gay men living in western countries have increasingly made use of commercial surrogacy services (Everingham, Stafford-Bell, and Hammarberg). The increased use of these services has become possible as a result of legislative change in countries such as the U.S. (in which many states now allow for the contracting of surrogacy services), in addition to the provision of services in countries where the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Crone and Moon, Umbilical Cords/Blood Ties</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>REID</surname>
                           <given-names>BRESCIA NEMBER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>88</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The subsequent illustration, cut-out in black paper, offers a depiction of the intergenerational continuum of birth. This work imagines a family line, with umbilical cords still attached, a snapshot of multiple generations seen at once, in non-linear time. Centering a representation of queer birthers, including trans folks and LGBT-TIQ2S people, is integral to this web of generations. Homage is paid to the curious reality of human reproductive physiology—a fetus with ovaries is born containing their entire life’s supply of “eggs” (Moore, Persaud, and Torchia 269). This means that the eggs that were fertilized to become each of us were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Imminent</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LONG</surname>
                           <given-names>JENNIFER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For over fifteen years, my artistic practice has explored issues of doubt, vulnerability, perceived ideals, and communication within the context of interpersonal relationships. Working with constructed narratives and a feminist lens, I describe the emotions and quiet moments of everyday life. Touch, gesture, and gaze all play significant roles as conduits of conscious and unconscious modes of communication. My artwork parallels my life experiences and has recently concentrated on pregnancy and mothering through the series<italic>Swallowing Ice</italic>,<italic>Fold</italic>, and<italic>Imminent</italic>.<italic>Imminent</italic>began as a series of self-portraits that visually articulated my reflections of being pregnant and the primary caregiver to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Heroes and Villains:</title>
                     <subtitle>Representations of Midwives in Ontario’s Late Twentieth Century Midwifery Revival</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ALLEMANG</surname>
                           <given-names>ELIZABETH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contrary to the popular belief that midwifery is one of the oldest female professions, midwifery is considered a “new” profession in Canada (Shroff 11). Throughout much of the twentieth century, Canada was the only western industrial nation and one of only nine of the 250 World Health Organization member countries without legal provisions for midwifery (Barrington 14-5). While the majority of babies around the world are born into the hands of midwives, the modern Canadian maternity care system was built on the model of a doctor-nurse team without the presence of the midwife as an expert in normal birth (Biggs,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Spacemaking and Midwifery:</title>
                     <subtitle>With, Within, Without</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SHARPE</surname>
                           <given-names>MARY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCGRATH</surname>
                           <given-names>KORY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>127</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter focuses on a particular realm of tocology (the study of birth) expressed through topology (the study of space). It explores some meanings that the phenomenon and treatment of “space” hold for the woman, the midwife, and their relationship during pregnancy, birth, and the postpartum. It navigates the interior and exterior landscape, the interplay between the tangible and intangible. And it describes how midwives and women are co-creators of a “precreative” space in this ambience. Drawing from literature that examines woman-midwife relationships, relational aesthetics, institutional ethnography, and urban and feminist theory, the chapter examines spacemaking from the personal to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Refusing Delinquency, Reclaiming Power:</title>
                     <subtitle>Indigenous Women and Childbirth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FLETCHER</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAIRE DION</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOURGEOIS</surname>
                           <given-names>CHERYLLEE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The prevalence of imagery and metaphor related to pregnancy, birth, and mothering in Indigenous cultures of Turtle Island reveal the significance of these life events within these communities. While negative representations of Indigenous women are used by colonizing forces to legitimize extermination and assimilation projects, Indigenous artistic representations of pregnancy, birth, and mothering continue to be a powerful tool to push back against these efforts. Artwork by contemporary Indigenous artists depicting pregnancy, birth, and mothering present a positive image of contemporary cultures, recognizing the ceremonial value of these experiences and creating powerful narratives of Indigenous women and communities.</p>
                     <p>The artwork</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Resistance and Submission:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Critique of Representations of Birth</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>EINION</surname>
                           <given-names>ALYS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper emerged from my work for a Ph.D. in Creative Writing. Motivated by a desire to analyse women’s life stories, and informed by many years as a midwife, I took on the task of retelling a life story revolving around the centrality of the character’s bodily experience of womanhood, manifested through her experiences of rape, intimate violence, birth, and mothering. This enterprise opened the door to a critical understanding of the nature of subjectivity as represented and re-presented in fiction and non-fiction in the form of birth narratives. As a midwife and a feminist, I had long been aware</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Representations of Birth and Motherhood as Contemporary Forms of the Sacred</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HENNESSEY</surname>
                           <given-names>ANNA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>194</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper examines ways in which images of birth and the maternal body are contemporary forms of the sacred, and, controversially, how their production represents a renewed interest in birth and mothering as primary sources of empowerment for many women. Through research in art history, religious studies, philosophy, medical anthropology, and feminism, I first show how members of an international movement devoted to birth and art are actively using religious, secular, and re-sacralized art imagery in the visualization of labour and birth and as a ritualistic part of birth as a rite of passage. While this process of ritualizing art</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Does Labour Mean Work?</title>
                     <subtitle>A Look at the Meaning of Birth in Amish and Non-Amish Society</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JOLLY</surname>
                           <given-names>NATALIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter, I examine the social landscape of femininity to contextualize women’s fear of pain in childbirth. For many women, vaginal delivery has become something to avoid. Trends in medicalization and surgical intervention (including increased rates of elective cesarean section) suggest that childbirth need not involve labour (both generally, in terms of effortful work, and specifically, in terms of the three stages of the birth process). In this chapter, I consider what has motivated this trend towards increased medicalization of birth, with an eye towards the cultural features of our social world. In particular, I suggest that the components</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Representing Birth:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Inquiry into Art Making and Birth Giving: Implications for Teaching Student Midwives</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LYONS</surname>
                           <given-names>JEANNE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>232</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As a midwife and an artist, I see many commonalities between art making, midwifery, and birth giving. As a midwifery educator I find value in representing the point of view that birth is a work of art that we are privileged to participate in. As well, I find value in using artistic modalities to explore and teach the art of midwifery. How birth is represented can leave long-term and powerful impressions. How do we, as midwives, present birth to the families we serve? What impressions are left on midwifery students as they traverse our educational systems, and in turn what</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Birth is a Labour of Art</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KOTAK</surname>
                           <given-names>MARNI</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>251</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>For me, my existence as an artist and a mother are deeply intertwined and reflect my belief that human life is the most profound work of art. Being a mother as an artist has the potential to unlock cultural institutions that have traditionally codified the maternal body as irrational, weak, and economically ineffectual (Liss 2). Giving birth and raising my child as a work of art challenges our capitalist society that glorifies products over people and the spectacle over authentic human experience.</p>
                     <p>I believe that the pressures upon women artists of the second wave to keep motherhood and art separate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Split Open</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>PARKER</surname>
                           <given-names>ARA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The very act of birthing forced me to completely surrender to the throws of labour and natural delivery. There was no sidestepping the inevitable birthing. Why had I not been told more about this initiation into being? Not my child’s, but my own!</p>
                     <p>In this moment of birthing, I was<italic>split open</italic>at once. It was like a lightning bolt went in through the crown of my head right through the birth canal and split me open like a dry log under the axe. I had died and been reborn in that instant of my daughter’s birth.</p>
                     <p>My child came</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Flower of My Flesh</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROSENZWEIG</surname>
                           <given-names>ROSIE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When I was pregnant for the first time in 1959, I was working as a librarian at the Indiana State Library, with all the most recently published books at my disposal. Hot off the press, Marjorie Karmel’s book<italic>Thank You, Dr. Lamaze</italic>was read in one sitting. Ms. Karmel described a new method of giving birth without drugs, a method that her French doctor modelled after his experiences in Russia at the time. It became known eventually as the Lamaze method of childbirth. The Mayo Clinic describes that the goal of this method is to increase confidence in your ability</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Birth Shock:</title>
                     <subtitle>Exploring Pregnancy, Birth, and the Transition to Motherhood Using Participatory Arts</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HOGAN</surname>
                           <given-names>SUSAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BAKER</surname>
                           <given-names>CHARLOTTE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CORNISH</surname>
                           <given-names>SHELAGH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCCLOSKEY</surname>
                           <given-names>PAULA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib5" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WATTS</surname>
                           <given-names>LISA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The birth project is funded research by the Arts and Humanities Research Council, UK. New mothers are being given the opportunity to explore their experiences of pregnancy, birth, and post-natal readjustments using different art forms: phototherapy, photo-diaries, and participatory arts. In The Birth Project, the arts are being used to interrogate this complex topic. We situate this endeavour in the context of an emerging practice of health humanities (Crawford et al.) art as social action (Levine and Levine) and visual research methodologies (Pink,<italic>Advances, The Future</italic>). This chapter will focus on the participatory arts work already undertaken to date with</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Making Meaning of Stillbirth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MCGRATH</surname>
                           <given-names>KORY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FARRALES</surname>
                           <given-names>LYNN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>296</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sensitive language, remembrance photography, and mementos have become integrated into stillbirth care practices in North American health care institutions for parents and families who have experienced the death of an infant. While representations reflect how families, caregivers, and society understand stillbirth, they also help shape our relationship with birth, death, and both as they occur together. From both subjective and objective points of view, this chapter will explore how words, images, and artifacts come to represent multiple meanings of stillbirth in a way that can both challenge and contribute to the silence, stigma, and emancipation of bereaved parents from ambiguity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Kids Aren’t Cute</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>OSNES</surname>
                           <given-names>BETH</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>317</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let’s get a few more things straight about kids. Kids aren’t cute. Kids aren’t cute, but they are little and little is cute, but it’s only the little that’s cute, not the kid. Think about it, a six-foot newborn would not be cute. Not only are kids not cute, they don’t like cute things. They don’t even like primary colours. Given the chance, they always go for the black remote control. They don’t want fuzzy stuffed animals; they want to turn the oven on. They want to drive the car. They want to work that new table saw. They only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Paternal Loss and Anticipation:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Artist’s Perspective</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BULLER</surname>
                           <given-names>RACHEL EPP</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>321</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Maternity is becoming a visible presence on the contemporary art scene. Around the world, artists like Rineke Dijkstra, Katharina Bosse, Maru Ituarte, Mariángeles Soto-Díaz, Zorka Project, Kate Kretz, Gail Rebhan, and Jess Dobkin address pregnancy, lactation, the postpartum body, the mother-child relationship, and societal expectations of mothers. Some creative practitioners use their maternal position as a point of activist departure, turning to social and political engagement to effect cultural change for parents and children.¹ While many artist-mothers have confronted cultural taboos to speak more fully to their own lived experiences and to challenge heteronormative, raced, and classed expectations of motherhood,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Two Mums and Some Babies:</title>
                     <subtitle>Queering Motherhood</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ENGLISH</surname>
                           <given-names>REBECCA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>JOHNS</surname>
                           <given-names>RAECHEL</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DWYER</surname>
                           <given-names>ANGELA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gay and lesbian parents are a new front in parenting research. Coining the term<italic>lesbian baby boom</italic>, Morris, Balsam and Rothblum indicate the numbers of lesbian mothers has increased rapidly over the last two decades. Following that paper, there has been a good deal of research that explores the experience of lesbians as parents. Much of this research (see Lubbe; Tasker and Patterson) has focused primarily on family identity. In one study, Lubbe found that the children of lesbian parents were aware of their non-standard familial identity and its impact on society. These children were aware that the reactions from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Go the Fuck to Sleep Prince George?</title>
                     <subtitle>Juxtaposing Cultural Representations of Motherhood and Exploring the Politics of Authenticity</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MARTIN</surname>
                           <given-names>BETTY ANN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Noted anthropologist clifford geertz defines culture as “the ensemble of stories we tell ourselves about ourselves” (448). In keeping with this theory, Fred Inglis suggests that identity is formed through a process whereby we observe and “inhabit the narratives of how to live” available within a given culture (“Culture and Sentiment” 2). Such narratives generally reflect the dominant discourse and accepted range of meanings in relation to socially defined roles. In terms of the negotiated meaning of motherhood, however, there is a growing tension between competing narratives and representations that highlight the juxtaposition between culturally constructed fantasies of maternal perfection</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1rrd8tc.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>About the Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
