<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7mjv0</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">HN981.V5 A75 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Political violence</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Developing countries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Social conflict</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Developing countries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Civil society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Developing countries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Citizenship</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Developing countries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Humanity</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Developing countries</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Developing countries</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social conditions</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Anthropology</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Life, Emergent</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Social in the Afterlives of Violence</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Arif</surname>
               <given-names>Yasmeen</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781517900557</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781452953076</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1452953074</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Regents of the University of Minnesota</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt1g69wbt"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How does an inquiry into life as it lives (or dies) amid mass violence look like from the perspective of the "social"? Taking us from Sierra Leone to India to Lebanon,<italic>Life, Emergent</italic>challenges conventional understandings of biopolitics, weaving a politics of life through the lens of life, not death.</p>
         <p>Arguing that the "letting die" element of biopolitics has been overemphasized, Yasmeen Arif zeros in on biopolitics' other pole: "making live." She does so by highlighting the various means and the forms of life configured in the aftermath-or after<italic>lives</italic>-of violent events in contexts of law, justice, community, and identity. Her analysis of the social repercussions is both global and local in scope. Arif examines the convictions made in the Special Court of Sierra Leone, the first hybrid court of its nature under international criminal law. Next, she explores the making of a justice movement in the context of Hindu-Muslim violence in 2002 in the state of Gujarat, India. From there she revisits the Sikh carnage in Delhi of 1984. Finally, she explores a span of civil violence in Lebanon, and particularly, its effects on the city of Beirut.</p>
         <p>This rigorously argued book brings together the various strands of life and the social that each chapter has disentangled-and in doing so it begins to frame a politics of, and in, life.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="272"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[v]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>Afterlife: VIOLENCE, THE SOCIAL, AND LIFE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The query, what is life? is an arrogant one. With due restraint, this book does pose such a query, but with the following intent: how can the question of damaged life, in all its incessant living and dying, be posed as a query of the social? The possibility of answers is sought in archaeologies of the contemporary, in an assembly of locations of mass violence where such articulations could be found and which calls them<italic>afterlife</italic>—“afterlife” as a metaphor or a metonym that suggests life after damage.</p>
                     <p>Life, as it lives or dies, in a momentum consonant with damage,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The International Social:</title>
                     <subtitle>HUMANITY, CRIME, AND LAW IN SIERRA LEONE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sierra Leone gained independence from British control in 1961. After several years of political instability, including several military coups, Sierra Leone became a one-party state in 1978 under the prime ministership of Siaka Stevens, leader of the APC, or the All People’s Congress, which became the only legally recognized political party. Their main rivals over the years of political turbulence have been the SLPP, Sierra Leone’s People’s Party. The APC regime was, however, challenged in the late 1980s by the Revolutionary United Front (RUF), under the leadership of Foday Sankoh, an erstwhile corporal in the Sierra Leonean Army who was</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Compassionate Citizenship:</title>
                     <subtitle>NYAYAGRAH, GANDHI, AND JUSTICE IN GUJARAT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Gujarat 2002 episodes of violence are widely understood to be a calculated attack on the Muslim population in the western state of Gujarat in India that began on February 28, 2002. The immediate trigger was the burning of two compartments of the Sabarmati Express a little away from the Godhra station on the early morning of February 27, 2002. On that day, the train arrived at the station carrying a number of Hindu pilgrims, or<italic>karsevaks</italic>(those who worship through service), who were returning from the north Indian town of Ayodhya, where they had been to participate in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Wounding Attachment:</title>
                     <subtitle>SUFFERING, SURVIVING, AND COMMUNITY IN DELHI</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the morning of October 31, 1984, the prime minister of India, Indira Gandhi, was walking toward her morning appointments in her official residence when her accompanying bodyguards turned their guns on her and shot her down. Her bodyguards belonged to the Sikh community, and this assassination of the country’s reigning political leader was connected to the prevailing Sikh militancy of the time. The north Indian state of Punjab, the territorial home of the Sikh community, had been in violent political turmoil for several years leading up to this event. Led by a charismatic religious leader, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Emotional Geographies:</title>
                     <subtitle>WAR, NOSTALGIA, AND IDENTITY IN BEIRUT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The cycles of violence in Lebanon, particularly in the capital city of Beirut, are about the nation’s multiple genealogies of ethnic hostilities and arguably also about its location in regional hostilities that involve Israel, Palestine, Syria, and the larger Middle East as well as the Mediterranean. Be that as it may, the sketch here does not take on the formidable task of summarizing the historical political conditions leading to violence in the region or the nation; rather, it focuses on the city of Beirut, outlining a set of events and rendering a reading of them.</p>
                     <p>The first set of events</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Bios, Pathos, and Life Emergent</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>169</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Deleuze takes a vignette out of Dickens (<italic>Our Mutual Friend</italic>) to find a remarkable allusion to life between life and death, when a sense of life pervades and overwhelms any sense of good or bad.¹ Before or after, it would seem, a surrounding, an environment, objectivity or subjectivity, internality or externality, would take over and make it a social presence (with its “goodness” and “badness”). But, in between, it is a pure sense of life, a belief, a common, which I have suggested as a belief morphed into knowledge, that overwhelms and blurs all else. My explorations here have started</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>233</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>247</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1g69wbt.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
