<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">ML3800.K73 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Music</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy and aesthetics</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Musicology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Knowledge, Theory of</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Music</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Thought of Music</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Kramer</surname>
               <given-names>Lawrence</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>12</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780520288799</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780520963627</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0520963628</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Oakland, California</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Regents of the University of California</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/j.ctt19cc225"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>What, exactly, is knowledge of music? And what does it tell us about humanistic knowledge in general?<italic>The Thought of Music</italic>grapples directly with these fundamental questions-questions especially compelling at a time when humanistic knowledge is enmeshed in debates about its character and future. In this third volume in a trilogy on musical understanding that includes<italic>Interpreting Music</italic>and<italic>Expression and Truth</italic>, Lawrence Kramer seeks answers in both thought<italic>about</italic>music and thought<italic>in</italic>music-thinking in tones. He skillfully assesses musical scholarship in the aftermath of critical musicology and musical hermeneutics and in view of more recent concerns with embodiment, affect, and performance. This authoritative and timely work challenges the prevailing conceptions of every topic it addresses: language, context, and culture; pleasure and performance; and, through music, the foundations of understanding in the humanities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="224"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                     <subtitle>THE THOUGHT OF MUSIC</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Music and the Forms of Thought</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So: what do we know about music? What do we think we know? What kind of knowledge is that and what is its relationship to other kinds? As I write, thinking about music has passed through almost a quarter-century of intellectual ferment. Has anything been settled? What do we want to know? What should we be asking these days?</p>
                     <p>Much recent work, both pro and con, suggests that one thing we should be asking—still—is this: What does music have to do with ideas? The form of the question implies that the ideas at issue are not ideas about</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>Speaking of Music:</title>
                     <subtitle>IN SEARCH OF AN IDIOM</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Thinking musically entails speaking musically, but what does speaking musically entail? The burden of this chapter is to say that, like thinking musically, speaking musically is something done both<italic>about</italic>music and<italic>by</italic>music.</p>
                     <p>Speaking of music is also speaking<italic>for</italic>music, not in the sense of appropriation or ventriloquism, though neither can be entirely ruled out, but in the sense of acting with care or concern, of speaking on music’s behalf. With music, as with anything else, speech, language, may be deferred but it cannot be avoided. But that necessity settles nothing by itself. Speaking of music may be</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>The Ineffable and How (Not) to Say It</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Musicology is now well into its second revolution in as many decades. So it seems, at any rate, from a North American perspective. When the 1990s ushered in critical musicology, the so-called New Musicology, with its cultural and hermeneutic interests, the more introverted vocabularies that had long set the terms of musical understanding began to break down. Talk about music took on forms previously limited or prohibited; it made sense in terms that would formerly have been spurned as nonsense. The old vocabularies were sometimes put to new uses and sometimes put in the attic. Music thus entered the world,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Pleasure and Valuation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The title<italic>The Thought of Music</italic>might seem to indicate a primarily conceptual orientation, something that has been strongly evident in the preceding chapters. Chapter 1 concerned itself with conceptual questions directly by focusing on ideas, and the succeeding two chapters continued that concern by focusing on language, which, insofar as it makes sense—and it doesn’t always—is permeated with conceptuality. But music is obviously also a sensory medium. Music thinks in feelings, and thinking about music and with music must take account of that. The sensory force of music—sensory knowledge, sensory memory—is also obviously a force</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>The Cultural Field:</title>
                     <subtitle>BEYOND CONTEXT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have now come to a threshold. Regardless of whether the preceding chapters have examined musical knowledge via concepts, language, or sensation, the knowledge proposed has always been culturally inflected. What else could it have been? Musical knowledge is cultural knowledge. That is so virtually by definition. Or it would be, if we could somehow stabilize the protean term<italic>culture</italic>. Culture is something—a word, an idea, a metaphor—that we cannot seem to do without but that we always ask to do too much work for us. For present purposes, the term may be taken to denote the loose</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Virtuosity, Reading, Authorship:</title>
                     <subtitle>A GENEALOGY</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1840 Josef Danhauser painted a famous picture of Liszt at the piano that now hangs in the Alte Nationalgalerie Berlin. Liszt’s audience consists primarily of famous composers (Paganini, Rossini) and authors (Sand, Hugo, de Musset); he also has a silent auditor in a large bust of Beethoven that sits in the window at the upper right. The bust is prominent enough to suggest that it is Beethoven’s music that Liszt is playing, a suggestion that also makes good historical sense. If so, the picture is also a puzzle. The mingling of composers and authors in the scene makes an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>The Newer Musicology?</title>
                     <subtitle>CONTEXT, PERFORMANCE, AND THE MUSICAL WORK</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The vicissitudes of authorship revisited in chapter 6 point to a larger issue. Since around 2000 there has been a lot of musicological effort lavished on the “workconcept” and the competing claims of the fixed, authoritative musical work and the creative act of performance, mostly to the detriment of the work. Like most such binary quarrels, this one reveals a little and obscures a lot. It certainly oversimplifies the historical situation, which is full of complex instances in which the roles of the work—as inscription, conception, or instruction—and of performance—as animation, interpretation, or reproduction—meet, mix, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>POSTSCRIPT:</title>
                     <subtitle>IMAGINING THE SCORE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The musical score is iconic in classical music. Only with the score can fully composed music, musical works, be transmitted intact for realization in multiple performances. The score, one would think, is a wonderful invention. But in recent years the score has lost a good measure of the authority and prestige that once seemed to accrue to it automatically. For some, at any rate, the chief features of the score are its incompleteness and imprecision, up to and including a fundamental falseness.</p>
                     <p>The indictment has many counts. Scores always leave out something essential; they are never wholly unambiguous; they seek</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF NAMES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>199</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt19cc225.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX OF CONCEPTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
