<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1647ckf</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P96.W352 U553 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War in mass media</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Mass media and war</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">War and society</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">United States</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">History</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject content-type="lcsh">21st century</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>In/visible War</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Culture of War in Twenty-first-Century America</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">EDITED BY</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SIMONS</surname>
               <given-names>JON</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>LUCAITES</surname>
               <given-names>JOHN LOUIS</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>14</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813585383</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813585406</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0813585406</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Brunswick, Camden, Newark, New Jersey; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Rutgers, The State University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pv89fv"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>
            <italic>In/Visible War</italic>addresses a paradox of twenty-first century American warfare. The contemporary visual American experience of war is ubiquitous, and yet war is simultaneously invisible or absent; we lack a lived sense that "America" is at war. This paradox of in/visibility concerns the gap between the experiences of war zones and the visual, mediated experience of war in public, popular culture, which absents and renders invisible the former. Large portions of the domestic public experience war only at a distance. For these citizens, war seems abstract, or may even seem to have disappeared altogether due to a relative absence of visual images of casualties. Perhaps even more significantly, wars can be fought without sacrifice by the vast majority of Americans.Yet, the normalization of twenty-first century war also renders it highly visible. War is made visible through popular, commercial, mediated culture. The spectacle of war occupies the contemporary public sphere in the forms of celebrations at athletic events and in films, video games, and other media, coming together as MIME, the Military-Industrial-Media-Entertainment Network.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="286"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Paradox of War’s In/visibility</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LUCAITES</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN LOUIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SIMONS</surname>
                           <given-names>JON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Those born in the United States in the twenty-first century—or at least subsequent to September 11, 2001—have never known a time at which the nation was not at war. This in itself is not so strange, as the United States has been at war for 93 percent of its history.¹ The conflicts in Afghanistan and Iraq stand out as what we might consider traditional, full-scale wars measured by the invasion and occupation of national territories by air and ground forces supported by nation-states. But these confrontations are the least of it, because the United States has also been</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>HOW PHOTOJOURNALISM HAS FRAMED THE WAR IN AFGHANISTAN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>CAMPBELL</surname>
                           <given-names>DAVID</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Images are central to contemporary geopolitics. We encounter other people and places in a “field of perceptible reality” that is enacted by visual representations, making some things visible while rendering others invisible.¹ Photographs, paintings, video, film, computer games—each and every pictorial artifact—helps establish what can be represented and how it can be shown. In turn, those images are made possible by a series of historical, cultural, and political frames or infrastructures.²</p>
                     <p>In this essay I consider how one set of pictorial artifacts—the contemporary war images of photojournalism—were produced in Afghanistan during U.S. military operations there. In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>RETURNING SOLDIERS AND THE IN/VISIBILITY OF COMBAT TRAUMA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GILBERT</surname>
                           <given-names>CHRISTOPHER J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>LUCAITES</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHN LOUIS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The signs and symptoms of combat trauma are all around us: in images of troops under attack on the battlefield; in photographs of resuscitative and surgical procedures performed in the line of duty; in pictures of soldiers in combat fatigues affecting the thousand-yard stare; in videos of families grieving over a loved one, now a military casualty; in snapshots of wounded warriors, their damaged bodies, their severed limbs, their prostheses; and in statistics that report our wartime death toll in terms of veteran suicides. We encounter these tragic effects of war on an almost daily basis if for no other</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>(RE)FASHIONING PTSD’S WARRIOR PROJECT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>GORDON</surname>
                           <given-names>JEREMY G.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On the surface, veteran trauma is layered with mythic references that make it in/visible to those not materially, literally experiencing it, rendering it legible, but in ways that naturalize and invoke unreflective ways of seeing. Put differently, the struggle with combat trauma is envisioned as a warrior project in which only those who embody a heroic, if not Homeric, ethos are able to take on and defeat the shock, pain, and distress of posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD). Indeed, one does not have to look hard to see how images of Achilles and Odysseus saturate cultural attempts to redress the phenomenon,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>UNREMARKABLE SUFFERING:</title>
                     <subtitle>Banality, Spectatorship, and War’s In/visibilities</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ADELMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>REBECCA A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KOZOL</surname>
                           <given-names>WENDY</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Critics of the U.S. War on Terror have long called for an alternative optic to the relentlessly myopic perspective of American news media. The presumption behind this call to look elsewhere is that doing so will reveal images that are authentic or compelling enough to disabuse American spectators of their ambivalence about the casualties of militarized violence. This logic imagines the grisly “truth” of war to happen somewhere beyond or outside the frame of mainstream representations of combat. What happens, however, when conflict photographers who seek visually graphic and affectively searing images of war find evidence of its banality instead?</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“WAR IS FUN,”</title>
                     <subtitle>A Photo-Essay</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BERMAN</surname>
                           <given-names>NINA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Fans cheer as billion-dollar weapons systems fly over baseball stadiums. Attack helicopters touch down on state parks while families run to greet armed Marines. On beaches and boardwalks, military recruiters teach children to aim assault rifles. An armored vehicle arrives in Times Square. Crowds dance to “Locked and Loaded,” a song by the Air Force rock band. This year’s Navy campaign is #selfiewithasailor.</p>
                     <p>The U.S. military sells its image to the public by sponsoring hundreds of family-friendly events that bring civilians face to face with the nation’s fighting forces. Central to the audience experience is the invitation to participate in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>LAYING BIN LADEN TO REST:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Case Study of Terrorism and the Politics of Visibility</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MADEIRA</surname>
                           <given-names>JODY LYNEÉ</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early on the morning of September 11, 2001, nineteen terrorists hijacked four planes and crashed them into the World Trade Center towers, the Pentagon, and a farm field near Shanksville, Pennsylvania. The attacks killed 2,996 people and spawned a global “War on Terror” in Iraq and Afghanistan. Al-Qaeda claimed responsibility for the 9/11 attacks; U.S. forces pursued its leader, Osama bin Laden, for more than nine years and ultimately killed him in a raid on his Abbottabad, Pakistan, compound on May 2, 2011. Following his death, soldiers removed bin Laden’s body and transferred it to the U.S.S.<italic>Carl Vinson</italic>, where</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>DIGITAL WAR AND THE PUBLIC MIND:</title>
                     <subtitle>Call of Duty Reloaded, Decoded</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>STAHL</surname>
                           <given-names>ROGER</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the dozen years since 9/11, the U.S. War on Terror has kept pace, complementing troop draw-downs in Afghanistan and Iraq with drone strikes that have expanded to at least six countries, sweeping surveillance of the global digital grid, and traditional air strikes in Libya and Syria. At the same time, however, the war has faded to invisibility as these conflicts precipitously dropped from the news screen. Beginning in 2005, the occupations of Iraq and Afghanistan migrated from lead story to background noise. By this time, reporters had disembedded en masse, handing over their significantly attenuated role as the “fourth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>A CINEMA OF CONSOLATION:</title>
                     <subtitle>Post-9/11 Super-Invasion Fantasy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KILGORE</surname>
                           <given-names>DE WITT DOUGLAS</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The striking thing about September 11, 2001, and the War on Terror that followed is the way in which a spectacular event was momentarily rendered invisible, placed beyond the seeable either by reason of its traumatic visibility or by responses to the political history of images inherited from previous conflicts—especially the Vietnam War. In the month following 9/11, the American film industry became embroiled in a moral panic about what to do with the iconic, cinematic visibility of the New York City skyline. One initial solution was to digitally excise the World Trade Center Towers (WTC).¹ This brief banishment</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>DIFFERENTIAL CONFIGURATIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>In/visibility Through the Lens of Kathryn Bigelow’s The Hurt Locker (2008)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BREGER</surname>
                           <given-names>CLAUDIA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The critical reception of Kathryn Bigelow’s<italic>The Hurt Locker</italic>(2008) presents a puzzle. Although Bigelow’s more recent<italic>Zero Dark Thirty</italic>(2011) stirred significant controversy for its representation of torture during the “Wars on Terror,”<italic>The Hurt Locker</italic>, which focuses on a three-man bomb defusal team in Iraq, was almost exclusively greeted with praise.¹ Not only did the film earn six Academy Awards, including those for Best Director and Best Picture, along with many other accolades, it also was an overwhelming critical success—although most commentators agreed that the film’s visceral images of a series of dangerous bomb deactivation operations do</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>THE CANINE-RESCUE NARRATIVE, CIVILIAN CASUALTIES, AND THE LONG GULF WAR</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BOSE</surname>
                           <given-names>PURNIMA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In recent years, a new genre of memoirs of U.S. soldiers serving in Iraq has emerged that foregrounds a softer side of military intervention, which takes as its primary subject matter a soldier’s strong attachment to a stray dog and the challenges of bringing this canine companion safely back to the United States. Sporting such titles as<italic>From Baghdad, With Love: A Marine, the War, and a Dog Named Lava</italic>and its sequel<italic>From Baghdad to America: Life after War for a Marine and His Rescued Dog</italic>, as well as<italic>Welcome Home, Mama and Boris: How a Sister’s Love Saved</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>THE IN/VISIBILITY OF LIBERAL PEACE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Perpetual Peace and Enduring Freedom</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SIMONS</surname>
                           <given-names>JON</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Episode 7 of the first season of<italic>The Newsroom</italic>, a TV drama created by Aaron Sorkin, the news breaks that Osama bin Laden has been killed.¹<italic>The Newsroom</italic>is an enactment of the American liberal imaginary showing an idealized version of television journalism fit for liberal democracy.² The opening credits for Season 1 are “a montage of great moments in the history of TV journalism” that evokes a past, golden age.³ Sorkin admits to portraying “a romanticized, idealized newsroom” in his script that delivers a message that “corporate concerns and ratings-chasings have left the US with an embarrassingly skewed,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>WHY WAR?</title>
                     <subtitle>Derrida, Baudrillard, and the Absolute Televisual Image</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>RUBENSTEIN</surname>
                           <given-names>DIANE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On February 19, 2003, shortly before the start of the war in Iraq and immediately following mass antiwar demonstrations the prior weekend, French psychoanalyst René Major organized an impromptu roundtable discussion between Jacques Derrida and Jean Baudrillard concerning the likelihood and stakes of future hostilities in the Gulf¹ (fig. 11.1). The debate was structured around a series of questions, formulated by René Major, to serve as an introduction to each author’s thought concerning war and its representation.² Would a war take place (<italic>avoir lieu</italic>)? What would such a taking place consist of in light of “live” television coverage? Was war</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>WAR IN THE TWENTY-FIRST CENTURY:</title>
                     <subtitle>Visible, Invisible, or Superpositional?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>DER DERIAN</surname>
                           <given-names>JAMES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Early in the twenty-first century, late one evening, war took an interest in me. The first feint came in an e-mail, an invitation to address a conference in Australia on “War 2.0.” Unlike most numerically annotated wars signifying duration or repetition, “2.0” clearly intended a new, different, and possibly improved version of organized violence. Upon opening, however, the attached invitation disappeared in the blink of an eye behind a pop-up message of menace: “Warning: Security software updates are now available for your computer. Cancel or Accept.”</p>
                     <p>The pair of messages triggered more than a few questions about wars visible and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lucaites</surname>
                           <given-names>John Louis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Simons</surname>
                           <given-names>Jon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES ON CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>267</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PHOTO CREDITS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv89fv.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
