<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PR3562 .F64 2003</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">MILTON, JOHN, 1608–1674. PARADISE LOST</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">CHRISTIAN POERTY, ENGLISH</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">HISTORY AND CRITICISM</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">EPIC POERTY, ENGLISH</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">HISTORY AND CRITICISM</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">MILTON, JOHN, 1608–1674</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">CHARACTERS</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">DEVIL</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">DEVIL IN LITERATURE</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">EVIL IN LITERATURE</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Satanic Epic</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FORSYTH</surname>
               <given-names>NEIL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780691113395</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">0691113394</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781400825233</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>PRINCETON; OXFORD</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2003</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>PRINCETON UNIVERSITY PRESS</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt7rwjm"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The Satan of<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>has fascinated generations of readers. This book attempts to explain how and why Milton's Satan is so seductive. It reasserts the importance of Satan against those who would minimize the poem's sympathy for the devil and thereby make Milton orthodox.</p>
         <p>Neil Forsyth argues that William Blake got it right when he called Milton a true poet because he was "of the Devils party" even though he set out "to justify the ways of God to men." In seeking to learn why Satan is so alluring, Forsyth ranges over diverse topics--from the origins of evil and the relevance of witchcraft to the status of the poetic narrator, the epic tradition, the nature of love between the sexes, and seventeenth-century astronomy. He considers each of these as Milton introduces them: as Satanic subjects.</p>
         <p>Satan emerges as the main challenge to Christian belief. It is Satan who questions and wonders and denounces. He is the great doubter who gives voice to many of the arguments that Christianity has provoked from within and without. And by rooting his Satanic reading of<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>in Biblical and other sources, Forsyth retrieves not only an attractive and heroic Satan but a Milton whose heretical energies are embodied in a Satanic character with a life of his own.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="408"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Paradise Lost</italic>is not an orthodox poem and it needs to be rescued from its orthodox critics. This book contends that the best way back to the poem Milton composed, rather than the one the orthodox would have us read, is to reassert the importance of Satan, heretic and hater. I shall be doing this in various ways. One is through revising the history of the Satan that Milton reimagines for us, since a mistaken idea about it has been widely accepted in recent years. It is the combat myth, I argue, that has always been at the center of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>A BRIEF HISTORY OF SATAN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the middle books of<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>, Adam and Eve listen to the angel Raphael’s story of the war between God’s troops and the rebel angels. They are filled</p>
                     <p>With admiration, and deep Muse to heare</p>
                     <p>Of things so high and strange, things to thir thought</p>
                     <p>So unimaginable as hate in Heav’n,</p>
                     <p>And Warr so neer the Peace of God in bliss</p>
                     <p>With such confusion.</p>
                     <p>(PL 7.52–56)</p>
                     <p>The story is beyond them. That hate in Heaven is “unimaginable” points to the role of Milton’s Satan and to the problem he poses his audience. Evil arises in bliss. The phrase</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>THE EPIC VOICE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In André Gide’s<italic>Les Faux-Monnayeurs</italic>(<italic>The Counterfeiters</italic>) the “demon” who appears in the first paragraph may be read as a figure for the text itself in all its sinuous and self-reflexive turns. What is obvious in the case of a modernist and experimental novel, however, may take a little more demonstration if we are to make a similar case for Milton’s epic. Clearly Satan is the figure who begins the story. But what of the narration itself?</p>
                     <p>In the first books of the poem, Satan and narration are closely related. Almost as soon as the poem gets under way, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>FOLLOW THE LEADER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>114</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The adversarial relation between narrator and Satan is less insistent and even harder to discern after the Hell scenes of the opening books. And indeed the authority of the narrator, as I have tried to show, may itself be questioned. The poem even encourages us to do so. There is a curious example to which Stanley Fish (unfortunately for his argument) calls attention in the preface to the second edition of<italic>Surprised By Sin</italic>. He calls it “an apparently small moment in Book II.” Satan has just thrown himself into the “wilde Abyss” (2.910) and begun his journey to our</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>“MY SELF AM HELL”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>147</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The eminent biologist, Richard Lewontin, once wrote that however important Aristotelian rhetorical analysis may be for the history of science, it will not tell us why we accept what we otherwise would not believe simply because it is well put. His example is Milton’s Satan:</p>
                     <p>Although every moral and political conviction I have speaks against it, I am nearly driven by Milton’s insidious poetry to believe that it is “Better to reign in Hell than serve in Heaven.” (PL 1.263) For a pedagogical Aristotle this would be a particularly fine example of an “antithesis” in the “periodic” mode dissected in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>SATAN’S REBELLION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Paradise Lost</italic>establishes first its concern with firsts. “Say first what cause,” it urges the Muse, a phrase that invokes its own originals, the classical epics of Homer, Hesiod, and Vergil, which also tell about origins, and ask about initiating causes—for the universe itself in the case of Hesiod.<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>is thus not shy about claiming to be a song of origins—especially and even in its first line about the origin of error, of what went wrong.</p>
                     <p>In this respect it recalls the ritual practice of certain shamans reported by Mircea Eliade. When someone falls sick, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>The Language of “Evil”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>188</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The ambivalence of Satan’s relation to evil is important for the meaning of the poem. As we have seen, he explicitly rejects Michael’s term “evil” for the War in Heaven, which “wee style / The strife of Glorie” (6.289–90). And when, for the only time, he is called “the Evil one,” it is at the very moment when he stands “Stupidly good” (9.465) abstracted “From his own evil.”¹ Nonetheless the poem is about the origin of evil, and in this chapter I shall investigate the scrupulous ways in which Milton deploys what he knew to be the various sources</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>OF MANS FIRST DIS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter, I analyzed some of the words for “evil” that Milton deploys in strategic ways throughout the poem. Now it is time to notice that, beyond the specific words that “mean” evil or Satan, there is a network of echoing sounds and words that extends and complicates the Satanic focus of the epic. And it begins at the beginning. That remarkable forward shift of stresses in the opening pentameter of<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>places special emphasis on the first syllable of the long word “disobedience.”</p>
                     <p>The sound of the line initiates a series of<italic>calembours</italic>that makes the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>HOMER IN MILTON:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE ATTENDANCE MOTIF AND THE GRACES</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we turn the coin, from “disgrace” back to “grace.” Milton draws various parallels between Eve and Homer’s graceful heroines. Helen, for example, refers to herself as the cause of the Trojan War and wishes she had preferred death to Paris (e.g.,<italic>Iliad</italic>3.173). In her regret at what has happened, Eve, too, wishes for death, indeed proposes a suicide pact (PL 10.1001). She also refers to herself as a “snare” for Adam, and goes on to wonder at the irony in her name: “That I who first brought Death on all, am grac’t / The sourse of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>SATAN TEMPTER</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The well-known anthropologist Ruth Finnegan, author of important books such as<italic>Oral Literature in Africa</italic>and<italic>Oral Poetry</italic>, did her initial fieldwork among the Limba people of Sierra Leone. She spent a lot of time collecting their traditions, especially their tales, for her thesis. One day they told her, now its your turn. We’ve told you lots of our stories, now you tell us one of yours. She protested briefly, but then chose to tell them the story of Adam and Eve. They listened politely but made little comment at the time. Two years later she went back to Sierra</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>“IF THEY WILL HEAR”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>285</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The high point of<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>as the Satanic epic is the entanglement with the text that I have attempted to show is our experience of Book 9. Yet it is one of the paradoxes of the poem that, in the very aftermath of Satan’s success, the poem manages to detach itself from the dominance of Satan, and continues thereafter as a very different, and what some readers find a much duller, poem. The change happens in Book 10. The two plots, divine and earthly, linked in Book 9, now diverge, and we see by contrasts. While Satan returns in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>AT THE SIGN OF THE DOVE AND SERPENT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>301</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We have just been exploring the contrasting but related activity of the poem’s two protagonists, Son and Satan, in Book 10. This opposition, which is essential to the combat myth Milton is retelling, is actually signalled very early in the poem and pervades it from then on. But so many things are happening in the first few lines of<italic>Paradise Lost</italic>that we are in danger of missing the wood for the trees. Thus we may miss the fact, obvious enough when we think about it, that the narration places two symbolic animals close to the beginning. First, as the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>“FULL OF DOUBT I STAND”:</title>
                     <subtitle>THE STRUCTURES OF Paradise Lost</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>314</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Paradise Lost</italic>was published in two different editions during Milton’s life. The first edition of 1667 appeared in ten books, the second of 1674 in twelve. Apart from some fifteen new lines, there were no other important changes between the two editions, yet the alteration of its external form shifts the way in which one perceives the poem’s informing structure, what Aristotle called the<italic>mythos</italic>. The longest books of the first edition were the last four. These were divided into six for<italic>1674</italic>. Most of the extra lines also occur in the second half of the poem, changes that had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Conclusion:</title>
                     <subtitle>Signs Portentous</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>329</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the comet Hale-Bopp made its graceful way across our skies in 1998, most informed people were impressed by its beauty and curious about the science. But a few people were driven by religious fanatics to various tragic episodes of mass-suicide. They read the comet as a message, which they interpreted in the conventional way as a sign of the Apocalypse. The contrast between these two kinds of reaction to astronomical phenomena is discernible already in the seventeenth century. But the proportions would have been quite different: a majority would have taken the religious view, even some members of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7rwjm.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
