<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PN3331.H35 2014</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Fiction</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">History and criticism</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Theory, etc.</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>What Is Fiction For?</book-title>
         <subtitle>Literary Humanism Restored</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Harrison</surname>
               <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>29</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780253014061</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780253014122</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0253014123</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Indiana University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Bloomington; Indianapolis</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Bernard Harrison</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gzkgb"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How can literature, which consists of nothing more than the description of imaginary events and situations, offer any insight into the workings of "human reality" or "the human condition"? Can mere words illuminate something that we call "reality"? Bernard Harrison answers these questions in this profoundly original work that seeks to re-enfranchise reality in the realms of art and discourse. In an ambitious account of the relationship between literature and cognition, he seeks to show how literary fiction, by deploying words against a background of imagined circumstances, allows us to focus on the roots, in social practice, of the meanings by which we represent our world and ourselves. Engaging with philosophers and theorists as diverse as Wittgenstein, Sartre, Merleau-Ponty, Foucault, Derrida, F. R. Leavis, Cleanth Brooks, and Stanley Fish, and illustrating his ideas through readings of works by Swift, Woolf, Appelfeld, and Dickens, among others, this book presents a systematic defense of humanism in literary studies, and of the study of the Humanities more generally, by a distinguished scholar.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="622"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harrison</surname>
                           <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xxv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>HUMANISTIC LITERARY CRITICISM, THE TRADITION SHARED both by academic critics of the stamp of Lionel Trilling, F. R. Leavis, Northrop Frye, or M. H. Abrams, and by independent writers and literary intellectuals of the caliber of Edmund Wilson, George Orwell, T. S. Eliot, D. H. Lawrence, E. M. Forster, Virginia Woolf, or Cynthia Ozick, took it for granted that major creative literature constitutes one of our main resources for critical reflection on the human condition, both individual and cultural. For the past half century that tradition has found itself under sustained attack from a generation of literary theorists whose main</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>Humanism and Its Discontents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of literature in universities – “humane letters,” as it was once quaintly known – has traditionally been held to belong, along with history, and for that matter with philosophy in its most central aspects, to “the humanities.” T.hat term trades on the common distinction between the natural world, the world of birds and beasts, stone, stars, and the sea, and the human world, the world of politics, religious beliefs, sexual and familial practices, cultural institutions, beliefs, loves, hatreds, hopes, and fears. The former, we tend to think, is the province of the natural sciences; the latter is that of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>The Mirror of Nature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>40</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Taking our philosophical umbrella firmly in hand, in the manner of the British Museum vandal of 1845, we have duly smashed the Portland Vase. Let us now see if we can put it together again.</p>
                     <p>As we have just seen, one of the most striking features of the assault on literary humanism over the past half century is the apparent diversity it displays, both in its general sources and in the detailed battery of charges brought against humanism. The main sources are three in number: There is the assault on behalf of “the sciences” (physical or social as the case</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>Truth, Meaning, and Human Reality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Our task in this chapter is to find a persuasive reply, one that does without mimeticism, to the discordant chorus of charges against literary humanism I have outlined. It is not easy to know where to begin. The problem is not only that, in the equally bewildering array of arguments underpinning the main charges against literary humanism, it is difficult to distinguish those whose centrality makes them most worthy of attack. Matters are made still worse by the fact that the claims traditionally regarded as fundamental to literary humanism, here summarized as CIC and the six claims of literature study,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Leavis and Wittgenstein (1):</title>
                     <subtitle>A Living Language</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The main lines of the defense of literary humanism offered in chapter 3 were originally worked out in a series of essays that were the basis for some of the later chapters in this book. When I wrote them, my acquaintance with the work of F. R. Leavis was minimal. Readers of these essays were not long in pointing out to me, however, that some of the notions developed in them – notably, that of literature as one of the main activities involved in the constitution of “human worlds” – bear a strong family resemblance to related ideas advanced, with similar goals</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>Leavis and Wittgenstein (2):</title>
                     <subtitle>The “Third Realm”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>124</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although the issue of reductive clarity versus semantic complexity is central to Leavis’s discomfort with what the French like to call<italic>l’esprit cartésien</italic>, his quarrel with Descartes by no means ends there. Still more central to Leavis’s thought is his resistance to Cartesian dualism. Descartes’s most enduring achievement was to saddle subsequent Western thought with the idea that the world contains two radically different kinds of thing – material objects and minds – which are known to us in radically different ways. The material world, the world of trees and mountains, stone and water, is accessible in common to numerous observers. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>Nature and Artifice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>170</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Part 1 proposed a new theoretical basis for the ancient idea that in major creative literature the manipulation of language in the context of a poem or fictional narrative can suffice to throw light on something worth calling real. Its central pillar is an account of meaning derived from a new reading of Wittgenstein that departs radically from the traditional account, entrenched for many centuries in Western philosophy, of how language connects with reality. According to that traditional account, to bestow meaning upon a noun is automatically to connect it to reality, since to bestow meaning on a noun is,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Virginia Woolf and “the True Reality”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Have I the power of conveying the true reality?” wrote Virginia Woolf in her diary entry for June 19, 1923. Recent critical theory returns a dusty answer: no writer has, or could even intelligibly envisage having, such a power. It seems to many at present that talk of such a power must necessarily imply what Paul de Man liked to call a specular relationship between the text and something outside it, which we might call in clumsy English “the extratextual” or, following Derrida and in only slightly less clumsy French, the “<italic>hors-texte</italic>.” In an obvious sense, of course, what is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Aharon Appelfeld and the Problem of Holocaust Fiction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The problem many find with literary fiction about the Holocaust is that it is fiction. Such fiction presents us, therefore, no doubt among other more important things, with a further challenge to bring the arguments concerning fiction and reality that occupied us in part 1 down from the abstract empyrean of philosophical debate to the firm ground of practical literary criticism.</p>
                     <p>The thought that governs our discomfort with the idea of writing fiction about the Holocaust is primarily a moral one, but it is also one with epistemic implications lurking in its depths. We feel ourselves under a duty to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>The Limits of Authorial License in Our Mutual Friend</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>262</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To expose the intimate connections between intellectual confidence and selective blindness, it is often sufficient to confront current certainties with the exploded convictions of a vanished age. In this Pickwickian sense, G. K. Chesterton’s 1911 essay on<italic>Our Mutual Friend</italic>remains a useful companion to the novel.¹ Chesterton is as convinced that literature is “referential,” that its prime business is to represent reality, as we are that it is not. He celebrates Dickens for many things, but always, and centrally, for the accuracy of his descriptions of manners: “The particular kind of chaos that is created by the hospitality of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>Reactive versus Interpretive Criticism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>290</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In part 1 of this book I presented a general case in favor of the traditional humanist assumption that major creative literature is of<italic>cognitive</italic>value – of value, among other things, for “what it can teach us” about “the human condition.” And in part 2, in the course of rerunning those arguments in some new contexts designed to bring out further aspects and implications of the general position they define, I offered some concrete examples, with reference to Dickens, Woolf, Appelfeld, and others, of the sort of thing that might in practice constitute, exemplify, the sort of cognitive gain to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Houyhnhnm Virtue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>338</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nineteenth-and twentieth-century criticism has found Book IV of<italic>Gulliver’s Travels</italic>a hard nut to crack. Here is Wayne Booth, sketching in 1961 the outlines of the critical stalemate as it stood at that date:</p>
                     <p>The debate about where Swift stands in the fourth book . . . is apparently as much alive today as it ever was – not because Swift has left any doubt about the presence of irony but because it is very hard to know how much distance there is between Gulliver and Swift and precisely which of the traveller’s enthusiasms for the Houyhnhnms is excessive. Whatever Swift’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Sterne and Sentimentalism</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>368</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Tristram Shandy</italic>is, at the very least, a clever and mildly salacious book. Moreover, it has the annoying trick of involving the reader, willy-nilly, in its salacities: he must grant, however unwillingly, that he knows, and that Sterne was safe in assuming he would know, what a nose is, or what “place” Mrs. Wadman has in mind. It is a disturbing book, then, for a polite age. The discomfort and irritation of the polite reader have broken out from the very beginning in invective against the alleged crudity and moral evasiveness of the book. Leavis’s “nasty trifling” is only the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Reanimating the Author</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>416</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the background of proclamations, by late twentieth-century literary theorists-cum-cultural critics, of “the death of the author,” and in the last analysis motivating them, stand the two traditional doctrines of Marxism mentioned briefly in section 2 of chapter 1. The first is the doctrine that culture per se is causally ineffective – a mere reflection, or epiphenomenon, of the underlying realities of exploitation and class conflict that actually govern historical change. The second is the connected, though not wholly consistent doctrine that the primary functions of the institutions of culture are<italic>ideological</italic>in the Marxist sense of that term. That is,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>Persons and Narratives</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>446</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Don’t philosophise by allusion,” wrote Iris Murdoch on an undergraduate essay by an Oxford friend of mine, who subsequently, whether by following his tutor’s advice or by natural processes of maturation, discovered his own voice, began to give vent to a powerful flow of robust and idiosyncratic argument of his own invention, and became in due course a moderately distinguished figure in his own right.</p>
                     <p>Since the Renaissance, such a process has been standard in the formation of European intellectuals. To “find oneself” and “to find one’s own voice” are near-synonyms to this way of thinking, and what both posit</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>Reading and Reading-In</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>476</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is a central presupposition of humanism that a language and its literature are the common property of anyone who speaks the language and cares to read books. Such people constitute a “community” only in the sense of a community of common interests. What connects them, the humanist holds, is not a common doctrine or a common set of principles, let alone a set of laws, institutions, or – God forbid! – institutional criteria for admission to some charmed circle of initiates, but merely a common willingness to look at each new book, as far as possible, with fresh eyes, a desire</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>Meaning It Literally:</title>
                     <subtitle>Derrida and His Critics Revisited</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>508</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Derrida’s essay “La mythologie blanche” was originally published in<italic>Poétiques S</italic>(1971) and reappeared as the longest of the eleven essays in<italic>Marges de la philosophie</italic>(<italic>Les éditions de minuit</italic>, 1972), essays that, in various ways and from various directions, “argue their way through a rigorous and consequential treatment of the various blind spots, aporias or antinomies that characterise the discourse of philosophic reason.”¹ Its topic is, broadly speaking, the place of metaphor in philosophical discourse.</p>
                     <p>The title is taken from Anatole France’s acidly witty dialogue “Ariste and Polyphile; or, the Language of Metaphysics,” from<italic>The Garden of Epicurus</italic>.² Polyphile</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Telling the Great from the Good</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>541</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Part of my purpose in this book, as set out in chapter 1, has been to defend academic literary studies as a cornerstone of the humanities. That can hardly be done unless it can be shown that some works of literature are more worth studying than others, because they are<italic>better as literature</italic>than others. Why, otherwise, spend time and energy discussing Shakespeare or Sterne with students; why allocate the funds to support the departments, the journals, and the postgraduate research that constitute the essential infrastructure of such teaching if those students’ time might as well be spent in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>553</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>571</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>581</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gzkgb.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>594</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
