<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GV1469.3.V565 2015</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Video games</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Video games</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Cross-cultural studies</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Technology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Video Games Around the World</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wolf</surname>
               <given-names>Mark J. P.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="foreword-author" id="contrib2">
            <role>FOREWORD BY</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>IWATANI</surname>
               <given-names>TORU</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780262527163</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780262328487</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0262328488</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>The MIT Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts; London, England</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt17kk7tc"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Video games have become a global industry, and their history spans dozens of national industries where foreign imports compete with domestic productions, legitimate industry contends with piracy, and national identity faces the global marketplace. This volume describes video game history and culture across every continent, with essays covering areas as disparate and far-flung as Argentina and Thailand, Hungary and Indonesia, Iran and Ireland. Most of the essays are written by natives of the countries they discuss, many of them game designers and founders of game companies, offering distinctively firsthand perspectives. Some of these national histories appear for the first time in English, and some for the first time in any language.Readers will learn, for example, about the rapid growth of mobile games in Africa; how a meat-packing company held the rights to import the Atari VCS 2600 into Mexico; and how the Indonesian MMORPG<italic>Nusantara Online</italic>reflects that country's cultural history and folklore. Every country or region's unique conditions provide the context that shapes its national industry; for example, the long history of computer science in the United Kingdom and Scandinavia, the problems of piracy in China, the PC Bangs of South Korea, or the Dutch industry's emphasis on serious games. As these essays demonstrate, local innovation and diversification thrive alongside productions and corporations with global aspirations.Africa • Arab World • Argentina • Australia • Austria • Brazil • Canada • China • Colombia • Czech Republic • Finland • France • Germany • Hong Kong • Hungary • India • Indonesia • Iran • Ireland • Italy • Japan • Mexico • The Netherlands • New Zealand • Peru • Poland • Portugal • Russia • Scandinavia • Singapore • South Korea • Spain • Switzerland • Thailand • Turkey • United Kingdom • United States of America • Uruguay • Venezuela</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="720"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FOREWORD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Iwatani</surname>
                           <given-names>Toru</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <role>translated by</role>
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hartzheim</surname>
                           <given-names>Bryan Hikari</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Video games today are often played largely for personal use on smartphones, but if we look at the history of gaming, we see that people played games very differently, in arcades—amusement centers that were once a staple of every city. These arcades date back to the coin-operated Edison parlors that first emerged in the United States during the 1890s. In these amusement centers, customers would insert coins into machines for music and visual entertainment.</p>
                     <p>If we look back at the changes that media such as computers, phones, and video games have undergone, we can see how computers migrated from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xv</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wolf</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark J. P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the enormous growth of the World Wide Web in the last two decades, the rise of mobile platforms and casual games, and an increasing number of game creation programs, the entrance requirements to the global video game industry are lower than ever. Small video game companies are appearing all around the world, each hoping for a hit that will bring it international attention and fame, both of which can grow much faster due to the Internet. With this rise in game production, many more countries have their own video game industries and their own national histories of video games,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AFRICA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kirinya</surname>
                           <given-names>Wesley</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>17</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Games in general have been an integral part of African culture, just like any other culture in the world. Most games were created not just for fun, but also as tools to preserve culture and educate the young in the community. They were usually played on special occasions and ceremonies. For example, just before a woman becomes a wife, her father will ask her and her sisters to cover themselves. The groom will then be faced with the “strategic” task of picking out his bride.</p>
                     <p>There is not much on record regarding games in most African countries for the last</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ARAB WORLD</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kasmiya</surname>
                           <given-names>Radwan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>[<italic>Editor’s note: Originally, in the early planning stages of this book, Radwan Kasmiya, game designer and cofounder of the company Falafel Games (established in 2011 with Vince Ghossoub), had planned to write a chapter on video games in the Arab World; however, due to the political instability of his native Syria and the resulting upheavals that followed, he and his family were forced to flee as refugees, a harsh reminder that the relative peace and tranquility necessary for academic research to occur is still not something enjoyed by all. I had asked Radwan to write this essay since he had</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ARGENTINA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Horacek</surname>
                           <given-names>Graciela Alicia Esnaola</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Iparraguirre</surname>
                           <given-names>Alejandro</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Averbuj</surname>
                           <given-names>Guillermo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib4" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Oulton</surname>
                           <given-names>María Luján</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Argentina over the last thirty years, the consumption of technology in general, and video games in particular, has increased due to the new distribution platforms (social networks) and the massive use of mobile devices (such as tablets and smartphones). These “cultural products” (Garcia Canclini 1999) have allowed millions of users to be connected online simultaneously. These global technologies helped digital games become a mass-consumption product.</p>
                     <p>Argentine research from 2005 to 2011¹ discovered that video games account for 70% of the cultural consumption of youths age ten to eighteen years old. The profile of the typical gamer has changed and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AUSTRALIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Apperley</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Golding</surname>
                           <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Australia has experienced a relatively long history of local game development, which in recent years has been quite turbulent, but not without promise from emerging models of game development. For many years, Australia also experienced a unique—and arbitrary, possibly draconian—system of digital game classification, which has only recently been changed to measures that are more similar to those found in other Western democracies. It is for these two issues that Australia is primarily known in digital gaming circles. It may therefore appear somewhat paradoxical that a country with high-tech innovative studios—such as<italic>LA Noire</italic>(2011) developers Team</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>AUSTRIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mitgutsch</surname>
                           <given-names>Konstantin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rosenstingl</surname>
                           <given-names>Herbert</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2005, at its peak, the Rockstar Games subsidiary Rockstar Vienna was one of the biggest game development studios in Germany and Austria, with over one hundred employees. In the late 1990s, the Austrian game developer Max Design surprised the games market by selling over two million copies of<italic>Anno 1602</italic>(1998), but Rockstar Vienna’s establishment heralded a new era of game development in Austria. At this point in time, the future of Austrian video game development seemed bright. Together with other Austrian game development studios such as JoWooD (established in 1989), Pixlers Entertainment (1991), Greentube (1998), Sproing (2001), Xendex</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BRAZIL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alves</surname>
                           <given-names>Lynn Rosalina Gama</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Brazil, the history of video games began in the 1980s when the first video game appeared on store shelves. According to Chiado (2011, 26), the first Atari VCS (1977), “half mounted and half manufactured in Sao Paulo,” reached stores in April 1980. Joseph Maghrabi, a 1980s entrepreneur, was instrumental in bringing video games to Brazil and created Channel 3, a pioneering club that manufactured game cartridges. As Maghrabi stated in an interview, “Before creating Channel 3, I founded the Atari Electronics Company. It was for the importing of devices and accessories of the Atari console. We imported the printed</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CANADA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Arsenault</surname>
                           <given-names>Dominic</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Guay</surname>
                           <given-names>Louis-Martin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To understand the development and importance of video games in Canada, a few geographical and sociological facts must first be pointed out. Canada occupies the northern part of North America and is surrounded by three oceans and its only neighbor, the United States. While Canada is the second-largest country in the world by total area (9,984,670 square kilometers, which is approximately 5% larger than the United States’ 9,526,468 square kilometers), it has a relatively small population of approximately 34 million (Statistics Canada 2012). When compared to the United States’ 2010 population of 308 million (US Census Bureau 2010), it is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CHINA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Anthony Y. H. Fung</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Sara Xueting Liao</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Video games have become an increasingly popular activity in everyday life, especially with the strong growth of online games, which are now the cause of a worldwide mania. In 2010, the revenue of the global game market was USD $52 billion, and it is expected to increase to USD $70 billion in 2017 (DFC Intelligence 2012). A research report from Gartner also foresees that the global gaming industry will even exceed USD $74 billion in 2011 and possibly reach USD $112 billion by 2015 (McCall and van der Meulen 2011).</p>
                     <p>In China, as in other Asian-Pacific areas such as Japan</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>COLOMBIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parra</surname>
                           <given-names>Luis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <collab>Global Game Designers Guild (GGDG)</collab>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of video games in Colombia begins in the 1980s and 1990s, when a group of enthusiastic young people, motivated by classics like the Mario Bros. franchise, started programming short game experiences, recreating games like Tejo, a traditional sport in Colombia. Later on, they would write games using Symbian and Java for the mobile game market. Colombians have had access to the latest games and consoles almost as they appeared in the US market, giving the young enthusiasts the right motivation and role models to push their efforts. These young developers later became the pioneers of an entertainment industry</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CZECH REPUBLIC</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Vacek</surname>
                           <given-names>Patrik</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Though relatively small in geographic terms and population, the Czech Republic has, since the 1990s, played an increasingly important role within the video game industry of the territory known as Central and Eastern Europe. Czech game designers have not only produced commercially successful mainstream titles and received considerable critical acclaim, but they have also been instrumental in creative efforts ranging from mobile phone games to underground or independent titles to modifications of well-known game products.</p>
                     <p>A history of video games in the Czech Republic is not complete without a closer look at the socio-historic and cultural conditions of the country</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FINLAND</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mäyrä</surname>
                           <given-names>Frans</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Finland, a sparsely populated Nordic country with 5.4 million inhabitants, has a fast-growing and disproportionately large video game culture and industry. Combining high technology with the spirit of experimentation, Finnish game design has managed to join other Finnish success stories in high technology, such as the Linux operating system and Nokia mobile phones. On the other hand, the public perception of gaming in Finland has often been conflicted. The studies conducted have nevertheless revealed Finns of all ages to be rather active game players.</p>
                     <p>The earliest game playing in Finland relates to the rich tradition of folk games. Ranging from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>FRANCE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Blanchet</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexis</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Consideration of the history of video games in France prompts the historian to wonder about the French history of video games and the history of French video games. These two histories cross paths but proceed from different dynamics: on the one hand, around the start of the 1970s, the arrival in France of a new form of entertainment and the development of a globalized industrial, economic, and cultural sector; on the other hand, the emergence of national structures (production studios, editors, a specialized press, and cultural institutions such as museums and libraries) that—dedicating themselves to the creation of video</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>GERMANY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lange</surname>
                           <given-names>Andreas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Liebe</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In describing the computer gaming culture in Germany, one must deal factually with two different countries at least until 1990, when the GDR and FRG were united.¹ This is not an uninteresting chapter in Germany’s history; while computer games and video games were unavailable to most people in East Germany, in West Germany, as in all industrialized countries, games were quickly developing into a popular medium. This makes it possible to compare the development of computer games in two entirely different systems, which differ both socially and politically, yet have a common history and culture. This will be taken into</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HONG KONG</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Benjamin Wai-ming Ng</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Hong Kong, a free port city with a population of more than 7.1 million, is one of the major game consumption centers in Asia. More than being a mainstream young male culture, gaming has become a citywide entertainment, actively consumed by people of different ages, genders, and socioeconomic backgrounds. Children and adults are as ardent as teenagers in gaming, and the number of female players has increased tremendously. There is no obvious difference between white-collar and blue-collar patterns of game consumption; wherever you go, you will always find someone playing games. At home, people play console games, outside the home,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HUNGARY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Beregi</surname>
                           <given-names>Tamás</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>219</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When the average foreigner is asked about Hungary, he or she can usually mention only a few names from the twentieth century, such Béla Bartók, the composer and pianist, Ferenc Puskás, the legendary football player, and Ernő Rubik, inventor of the famous Rubik’s Cube, which led to a worldwide fever in the early 1980s. The cube, just like the Russian game<italic>Tetris</italic>(1984), became the symbol of Eastern European creativity, which flourished even behind the Iron Curtain, a symbol of a game that is free in its abstraction and that follows strict mathematical laws, yet still is immensely variable.</p>
                     <p>The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
                           <given-names>Souvik</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>India is the sleeping giant of the video game world. Recent developments in the industry and the entry of new gaming consoles, however, mark a significant shift in the culture and reception of video games. As game designer Ernest Adams comments, “India has the talent, the resources, and the attitudes required to become a major player in this industry. All [they are] lacking is experience, and that will come with training and time” (Adams 2009). Adams’s optimism is echoed by Thomas Friedman in<italic>The World Is Flat</italic>with the warning, “So today India is ahead, but it has to work</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDONESIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rakhmani</surname>
                           <given-names>Inaya</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Darmawan</surname>
                           <given-names>Hikmat</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter provides a general overview of the video game industry and practices in Indonesia. The term “video game” is often used to mean arcade games, console games, computer games, and online games that have become popular over the past twenty years.¹ However, we have found through interviews and literature reviews that console and online games have had the most significant economic and cultural implications in Indonesia, a country of 240 million citizens, 130 million of whom live on the island of Java, where physical and information infrastructure are significantly more developed compared to the rest of the country.²</p>
                     <p>With</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>IRAN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ahmadi</surname>
                           <given-names>Ahmad</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>A roaring flood of video games from the Western world reached Iran when its first generation arrived during the Iran-Iraq War in the early 1980s. The Atari VCS 2600 was among the first generation of game consoles that officially entered Iran, and<italic>Pac-Man, Pitfall</italic>, and<italic>Missile Command</italic>were some of the best-selling games at that time. When the war’s status was “white” and the ominous “red” alarm was off, groups of children found opportunities to sit in front of the TV and shook their new black-and-gray joysticks up and down, taking turns and sometimes even fighting over them.¹ Now, after</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>IRELAND</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Mellamphy</surname>
                           <given-names>Deborah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although video game play has long been an important part of popular culture in Ireland, video games were never treated seriously by the Irish government or Irish society in the past, which is demonstrated by the enormous lack of information on the early history of video games in the country; the Irish government and media never recognized the potential until recently when global video game companies began to develop operations in Ireland. It is surprising that Atari established a manufacturing base in rural Tipperary in 1978, employing just over 200 people in their plant, manufacturing Atari arcade cabinets, which were</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ITALY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Gandolfi</surname>
                           <given-names>Enrico</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>305</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It’s quite hard to try to get a coherent overview of the reality of video games in Italy. On one hand, we are referring to a well-established market with numbers similar to the most important European countries. On the other hand, we observe a borderline presence of national producers and a lack of institutional attention to the medium.</p>
                     <p>In the history of digital entertainment, in the past as well as the present, Italy usually appears in terms of characters and settings: from Super Mario to Ezio Auditore passing through the mafia’s topoi, the stereotypes and the artistic patrimony of this</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>JAPAN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>deWinter</surname>
                           <given-names>Jennifer</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>319</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Japan is a densely populated island country with a population of 127.52 million as of 2012 (“Statistical Handbook of Japan” 2013) coupled with an active US military population of 39,222 (Department of Defense 2011). Since the late 1970s, Japan has had a strong role in the international computer game market, developing both successful hardware and software brands. This success is of particular note when compared to the rather weak-performing IT industries in Japan (Casper and Storz 2012; Azuma et al. 2009). The Japanese game industry’s success may be attributed to the rather strong influences of related entertainment industries, such as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>MEXICO</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cervera</surname>
                           <given-names>Humberto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Quesnel</surname>
                           <given-names>Jacinto</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>345</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter we will explore the history of video games in Mexico. Given the lack of previously published information, this will be an exploration of the word-of-mouth side of this story. We will explore the retail industry, game journalism, and game development; there is little to no written record of Mexico’s video game history, so this chapter is based on interviews with a few key players in the industry. There is still a lot missing in this tale; sadly, some key players couldn’t be found or did not agree to be interviewed by the authors. This small piece is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE NETHERLANDS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van Grinsven</surname>
                           <given-names>Christel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Raessens</surname>
                           <given-names>Joost</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>359</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gaming is a hot topic in the Netherlands. Dutch consumers make up the most active online gaming market in Europe. The Dutch games industry is a young and dynamic sector that has a lot of potential. While there is a clear focus on entertainment gaming worldwide, strikingly, the Dutch industry shows an almost fifty-fifty split between entertainment and serious gaming. In the varied Dutch market, small independent (indie) developers, innovative serious (or applied) gaming developers, and developers of entertainment games are all represented.¹ Digital distribution of games is a big focus of Dutch businesses, and a large number of companies</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NEW ZEALAND</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Swalwell</surname>
                           <given-names>Melanie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>377</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter focuses on the history of video games in New Zealand during the “long” 1980s. Beginning in the late 1970s and extending well into the 1980s, New Zealand had a booming digital games industry across the spectrum of arcade, console, handheld, and microcomputer games. This is a largely unknown history. Apart from my own research on this topic, written accounts have largely been compiled by private collectors, who continue to deepen understanding of the specificities of particular games software and hardware (Davidson n.d.; Lord n.d.; “SegaSC-3000 Survivors” n.d.; Stephen 2012). Much of the chapter focuses on the domestic production</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PERU</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Nakasone</surname>
                           <given-names>Arturo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The adoption and expansion of video games in Peru has been relatively slow, mainly due to the hard economic situation the country was going through during much of the 1980s and the first half of the 1990s. Video game history in Peru basically starts with the introduction of arcade machines during the beginning of the 1980s. At that time, a small number of businesses appeared, ranging from medium-sized arcade game centers, which deployed tens of machines, to small stores that had just a handful of them. The majority of arcade machines was provided by Japanese manufacturers such as Namco, Konami,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>POLAND</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Budziszewski</surname>
                           <given-names>P. Konrad</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“You need to appreciate how much our team had to rule for guys in America to trust us with their precious baby—their biggest money-maker ever. It’s as though some Polish company took its most successful product and farmed it out to Kazakhstan” (Chmielarz 2007, 126). Thus spoke Adrian Chmielarz, cofounder and creative director of People Can Fly (PFC), reflecting on the latter’s relationship with Epic Games—a relationship that netted the studio a contract for the PC version of<italic>Gears of War</italic>(2007) and led to partial acquisition by Epic. In a peculiar combination of self-aggrandizement and self-effacement, Chmielarz</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PORTUGAL</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Zagalo</surname>
                           <given-names>Nelson</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>425</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It took ten years after<italic>PONG</italic>(1972) and the arrival of Sinclair microcomputers (Adamson and Kannedy 1986) for Portuguese game development history to begin. The first video game we have been able to trace was José Oliveira’s<italic>Laser</italic>(1982), created on a Sinclair ZX81. During the last decades, the Portuguese video game community has been able to create and implement for almost any game platform, creating around 350 video games; however, the main platform has always been personal computers, rather than proprietary consoles, and the latter figure very little into the country’s video game history.</p>
                     <p>Portuguese video game history is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>RUSSIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Fedorov</surname>
                           <given-names>Alexander</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>439</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The history of video games in Russia goes back to the early 1980s. In the beginning of the computer era, Soviet arcade games, very primitive compared to today’s standard, included a large number of slot machines or electromechanical arcade games such as<italic>Morskoi Boi</italic>(<italic>Sea Battle</italic>, 1981),<italic>Tankodrom</italic>(1981),<italic>Rally-M</italic>(1981),<italic>Sniper</italic>(1981), and<italic>Safari</italic>(1982). In<italic>Sea Battle</italic>, the player had to shell enemy ships, while<italic>Rally-M</italic>was a racing game, and in<italic>Sniper</italic>, the player had to shell the target (seehttp://www.15kop.ru/en/). These games were coin-operated; it was necessary to insert fifteen kopecks into the machine, which gave you</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SCANDINAVIA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Konzack</surname>
                           <given-names>Lars</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>451</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Scandinavian countries (Sweden, Denmark, Norway, and Iceland) are not known for their video game consoles. Neither is Scandinavia known for big video game distribution companies. However, there have been a number of significant video game production companies throughout Scandinavia, and major video game hits have been launched. Furthermore, Scandinavia has been deeply involved in demo parties and the development of video game theory. But let us first go back to the beginning.</p>
                     <p>Computers were a new invention in the 1950s. The first Swedish computer, BARK¹ (Binär Automatisk Relä-Kalkylator), was from 1950, and the Swedes already had their second computer in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SINGAPORE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Peichi Chung</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>469</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Digital entertainment has become one of the world’s most profitable industries, with global annual sales that now surpass sales generated by traditional media industries. Since 2007, the rapid growth of this new industry developed most conspicuously in the area of video games. In 2011, software and hardware constituted 60% and 24% of global video game sales, earning USD $44.7 billion and USD $17.8 billion respectively, while online game sales took 16% of the market share, with earnings of USD $11.9 billion. Major video game titles have already achieved higher market success than even blockbuster Hollywood movies. Major video game titles</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SOUTH KOREA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <string-name>Peichi Chung</string-name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>495</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter introduces the developmental history of South Korea’s video game industry. It first traces the political and social factors that led to the birth of Asia’s online game industry. It then examines the history of video gaming in South Korea since the 1970s, highlighting the types of video games and processes of production and consumption that developed during particular stages of the industry’s growth. This provides an opportunity to document foreign game imports and analyze their influence on South Korea’s domestic industry, particularly the country’s development as a cultural exporter between 2002 and 2012. The indigenous video game culture</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SPAIN</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garin</surname>
                           <given-names>Manuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Martínez</surname>
                           <given-names>Víctor Manuel</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>521</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us begin with a cliché: just like Spain has been considered, historically and aesthetically, a place of and for contrasts, full of cultural crossbreeding, the history of Spanish video games is one of imbalances, changing from mystified golden ages to looping crises and—maybe too—great expectations. If world-renowned critics such as Erich Auerbach (2003, 357) and Harold Bloom (1995, 124) have stated that<italic>the world as play</italic>constitutes the greatest creative contribution of Cervantes’<italic>El Quijote</italic>(1605), a sort of literary<italic>gameplay</italic>, we are forced to admit that four centuries later the—still young—history of Spanish game</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>SWITZERLAND</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pellet</surname>
                           <given-names>Matthieu</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Javet</surname>
                           <given-names>David</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>535</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In order to consider the status of video games in Switzerland, one must adopt a cultural, historic, and geopolitical approach regarding the place of this country on the international stage: four national languages and five bordering countries are unique elements that define Swiss culture, with the idea of diversity at its core. First, its geographical position—at the center of Western Europe—places Switzerland in the position of a complex cluster for market strategies and legal practices in and out of its bordering countries. In addition, while being at the heart of the European continent, Switzerland is not part of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THAILAND</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Soranastaporn</surname>
                           <given-names>Songsri</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>545</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Video games (sometimes called “VDO games” in Thailand) are popular and attract massive numbers of players around the world. Thai players engage console games, computer games, online games, and handheld games, and many organizations and companies are involved in video games in Thailand, yet there are few studies on the subject. Therefore, this chapter will describe the history of video games, the current situation of video games, and explain the behavior of video game players in Thailand. The population in this study included four groups who are involved in video games, including e-learning, animation and computer graphics, movie production companies,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.40</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>TURKEY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tuker</surname>
                           <given-names>Cetin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Yılmaz</surname>
                           <given-names>Erdal</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Cagiltay</surname>
                           <given-names>Kursat</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>565</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Turkish people may have encountered computer games later than many Westerners, but they have wasted no time catching up. The modern Turkish game industry is one of the most rapidly growing markets in the world (Newzoo 2012). Thus, almost all game hardware producers and major game development companies have been paying special attention to Turkey. The average game playing durations, habits, and preferences of Turkish survey respondents are similar to those of developed countries (Karakus, İnal, and Cagiltay 2008; Durdu, Tüfekçi, and Cagiltay 2005). In the area of game development, however, Turkey remains far behind; no game hardware development activity</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.41</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>UNITED KINGDOM</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Donovan</surname>
                           <given-names>Tristan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>579</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The United Kingdom is one of the world’s foremost producers and consumers of video games. Based on revenue, the country is the largest consumer of games in the world after the United States and Japan (Padilla and Swift 2012). A third of its 63 million people identify themselves as game players, and half of its households own at least one game console (UKIE 2011). Britain also has some of the highest levels of smartphone ownership, social media use, and broadband Internet access in Europe (ComScore Data Mine 2013; Woollaston 2013; Jackson 2013).</p>
                     <p>Alongside its voracious appetite for playing games, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.42</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>UNITED STATES OF AMERICA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wolf</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark J. P.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>591</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the birthplace of video games and a major producer of them, the United States of America is the location of much of video game history, which is often covered in detail when the history of video games is recounted. Since this history is too extensive to cover adequately in a few thousand words and has already appeared a number of times (many book-length histories of video games center on the United States), this chapter will be different from the others in this collection in that it will focus specifically on the way US history shaped and influenced its video</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.43</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>URUGUAY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frasca</surname>
                           <given-names>Gonzalo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>609</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Uruguay is a small country squeezed between two giants, Argentina and Brazil. Unlike its neighbors, Uruguay never produced consoles or computers but benefited from their hardware endeavors. Circa 1975, Argentina created the Telematch de Panoramic, a hacked Magnavox Odyssey clone that removed many of the superfluous original games. It even added a brand new game that was almost a cultural requirement of the region—soccer—and incorporated extra buttons to control the goalies. Little is known about this machine, but it is very likely that a few made it to Uruguay. Brazilian clones had a bigger impact in the mid-1980s,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.44</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>VENEZUELA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Apperley</surname>
                           <given-names>Thomas H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>613</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The central role of information in the global networked society creates and entrenches regions of inclusion and exclusion, thus establishing classes of locations and people that are not valued by, or fully connected to, global networked society. Two worlds are emerging: “one is information as well as economically rich, the other is information and economically poor” (Yar 2008, 617). However, new forms of communication that are emerging on the same networks also offer feasible strategies for economic and social inclusion (Martin-Barbero 2011, 47). In Venezuela, digital games are one of these technologies that potentially both increase and mitigate forms of mitigate</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.45</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>629</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt17kk7tc.46</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>645</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
