<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BH39 .W555 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Art</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Conservatism</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Conservatism and literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Burke, Edmund, 1729–1797</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Maritain, Jacques, 1882–1973</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Christianity</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Platonists</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Vision of the Soul</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wilson</surname>
               <given-names>James Matthew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780813229287</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780813229294</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Catholic University of America Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Catholic University of America Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1pv897r"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Ours is an age full of desires but impoverished in its understanding of where those desires lead-an age that claims mastery over the world but also claims to find the world as a whole absurd or unintelligible. In<italic>The Vision of the Soul</italic>, James Matthew Wilson seeks to conserve the great insights of the western tradition by giving us a new account of them responsive to modern discontents. The western- or Christian Platonist-tradition, he argues, tells us that man is an intellectual animal, born to pursue the good, to know the true, and to contemplate all things in beauty. Wilson begins by reconceiving the intellectual conservatism born of Edmund Burke's jeremiad against the French Revolution as an eff­ort to preserve the West's vision of man and the cosmos as ordered by and to beauty. After defining the achievement of that vision and its tradition, Wilson off­ers an extended study of the nature of beauty and the role of the fine arts in shaping a culture but above all in opening the human intellect to the perception of the form of reality. Through close studies of Theodor W. Adorno and Jacques Maritain, he recovers the classical vision of beauty as a revelation of truth and being. Finally, he revisits the ancient distinction between reason and story-telling, between mythos and logos, in order to rejoin the two.Story-telling is foundational to the forms of the fine arts, but it is no less foundational to human reason. Human life in turn constitutes a specific kind of form-a story form. The ancient conception of human life as a pilgrimage to beauty itself is one that we can fully embrace only if we see the essential correlation between reason and story and the essential convertibility of truth, goodness and beauty in beauty. By turns a study in fundamental ontology, aesthetics, and political philosophy, Wilson's book invites its readers to a renewal of the West's intellectual tradition.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="352"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION.</title>
                     <subtitle>The Drama of Cultural Conservatism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The reflections with which I begin these pages may seem, at moments, to indulge in the barbed and the bitter, and the reader unfamiliar with my subject and with my own work, and otherwise disinclined to assertive denunciation, may be tempted to let the book slip back quietly to the shelf. But what I have to say on the matter of conservatism and culture emerges from my own life experience and comes in answer to questions salient to my own search for self-knowledge as well as to questions of a more obviously public nature regarding the goods of political and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ONE</label>
                     <title>The Hunger for Reality</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When we look at the world around us, we see it positively teeming with desires: squirrels foraging for food to fill their bellies, dogs on the prowl for a mate, flowers craning their heads upward to drink in the sun. Indeed, desire is not limited to living things, as all material objects tenaciously cling and conform to the laws of nature, though not by a will of their own.¹ Human beings offer the most varied spectacle of desire, not only seeking a wide range of objects to slake their hungers, but also seeming to be moved by desires that are</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWO</label>
                     <title>What Is the Western Tradition?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We saw in the Introduction that conservatism seeks to defend a particular vision of human life that George Santayana defined as Christian Platonic in nature. In chapter 1, I considered one aspect of that vision: how it envisions human happiness in comparison with typical modern accounts of it. It now seems appropriate to ask a more foundational question. If conservatism seeks to conserve the western tradition, then what are that tradition’s constitutive principles?</p>
                     <p>To answer this question, I should probably begin by stating an assumption that may no longer be obvious to some readers: there is a recognizable tradition of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THREE</label>
                     <title>We Must Retranslate Kalon</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Even before the elections in November 2008, particularly astute conservatives had lamented that many of the supposed victories for their cause were in truth nothing to celebrate. In the years since, the volume of this lament has grown to the point of becoming audible within the main corridors of contemporary political debate. Most of these persons were “paleo” or traditional conservatives, who saw in the George W. Bush administration little that was genuinely conservative and much that testified to the further usurpation of the word “conservative,” and of the Republican Party, by a neo-conservative agenda.¹ That agenda was largely repugnant</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOUR</label>
                     <title>Style and Truth:</title>
                     <subtitle>CONSERVATISM AS LITERARY MOVEMENT</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>125</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the Anglo-American tradition, conservative thought was born of beauty, particularly literary beauty. If conservatism is a movement, it is first a literary one. By this, I do not refer to Dr. Johnson and Dean Swift, who, along with many other great men of letters of the eighteenth century, were Tories—a detail that may help explain the essentially backward look of satire in that or any period, but does not in itself forge a necessary link between the Tory cause and literature. Rather, I refer to that moment when Tory thought was transformed and diluted into a new compound</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIVE</label>
                     <title>What Dante Means to Us</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>138</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In our day, we tend to shrug off discussion of metaphysics, as if no knowledge were to be gained from learning what it means<italic>to be</italic>. The distinction between the practical and the speculative has come to appear as the divide between proof and make believe. We are concerned with facts; facts are real; but, as to what makes a fact a fact, we think the matter beyond discussion and perhaps even beneath contempt.</p>
                     <p>When we enter a book emporium at the mall, we may find an entire row under the heading “Metaphysics,” but this intends something other than the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIX</label>
                     <title>“Only What Does Not Fit into This World Is True”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>151</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To speak, in contemporary society, of art and beauty in the same sentence, much less as realities integrally involved with one another, is to risk becoming the object of smiling condescension. The great philosophers of beauty in the eighteenth century, including Burke, Hume, and Kant, treated beauty as a matter of sensation or taste, as either a physiological experience or a spiritual one, but always a subjective one. The arts of the beautiful were thought “to gentrify” the soul, softening it, making it more sympathetic in itself and sociable as part of a culture.¹ They succeeded in providing to the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Re-Reading the Book of Nature</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter, I concluded with the observation that the form of Theodor W. Adorno’s philosophy is patterned on his vision of the artwork. We must ask, then, what is art itself and whence comes the truth it reveals? I shall discuss four ways of thinking about art that seem to command the attention of the skeptic who doubts its value as anything more than an empty gesture of liberal humanism. These four ways are also, in a qualified way, consonant with the account, which is a central claim of this book, of the reality of beauty as a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>EIGHT</label>
                     <title>Art as Intellectual Virtue</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jacques Maritain’s<italic>Art and Scholasticism</italic>(1920) constitutes one of the French neo-Thomist philosopher’s briefest and most austere works; and yet, belying the more or less serviceable prose and apparent modesty of scope, it is a wide ranging series of interventions on nearly every significant philosophical question of Maritain’s—or any—day. In speaking of beauty, Maritain sought to guide the intellectual life of an entire age. This can make the short treatise and the essays and notes later appended to it difficult reading: one cannot fully appreciate the significance of Maritain’s claims if one does not also sense the positions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>NINE</label>
                     <title>Beauty as a Transcendental</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One can readily see how Maritain’s Thomistic reflections on art at once flattered and admonished the artists of Paris’s Left Bank and beyond. He corrected the romantic intuitionism of those who had learned from Kant that artistic beauty was that which pleases universally<italic>without a concept</italic>, but who had blended that philosopher’s theory of genius with the sensationalism of Hume and Burke so that art had come to be thought of as not only beyond all intelligible rules save those the genius himself imposes, but also derived from something other than the intelligence. Maritain did this by rearticulating whatever truth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TEN</label>
                     <title>The Need for Proportion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>210</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I noted in the last chapter, how one defines and orders the three qualities of beauty will determine how one understands beauty as a whole. One can accept integrity, proportion, and clarity as the three conditions or elements of beauty and still, by emphasizing one over another, arrive at strikingly incompatible accounts of the beautiful. It will be the purpose of this chapter to consider the three different possible emphases and to examine their various implications. This will include a partly negative critique of Maritain’s emphasis on<italic>claritas</italic>, which will lead us, finally, to a judicious appreciation of proportion</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>ELEVEN</label>
                     <title>Reasoning about Stories</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Years ago, it was not uncommon to hear literary theorists proclaim ours a postmodern age, by which they meant an age so suspicious of stories about our cultures and civilization as to have lost the means of reciting its own story to itself.¹ Eventually, someone got around to noticing that to say that we have passed through an age beholden to comprehensive (“master”) narratives into one that refuses all such narratives is, well, itself a staggeringly comprehensive narrative.² And so it is. All historical discussion, all arguments about one age or another, including that of conservatives about the modern condition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>TWELVE</label>
                     <title>Mnemosyne:</title>
                     <subtitle>MOTHER OF THE ARTS</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>244</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>So successful was the advent of modernist poetic, musical, and visual art in disrupting the critical vocabulary by which we describe them that we have all but lost the means to account for how art actually works. So blinding was its revolutionary blast that we have sometimes failed to distinguish the various courses these arts took during the modernist period; moreover, we have often assumed modern art effected more radical changes than it did, as if it put the aesthetic upon an entirely new basis. Abstraction in painting, dissonance and atonality in music, and free verse in poetry stand of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>THIRTEEN</label>
                     <title>Novel, Myth, Reality:</title>
                     <subtitle>AN ANATOMY OF MAKE-BELIEVE</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>258</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the last chapter, I contended that all art depends upon narrative. Even those modernist works, such as nonrepresentational painting, that seem most to escape the gravity of story-telling end up simply rendering the narrative exogenous but no less essential. I concluded by urging artists and writers to appreciate what such modernist experiments help reveal about the nature of art, but also to return to formal practices that better respect Mnemosyne as the mother of the arts and, in turn, better respect the form of the story as an essential means to understanding the human condition. In this recommendation, I</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FOURTEEN</label>
                     <title>Retelling the Story of Reason</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>272</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is now time to weave together a number of threads we have followed in earlier parts of this book, and to define what they have to tell us on the role of narrative in human life—and particularly in the life of reason and its vocation to truth. As we have seen in discussing both Burke and Dante, venerable claims have been made in our tradition for the power of the poetic and literary imagination; but Burke’s counter-revolutionary importance should also remind us that many of those claims have been compensatory for losses experienced elsewhere. Consider, for instance, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>FIFTEEN</label>
                     <title>The Consequences of Our Forgetting</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>314</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Let us begin with a distillation of the long argument we have been pursuing. I have contended that modern thought routinely sets<italic>logos</italic>(reason) in opposition to<italic>mythos</italic>(story-telling), and favors<italic>logos</italic>as authoritative and true. This habit breeds an unhappy myth of its own: mankind was once subject to the vague powers of hearsay, superstition, and old wives’ tales, but has emerged triumphant from such antiquated miasma into the knowing precisions of a rational age. While such a myth gained traction in the modern age, particularly during the Enlightenment, its basic form dates back to Plato. Or rather, it</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>SIXTEEN</label>
                     <title>Still Interested in the Truth</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>326</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We began this study with the claim that conservatism should be viewed as the modern, settled disposition that perceives the form of politics, of culture, and of reality as an essentially aesthetic one. These things are ordered by and to beauty. The conservative is one who sees their forms, recognizes them as both good and true, and who therefore seeks to conserve and cultivate these orders in shifting, often hostile, circumstances. The tradition Burke inaugurated is distinctively modern, because it was formulated in response to the modern doxa forged during the Enlightenment, but it is also ancient and venerable, because</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pv897r.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>351</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
