<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC261.M47C66</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Merleau-Ponty, Maurice, 1908-1961</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Political science</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Merleau-Ponty and Marxism</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>COOPER</surname>
               <given-names>BARRY</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>1979</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781442639355</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781442653108</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Toronto; Buffalo; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1979</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Toronto Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3138/j.ctt1h1hq7v"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Barry Cooper's study of this important contemporary thinker gives context for an understanding of Merleau-Ponty's politics and, in so doing, brings together the complex issues and ideas that have shaped modern European political and philosophical thought.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>the philosophical basis of Merleau-Ponty’s humanism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is a study of Maurice Merleau-Ponty’s politics. For one reason or another, students of Merleau-Ponty’s thought have only superficially examined its political dimension. Most scholars have sought to explain particular aspects of his philosophical work. Some have used his writings as a quarry of raw materials to be extracted and refined for their own constructions. A few have studied Merleau-Ponty’s writings sympathetically in order to think along with him and reason through new matters in a style they have learned from him. But this is to be a critical account. It treats his views of public affairs and political</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>The post-war context</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>I have argued that humanism was the central term in Merleau-Ponty’s political vocabulary. It brought together the various interpretations of collective life to which human beings have committed themselves. The intellectual and spiritual change that Merleau-Ponty underwent has been described as cutting himself off from ‘vertical’ transcendence in the religious or philosophical sense, implying that the act was a mistake. It was motivated by his rejection of religious and philosophical dogma and the existential attractions of Hegel’s idea of commitment to humanism or a regime of mutual recognition.</p>
                     <p>If Merleau-Ponty was right, religious experience is illusion, an ersatz reality sustained</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>Recognition and violence</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>37</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Merleau-Ponty’s chief criticism of his contemporaries, as we have seen, was that they were wrong in refusing to acknowledge that intentions and consequences presented a problematic. One might also speak here of a dialectic of intentions and consequences, but in either case the connotation was of an unavoidable practical or pragmatic uncertainty. A problem can be solved, but a problematic must be coped with for better or for worse. To resolve a problematic into its analytically distinct constituent elements is to destroy its characteristic tension between (or among) those elements. Likewise, a dialectic contains its own internal dynamic, for example</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Historical responsibility and the Soviet Union</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over half of<italic>Humanisme et Terreur</italic>, published in 1947, was devoted to an interpretation of the Moscow Trials; Merleau-Ponty disputed Arthur Koestler’s interpretation in his famous novel<italic>Darkness at Noon</italic>, as well as the current liberal interpretation and Trotsky’s view. The evidence used in his argument was primarily from the<italic>Report of Court Proceedings</italic>of the March 1938 trial of Bukharin, Rykov, Yagoda, and eighteen lesser known men. It was the only full-length analysis of political events that Merleau-Ponty ever undertook;<italic>Les Aventures de la Dialectique</italic>, his only other book devoted entirely to a political theme, was presented in the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The eclipse of the middle way</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sartre called Merleau-Ponty’s understanding of Soviet and world politics during the immediate post-war period ‘one-eyed’ while everyone else’s was blind.¹ Yet his recognition of the hazy and ambiguous forces at work in the world only prompted vilification from blind men who thought they saw things clearly.<italic>Humanisme et Terreur</italic>, Merleau-Ponty’s first extended reflection upon public affairs, provoked hostility from both left and right, a preview of how virtually all his political writings were to be received. Often, though, the criticisms of his contemporaries were the result of gross and perhaps wilful misunderstanding.</p>
                     <p>Communist intellectuals, it is true, reserved their most</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>A reappraisal of dialectic</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Merleau-Ponty’s doubts about classical Marxism were nourished by his integrity and the seriousness of his commitment to humanism. Proletarian internationalism and proletarian spontaneity had ceased to be effective factors in politics, and proletarian control of the means of production was grotesquely distorted by the Stalinist regime. Nevertheless the pressure of events compelled him, not to abandon Marx’s teaching, but to reinterpret it. Sartre was right to note that Merleau-Ponty had returned to his inner life, but his refuge was no more than a strategic retreat. In his lectures at the Collège de France he was undertaking an intellectual overhaul that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Virtù without resignation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>134</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>What attention has been paid to<italic>Les Aventures de la Dialectique</italic>has shown little appreciation for its structure or its significance. Understandably enough, philosophers have tended to direct their concern towards the essays in<italic>Signes</italic>and the limpid but indirect prose of his two posthumous works. For example, Claude Lefort, who has devoted as much attention to the texts of Merleau-Ponty as anyone, traced the line of thought indicated initially in<italic>Titres et Travaux</italic>through its successive incarnations first in<italic>La Prose du Monde</italic>, a manuscript from the 1951-2 period, then in his lectures at the Collège de France, and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>interrogation and reform</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>166</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Merleau-Ponty’s earliest public writings showed him to be a young philosopher acutely sensitive to what I have called, perhaps a little crudely, the transcendent dimension to human existence. In his first phenomenological studies, which included Scheler and Marcel, he learned the importance and significance of commitment as being a constituent element of knowledge. On the one hand this insight led him to abandon the dogmatic philosophical and religious traditions in which he had been reared. On the other it led him to make new commitments with a more practical significance. The first of these, the personalism of Mounier and his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1h1hq7v.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
