<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Law</subject>
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Levinas, Ethics and Law</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Stone</surname>
               <given-names>Matthew</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>30</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781474400763</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781474400770</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1474400779</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Edinburgh University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Matthew Stone</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.3366/j.ctt1bh2jr8"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Matthew Stone asks what unites apparently disparate applications of Levinas' ideas about law and explores the ethical challenge of law's relationship with 'the Other'. Ultimately, he is sceptical that Levinasian ethics can be invested in legal institutions and instead proposes that it should be embodied in the perpetual critique of law.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="184"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Law’s Other</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The truest violence of law is not attributable to its errors, but to its essence. As a structure of meaning and a source of norms, framed through general and abstract standards, law has an especial, inevitable capacity to misrecognise ‘the other’ at the precise moment that the other is in most need of its justice. The significance of the other, upon which Levinas speaks with unparalleled philosophical authority, is instead personal, unique, singular, and fundamental in informing our understanding of ourselves, our desires and our duties. This book addresses law’s difficult task of responding meaningfully to the type of ethical</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The Ethics of Emmanuel Levinas</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Levinas’s philosophy could be described as a theory of subjectivity first, and a theory of ethics second. If this observation stands up, it does so not only with respect to conceptual focus, but also chronology: his early works barely mention ethics at all. His ideas sprang out of a vehement critique of philosophies of ontology, where ‘ontology’ came to be defined by Levinas somewhat idiosyncratically as the reduction of the other to the same via a conception of being.¹ His thinking is preoccupied with the question of how we understand ourselves in our place in the world, but also the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Can Law Be Ethical?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Moving from the ethical to the legal (or, indeed, the political) is an irreducible problem within the Levinasian framework. This is not an internal failing of his thought. Were it not a problem, were there an easy solution to this relationship, Levinas’s ethics would of course lose all of their radical purchase. Ethics is, by definition, a unique relationship. It is the very singularity of subjectivity put into discord with the infinitely chasmic accusation by the other that constitutes not only ethics but the very movement of subjectivity. The question is how we move from the singular to the general,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Adjudication, Obligation and Human Rights:</title>
                     <subtitle>Applying Levinas’s Ethics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter will instantiate some of the discussion in the last by providing a critical reading of existing literature on how, and to what extent, Levinas can be turned to directly legal questions in a more grounded fashion. There are three principal approaches that this chapter will explore: first, the idea that Levinasian ethics can be embodied within the state apparatus of the judiciary; secondly, that such ethics can inhere in our civil legal relations with other private citizens; and thirdly, we can examine the specific literature, prompted by Levinas’s own writings, that suggests ethical responsibilities can be protected by</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>The Law of the Same:</title>
                     <subtitle>Levinas and the Biopolitical Limits of Liberalism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having provided an overview of the various ways we might read Levinas in relation to law, and the issues they raise, it is time to put forward the substantive argument of the book. This is the first of two concluding chapters making the argument that Levinas is best read as someone who offers us the possibility of thinking about ethics as perpetual critique of the law, rather than as a legal theorist. In other words, instead of using his work to think about how we inject ethics into law or unveil law’s ethical foundation, his philosophy provides resources to understand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Law, Ethics and Political Subjectivity</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter begins with an outline of its central arguments as well as the concluding claims of the book as a whole. As covered in Chapter 4, applications of Levinas to law typically ask us to imagine law as a responsive site for the ethical encounter – whether in its institutions, its procedures, or reflected in its substance. This rests on a typically unstated but nevertheless unavoidable premise, that law operates as the servant of human will. This largely reflects how Levinas understood law himself, as being the necessary framework in which we do the hard work of creating social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>160</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bh2jr8.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>174</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
