<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BT40 .F2713 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophical theology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Crossing the Rubicon: The Borderlands of Philosophy and Theology</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FALQUE</surname>
               <given-names>EMMANUEL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Shank</surname>
               <given-names>Reuben</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>06</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823269877</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823269907</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1bmzm0r"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In France today, philosophy--phenomenology in particular--finds itself in a paradoxical relation to theology. Some debate a "theological turn." Others disavow theological arguments as if such arguments would tarnish their philosophical integrity, while nevertheless carrying out theology in other venues. In Crossing the Rubicon, Emmanuel Falque seeks to end this face-off. Convinced that "the more one theologizes, the better one philosophizes," he proposes a counterblow by theology against phenomenology. Instead of another philosophy of "the threshold" or "the leap"--and through a retrospective and forward-looking examination of his own method--he argues that an encounter between the two disciplines will reveal their mutual fruitfulness and their true distinctive borders. Falque shows that he has made the crossing between philosophy and theology and back again with audacity and perhaps a little recklessness, knowing full well that no one thinks without exposing himself to risk.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="208"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FARLEY</surname>
                           <given-names>MATTHEW</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In June of 2013, I went to Paris to study<italic>Passer le Rubicon</italic>with Emmanuel Falque (there was at that time no English translation—a want that Reuben Shank here patiently redresses). Gladly, we held many of our conferences in the environs of Jardin du Luxembourg at the<italic>Café Doucet</italic>, cornerwise from the L’institut catholique de Paris, where Falque was, at the time, Dean of Philosophy. In one of those meetings over a Kronenbourg, Falque impressed upon me his respect for the integrity of the unbeliever. After all, the unbeliever these days, Falque explained, is no longer Dante’s contemptuous Farinata,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Opening</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Leibniz’s<italic>term monad</italic>, found in his<italic>Discourse on Metaphysics</italic>, is suffi-ciently well-known that it should give us no reason to pause. It is far more important to compose a philosophical plea capable of justifying an enterprise begun years ago. To begin, I will meditate on the Rubicon, a river<italic>(flumen )</italic>or small coastal waterway of Emilie-Romagna in northern Italy that once knew a singular destiny. To risk the crossing of this boundary was to violate the Roman Senate’s laws. Nevertheless, a now well-known general decided to cross fully armed. With all his legions, he passed the boundary that separated</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Is Hermeneutics Fundamental?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this crossing of the Rubicon, the trumpets first sound in homage to Ricoeur. Yet I will conclude with an accepted and even affirmed gap between his hermeneutics and the approach advanced here. Any tribute to a master must refl ect his greatness as well as his limitations, at least in the context of a legacy to be both received and transformed. Of course, one could proceed with pure and simple repetition. Ricoeur’s concept of distanciation, however, may be productive at this juncture, prompting the declaration that the times have changed and that one must orient oneself anew. After all,the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>For a Hermeneutic of the Body and the Voice</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Hic intelligenda est vox Verbi quod ibi caro Dei</italic>—“the voice of the Word must be understood at present as the flesh of God was understood then.”¹ Th is single formula from Hugh of Saint-Victor is sufficient to illuminate the Catholic hermeneutic of the body and the voice as introduced so far. The reminder is certainly appropriate. A “Catholic” hermeneutic should not be opposed to a “Jewish” hermeneutic or to a “Protestant” hermeneutic in a confessional struggle, which fortunately today is by and large left behind. Catholic theology lives in an ecumenism of good taste; it regularly recognizes its debt</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Always Believing</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It was necessary to interpret (Part I). It is now time to decide (Part II). The hermeneutic<italic>of the body and the voice</italic>, which I have named Catholic, opens unto “a phenomenology of believing” that grounds it. Where hermeneutics drew out<italic>meaning</italic>, albeit anchored in the body rather than in the text, phenomenology describes a<italic>mode</italic>of being-there rooted in believing. The experience of being-there and believing sends us back first to a human community. As we just underlined, ecclesiality opens a space for the Eucharistically incorporated voice, which gives a concrete body to the body—the church—empowered by the force</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>Kerygma and Decision</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>99</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Chapter 3, I claimed there is no confessing faith outside of an original philosophical faith. A common ground of<italic>believing</italic>always precedes the<italic>decided</italic>act of believing. To recognize oneself as “believing otherwise” is then not to disregard faith or to condemn the so-called unbeliever. This position is neither a kind of ostracism nor a kind of conformism, nor does it aim to relativize. On the contrary, it arises from a real resolution. Believing<italic>theologically</italic>in God rests on first believing<italic>philosophically</italic>in the world or in others—whether via a Cartesian act of negation, a Husserlian suspension of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>“Tiling” and Conversion</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The pathway from hermeneutics in Part I to belief in Part II, or from interpreting to deciding, opened a space for a philosophy of religious experience that was not content with a philosophy of religion. The importance of the kerygma calls for the rediscovery or reestablishment of an act of philosophizing, as proved by Pascal and Kierkegaard in their day, for which the experience of believing is not dismissed as a matter of course. In this Part III, the time has come to formalize what this essay on the boundaries between philosophy and theology truly aims to express from the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Finally Theology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“Finally theology.” A theologian should utter this phrase—not a philosopher. One could fear that the great crossing fi nally had no other goal than to push us across the ford, as if the crossing of the Rubicon signified only the time of an Iliad without an Odyssey. Yet my principal thesis is that the two-way journey, there and back again with a definite return, is necessary to give each riverbank its specificity. I am first of all a philosopher and want to remain one. I am all the more committed to remaining a philosopher after having engaged in a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>And Then . . . ?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Primum vivere deinde philosophari</italic>—“first live and then philosophize.” This famous saying of the ancients reminds us what is at stake in the act of writing and thinking. We do not first write and then live afterward or “on the side,” as it were. Rather,<italic>we live and then we write.</italic>The first imperative is not to know how to write but to learn to live; otherwise we run the risk of having nothing to say. The particularity of the philosopher is that he participates in the incarnate. No error is greater than his confusing himself for an abstraction, whereby</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1bmzm0r.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
