<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Becoming Human Again</book-title>
         <subtitle>The Theological Life of Gustaf Wingren</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Uggla</surname>
               <given-names>Bengt Kristensson</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="translator" id="contrib2">
            <role>Translated by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Olson</surname>
               <given-names>Daniel M.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>26</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780227176030</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780227905616</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>James Clarke &amp; Co</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Cambridge, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Bengt Kristensson Uggla</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1p5f1x6"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>One of the most influential Swedish theologians of the twentieth century, Gustaf Wingren’s career spanned more than forty years of upheaval both in his field and around the globe. Provocative and challenging, Wingren revelled in a good argument and this attitude set the tone for much of his scholarship. A Swedish Lutheran, he made his name through his research into the theology of Martin Luther, breaking away from both traditional interpretations of Luther and the theology of his famous teachers, Karl Barth and Anders Nygren, before shifting his focus onto systematic theology. In a fresh take, Bengt Kristensson Uggla delves into the influence of Wingren’s second wife, Greta Hofsten, on the direction of his theology. Hofsten, a left-wing political activist who was searching for a new language of faith, wove Wingren’s work together with her own political philosophy to create an unusual kind of Christian socialism. Her thinking had a profound effect on Wingren, causing him to recontextualise his older work entirely. In Becoming Human Again, Uggla examines how Wingren’s combative nature often served him well as a theologian, driving him to engage with innovations in the field and re-examine his older views.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="400"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>Entering Wingren’s Theological Life</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book deals with Gustaf Wingren (1910–2000), one of the most influential and creative Swedish theologians of the twentieth century. I became acquainted with him around 1980, after he had retired. I had known about Wingren before then, and attended several of his many public lectures during the latter half of the 1970s. At that time in Sweden, Wingren’s name was on the lips of many, and at several of the public events at which he lectured I was given the opportunity to speak to him briefly. It was, however, not until I had left Gothenburg, where I had</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>The First Confrontation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where does the story of Gustaf Wingren begin? As with the telling of any history, there are many possible ways to begin, and almost as many ways to continue and conclude. The narrator’s first step has its own implications; the starting point determines very much how the story will proceed. I have chosen to begin my own story about Wingren in a way that focuses on his ideas, contextualized though they may be, and at the same time in a way that from the very beginning emphasizes Wingren’s obvious affinity with the academic context and public.</p>
                     <p>However, the fact that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Sources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>70</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Behind every story there is always another hidden story. Every memory contains an excess of forgetfulness. Thus, in order to recall something from the past it is necessary to suppress even more than we recount. When we remind ourselves about something from the past, it means, necessarily, that we must exclude so much more. To tell a story means inevitably to remove the largest part. Each memory that we retrieve requires simultaneously a great deal of forgetting. Therefore, there is always already another story waiting to be told before each story begins. Every history has its own history. One of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Practical Turn</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>116</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his book<italic>Cosmopolis: The Hidden Agenda of Modernity</italic>, Anglo-American philosopher of science Stephen Toulmin outlines a perspective on how the Western concept of knowledge has throughout the ages swung like a pendulum between theoretical-minded Platonists and practical-minded Aristotelians. This tension between<italic>theory</italic>and<italic>practice</italic>was also evident when the new interest in practical wisdom (<italic>phronesis</italic>), which occurred in the carnival-like scientific atmosphere of the sixteenth century, with its focus on concrete, practical life and time-bound local practices, was supplanted around 1630 by an abstract and universalistic scientific paradigm, which instead took as its point of departure theoretical understanding (<italic>episteme</italic>).</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Metamorphosis and Recontextualization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>167</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The 1960s appear as a remarkable period of transformation in modern history, when many things came to an end and so many new things began. The decade of the 1960s saw the convergence of a number of processes of change that would continue to alter the world toward the turn of the millennium. On a superficial level, the changes were evidenced by the emergence of an entirely new youth culture and new social movements on the world scene. One lasting image of the new expressions of popular culture and the new ways of life that were developing during this time</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>The Final Academic Battlefield</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>214</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gustaf Wingren retired in 1977 after an academic career spanning more than forty years. His position as a tenured professor at Lund University had allowed him to fully engage himself in his work. The basic structure and frame of reference for his theological project were largely complete by the 1950s and were magnificently concluded with the Swedish edition of his book<italic>Gospel and Church</italic>(1960/1964). In any case, he penned no other books of the same caliber or scale for the rest of the 1960s.</p>
                     <p>Then came some dramatic changes. The sixty-year-old professor underwent a metamorphosis. Beginning in the 1970s,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>Systematic Theology Turned Critique of Civilization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The same process of modernization and industrialization that successfully transformed the entire world by materializing the project of the Enlightenment has always co-existed with a tradition of critique of civilization that aims to disclose a darker reality beneath the surface of this success story. One does not need to use words such as<italic>Wideraufklärung</italic>, expressions of a sort of anti-Enlightenment, in order to recognize that every civilization in history tends to be blind to its own barbarism; it is sufficient to state that the Enlightenment has always been imbued with a sort of Romanticism. Somewhat as belated second thoughts, like</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>“This Plague of Egocentricity”</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>During the last century the importance, position, and conditions of the church in Swedish society have changed dramatically. At the time of Gustaf Wingren’s birth in November 1910, Sweden was still largely a homogeneous Lutheran society, almost without any kind of freedom of religion, as we know the term today. Although the growing free church movement that had begun in the mid-1800s had given rise to the beginnings of religious pluralism in Sweden, it had done so within the framework of Christianity in general and Protestantism in particular. Wingren himself would be forty years old by the time blasphemy ceased</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>367</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Postscript to the English Edition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>371</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In association with the English edition of this book, I have resisted the temptation to rewrite the text, thus transforming it into a new book. Of course, some few corrections and explanations have been necessary to add in order to make the presentation accessible for non-Swedish readers. Besides the fact that I have included information about the posthumously published<italic>Homilies: Gustaf Wingren Preaches</italic>(<italic>Postilla: Gustaf Wingren predikar</italic>, 2010), I have refrained from investigating the English-speaking reception of Wingren’s theology—and limited myself to the intention to further contribute to a broader picture of this work in future research. In general,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Literature and Other Sources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>373</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1p5f1x6.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
