<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BD181.7.M49 2010</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory (Philosophy)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Memory</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Social aspects</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Psychology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Memory</book-title>
         <subtitle>Histories, Theories, Debates</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>RADSTONE</surname>
               <given-names>SUSANNAH</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>SCHWARZ</surname>
               <given-names>BILL</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>08</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780823232598</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780823275120</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>NEW YORK</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Fordham University Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1c999bq"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Memory has never been closer to us, yet never more difficult to understand. In the more than thirty specially commissioned essays that make up this book, leading scholars survey the histories, the theories, and the faultlines that compose the field of memory research.The volume reconstructs the work of the great philosophical and literary figures of the last two centuries who recast the concept of memory and brought it into the forefront of the modernist and postmodernist imagination-among them, Bergson, Halbwachs, Freud, Proust, Benjamin, Adorno, Derrida, and Deleuze. Drawing on recent advances in the sciences and in the humanities, the contributors address thequestion of how memory works, highlighting transactions between the interiority of subjective memory and the larger fields of public or collective memory.The public, political life of memory is an increasingly urgent issue in the societies we now inhabit, while the category of memory itself seems to become ever more capacious.Asking how we might think about the politics of memory, the closing chapters explore anumber of defining instances in which the troubled phenomenon of memory has entered and reshaped our very conception of what makes and drives the domain of politics. These include issues of slavery, the Soviet experience, the Holocaust, feminism and recovered memory, and memory in post-apartheid South Africa.</p>
      </abstract>
      <funding-group>
         <award-group>
            <funding-source>Knowledge Unlatched</funding-source>
         </award-group>
      </funding-group>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="500"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Mapping Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Radstone</surname>
                           <given-names>Susannah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schwarz</surname>
                           <given-names>Bill</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The idea of memory runs through contemporary public life at high voltage, generating polemic and passionate debate in the media, in the spheres of politics and in the academy. Yet although the contemporary “presentness” of memory is evident, how this is to be understood remains a matter of dispute. It is not clear what meanings attach themselves to the generic conception of memory itself; and while in the academy there is a common belief that memory is “everywhere,”¹ what this means remains an open matter.<italic>Memory: Histories, Theories, Debates</italic>constitutes one collective response to the contemporary salience of memory and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1.</label>
                     <title>How to Make a Composition:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory-Craft in Antiquity and in the Middle Ages</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Carruthers</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The so-called “arts of memory,”<italic>artes memorandi</italic>, which were taught commonly in the curricula of dialectic and rhetoric for roughly two thousand years between the fourth century BCE and the sixteenth century CE, belong to a different psychological country from that of the modern Western, post-Enlightenment “memory” that is the concern of most of the rest of this volume. Of course, there are also complex medieval attitudes and practices regarding history and commemoration of the dead, but it is not with these that the<italic>artes memorandi</italic>are concerned.¹ Academic redefinitions and reclassifications of the old natural and philosophical sciences, especially</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2.</label>
                     <title>The Reformation of Memory in Early Modern Europe</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sherlock</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>30</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Europe witnessed a revolution in memory during the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries. By the eighteenth century, the ancient “arts of memory” were archaic. The explosive power of print had made it possible both to archive and to multiply knowledge cheaply and efficiently in books. Oral testimony was increasingly displaced by written records. New bureaucratic structures designed to record information on evergreater numbers of individuals abounded. Scientific discoveries forced a reappraisal of the very nature of the universe, including time as well as space. Most potently of all, social memory was hotly contested as polemicists sought to shape and legitimize the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3.</label>
                     <title>Memory, Temporality, Modernity:</title>
                     <subtitle>Les lieux de mémoire</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Schwarz</surname>
                           <given-names>Bill</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“She wanted to have no past.” These words, with no hint of equivocation, come from D. H. Lawrence’s<italic>Women in Love</italic>, first published in 1921. They tell us of the reveries of Ursula Brangwen, whom, at the start of the novel, the narrator portrays as a decidedly “modern girl,” and who is later attired in canary-yellow stockings, thus proving the point. Lawrence continues:</p>
                     <p>She wanted to have come down from the slopes of heaven to this place, with Birkin, not to have rolled out of the murk of her childhood and her upbringing, slowly, all soiled. She felt that memory</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4.</label>
                     <title>Bergson on Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ansell-Pearson</surname>
                           <given-names>Keith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In this chapter on Bergson and memory I shall focus on two key questions that Henri Bergson sought to establish as the foundation for a philosophical treatment of memory. First, what is the relation between past and present? Is it merely a difference in degree, or it possible to locate the difference between them as one of kind? If we can do the latter, what will this reveal about memory? Second, what is the status of the past? Is it something merely psychological, or might it be possible to ascribe an ontological status to it? In other words, what is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5.</label>
                     <title>Halbwachs and the Social Properties of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Apfelbaum</surname>
                           <given-names>Erika</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1924, the French social scientist Maurice Halbwachs published<italic>Les cadres sociaux de la mémoire</italic>(<italic>On Collective Memory</italic>).¹ Its publication was immediately seen by his contemporaries as a major event, its importance acknowledged even by those who did not fully share his theoretical views. Prophetically, the historian Marc Bloch saw the analyses presented by Halbwachs in this book as a major contribution to the developing discipline of social science. Halbwachs, in delineating the social and collective dimensions of individual memory, tracing their dialectical links in the process of elaboration and transformation, in addition to analyzing the mechanisms and modes of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6.</label>
                     <title>Memory in Freud</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Terdiman</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When Freud set out to understand how memory worked in the psyche, he wasn’t thinking about whether his ideas harmonized with the historical and cultural complex we know as “modernity.” But the theory of memory that Freud developed puts his conception of memory at modernity’s heart.</p>
                     <p>In the modern period, memory seems caught in a distinctive form of crisis. We could think of modernity’s “memory” as involving two contrary mismatches between recollection and its object. Memory is either frustrated by insufficiency, or it is cursed with exaggeration:<italic>too little</italic>memory, or<italic>too much</italic>. Modernity is either haunted by the near-impossibility</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7.</label>
                     <title>Proust:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Music of Memory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wood</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“And no one will ever know, not even oneself, the melody that had been pursuing one with its elusive and delectable rhythm.”² Underneath these words, probably written in 1909 and certainly part of a draft of what was to become<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, Proust wrote “Finish there.”³ The melody is a missing memory; and memory itself, in Proust, repeatedly appears as a melody. The analogy helps us, I believe, to bring together the more obvious and the more elusive elements of Proust’s view of this subject, so central to his thought and writing, and especially to understand</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8.</label>
                     <title>Siegfried Kracauer and Walter Benjamin:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory from Weimar to Hitler</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leslie</surname>
                           <given-names>Esther</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In mid-December 1932 Siegfried Kracauer wrote a short newspaper article entitled “Street without Memory.” Here he describes Berlin’s fashionable shopping street, the Kurfürstendamm, as a place voided of memory: “the embodiment of empty flowing time, where nothing persists.”¹ He relates how on visiting a café where he often ate, and where he was sure he had peeked in the night before, he found it closed, its interior emptied. A year later he found that the café’s replacement, a patisserie, had suffered the same fate. Having disappeared, these spaces do not become part of memory, for “constant change purges memory.”² Reflecting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9.</label>
                     <title>Adorno on the Destruction of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Connor</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>136</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In Theodor W. Adorno’s philosophy, memory is analyzed as a form of knowledge that has become problematic. Adorno argues that what we can know through memory is threatened with eclipse by certain allegedly more rational forms. That eclipse, though, amounts to an act of forgetting that is, as he puts it, equivalent to a “destruction of memory.”¹ Now obviously not all events or all things can be remembered or ought to be remembered. Adorno’s considerations of the issue, in fact, pivot specifically both on the loss of<italic>individuality</italic>and on the danger of forgetting<italic>human suffering</italic>. This places memory at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10.</label>
                     <title>Acts of Memory and Mourning:</title>
                     <subtitle>Derrida and the Fictions of Anteriority</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Richter</surname>
                           <given-names>Gerhard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>150</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In a remarkable letter to Käthchen Schönkopf from December 12, 1769, the young Goethe records a description of her as she had appeared in his guilt-ridden dream the night before. Having failed to respond to her most recent missive for what suddenly seemed like an eternity, his sleep was fitful: “A dream last night reminded me that I owe you an answer. It is neither that I had forgotten entirely, nor that I never think of you; no, my friend, every day tells me something of you and of my debts.” Goethe continues: “But it is strange—and this is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11.</label>
                     <title>Deleuze and the Overcoming of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ansell-Pearson</surname>
                           <given-names>Keith</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>161</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Gilles Deleuze’s reading of Proust’s novel<italic>In Search of Lost Time</italic>(<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>) in<italic>Proust and Signs</italic>contains the striking claim that what constitutes its unity is not memory, not even involuntary memory. The “search” is not steered by the effort of recall or the exploration of memory, but by the desire for truth (which, following Nietzsche, we can say is always “hard”).¹ Memory intervenes in this search only as a means but not the most profound means, just as past time intervenes as a structure of time but not the most profound one. Moreover, according</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12.</label>
                     <title>Memory and the Unconscious</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kennedy</surname>
                           <given-names>Roger</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From its early days the place and function of memory has been central to the theory and technique of psychoanalysis, though the picture of how memory functions from a psychoanalytic point of view has undergone many transformations. From memories that arose from the hypnotic treatment of adults, Freud began with the notion that hysteria was caused by the sexual molestation of children. As is well known, Freud later felt that in this early work on hysteria, he had overvalued reality and undervalued fantasy.¹ In his later work, the main emphasis passed away from actual sexual abuse as a cause of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13.</label>
                     <title>Memories Are Made of This</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Rose</surname>
                           <given-names>Steven</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>198</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“If any one faculty of our nature may be called more wonderful than the rest, I do think it is memory. There seems something more speakingly incomprehensible in the powers, the failures, the inequalities of memory, than in any other of our intelligences. The memory is sometimes so retentive, so serviceable, so obedient—at others, so bewildered and so weak—and at others again, so tyrannical, so beyond controul!—We are to be sure a miracle in every way—but our powers of recollecting and forgetting, do seem peculiarly past finding out.”</p>
                     <p>Thus Fanny Price, Austen’s long-suffering heroine in<italic>Mansfield</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14.</label>
                     <title>Memory and Cognition</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Sutton</surname>
                           <given-names>John</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Harris</surname>
                           <given-names>Celia B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib3" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Barnier</surname>
                           <given-names>Amanda J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his contribution to the first issue of<italic>Memory Studies</italic>, Jeffrey Olick notes that despite “the mutual affirmations of psychologists who want more emphasis on the social and sociologists who want more emphasis on the cognitive,” in fact “actual cross-disciplinary research . . . has been much rarer than affirmations about its necessity and desirability.”¹ The peculiar, contingent disciplinary divisions that structure our academic institutions create and enable many powerful intellectual cultures, but memory researchers are unusually aware that uneasy faultlines and glaring gulfs lie in the uncertain zones between them. The processes of memory are simultaneously natural and cultural.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15.</label>
                     <title>Physiological Memory Systems</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Caygill</surname>
                           <given-names>Howard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of cultural memory depends almost without exception upon a prior physiological or psychological account of individual memory. Aby Warburg’s influential studies of cultural memory, including his innovative<italic>Mnemosyne</italic>project of the mid-to late 1920s are rooted in his early work on energetic models of the physiology of memory, 1 contemporary with those that provided the point of departure for Freud’s analyses of the pathologies of memory in the 1895<italic>Project for a Scientific Psychology</italic>and for Bergson’s 1896<italic>Matter and Memory</italic>. Charting the relationship between cultural processes of memory and the formation of individual memory remains a challenge</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16.</label>
                     <title>Memory-Talk:</title>
                     <subtitle>London Childhoods</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Alexander</surname>
                           <given-names>Sally</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marc Bloch’s remark comes halfway through the unfinished final chapter of<italic>The Historian’s Craft</italic>, on historical causation. For Bloch human consciousness is “the subject matter of history . . . reality itself.” To ask why something happened or how it happened and under what conditions is a “common law of the mind,” Bloch avers, an “instinctive need of understanding.” Historical facts are psychological facts in the sense that however “brutal” are external forces, “their action is weakened or intensified by man and his mind.” Man’s mind is not always conscious, logical, or rational, Bloch continues; it can be explained neither</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17.</label>
                     <title>Affect and Embodiment</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Callard</surname>
                           <given-names>Felicity</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Papoulias</surname>
                           <given-names>Constantina</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his book<italic>Neuropolitics: Thinking, Culture, Speed</italic>, political theorist William Connolly protests against “the insufficiency of . . . intellectualist and deliberationist models of thinking’’ by suggesting that such models, as manifested in philosophy and the human sciences, give too much priority to the highest and conceptually most sophisticated brain nodules in thinking and judgment [and may] . . . underestimate the importance of body image, unconscious motor memory, and thought-imbued affect.²</p>
                     <p>Connolly is specifically interested here in expanding what thinking is and does, but to do so, he immediately turns to reconceptualizations of thinking currently taking place within neuroscience.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18.</label>
                     <title>Telling Stories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory and Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Freeman</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Ever since the pioneering work of Sir Frederic Bartlett, it has become commonplace to assume that the process of remembering the personal past is a reconstructive one mediated by a host of significant factors, ranging from prevailing conventions of remembering all the way to the inevitable impact of present experience on the rendering of the past.¹ The recognition of this simple and seemingly indisputable fact has become something of a double-edged sword in the conceptualization of memory. On the one hand, it has vastly expanded the field of memory studies: memory, far from being the mere videotape-like replica of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19.</label>
                     <title>Ritual and Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Feuchtwang</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The study of ritual has received its greatest elaboration in the work of anthropologists. This chapter, then, will be a discussion of how anthropologists, including psychological anthropologists, say ritual is related to human memory. Let me begin the discussion with the first question a reader may ask: What is ritual?</p>
                     <p>The simplest definition of ritual is repeated and standardized communicative action, in which communication is not simply through signs but also through symbols. In the<italic>International Encyclopaedia of the Social Sciences</italic>’s entry on ritual, Edmund Leach defines it as any form of repeated action that is not only functional or</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20.</label>
                     <title>A Long War:</title>
                     <subtitle>Public Memory and the Popular Media</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hamilton</surname>
                           <given-names>Paula</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>299</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most difficult theoretical issues confronting the study of memory has been the conceptual problem of group memory and how memories carried by individuals become part of a larger social dynamic. While there has been much debate about descriptive, adjectival terms such as “collective,” “cultural,” “popular,” and “social” memory, terms that are often invoked with noticeable imprecision, less consideration has been given to questions of what social relations make memory public or how we understand the very “publicness” of memory. When we think of<italic>the</italic>public, or<italic>a</italic>public, it is<italic>out there</italic>, encompassing the notion of being</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21.</label>
                     <title>Sites of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Winter</surname>
                           <given-names>Jay</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>312</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sites of memory are places where groups of people engage in public activity through which they express “a collective shared knowledge . . . of the past, on which a group’s sense of unity and individuality is based.”¹ The group that goes to such sites inherits earlier meanings attached to the event, as well as adding new meanings. Such activity is crucial to the presentation and preservation of commemorative sites. When such groups disperse or disappear, sites of memory lose their initial force, and may fade away entirely.</p>
                     <p>The term, abumbrated in a seven-volume study edited by Pierre Nora,² has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>22.</label>
                     <title>Cinema and Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Radstone</surname>
                           <given-names>Susannah</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The recent film<italic>The Butterfly Effect</italic>(Eric Bress and J. Mackye Gruber, 2004) tells the story of a young man, Evan, whose capacity to recover lost memories goes further than most, for once his memories return, he learns how to “jump into” the scenes of his past, traveling back in time to divert fate and put right the wrongs of the past. But this “memory travel” turns out to be doomed from the start. Only by killing himself at birth, Evan discovers, can he change the past and save the girl he loves. In an early scene, Evan is undergoing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>23.</label>
                     <title>Machines of Memory</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Goodman</surname>
                           <given-names>Steve</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Parisi</surname>
                           <given-names>Luciana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>343</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the age of sampling, chronology is twisted from a straight line into a loop. Cybernetic memories are plucked out of history, stored in machine banks, to be potentially mutated, then reassembled in any combination rhythmically. Digitally coded events leave sensory residue across distributed networks of body-machines. Memories are transgenetically transported across species and scales; biological programming becomes folded into unintended host bodies in a mnemonic symbiosis: layers of memory stratified into a machinery of achronological time.</p>
                     <p>The evolution of capitalism is marked by the technological development of human history. The idea that this evolution will result in homeostatic equilibrium</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>24.</label>
                     <title>Slavery, Historicism, and the Poverty of Memoralization</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Palmié</surname>
                           <given-names>Stephan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>363</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Visiting revolutionary Cuba in the winter of 1967–68, the Jamaican writer Andrew Salkey was one of the last ever to record a conversation with a person who remembered once having been a slave in a New World plantation society.¹ Born in 1860 to enslaved parents on a plantation in the province of Villa Clara, Salkey’s centenarian interlocutor, Esteban Montejo, had run away as an adolescent, hiding in the woods for what may have been several years until news of the end of Cuba’s first war of independence and the gradual abolition of slavery reached him. Yet slavery did not</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>25.</label>
                     <title>Soviet Memories:</title>
                     <subtitle>Patriotism and Trauma</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Merridale</surname>
                           <given-names>Catherine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>376</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Citizens of the former Soviet Union, the men and women who grew up under Communism, share many extraordinary experiences of hardship, violence, and trauma. They have also spent the greater part of their lives interpreting and discussing their experience in a language almost entirely shaped by ideology. These aspects of their mental world lend special resonance to the work of collecting and analyzing their memories. In their case, too, the controversial term “collective memory” has real meaning. The Soviet state was very largely sealed from outside influences for several decades beginning in the 1930s. Official discourse was carefully shaped and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>26.</label>
                     <title>The Witness in the Archive:</title>
                     <subtitle>Holocaust Studies/Memory Studies</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hirsch</surname>
                           <given-names>Marianne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Spitzer</surname>
                           <given-names>Leo</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>390</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“In the past half-century, two works have marked what can be called conceptual breakthroughs in our apprehension of the Holocaust,” writes Shoshana Felman in her 2002 book<italic>The Juridical Unconscious</italic>.¹ “The first was Hannah Arendt’s<italic>Eichmann in Jerusalem</italic>, which appeared in the United States in 1963 as a report on the Eichmann trial held in Israel in 1961. The second was the film<italic>Shoah</italic>by Claude Lanzmann, which first appeared in France in 1985.” These two works, Felman elaborates, changed “the vocabulary of collective memory”—they added a “<italic>new idiom</italic>to the discourse on the Holocaust.” A new idiom, Felman</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>27.</label>
                     <title>The Long Afterlife of Loss</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hoffman</surname>
                           <given-names>Eva</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>406</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Loss leaves a long trail in its wake. Sometimes, if the loss is large enough, the trail seeps and winds like invisible psychic ink through individual lives, decades, and generations. When the losses are as enormous as those that followed from the Holocaust—when what was lost was not only individuals but a world—the disappearances and the absences may haunt us unto the third generation; and they may inform our very vision of the world.</p>
                     <p>The transmission of loss across generations undoubtedly happens in the aftermath of every collective atrocity. But the Holocaust was a history-altering event, the great</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>28.</label>
                     <title>Migration, Food, Memory, and Home-Building</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hage</surname>
                           <given-names>Ghassan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>416</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The relation between home and food is an essential one. Its ideological power is constantly exhibited in various items of everyday life such as the status of the “homemade” on the food market. That a quiche, for example, is labeled “homemade” at one’s local delicatessen distinguishes it from the mass-produced. It makes it ooze that specifically homely goodness: intimations of sound nutrition, careful choice of ingredients, and careful labor (of love). That is, it becomes a bit of “mother’s cooking”—which, at an important level, is, of course, a continuation of breast-feeding, the most homely of the homely yearnings and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>29.</label>
                     <title>The Seventh Veil:</title>
                     <subtitle>Feminism, Recovered Memory, and the Politics of the Unconscious</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Haaken</surname>
                           <given-names>Janice</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>428</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>The Seventh Veil</italic>, released in 1945, represents one of the earliest cinematic portrayals of gothic psychiatric narratives— stories that position the female psyche as a darkly shrouded mystery, revealed through the investigations of a pioneering psychiatrist.¹ As a prototype of this genre,<italic>The Seventh Veil</italic>registers the emerging position of the psychiatrist in facilitating modern forms of female subjectivity—forms that require a reworking of memory and a therapeutic encounter with a debilitating past.</p>
                     <p>The film opens with Francesca Cunningham, a talented young concert pianist, languishing in a catatonic state after a car accident. Physically recovered but emotionally paralyzed, she</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>30.</label>
                     <title>The Gender of Memory in Post-Apartheid South Africa</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Coombes</surname>
                           <given-names>Annie E.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>442</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Established in 1996 as an essential component of nation-building and the peace process, the Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC) was born out of the historic compromise brokered in 1993– 94 between black and white nationalism in South Africa, a compromise that many have insisted inevitably circumscribed the commission’s work, thwarting its attempts to “heal the nation.”² The commission’s brief, in the words of its chair, Archbishop Desmond Tutu, was to</p>
                     <p>unearth the truth about our dark past, to lay the ghosts of that past so that they will not return to haunt us and that we will thereby contribute to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Afterword</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Passerini</surname>
                           <given-names>Luisa</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>459</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The present state of memory studies requires a particular attention to the transmission of what has been accumulated in this field since the 1970s. That was a decade in which many of the energies that had been employed in direct political activism during the previous decade were translated into cultural terms, opening up new areas of research, in which memory was central. I am thinking of the role memory has played over the past four decades in the constitution of cultural history and cultural studies in general, and more specifically of gender studies, cinema and literary studies, area studies, age</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>465</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>537</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1c999bq.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>545</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
