<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BF1078.H86 1989</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dreams</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Dreams</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Research</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Cognitive psychology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="nlm">Dreams</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="nlm">Psychoanalytic Interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Multiplicity of Dreams</book-title>
         <subtitle>Memory, Imagination, and Consciousness</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Hunt</surname>
               <given-names>Harry T.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>10</day>
         <month>09</month>
         <year>1989</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300043303</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300237948</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1989</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1xp3sfz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Dreams have been interpreted as divine revelations, previews of the future, relivings of the past, and expressions of unconscious conflicts. In this fascinating and comprehensive book, psychologist Harry T. Hunt provides a thorough look at all aspects of dreaming, from the theories of Freud and Jung to the latest developments in sleep laboratories. Drawing on insights from anthropology and psychiatry as well as from cognitive psychology, Hunt argues that there are many types of dreams, and he classifies them systematically for the first time.</p>
         <p>Hunt discusses the ways in which dreams can teach us about the mind, relating dreaming to memory, creativity, and visual thinking. he integrates recent research on such topics as lucid dreams (in which the dreamer is conscious of dreaming and controls the course of the dream), archetypal dreams, and nightmares, as well as the symbolic meaning of dreams, dreams in young children, and the relations between narrative structure and visual-spatial metaphor in dreams.</p>
         <p>This book is richly rewarding to both scientists and the general public, for it proposes a pluralistic interpretation of dreams that will be of great interest to experts and at the same time explains in language accessible to nonprofessional readers what we know about dreams-those absorbing creations of our own minds.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="271"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>Dream Studies and the Fundamental Question of Meaning</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Dream research, both experimental and clinical-phenomenological, has arrived at a point of historical hiatus. Research on the psychophysiology of the REM (Rapid Eye Movement) state, once widely heralded as a means of testing Freudian dream theory and settling mind–brain controversies, now faces skepticism, disillusionment, and lack of funding. True, a great deal has been learned about the unique physiology of the REM state as a periodic, chemically mediated condition of arousal in mammalian sleep, but the anticipation that understanding REM will explain dreaming has been shaken as researchers realize that dreaming involves far more than the specific conditions of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>Further Antinomies of Dreams, Dreaming, and Dream Research</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Having set out the superordinate dimensions of our analysiscognitive science versus organismic—holistic cognition, Freud versus Jung, representational versus presentational symbolism, and causal process versus meaning—we complete our review of the literature by considering the more specific antinomies of current dream research. Each side of these contrasting dimensions is supported by important research findings and consistent theory. This in itself may illustrate the actual multiplicity of the processes of dreaming. It is equally important to locate whatever syntheses are afforded by this material and to understand them as necessarily provisional and temporary-both because of the open-ended and indeterminate nature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>Pax Memoria:</title>
                     <subtitle>Memory versus Imagination in the Psychology of Dreaming</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is fascinating how often ostensibly empirical debates in the human sciences actually rest on largely unarticulated philosophical antinomies. So it is that within cognitive approaches to dreaming we find intimations of a hidden and very old agenda. Does an empirically based account of dreaming require a theory of constructive imagination—with its roots in the idealist/romanticist tradition of Western thought? Or rather does it afford yet another opportunity to demonstrate that all imagination is really just a complex form of memory and learning-an extension of the rationalist and reductionist attempt, now computerized, to understand the complex in terms of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>Problems in the Definition of Dreaming</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since Hughlings-Jackson, neurologists and psychiatrists have attempted to distinguish between<italic>positive symptoms</italic>—anomalous behavior and experience that seem to define a syndrome or condition—and the more fundamental<italic>negative</italic>or<italic>loss of capacity symptoms.</italic>The latter constitute the core dissolution, for which the positive and more obvious signs compensate as the essentially normal capacities still left intact. Freud (191 1, 1919a) was influenced by this tradition: he understood hallucinations and delusions as spontaneous attempts to recover interest in the world in the face of a more primary narcissistic withdrawal. Generally it is assumed that the negative core is harder to</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>The Multiplicity of Dreaming in Anthropology, the Ancient World, and the Nineteenth Century</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Nineteenth-century dream studies, prior to Freud, continue to fascinate, in part because they are based on careful observations by single individuals (and their like-minded friends) of their own often distinctive and unusually developed dreams. Precisely because long, sustained self-reflection on dreams seemed to change their dreams in mulitple but characteristic directions, these writers also cast a unique light on normative dreaming (at least within our own tradition). William James, Sigmund Freud, and A. R. Luria all held that only the selective exaggeration of the average allows us to see its normally masked dimensions and processes. On this approach exaggeration, excess,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Basic Dimensions of the Dream Diamond</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The origins of the following system of classification are of interest in light of the historical and contemporary antinomies of dream research. At a recent conference of the Association for the Study I of Dreams, Robert Monroe, a former television executive who has described his elaborate altered-state experiences in<italic>Journeys Out of Body</italic>and<italic>Far Journeys</italic>and is head of a private foundation for the study of out-of-body experience, gave an invited address. The laboratory-oriented members of ASD were somewhat uncomfortable with Monroe, but the crowded auditorium was in marked contrast to the sparse attendance at earlier research sessions. Monroe,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>Specific Imaginative-Intuitive Faculties as Forms of Dreaming</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>102</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Evidence of creative imagistic activity in dream formation does not encourage us to assimilate all dreaming to representational language. Still, the difficulty in evaluating when dream imagery goes beyond prior verbal understanding suggests that imagery and language must continuously interact anyway. The linguistic processes that enter dreams most readily are more presentational than representational—in that “the whole domain of verbal wit is put at the disposal of the dreamwork” (Freud, 1900, p. 376). Certainly, in many of Freud’s own dreams ordinary language has been spontaneously rearranged in the form of rebuslike wordplay, visual hieroglyphics based on special turns of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 8</label>
                     <title>Lucid Dreams and Nightmares:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Transition to Formal Self-Reference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Because lucid dreams (and related subtypes) violate all traditional attempts to define an essence of dreaming, their study is especially useful in highlighting the dangers of such a monolithic approach. This in turn helps to explain the defensive hostility with which current research on lucidity has been greeted. Several attempts at a logicophilosophical account of dreaming (Sartre, Boss, Malcolm) have been predicated on the impossibility of what we now term fully lucid dreaming. Indeed, the analytical philosopher Norman Malcolm insists that at best we can only<italic>dream</italic>that we dream; we cannot know it as we know facts when awake.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 9</label>
                     <title>Archetypal and Titanic Dreams:</title>
                     <subtitle>Abstract Imageries of Formal Self-Reference</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>128</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Archetypal dreams, essentially the same as the culture pattern dreams of anthropology (see chapter lo), are more like self-sufficient cohesive visions than the patchwork mnemic reorganizations of ordinary dreaming.¹ Jung’s own dreams, recounted in his autobiography<italic>Memories, Dreams, Reflections</italic>(1961), provide evident examples (see chapter 10 for a detailed comparison of the dreams of Freud and Jung). However, my colleagues and I (Hunt et al., 1982) have found evidence that most subjects report archetypal dreams like those of Jung when asked to provide their most “fantastic dreamlike dream” (see appendix, table 1). Thus, although statistically speaking, subjects tend to have</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 10</label>
                     <title>Freud, Jung, and Culture Pattern Dreams:</title>
                     <subtitle>Archetypal Imagination versus Cultural Programming</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>It is quite clear that Freud’s and Jung’s dreams differed markedly in style or form-yet with enough overlap to suggest that they represent variations within a single dreaming process. The old saw that Freudian patients dream Freudian dreams, and Jungians dream Jungian, also seems likely, although causation is less clear. Dreaming is socially malleable, but given the differences in the dreams of the founders, it may well be that people are drawn to one tradition or the other because it mirrors their lives (awake and asleep).</p>
                     <p>A continuing debate, also reflected within the anthropological literature on culture pattern dreams, revolves</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 11</label>
                     <title>Narrative Structures:</title>
                     <subtitle>Story Grammar versus Imagistics</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Any cognitive psychology of dreaming must encounter and reconcile two statements: “the dream is a story” and “the dream is imagery.” Neither statement is as obvious as it initially appears, I I because there is no agreement in contemporary cognitive psychology on the ultimate relation between visual-spatial imagery and language. Much evidence and theory supports both the view that a visual-spatial imagistic intelligence rests directly on and creatively reorganizes the processes of perception and the view that mental imagery is a surface paraphrase of abstract propositional knowledge, whose deep structure is accordingly far closer to verbal syntax than visual imagery.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 12</label>
                     <title>The Visual-Spatial Side of Dream Formation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>180</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The correlation of visual-spatial forms of dream bizarreness with waking measures of imagination and creativity is not sufficient to establish the metaphoric roots of such experience. Despite recent demonstrations of cortical antecedents in phasic REM discharge, it could still be that imagistic bizarreness works on the randomization model of creativity, so favored in current artificial intelligence accounts. On that model, creative imagery would operate by destroying the continuity of ongoing propositional intelligence, so that its later reestablishment would have to include novel and so potentially useful elements. The question becomes whether visual-spatial transformations in dreams and closely related features of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 13</label>
                     <title>Dreaming:</title>
                     <subtitle>Deconstruction and Reconstruction</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In beginning an overview of dreaming we could do worse than return to the nineteenth-century dream phenomenologists—who at least knew what later laboratory researchers and clinicians I I have forgotten, that description and classification are primary in science. DuPrel, Schemer, and Saint-Denys anticipated recent rating systems of dream bizarreness by calling attention to the positive and negative sides of dreaming. Dreaming tends always toward a delirium syndrome, but the corresponding impairment of verbal-reflective thinking allows a positive release of visual-spatial metaphor and intuition, the frames or modules of mind that are based on a relative simultaneity of expression. Carl</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPENDIX</title>
                     <subtitle>Variations across Multiple Groups in Forms of Dreaming</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>References</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>237</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1xp3sfz.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>263</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
