<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7mjb8</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">NX180.S3 S77 2017</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Science and the arts</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Biology</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Aesthetics</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
         <subject>General Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Bioaesthetics</book-title>
         <subtitle>Making Sense of Life in Science and the Arts</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>STRATHAUSEN</surname>
               <given-names>CARSTEN</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="series-editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>WOLFE</surname>
               <given-names>CARY</given-names>
            </name>
            <role>SERIES EDITOR</role>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>15</day>
         <month>10</month>
         <year>2017</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781517900755</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781452955131</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1452955131</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Minnesota Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Minneapolis; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Regents of the University of Minnesota</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt1pwt828"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In recent years, bioaesthetics has used the latest discoveries in evolutionary studies and neuroscience to provide new ways of looking at art and aesthetics. Carsten Strathausen's remarkable exploration of this emerging field is the first comprehensive account of its ideas, as well as a timely critique of its limitations.</p>
         <p>Strathausen familiarizes readers with the basics of bioaesthetics, grounding them in its philosophical underpinnings while articulating its key components. Importantly, he delves into the longstanding problem of the "two cultures" that separate the arts and the sciences. Seeking to make bioaesthetics a more robust way of thinking, Strathausen then critiques it for failing to account for science's historical and cultural assumptions. At its worst, he says, biologism reduces artworks to mere automatons that rubber-stamp pre-established scientific truths.</p>
         <p>Written with a sensitive understanding of science's strengths, and willing to refute its best arguments,<italic>Bioaesthetics</italic>helps readers separate the sensible from the specious. At a time when humanities departments are shrinking-and when STEM education is on the rise-<italic>Bioaesthetics</italic>makes vital points about the limitations of science, while lodging a robust defense of the importance of the humanities.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2000, Ian Hacking, the renowned philosopher and historian of science, published a book titled<italic>The Social Construction of What?</italic>Written during the science wars of the 1990s and published a few years after the infamous Sokal hoax in 1996, Hacking’s study provided a trenchant critique of the various constructivist theories that influenced academic discourse at a time when scholars in all fields sought to expose the constructed nature of ever more phenomena. Although polemical at times, the main goal of the book was less to expose the fashion-driven nature of academic discourse than to clarify the distinct—and at</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>HUMAN NATURE AFTER KANT</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are good reasons to begin our discussion of bioaesthetics with Kant, who published at a time when academic disciplines were still being established and the “two cultures” did not yet exist.¹ Aesthetics, indeed, was a new academic discipline defined by the German philosopher Gottlieb Alexander Baumgarten in 1750 as the “science of sensory knowledge.” Aesthetics, according to Baumgarten, was meant to clarify the relation between the sensory data based on human experience, on the one hand, and the scientific knowledge that could be derived from that data via the use of reason, on the other. In his<italic>First Critique</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>MARXISM AND BIOLOGY</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The left needs a new paradigm,” Peter Singer argued in his 1999 manifesto<italic>A Darwinian Left</italic>. That new paradigm should be evolutionary theory to help correct the mistaken belief “that there is no fixed human nature,” a belief that, according to Singer, continues to shape the left’s knee-jerk rejection of Darwinism.¹ Many on the left, Singer claimed, profoundly misunderstand Darwinian theory: they identify it exclusively with the ruthless “struggle for existence” and “the survival of the fittest” elaborated by Herbert Spencer in the late nineteenth century, which led to the rise of twentieth-century totalitarianism and its racist politics of “social</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>CULTURAL EVOLUTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>103</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the summer of 1975, Harvard University Press published Edward O. Wilson’s<italic>Sociobiology: The New Synthesis</italic>.¹ The book, and its author, became notorious soon thereafter, and<italic>Sociobiology</italic>remained a subject of intense academic and public debate for years to come. There were various reasons for this notoriety, some related to the scientific and disciplinary questions raised by<italic>Sociobiology</italic>, others having to do with political and moral concerns about its potential influence on social politics in the United States.² We already encountered a similar mix of academic and political arguments during the Althusser–Monod debate discussed in the previous chapter. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>EVOLUTIONARY AESTHETICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Adorno’s opening statement in<italic>Aesthetic Theory</italic>still rings true today, almost a half century after its posthumous publication in 1970. It remains a commonplace not only within art history, but across the humanities in general, that traditional efforts to answer the age-old question “What is art?” are a waste of time at best and an ideological power play at worst. The problem is that a definitive theory of art amounts to a contradiction in terms. Art, the philosopher Morris Weitz said, is “an open concept,” and there will always be cases “that would call for some sort of<italic>decision</italic>on</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>NEUROAESTHETICS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>On November 11, 2007, the<italic>New York Times</italic>ran a full-page article in its Op-Ed section titled “This Is Your Brain on Politics.”¹ Cowritten by three neuroscientists, one public policy analyst, and three neuromarketing experts, the article summarized the test results of using fMRIs on twenty undecided voters who had to answer questions about their preferences for the upcoming 2008 presidential election. The results were hardly revolutionary: “Voters sense both peril and promise in party brands” was one of the findings in bold print. “Emotions about Hillary Clinton are mixed,” “The gender gap may be closing,” and “Mitt Romney shows</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CODA</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>227</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>“The enemy is the organism.”¹ The organism prevents the actualization of the body’s virtual power of becoming: “What a body can do is the nature and the limits of its power to be affected,” Deleuze famously stated in his book on Spinoza, and he added, “<italic>We do not even know of what affections we are capable, nor the extent of our power</italic>.”² In order to unleash this power, the human body must shed its organs and its organization. It must transcend both the evolutionary history of its species (phylogenesis) and its acquired habits during life (ontogenesis). The mind that pertains</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>239</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1pwt828.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>306</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
