<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Animation (Cinematography)</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Animated films</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Cartoonists</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>A Reader In Animation Studies</book-title>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Pilling</surname>
               <given-names>Jayne</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>22</day>
         <month>05</month>
         <year>1998</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780861969005</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">0861969006</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>John Libbey Publishing</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1997</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>John Libbey &amp; Company Pty Ltd.</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16gz839"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Cartoons-both from the classic Hollywood era and from more contemporary feature films and television series-offer a rich field for detailed investigation and analysis. Contributors draw on theories and methodology from film, television, and media studies, art history and criticism, and feminism and gender studies.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="304"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Society for Animation Studies:</title>
                     <subtitle>A brief history</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Deneroff</surname>
                           <given-names>Harvey</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>While I began the Society for Animation Studies (SAS) in Los Angeles in late 1987, I was an unemployed PhD and an adult child of an animator who had been harbouring a long-held frustration with the way the cinema studies establishment seemed to ignore animation. With no funds and lacking an academic affiliation, I nevertheless garnered immediate support from local universities and organisations, as well as a small cadre of academics, independent scholars and filmmakers who gladly agreed to serve on the SAS Steering Committee.</p>
                     <p>Armed with a grant from the Motion Picture Screen Cartoonists, IATSE Local 839 (it helped</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pilling</surname>
                           <given-names>Jayne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past decade, animation seems finally to have emerged from its previously very marginalised status, both in terms of a growing adult audience for the very heterogenous range of films that come under the rubric ‘animation’ and in terms of academic study.</p>
                     <p>This explosion of interest reflects a growing recognition of animation as a medium that spans a far wider range of films than that of cartoons only for children.</p>
                     <p>The creation of a Society for Animation Studies (SAS) in 1988 is an indication of this changing attitude, and also a significant contributor to it. This book comprises a</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>1</label>
                     <title>What is animation and who needs to know?</title>
                     <subtitle>An essay on definitions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Denslow</surname>
                           <given-names>Philip Kelly</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>There are many definitions of animation. The most obvious source of one, the<italic>Webster</italic>dictionary, says animation is:</p>
                     <p>a:a motion picture made by photographing successive positions of inanimate objects (as puppets or mechanical parts), b: Animated Cartoon, a motion picture made from a series of drawings simulating motion by means of slight progressive changes.</p>
                     <p>This is a fairly common understanding of the term animation, but it reflects a limited exposure to what the art form has to offer. Whether one agrees with it or not, the Webster definition is useful because one can learn something about who is doing the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>2</label>
                     <title>‘Reality’ effects in computer animation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Manovich</surname>
                           <given-names>Lev</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This is how Frederick Hartt, the author of a widely used textbook<italic>Art. A History of Painting, Sculpture, Architecture</italic>describes the importance of Giotto di Bondone, ‘the first giant in the long history of Italian painting’:</p>
                     <p>In contemporary Italian eyes the step from Cimabue to Giotto was immense in that weight and mass, light and inward extension were suddenly introduced in a direct and convincing manner.¹</p>
                     <p>Giotto’s miracle lay in being able to produce for the first time on a flat surface three-dimensional forms, which the French could achieve only in sculpture. For the first time since antiquity a painter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>3</label>
                     <title>Second-order realism and post-modern aesthetics in computer animation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Darley</surname>
                           <given-names>Andy</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper is concerned with questions of aesthetic form. It is about the relationship between computer imaging and the emergence of a new aesthetics of self – referentiality and surface play. I want to indicate some ways in which such an aesthetic is occurring, and attempt to locate and describe some of its defining characteristics and forms.</p>
                     <p>I shall do this by examining the short film<italic>Red’s Dream</italic>(1987) – a computer animation from the domain of popular entertainment. This film is an example of what I call<italic>secondary</italic>or<italic>second-order</italic>realism; that is to say, it involves an attempt to produce</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>4</label>
                     <title>The Quay brothers’ The Epic of Gilgamesh and the ‘metaphysics of obscenity’</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Weiner</surname>
                           <given-names>Steve</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>25</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The puppet animators Stephen and Timothy Quay, with producer Keith Griffiths, form the Atelier Koninck. Their first film,<italic>Nocturna Artificialia</italic>(1979), a single-puppet film and<italic>Ein Brudermord,</italic>a two-puppet film based on Kafka, were both heavily atmospheric.The Atelier then made a paper-puppet satire on Stravinsky and a film about the Flemish playwright De Ghelderode. Then followed three art documentaries, for which the Quays made puppet-animated inserts, on Punch and Judy, Janacek and Jan Svankmajer.<italic>Songs of the Chief of the Officers of Hunar Louse or This Unnameable Little Broom</italic>(1985) (called<italic>Gilgamesh</italic>for short), a film in which a moronic</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>5</label>
                     <title>Narrative strategies for resistance and protest in Eastern European animation</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moritz</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Soviet Russia’s domination of Eastern European countries for over 40years (from the fall of the ‘Iron Curtain’ around 1947 until the ‘Glasnost’ of about 1990) brought mixed blessings for animation. On the one hand, Soviet policy favoured cinema as an essential, powerful popular art form and maintained busy animation studios not only for each country but also for distinct ethnic groups; animators were often tenured civil servants with guaranteed full-time employment making not only theatrical cartoons but also public service and educational animation, children’s films of folk culture and titles and special effects for features. On the other hand, soviet</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>6</label>
                     <title>Putting themselves in the pictures:</title>
                     <subtitle>Images of women in the work of Joanna Quinn, Candy Guard and Alison de Vere</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Law</surname>
                           <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>48</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 1975, Laura Mulvey published her seminalarticle, ‘Visual Pleasure and Narrative Cinema’, arguing that the object of the gaze in classical Hollywood cinema is female while the subject is male.¹ Since then, many theorists have developed Mulvey’s theories in more detail, though others have contested her position. Nonetheless, the issue of the representation of women in film has become, without question, a central concern within media studies, including the realm of animation.</p>
                     <p>Many filmmakers working in live action and animation have been concerned to find alternative means of portraying women and women’s issues. This essay explores the animation of three</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>7</label>
                     <title>An analysis of Susan Pitt’s Asparagus and Joanna Priestley’s All My Relations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Couzin</surname>
                           <given-names>Sharon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>To describe the woman’s voice in contemporary animation requires a brief historical note on the representation of women in animation as well as their lack of participation in the planning and execution of these works. In addition, we must look to the role the feminist movement has played in both understanding and articulating the place of women in art in general – how at this point we can say the movement has re-politicised art; in this case, film.</p>
                     <p>To address these issues I wish to refer to two animations:<italic>Asparagus</italic>by Suzan Pitt and<italic>All My Relations</italic>by Joanna Priestley. While</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>8</label>
                     <title>Clay animation comes out of the inkwell:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Fleischer brothers and clay animation</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Frierson</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Clay animated films were produced in the United States as early as 1908 when Edison Manufacturing released a trick film entitled<italic>The Sculptor’s Welsh Rarebit Dream.</italic>In 1916, clay animation became something of a fad, as an East Coast artist named Helena Smith Dayton and a West Coast animator named Hopkins produced clay animated films on a wide range of subjects. Hopkins in particular was quite prolific, producing over 50 clay animated segments for the weekly<italic>Universal Screen Magazine.</italic>But by the 1920s, cartoon animation using either cels or slash system was firmly established as the dominant mode of animation</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>9</label>
                     <title>Bartosch’s The Idea</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moritz</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Berthold Bartosch deserves to be discussed among the important filmmakers – not just important animators – both for the intrinsic artistry of his 1932 film<italic>The Idea</italic>and for its seminal position as the first animation film created as an artwork with serious, even tragic, social and philosophical themes (as opposed documentary’, educational animations of McCay and the Fleischers or abstract of Ruttmann and Fischinger). That Bartosch does not always occupy position of honour in film history stems partly from the fact that the 25-minute<italic>Idea</italic>has not always been available to viewers and partly because<italic>The Idea</italic>could be his only</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>10</label>
                     <title>Norman McLaren and Jules Engel:</title>
                     <subtitle>Post-modernists</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moritz</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>104</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Of all the great names in animation, Norman McLaren has, paradoxically, suffered most from a kind of critical neglect. Everyone acknowledges his genius, but few discuss it. Numerous books and articles chronicle his life and describe his works, usually stressing the inventiveness of his filmic but rarely do they analyse his aesthetic qualities and achievements.¹</p>
                     <p>Most texts oriented toward animation as a Fine Art – such as the catalogue for the<italic>Film as Film</italic>exhibition that toured Germany and England from 1977 until ignore McLaren entirely while including Len Lye, Oskar Fischinger, Harry James Whitney and other animators who are McLaren’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>11</label>
                     <title>Disney, Warner Bros. and Japanese animation:</title>
                     <subtitle>Three world views</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Raffaelli</surname>
                           <given-names>Luca</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This paper essays an analysis of the philosophy behind two of the most prolific cartoon producers, Disney cartoons and the Japanese cartoon industry, while also examining that of contemporaneous non-Disney American cartoon studios. All were involved in serial production; that is, studios organised for the continuous production of animated films whether they were shorts or feature films for the cinema, television or the video-cassette market or television episodes or specials.</p>
                     <p>I concentrate on the birth and refinement of Disney’s philosophy during those years when Walt was working his hardest to promote the growth of his studios; that is, the period</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>12</label>
                     <title>The thief of Buena Vista:</title>
                     <subtitle>Disney’s Aladdin and Orientalism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Felperin</surname>
                           <given-names>Leslie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>We begin with a true story, but one so dense with stories within its stories, so layered with conflicting versions of the truth, that it seems to have garnered the narrational generative capacities of myth. It would take a modern Sheherezade far more than a thousand-and-one nights tounravel the complex skein of fact and fiction that surrounds the ur-narrative of the Gulf War of 1990. But that is not the purpose of this essay: here we are concerned with tracing how that vast story-cycle of fact is entangled with another story, the fictional film<italic>Aladdin</italic>, which is itself enmeshed in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>13</label>
                     <title>Animatophilia, cultural production and corporate interests:</title>
                     <subtitle>The case of Ren &amp; Stimpy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Langer</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>143</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the best-publicised events related to animation and video during 1992 was the conflict between Nickelodeon and filmmaker John Kricfalusi over the cablecast animation series<italic>The Ren &amp; Stimpy Show</italic>. Critics have hailed Kricfalusi as ‘a man of genius’ and the series as ‘the best animated cartoon come along since the glory days of the 1940s’.¹ Nickelodeon owned the rights to the programme and characters devised by Kricfalusi. Despite the acclaim for the filmmaker and the series, Nickelodeon transferred production from Kricfalusi’s Spumco studio to a new Games Productions studio,which used many former Spumco staff. Nickelodeon maintained that they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>14</label>
                     <title>Francis Bacon and Walt Disney revisited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Pummell</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Francis Bacon and Walt Disney</italic>is the provocative title of an essay byJohn Berger.¹ The provocation is in the link between ‘High Art’ and ‘Low Art’ as seen by the bourgeois art world and Berger uses the link to question the quality of Bacon’s work. However, he does so in such detail and in such a way that he reveals a potential link far more complex and suggestive than the dismissive intent of essay. Berger is always incisive and he uncovers connections where previously cultural assumptions concealed the tracks.</p>
                     <p>The opening of the essay brings together three strands of evidence</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>15</label>
                     <title>Body consciousness in the films of Jan Svankmajer</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Wells</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>177</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The work of Jan Svankmajer, celebrated Czechoslovakian animator and avant-garde filmmaker, demonstrates an ongoing pre-occupation with the codes and conditions of bodily function and identity. His fictions are characterised by the recognition of transience in the body and the place of the body as a defining instrument in socio-cultural mechanisms and indeed, as a socio-cultural mechanism. Svankmajer uses the unique vocabulary of animation in expressing these principles and essentially re-defines the conditions by which the body might be represented and re-defined aesthetically and politically.</p>
                     <p>This essay examines three main areas of address in Svankmajer’s work. Firstly, the body in transition;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>16</label>
                     <title>Eisenstein and Stokes on Disney:</title>
                     <subtitle>Film animation and omnipotence</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Pray</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Sergei Eisenstein loved the cartoon figure Mickey Mouse. The Soviet film director not only admired Walt Disney’s films but also made them part of the subject matter of his theoretical studies. With his characteristic ambition, these theoretical explorations of Disney’s animation were intended to serve as the bases for understanding animation and developing questions alluding to the nature of art itself.¹ Most of these writings are from the early 1940s, some years after his return from Hollywood where he had met Disney in 1937.² He was also reconsidering or at least reformulating his theoretical ideas, especially that of montage. That</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>17</label>
                     <title>Towards a post-modern animated discourse:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bakhtin, intertextuality and the cartoon carnival</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Lindvall</surname>
                           <given-names>Terrance R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Melton</surname>
                           <given-names>J. Matthew</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Mikhail Bakhtin complained that the wit of Voltaire and the Enlightenment era lacked the full-bodied comedy of the Medieval market place. In<italic>Rabela is and His World,</italic>Bakhtin celebrated the universal, ambivalent and grotesque ‘carnival comedy’ of the sixteenth century.¹ Enlightenment laughter is primarily mocking and satiric, subverting the folly of the hierarchy in its feasts of fools, asses and administrators. Medieval comedy, however, affirmed, renewed and revitalised the old, bringing forth new birth, life, hope and laughter. It simultaneously took apart and put together the Body of Humanity and the Christian Church. By means of deconstruction and then reconstruction,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>18</label>
                     <title>Restoring the aesthetics of early abstract films</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moritz</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Critical writing about the abstract films of the 1920s is generally ‘bogged down’ with the question of primacy. Hans Richter, who supplied information to most early film historians, stressed the point that his own films were the<italic>first</italic>abstract, experimental films ever made – along with Viking Eggeling’s<italic>Diagonal Symphony</italic>– which Richter dated 1919 or 1921, even in film titles that he had during the 1950s and 1960s. He consistently suggested that Walther Ruttmann Fischinger began filmmaking later, that Fischinger was a pupil and assistant Ruttmann’s, and furthermore insisted that Ruttmann was an artistic fraud whose lacked a true sense of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>19</label>
                     <title>Resistance and subversion in animated films of the Nazi era:</title>
                     <subtitle>The case of Hans Fischerkoesen</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Moritz</surname>
                           <given-names>William</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The average person today might not know much about German film during the Nazi era and even animation scholars might not know what German animation existed between 1933 and 1945. Such a gap in cinema studies reflects a larger problem present in the United States’ perception of this crucial period. Forty years after the World War II, many Americans still naively accept simplistic stereotypes of the Nazis such as the demonic fiend whose appetite for sadistic cruelty is matched only by his ravenous, perverse sexual appetite (who inhabits such dramatic works as Visconti’s<italic>The Damned,</italic>and is the bumbling fool,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>20</label>
                     <title>European influences on early Disney feature films</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Allan</surname>
                           <given-names>Robin</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>241</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Disney company today has become one of the most powerful entertainment conglomerates in the world. As the years go by it seems more than ever important to identify some of the cultural and aesthetic forces that influenced the founder of this empire, Walt Disney. The empire is based on film and still relies upon succeeding generations being familiar with the situations, stories and characters made popular through Walt Disney’s films, and the films themselves were indebted to an older cultural heritage which Disney absorbed and recreated for a new mass audience as part of the popular culture of his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>21</label>
                     <title>Norm Ferguson and the Latin American films of Walt Disney</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Kaufman</surname>
                           <given-names>J.B.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>261</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One of the most unusual chapters in the history of the Walt Disney studio began in 1941, when Disney was approached by the United States government to make a goodwill tour of South America. The United States had not officially entered World War II at that time, but the government noted with some concern a growing Nazi influence in South America and was seeking to counter that influence by promoting friendly ties between the Americas. Disney did make the trip, along with a group of his artists, and thus began a chain of events which eventually produced two feature-length pictures,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes on the contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>269</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16gz839.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>List of SAS Conference papers– 1989 to 1996</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>273</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
