<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt24h1dk</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">JC580 .P48 2004</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Truth commissions</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human rights</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Reconciliation</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Governmental investigations</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Political Science</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Shattered Voices</book-title>
         <subtitle>Language, Violence, and the Work of Truth Commissions</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Phelps</surname>
               <given-names>Teresa Godwin</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>01</month>
         <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780812219494</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780812203271</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University of Pennsylvania Press, Inc.</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2004</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University of Pennsylvania Press</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt3fh8vr"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Following periods of mass atrocity and oppression, states are faced with a question of critical importance in the transition to democracy: how to offer redress to victims of the old regime without perpetuating cycles of revenge. Traditionally, balance has been restored through arrests, trials, and punishment, but in the last three decades, more than twenty countries have opted to have a truth commission investigate the crimes of the prior regime and publish a report about the investigation, often incorporating accounts from victims. Although many praise the work of truth commissions for empowering and healing through words rather than violence, some condemn the practice as a poor substitute for traditional justice, achieved through trials and punishment. There has been until now little analysis of the unarticulated claim that underlies the truth commissions' very existence: that language-in this case narrative stories-can substitute for violence. Acknowledging revenge as a real and deep human need,<italic>Shattered Voices</italic>explores the benefits and problems inherent when a fragile country seeks to heal its victims without risking its own future. In developing a theory about the role of language in retribution, Teresa Godwin Phelps takes an interdisciplinary approach, delving into sources from Greek tragedy to<italic>Hamlet</italic>, from Kant to contemporary theories about retribution, from the Babylonian law codes to the South African Truth and Reconciliation Report. She argues that, given the historical and psychological evidence about revenge, starting afresh by drawing a bright line between past crimes and a new government is both unrealistic and unwise. When grievous harm happens, a rebalancing is bound to occur, whether it is orderly and lawful or disorderly and unlawful.<italic>Shattered Voices</italic>contends that language is requisite to any adequate balancing, and that a solution is viable only if it provides an atmosphere in which storytelling and subsequent dialogue can flourish. In the developing culture of ubiquitous truth reports, Phelps argues that we must become attentive to the form these reports take-the narrative structure, the use of victims' stories, and the way a political message is conveyed to the citizens of the emerging democracy. By looking concretely at the work and responsibilities of truth commissions,<italic>Shattered Voices</italic>offers an important and thoughtful analysis of the efficacy of the ways human rights abuses are addressed.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="192"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[i]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>[vii]</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Prologue for Paulina</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>In the winter of 1992 in London, I attended one of the first performances in English of <italic>Death and the Maiden</italic>, a play by Chilean writer Ariel Dorfman. Juliet Stevenson’s brilliant depiction of Paulina Salas presented a transfixed audience with a compelling question: what happens when a new and tenuous democracy, because of political necessity, turns its back on some of the victims of the regime it has replaced? Paulina is just such a victim, and the play provides a troubling answer.</p>
                     <p>The play opens when Gerardo, Paulina’s husband, returns very late to the isolated house he shares with Paulina.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter One</label>
                     <title>The Demise of Paulina’s Good:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Personal Revenge to State Punishment</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>“What about <italic>my</italic> good?” Paulina’s question embarrasses Gerardo, and it embarrasses most of us. If we or our loved ones are harmed, we call the police and thereafter depend upon the state to investigate, judge, and punish for us. As good citizens and emotionally stable individuals, we are taught to become procedurally and emotionally distanced from both the harm and its perpetrator. Victims who make a fuss about their own needs are treated as emotionally suspect.¹ Feeling and acting have collapsed into one impulse so that even when the state acts in our behalf, we are expected to relinquish an</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Two</label>
                     <title>The Demonizing of Revenge</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>24</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The first quotation, spoken by the ghost of Hamlet’s father at the initial meeting between the prince and the ghost, was written around 1600, the second in 1988. In less than 400 rears, the beliefs, in Western culture at least, that surround the taking of revenge have metamorphosed from viewing revenge as a natural and necessary component of love and the requisite mark of kinship to an all-out condemnation of revenge as unfit for “civilized people.” What happened in the interim? Revenge had a nearly sacrosanct place in early conceptions of justice. What changed the popular opinion concerning revenge from</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Three</label>
                     <title>Language, Violence, and Oppression</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The literary and philosophical traditions of many cultures reveal that the urge for revenge is an ancient, deep-rooted human need that has only tentatively been transferred to central authority in the form of state-sponsored retribution. If that need for revenge is not acknowledged by being in some way incorporated into formal systems of justice, as are the Furies by Athena in the <italic>Oresteia</italic>, it reemerges as private vengeance, as it does with Paulina in <italic>Death and the Maiden</italic>. It has the potentiality of “dripping poison over all the land,” as Athena fears the unsatisfied Furies will do in the <italic>Oresteia</italic>.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Four</label>
                     <title>What Can Stories Do?</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>52</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>If a state cannot enact traditional retribution for its citizens who were victimized by the former government, is there any point in the gathering and publishing of these victims’ stories? While the story of the evolution from revenge to retribution shows us that a state must do something, must take responsibility to effect a rebalancing for the victims or risk a reversion to personal revenge, our collective imagination has given us little in the way of alternatives to state violence. The pendulum of possible responses swings without pausing from the extreme of traditional retributive justice—requiring investigations, trials, and punishment</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Five</label>
                     <title>Telling Stories in a Search for Justice:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Argentinian, Chilean, and Salvadoran Truth Commissions</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>The rapid emergence of truth commissions and their collection and creation of narratives reflects, in part, the “return to narrative” that is prominent in diverse disciplines. Historians, philosophers, theologians, moralists, anthropologists, sociologists, psychologists, psychoanalysts, artists, and even legal scholars¹ have newly and increasingly embraced narrative as a valid and powerful mode of explanation and representation of reality.² This change is characterized as a “return to narrative” because narrative, once the primary mode of discourse, has been long devalued. From the time of the classical Greeks until recently, narrative was regarded as an inferior mode of discourse, frivolous and fanciful compared</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Six</label>
                     <title>Telling Stories in a Search for More Than Justice:</title>
                     <subtitle>The South African Truth and Reconciliation Commission</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>From the outset, the South African Truth and Reconciliation Commission faced a formidable task. Unlike the Latin American commissions, which were rebuilding moral and political communities that had at least in theory preexisted the periods of oppression, the South African commission was creating an entirely new and hitherto inconceivable state that had never existed on the southern cape of Africa. The postapartheid South African government was committed to building a bridge between the past and the present, a link that fully acknowledged the harms that had occurred during the reign of apartheid and the new society that embraced equality. The</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>Chapter Seven</label>
                     <title>The Truth Must Dazzle Gradually</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>118</fpage>
                  <abstract abstract-type="extract">
                     <p>My ongoing project is to explore the question as to whether there is any reason to think, indeed hope, that the collecting and publishing of victims’ stories—the activities that surround writing a truth report—can bring an end to the cycle of revenge that threatens the stability of an emerging democracy. Is it sensible to suppose that language can carry such a burden? By examining some of the history of revenge and our troubled and ambivalent relationship to it, the early chapters have provided, I hope, a clearer understanding of what a victim such as Paulina might mean when</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Bibliography</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt3fh8vr.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
