<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">PS1338F85 2006</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Twain, Mark, 1835-1910</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism and interpretation</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Religion and literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Theology in literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The REVEREND MARK TWAIN</book-title>
         <subtitle>THEOLOGICAL BURLESQUE, FORM, AND CONTENT</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>FULTON</surname>
               <given-names>JOE B.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>20</day>
         <month>12</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780814210246</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780814272527</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Ohio State University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Columbus</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>The Ohio State University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1kgqw8m"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>Description not available.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>PREFACE AND ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 1</label>
                     <title>“I WAS EDUCATED, I WAS TRAINED, I WAS A PRESBYTERIAN”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Conformity and Critique in Mark Twain’s Religious Dialogue</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>IN 1867, AS Twain told the story in the San Francisco newspaper the<italic>Alta California</italic>, he approached the organizer of the<italic>Quaker City</italic>expedition to the Holy Land by having a colleague introduce him as Mark Twain, the<italic>Reverend</italic>Mark Twain. One might reasonably doubt that this really happened, but historical accuracy is in this case beside the point. More apropos is Twain’s use of the incident in the<italic>Alta California</italic>letters that he later revised for<italic>The Innocents Abroad</italic>(1869). It was a typical sort of joke for Twain—one with a barb to it. The<italic>Quaker City</italic>expedition</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 2</label>
                     <title>“PROV’DENCE DON’T FIRE NO BLANK CA’TRIDGES, BOYS”:</title>
                     <subtitle>God, Grotesques, and Sunday-School Books in Mark Twain’s Roughing It</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>38</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE<italic>OVERLAND MONTHLY</italic>was hardly alone in its repeated estimation that<italic>Roughing It</italic>(1872) was a “grotesque” production (“Anonymous Review” 580, 581). In the years following the book’s publication, many reviewers noted the presence of the grotesque in<italic>Roughing It</italic>. Writing in<italic>Appleton’s Journal</italic>, George Ferris lauded the “grotesque and irresistible form” present in Twain’s work (17). B. B. Toby, reviewing the book for the<italic>San Francisco Morning Call</italic>, criticized the illustrations as “even more grotesque than the text,” yet found the “grotesqueness and absurdity” of the text strangely appealing (1). As for Twain’s most perceptive critic, William Dean Howells</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 3</label>
                     <title>MARK TWAIN’S HYMNS IN PROSE:</title>
                     <subtitle>Doxology and Burlesque in The Adventures of Tom Sawyer and Adventures of Huckleberry Finn</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>GIVEN SOME of Mark Twain’s comments about his novel<italic>The Adventures of Tom Sawyer</italic>(1876), it is somewhat surprising that the structure of the work has been the focus of many substantive articles. “Since there is no plot to the thing,” Twain wrote William Dean Howells, “it is likely to follow its own drift, &amp; so is as likely to drift into manhood as anywhere—I won’t interpose” (MTHL 1: 87–88). Of course, Twain made other comments belying this disingenuous assertion, and beyond his claims of artlessness stands the novel itself; scholarly commentary, too. Considering the tendency to neglect</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 4</label>
                     <title>MARK TWAIN’S CRUCI-FICTIONS:</title>
                     <subtitle>“The Second Advent” as a Burlesque Life of Christ</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>87</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THE DEGREE OF reverence accorded a subject in the nineteenth century was directly proportional to Mark Twain’s impulse to burlesque it. While many sober Christians would contend that Christ’s advent hardly seems the stuff of burlesque, popular reverent regard for Christianity’s foundational narrative demanded that Twain use the form as he had so many other genres of belief. The story of Christ’s humble nativity, teaching, crucifixion, and resurrection surpasses even the Adam and Eve mythos as a recognized and revered narrative structure. While Twain adopted and adapted the Adam and Eve story, notably in “The Tournament in 1870 A.D.” (1870),</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 5</label>
                     <title>THE MORPHOLOGY OF MARTYRDOM:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fairy Tale, Epic, and Hagiography in Personal Recollections of Joan of Arc</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>105</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>DESPITE HIS LATER practice of referring to himself as “Saint Mark,” in a mock canonization, Twain was not inclined to view saints positively. In<italic>The Innocents Abroad</italic>(1869), for example, Twain summarily dismisses saints and their relics as “Jesuit humbuggery” (45). Relics of the saints trigger comedy rather than reverence, with Twain chiding, “as for the bones of St. Denis, I feel certain we have seen enough of them to duplicate him, if necessary” (131). Twain complains less about the idea of sainthood than about relics and the depictions of them, labeling them “rude” (103), “coarse” (187, 237), and “grotesque”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 6</label>
                     <title>Q: WHAT DO SOCRATES AND THE SHORTER CATECHISM HAVE IN COMMON?</title>
                     <subtitle>A: Dialogic Influences on Mark Twain’s What Is Man?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>140</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>ON MAY 9, 1875, Olivia Clemens, wife of writer Mark Twain, sat writing a letter to her mother. “Mr. Clemens is reading aloud in ‘Plato’s Dialogues,’” she began, “so if I write incoherently you must excuse it” (Gribbon,<italic>Mark Twain’s Library</italic>2: 549). This “polyphony in the parlor” is emblematic of the sometimes unexpected influences on Twain’s work; far from causing Twain to “write incoherently,” as it may have for Mrs. Clemens, the writer thrived on a plurality of voices and influences. In the last decade, scholars have increasingly examined minority and female voices in Twain’s writing, analyzing the extent</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER 7</label>
                     <title>“PROPHECY WENT OUT WITH THE CHICKEN GUTS”:</title>
                     <subtitle>No. 44, The Mysterious Stranger and the Christian Prophetic Tradition</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>HAVING BILLED himself as the<italic>Reverend Mark</italic>Twain and<italic>Saint</italic>Mark at different stages of his career, it should surprise no one that in between those two points Mark Twain compared himself to the<italic>Prophet</italic>Samuel. In “Wit-Inspirations of the ‘Two-Year-Olds’” (1870), Twain relates the (obviously) fabricated conversation he had with his father upon the subject of his own naming. The infant rejects the name “Samuel,” even though, as his father points out, he was a “prophet.”</p>
                     <p>“What! There was Samuel the prophet. Was not he great and good?” “Not so very.”</p>
                     <p>“My son! With his own voice the Lord</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>CONCLUSION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>190</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>THEOLOGIAN, Missionary, Priest, Preacher, Prophet, Saint, Brother Twain, Holy Samuel, Bishop of New Jersey, and of course the<italic>Reverend</italic>Mark Twain: these ecclesiastical personae must be understood primarily as burlesques of religious literary genres, for in each case their adoption was associated with “the one right form” Twain adopted for his narratives. The writer’s poses are antigenres in the sense that Twain employs them to contextualize his criticism of church and society within the very genres by which church and society contextualize themselves.¹</p>
                     <p>In a speech introducing Winston Churchill at the Waldorf-Astoria, for example, Twain introduces himself as a “missionary”</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>NOTES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>193</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>WORKS CITED</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1kgqw8m.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>221</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
