<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">P96.V35V36 2016</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Vampires in mass media</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Sociology</subject>
         <subject>Film Studies</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Vampires and Zombies</book-title>
         <subtitle>Transcultural Migrations and Transnational Interpretations</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Fischer-Hornung</surname>
               <given-names>Dorothea</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mueller</surname>
               <given-names>Monika</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>02</day>
         <month>02</month>
         <year>2016</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781496804747</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">1496804740</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781496804785</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">1496804783</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>University Press of Mississippi</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>JACKSON</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2016</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>University Press of Mississippi</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1d2dq9t"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>The undead are very much alive in contemporary entertainment and lore. Indeed, vampires and zombies have garnered attention in print media, cinema, and on television. The vampire, with roots in medieval European folklore, and the zombie, with origins in Afro-Caribbean mythology, have both undergone significant transformations in global culture, proliferating as deviant representatives of the zeitgeist.</p>
         <p>As this volume demonstrates, distribution of vampires and zombies across time and space has revealed these undead figures to carry multiple meanings. Of all monsters, vampires and zombies seem to be the trendiest-the most regularly incarnate of the undead and the monsters most frequently represented in the media and pop culture. Moreover, both figures have experienced radical reinterpretations. If in the past vampires were evil, blood-sucking exploiters and zombies were brainless victims, they now have metamorphosed into kinder and gentler blood-sucking vampires and crueler, more relentless, flesh-eating zombies.</p>
         <p>Although the portrayals of both vampires and zombies can be traced back to specific regions and predate mass media, the introduction of mass distribution through film and game technologies has significantly modified their depiction over time and in new environments. Among other topics, contributors discuss zombies in Thai films, vampire novels of Mexico, and undead avatars in horror videogames. This volume-with scholars from different national and cultural backgrounds-explores the transformations that the vampire and zombie figures undergo when they travel globally and through various media and cultures.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="240"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>I</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>V</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FISCHER-HORNUNG</surname>
                           <given-names>DOROTHEA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MUELLER</surname>
                           <given-names>MONIKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Monsters loom large in the cultural imaginary. From folktales to splatter movies, from the Bible to computer games, from birth to death, monsters such as devils, werewolves, dragons, ghosts, cyborgs, zombies, and vampires inundate our imagination. Monsters, which can be understood as symbols of human vulnerability, can, however, also help us to imagine triumphing over danger. As Stephen T. Asma points out, they are “beneficial foes” that are “imaginative foils for thinking about our own responses to menace” (2009, online).</p>
                     <p>In his “Monster Culture (Seven Theses),” Jeffrey Jerome Cohen notes that monsters are “difference made flesh” (1996, 7), that they</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE SMILING DEAD; OR, ON THE EMPIRICAL IMPOSSIBILITY OF THAI ZOMBIES</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ANCUTA</surname>
                           <given-names>KATARZYNA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Although originating in Haitian vodou¹ culture, zombies have truly made their mark on the popular imaginary courtesy of the North American film industry. It is in their George Romero–inspired representation as slow-moving, instinct-driven, brain-eating corpses, rather than soulless (dead or alive) beings controlled by a<italic>bokor</italic>(a vodou priest) for the purpose of slave labor, that they continue to inspire filmmakers around the globe toward producing their own versions of the violently hungry (un) dead for local audiences. Thailand seems an exception here because, taking into consideration that horror remains one of the strongest Thai cinematic genres, it is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“SHE LOVES THE BLOOD OF THE YOUNG”</title>
                     <subtitle>The Bloodthirsty Female as Cultural Mediator In Lafcadio Hearn’s “The Story of Chūgōrō”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>METZGER</surname>
                           <given-names>SABINE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Compared to late nineteenth-century vampire and Gothic fictions, Lafcadio Hearn’s “The Story of Chūgōrō” (from the collection<italic>Kottō</italic>, 1902) appears at first glance to be a simple, if not mediocre, tale, devoid of any intricate plot and psychological depth: Chūgōrō, a young man, falls prey to a seductive stranger who, during several nightly rendezvous, deprives him of his blood. However, despite its bloodthirsty female protagonist and despite its evoking what Christopher Frayling in<italic>Vampyres</italic>calls “haemosexuality” (1991, 388), “The Story of Chugoro” is not a vampire tale, nor does it blend Western and Eastern supernaturalism. “The Story of Chūgōrō” is</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>OCTAVIA BUTLER’S VAMPIRIC VISION</title>
                     <subtitle>Fledgling as a Transnational Neo-Slave Narrative</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>ROBINSON</surname>
                           <given-names>TIMOTHY M.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>61</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The literary theorist Nina Auerbach proclaims that “every age embraces the vampire it needs” (1995, 145). Her observation that vampires are an ever-changing archetype reflecting societal concerns and anxieties of the particular generation that it derives from is well substantiated. However, the vampire’s broad appeal, for the most part, lies with European American writers and audiences, particularly as depicted in literature, film, and television.¹ One might ask why vampires are not represented to a greater degree in African American culture, especially literature—after all, vampires seem an ideal metaphor to describe North American slavery. The slave masters’ exploitation of labor</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>APPETITE FOR DISRUPTION</title>
                     <subtitle>The Cinematic Zombie and Queer Theory</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SIMONSEN</surname>
                           <given-names>RASMUS R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Warm Bodies, Zombieland, World War Z, The Walking Dead, Pride and Prejudice and Zombies</italic>: The living dead seem to have infested every corner of popular culture. Zombies have definitely enjoyed a resurgence in recent years—something that appeared unlikely even a decade ago—and the term<italic>renaissance</italic>(rebirth) seems entirely appropriate in this regard (see McGlotten and VanGundy 2013, 101). Be that as it may, I hesitate to call what we are witnessing now a zombie renaissance for the simple fact that, in most cases, what passes for a zombie in contemporary cinema is nothing more than a prop in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>VAMPIROS MEXICANOS</title>
                     <subtitle>Nonnormative Sexualities in Contemporary Vampire Novels of Mexico</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>BORGIA</surname>
                           <given-names>DANIELLE</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>110</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the early nineteenth century, vampire literature has been an accepted way to introduce transgressive representations of sexualities into the cultural imagination of the Western world. The earliest English-language vampire tales expand on the folk legend of the<italic>vardoulacha</italic>from Eastern Europe (specifically Romania, Hungary, and Greece), starting with John Polidori’s “The Vampyre” of 1819 featuring the malevolent Lord Ruthven. These sexual transgressions are symbolized by the heightened emotion of fear and disgust with which the human characters regard the vampire protagonists’ pleasure in the murders of their victims. As Nina Auerbach, Talia Schaffer, and others have demonstrated, the fictional</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>HYBRIDITY SUCKS</title>
                     <subtitle>European Vampirism Encounters Haitian Voodoo in The White Witch of Rosehall</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>MUELLER</surname>
                           <given-names>MONIKA</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>130</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Annie Palmer, “the white witch of Rose Hall,” was a Jamaican plantation owner of British descent, who, according to the widespread lore about her, not only killed her three husbands in the 1820s but also practiced voodoo¹ and acquired a reputation for excessively whipping her slaves. Her legend has inspired two novels, a folk song, and several performances. While Johnny Cash’s 1973 song “The Legend of Annie Palmer” focuses on Annie as a sadistic slave owner and husband killer, Herbert G. de Lisser’s 1929 novel<italic>The White Witch of Rosehall</italic>—the thematic focus of this essay—presents the legendary Annie</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>REVAMPING DRACULA ON THE MEXICAN SILVER SCREEN</title>
                     <subtitle>Fernando Méndez’s El vampiro</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>SERRANO</surname>
                           <given-names>CARMEN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Cinematic representations of the monstrous and the supernatural are an inextricable part of film history, and the vampire is among its international stars.<italic>The Devil’s Manor</italic>(1896), by French film pioneer Georges Méliès, is considered one of the first films to play with the vampire theme. In it, a bat-like creature flies into a Gothic castle and then is transformed into a sinister cloaked figure (see Abbott 2004, 12). In 1922 director F. W. Murnau made the critically acclaimed German expressionist film<italic>Nosferatu</italic>, which presents one of the most frightening versions of the aristocratic vampire as described in Bram Stoker’s</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>THE REANIMATION OF YELLOW-PERIL ANXIETIES IN MAX BROOKS’S WORLD WAR Z</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>FOX</surname>
                           <given-names>TIMOTHY R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>168</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>With the 2006 publication of<italic>World War Z: An Oral History of the Zombie War</italic>, novelist Max Brooks made history, both literally and figuratively. Literally, according to<italic>Publishers Weekly</italic>(2011, online), Brooks broke barriers and made publishing history with sales of all formats (hardcover, paperback, audio) reaching 600,000 within just five years of the book’s release. The 2013 release of the feature-length film produced by and starring Brad Pitt only served to help further boost sales of the novel (“Best Sellers” 2006, online), making sure it remained on top-sellers lists long after its initial publication.¹ Not only is<italic>World War</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“DOCTOR! I’M LOSING BLOOD!” “NONSENSE! YOUR BLOOD IS RIGHT HERE”</title>
                     <subtitle>The Vampirism of Carl Theodor Dreyer’s Film Vampyr</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>WEBER</surname>
                           <given-names>JOHANNES</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since John Polidori in 1819 made a vampire the eponymous hero of his Romantic tale “The Vampyre,” vampires have never disappeared from the pages of collections of supernatural tales, penny dreadfuls, or horror novels. They soon migrated to theater stages and movie screens, and more recently from the pages of serialized novels to weekly episodes on television. As cultural icons, vampires are the subject matter of an impressive body of academic writing. In his study<italic>Metamorphoses of the Vampire in Literature and Film</italic>, Erik Butler sums up:</p>
                     <p>
                        <italic>Representations of vampires in literature, film, and the visual arts are many and</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>DISRUPTIVE CORPSES</title>
                     <subtitle>Tales of the Living Dead in Horror Comics of the 1950s and Beyond</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>HAND</surname>
                           <given-names>RICHARD J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In his foreword to the zombie comic collection<italic>Fleshrot: Tales from the Dead</italic>(vol. 1) (2003), George A. Romero states that the anthology reminds him of the days when “I smuggled<italic>Tales from the Crypt</italic>into the house and chuckled, under the bedspread with a small flashlight casting dim light on the pages. The drawings in this book made me chuckle again. This is ballsout-what-it’s-all-about stuff” (2003, 4). In this statement, Romero, the director whose name is most frequently associated with zombie movies, gives us an insight into one of his earliest influences: the horror comics of the 1950s, the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>UNDEAD AVATARS</title>
                     <subtitle>The Zombie in Horror Video Games</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>KIRKLAND</surname>
                           <given-names>EWAN</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>229</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite the monster’s pervasive presence within the medium, academics writing about zombies in popular culture can have a somewhat smug attitude toward video games. There is often something slightly elitist in the attitude of theorists in their treatment of the video-game zombie as a lesser creature, a monstrous aberration in comparison to the true undead of cinema. Kyle Bishop’s disparaging description of the first<italic>Resident Evil</italic>film as “an action-packed science fiction movie that is more video game than narrative” (2009, 19) resonates with Geoff King and Tanya Krzywinska’s observation that, within the cultural hierarchy, comparing films to games represents</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>LIST OF CONTRIBUTORS</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1d2dq9t.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>INDEX</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
