<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt7pdhm</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s</book-id>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Language &amp; Literature</subject>
         <subject>Art &amp; Art History</subject>
         <subject>History</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>Edinburgh German Yearbook 9</book-title>
         <subtitle>Archive and Memory in German Literature and Visual Culture</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <role>Edited by</role>
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Osborne</surname>
               <given-names>Dora</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>01</day>
         <month>11</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781571139238</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781782046431</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Boydell &amp; Brewer</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Rochester, New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <edition>NED - New edition</edition>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Editor and Contributors</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.7722/j.ctt1814h2s"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>In recent years, the discourse of memory - and of German memory culture in particular - has become increasingly concerned with questions of the archive. An archive can refer to a physical place, the material found there, or the system that orders this material; in its broadest sense, it might refer to something public (records housed in a municipal building), or something private (photographs in a family album). The material and documentary qualities of the archive confer on it an authenticating function attributed only cautiously to memory, but theories of the archive have questioned the status of material, documentary vestiges of the past. Memory and the archive are inextricably linked, but how does this affect the mediation of the past? This volume explores the changing relationship between memory and the archive in German-language literature and culture since 1945. Contributions approach this topic from a range of perspectives (film, visual culture, urban culture, digital technology, as well as literature) and offer illuminating studies of Harun Farocki, Anselm Kiefer, Thomas Demand, Bernd and Hilla Becher, Jürgen Fuchs, Stefan Wolter, and Sasa Stanisic. Contributors: Priyanka Basu, Carol Anne Costabile-Heming, Regine Criser, Tobias Ebbrecht-Hartmann, Diana Hitzke and Charlton Payne, Caitríona Leahy, Dora Osborne, Annie Ring, Lizzie Stewart, Simon Ward. Dora Osborne is Lecturer in German at Durham University.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="218"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Osborne</surname>
                           <given-names>Dora</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2009, the Historical Archive of the City of Cologne, regarded as the most significant north of the Alps, collapsed, seemingly as a result of negligence in the construction of an underground train line. As the vast majority of its valuable holdings plummeted into the mud below, the archive became visible in wholly unintended ways. Precisely at the point of the archive’s catastrophic malfunction, the public saw exactly what had been carefully stored behind the walls of the municipal building they had probably, in many cases, never noticed. Prior to the collapse, the archive had been known in particular for</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Between Preservation and Destruction:</title>
                     <subtitle>Bernd and Hilla Becher’s Archive of “Anonymous Sculpture”</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Basu</surname>
                           <given-names>Priyanka</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This essay examines the archival practices of German photographers Bernd and Hilla Becher, focusing on their first decade working together beginning in 1959, during which they produced the earliest iterations of and statements about their ongoing project photographing the industrial structures they termed “anonymous sculpture.” It considers what they meant to achieve in this production by systematically documenting these edifices—pit heads, cooling towers, blast furnaces, water towers, and others used in resource extraction and processing—of the Siegerland and Ruhr regions of central and western Germany. The Bechers keenly sensed that the industries of which these structures were emblems</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Janos Frecot, Photographic Archives, and the Zero Hours of Berlin</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ward</surname>
                           <given-names>Simon</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Writing in 1982, the photographer and curator Janos Frecot claimed that “die Stunde Null in ihrer Offenheit scheint aktueller denn je” (the Zero Hour in its openness seems more urgently contemporary than ever).¹ If, given the manifold continuities in societal and political structures that followed the end of the war, particularly in West Germany, the caesura of the “Zero Hour” (or “Stunde Null”) is a myth rather than a historical fact, its value as the emblem of a missed opportunity was nevertheless something that was invoked, as here by Frecot, in attempting to imagine an alternative German society. Already in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Saving the Present:</title>
                     <subtitle>Anselm Kiefer as Self-Archivist</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Leahy</surname>
                           <given-names>Caitríona</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Marketing its 2014 retrospective of the forty-year career of Anselm Kiefer, the Royal Academy in London declared its exhibition “a testament to the career of a man driven to confront himself and the audience with the big and complex issues of our world’s past, present and future.”¹ Kiefer, the academy said, is “a colossus of contemporary art” who “takes over our main galleries,” filling them with his “quite simply monumental” artworks. The references to size here are apt in several ways: the physical immensity of Kiefer’s exhibits stretches the capacity of the Royal Academy to accommodate them; related to that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Thomas Demand’s Nationalgalerie:</title>
                     <subtitle>Reconstructing a German Archive</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Osborne</surname>
                           <given-names>Dora</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>85</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2009 Germany celebrated sixty years since the founding of the Federal Republic and twenty years since the fall of the Berlin Wall. That double-anniversary year two exhibitions opened in Berlin: the high-profile, popular show<italic>60 Jahre—60 Werke</italic>at the Martin-Gropius-Bau and a solo show in Mies van der Rohe’s Neue Nationalgalerie by the Munich-born artist Thomas Demand. Demand had been invited to participate in<italic>60 Jahre</italic>, but, fearing that the show was concerned with things other than art, had declined.¹ It seemed Demand was right: one critic dismissed<italic>60 Jahre</italic>as “kunsthistorische[r] Blödsinn” (art historical nonsense) and Günter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Turkish-German Comedy Goes Archival:</title>
                     <subtitle>Alamanya—Willkommen in Deutschland (2011)</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Stewart</surname>
                           <given-names>Lizzie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In 2011, Yasemin and Nesrin Samdereli’s family comedy<italic>Almanya—Willkommen in Deutschland</italic>(Almanya: Welcome to Germany, 2011) burst onto German screens with a comedic yet nostalgic re-telling of the history of fifty years of Turkish labor migration to Germany.¹ A surprise hit at the<italic>Berlinale</italic>film festival,<italic>Almanya</italic>has been referred to as “A<italic>Good Bye Lenin!</italic>for migration histories” by a number of reviewers.² Indeed, elements common to both films include a nostalgic representation of a difficult history, a rich and warm visual style which combines fiction with documentary footage, and an assertion of the place of previously marginalized</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Echoes from the Archive:</title>
                     <subtitle>Retrieving and Re-viewing Cinematic Remnants of the Nazi Past</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ebbrecht-Hartmann</surname>
                           <given-names>Tobias</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Film footage made in the Third Reich and since found in the archive has recently provoked new forms of cinematic engagement with the incriminating images that often emphasize the perpetrator’s perspective on historic events. Georges Didi-Huberman calls these visual remnants of the Nazi past “ill seen images”; “ill seen” because they have been “poorly described, poorly captioned, poorly classed, poorly reproduced, poorly used” by historians as well as filmmakers.¹ In the case of archive films that remain from the Nazi period we are left with footage that is, for the most part, fragmentary and that has sometimes been edited in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Harun Farocki’s Critical Film Archive</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Ring</surname>
                           <given-names>Annie</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Harun Farocki died in Berlin in July 2014 at the height of an unmatched career in political filmmaking. The oeuvre of this graduate of the Deutsche Film und Fernsehakademie (German Film and Television Academy Berlin; dffb) is characterized by a technique of repurposing moving-image archives in a critical documentary mode crafted to reveal the hidden processes of preparation, acculturation, and training that pervasively constitute the present-day West and render its citizens unwittingly yet habitually complicit. In this chapter I focus on Farocki’s works that piece together found footage drawn from such diverse sources as classic Hollywood feature film, prison CCTV</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preserving the Self:</title>
                     <subtitle>Constructs of Memory and Biography in the Works of Jürgen Fuchs</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Costabile-Heming</surname>
                           <given-names>Carol Anne</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>163</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The unprecedented decision to open the archives of the GDR’s Ministry for State Security (MfS or Stasi) in 1992 added a unique layer of documentary evidence to the memories of East Germans who had suffered at the hands of the Stasi. As Alison Lewis has written, the main objective for granting former GDR citizens access was to provide them “with evidence of the wrongs that had been committed against them.”¹ Certainly, the Stasi had never intended for these files to become public. By allowing victims to read their files, the Stasi Records Law empowered them to take control of their</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Disruptions of the Archive:</title>
                     <subtitle>Renegotiating German History in Autobiographical Fiction after 1989</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Criser</surname>
                           <given-names>Regine</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In her autobiographically inspired study of family photographs, tellingly entitled<italic>Family Secrets</italic>(1995), Annette Kuhn describes the family album as “one moment in the cultural construction of family,” further claiming that “it is no coincidence that the conventions of the family album—what goes in and how it is arranged—are, culturally speaking, rather circumscribed.”¹ Kuhn’s observation implies an interconnectedness between the construction of family and its visual representation in family photographs. This connection is manifested in the multiple memory layers of the family album, where memories of the album curator and the reader of the album merge. This “archive</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Verbalizing Silence and Sorting Garbage:</title>
                     <subtitle>Archiving Experiences of Displacement in Recent Post-Yugoslav Fictions of Migration by Saša Stanišić and Adriana Altaras</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Hitzke</surname>
                           <given-names>Diana</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib2" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Payne</surname>
                           <given-names>Charlton</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In the<italic>Archeology of Knowledge</italic>, Michel Foucault identifies in the archive a “particular level” that “between tradition and oblivion, […] reveals the rules of a practice that enables statements both to survive and to undergo regular modification. It is<italic>the general system of the formation and transformation of statements</italic>.”¹ Because statements emerge as meaningful discourse at a given time, their appearance is accompanied by the possibility that they might not appear. They thereby point to the ways in which language is an event, the possibility of something being said or not said, a matter of whether enunciations even take place</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1814h2s.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Back Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
