<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">j.ctt30ccm4</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">BS2615.52.J65 2007</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Bible. N.T. John</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Criticism, interpretation, etc.</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Jesus Christ</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Historicity</subject>
            <subj-group>
               <subject content-type="lcsh">Congresses</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Religion</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>John, Jesus, and History, Volume 2</book-title>
         <subtitle>Aspects of Historicity in the Fourth Gospel</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <role content-type="editor">Edited by</role>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Anderson</surname>
               <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib2">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Just</surname>
               <given-names>Felix</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
         <contrib contrib-type="editor" id="contrib3">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>Thatcher</surname>
               <given-names>Tom</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>07</day>
         <month>07</month>
         <year>2015</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9781589833920</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9781589833937</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>SBL Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>the Society of Biblical Literature</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt16ptndz"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>This groundbreaking volume draws together an international group of leading biblical scholars to consider one of the most controversial religious topics in the modern era: Is the Gospel of John-the most theological and distinctive among the four canonical Gospels-historical or not? If not, why does John alone among the Gospels claim eyewitness connections to Jesus? If so, why is so much of John's material unique to John? Using various methodologies and addressing key historical issues in John, these essays advance the critical inquiry into Gospel historiography and John's place within it, leading to an impressive consensus and convergences along the way. The contributors are Paul N. Anderson; Mark Appold; Richard Bauckham; Helen K. Bond; Richard A. Burridge; James H. Charlesworth; Jaime Clark-Soles; Mary Coloe; R. Alan Culpepper; Craig A. Evans; Sean Freyne; Jeffrey Paul Garcia; Brian D. Johnson; Peter J. Judge; Felix Just, S.J.; Craig S. Keener; Edward W. Klink III; Craig R. Koester; Michael Labahn; Mark A. Matson; James F. McGrath; Susan Miller; Gail R. O'Day; Bas van Os; Tom Thatcher; Derek M. H. Tovey; Urban C. von Wahlde; and Ben Witherington III.</p>
      </abstract>
      <counts>
         <page-count count="468"/>
      </counts>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>v</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Abbreviations</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aspects of Historicity in the Fourth Gospel:</title>
                     <subtitle>Phase Two of the John, Jesus, and History Project</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Thatcher</surname>
                           <given-names>Tom</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This book is the second in a series of volumes that have emerged from the deliberations of the John, Jesus, and History Group in the Society of Biblical Literature. Volume 1, subtitled<italic>Critical Appraisals of Critical Views</italic>(Anderson, Just, Thatcher 2007), featured papers from the Group’s 2002– 2004 meetings, which focused largely on the state of the field and problems of method. Volume 2 addresses<italic>Aspects of Historicity</italic>in the Fourth Gospel, the theme of the Group’s 2005–2007 program. Several more books are scheduled to emerge from the project, including a third collection of essays that will reflect the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Part 1:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aspects of Historicity in John 1–4</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John 1–4 covers the beginning of Jesus’ ministry, including his being pointed out by John the Baptist in the Transjordan region and his being joined by five disciples (John 1), Jesus’ first sign performed at the wedding feast in Cana of Galilee and his prophetic demonstration in the temple (John 2), Jesus’ dialogue with Nicodemus and further testimony about his being the anticipated Messiah by John the Baptist (John 3), and Jesus’ dialogue with the woman at the well, her effective mission to the Samaritans, and his second sign performed in Galilee, the healing of a royal official’s son</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“We Beheld His Glory!” (John 1:14)</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Keener</surname>
                           <given-names>Craig S.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Most scholars today concur that the Fourth Gospel includes both history and theology. Even many patristic interpreters, who often harmonized John with the Synoptics (hence apparently stressing history), recognized John as a “spiritual” Gospel, emphasizing its interpretive aspects. The Gospel clearly interprets theologically the eyewitness claim that apparently stands behind it (cf. 21:24); perhaps most conspicuously, in the Fourth Gospel as a whole the eyewitness claim of water and blood from Jesus’ side (19:34–35) is made to climax a motif of water running through the narrative (1:26, 33; 2:7 – 9; 3:5, 23; 4:10, 13 – 14; 5:2; 7:37 – 39; 9:7;</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jesus’ Bethsaida Disciples:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Study in Johannine Origins Mark Appold</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Appold</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>27</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Seldom do biblical scholars reach full agreement on issues of textual interpretation. That certainly has to do with the very nature of the texts themselves. One notable exception, the product of two centuries of scholarship, is the now generally accepted recognition that none of the four Gospels can be read simply as historical reportage but that each one must rather be taken as an ultimately irresolvable mix of discoverable “facts” and faith. The problem does not hang on a simple either/or but on an examination of the many points in between. Johannine scholarship has examined virtually every interpretive possibility that</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>“Destroy This Temple”:</title>
                     <subtitle>Issues of History in John 2:13–22</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>McGrath</surname>
                           <given-names>James F.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>35</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The material found in John 2:13–22, depicting Jesus’ action in the temple and the saying about its being destroyed and rebuilt in three days, is a key point of intersection between the Gospel of John, the Synoptics, and the Gospel of Thomas. As such, it provides one of the relatively few places where questions of John, Jesus, and history can be discussed, as it were, “synoptically.” Because of this multiple attestation, there are very few scholars who dispute that Jesus engaged in<italic>some sort</italic>of action in the temple, however small or symbolic, and that he spoke in<italic>some</italic>
                     </p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>John as Witness and Friend</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Coloe</surname>
                           <given-names>Mary</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Fourth Gospel is the most historical of all the Gospels. While it has been entitled “the spiritual Gospel,” its depth of spiritual insight does not in any way detract from its focus on the actual life and death of Jesus of Nazareth.¹ In fact, this Gospel proclaims that history is now the locus of the divine presence. In the flesh of Jesus, we have the eternal Word of God. For this reason, history is now radiant with the glory of God: “The Word became flesh and dwelt among us, and we have seen his glory, glory as of the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Symbology of the Serpent in the Gospel of John</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Charlesworth</surname>
                           <given-names>James H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Over the past two decades, specialists on the Gospel of John have customarily focused on the translation, composition-history, and exegesis of this masterpiece. Less attention is addressed to the symbolic world of the Evangelist. That dimension of Johannine studies is now much clearer, thanks to archaeological research and the study of symbolism (see Charlesworth 2006 and 2008), otherwise known as symbology. The present work will illustrate this emerging clarity by exploring the deeper and fuller meaning of an incredibly rich and well-known section of the Fourth Gospel: John 3:13–17.</p>
                     <p>Such a study is warranted, since over the last decade</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Woman at the Well:</title>
                     <subtitle>John’s Portrayal of the Samaritan Mission</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Miller</surname>
                           <given-names>Susan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The account of the meeting of Jesus and the Samaritan woman (John 4:4–42) portrays the positive response of a Samaritan woman to Jesus’ mission. The Samaritan woman recognizes Jesus as the Messiah, and she then tells others in her town about Jesus. As a result of her actions, Jesus stays two days in the Samaritan town, and more Samaritans come to faith in him. There is no account of a Samaritan mission, however, in the other Gospels. Mark does not make any reference to the Samaritans, while Matthew includes a prohibition to the disciples not to enter a city</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Royal Official and the Historical Jesus</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Judge</surname>
                           <given-names>Peter J.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>One would be hard-pressed nowadays to find many commentators with the opinion that John’s story of the cure of the royal official’s son (John 4: 46b–54) is not the same event as the cure of the centurion’s boy at Capernaum in the Synoptics (Matt 8: 5–13; par. Luke 7:1–10). Unmistakable similarities abound: some kind of officer at Capernaum approaches Jesus to seek healing for a member of his household; the sick person is healed instantaneously without Jesus going to the house of the officer; and the issue of faith is a focal point in all three versions</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aspects of Historicity in John 1–4:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Response</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Koester</surname>
                           <given-names>Craig R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>93</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The manner in which modern scholars investigate questions of historicity is one that the Fourth Evangelist would find peculiar. In contemporary research, the historical Jesus is the pre-Easter Jesus, and questions of historicity focus on how much we can know about the ministry of Jesus prior to his death. The writer of the Fourth Gospel, however, assumes that truly understanding the pre-Easter Jesus involves a post-Easter perspective. At points this Gospel specifically draws later insights into the meaning of Jesus’ words and actions and acknowledges that Jesus said and did things that were not understood prior to his resurrection (John</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Part 2:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aspects of Historicity in John 5–12</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John 5–12 covers the middle section of Jesus’ ministry, including three trips to Jerusalem (John 5; 7; 12), intense debates between Jesus and the religious leaders in Jerusalem (John 5; 7–10), the feeding of the five thousand and related events (John 6—the sea crossing, debates as to the meaning of the feeding, and the confession of Peter), the healing of a lame man by the Pool of Bethesda (John 5), the healing of a blind man and his washing in the Pool of Siloam (John 9), the raising of Lazarus from the dead (John 11), the anointing</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Jewish Feasts and Questions of Historicity in John 5–12</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Johnson</surname>
                           <given-names>Brian D.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>117</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Jewish feasts are mentioned frequently throughout the Gospel of John. These references occur from the first Passover, mentioned as the setting of the temple incident in John 2, to the final Passover, which provides the setting of John 12–19. The following table includes every explicit mention of a Jewish feast in John’s Gospel.</p>
                     <p>2:11, 23 Passover</p>
                     <p>4:45 reference back to Passover</p>
                     <p>5:1 unnamed feast</p>
                     <p>5:9, 10, 16, 18 Sabbath</p>
                     <p>6:4 Passover</p>
                     <p>7:2 Tabernacles</p>
                     <p>7:22, 23 Sabbath</p>
                     <p>7:37 last and greatest day of the feast</p>
                     <p>9:14, 16 Sabbath</p>
                     <p>10:22 Dedication</p>
                     <p>11:55; 12:1 before the Passover</p>
                     <p>13:1 Passover</p>
                     <p>18:28, 39; 19:14,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Feeding the Five Thousand and the Eucharist</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Evans</surname>
                           <given-names>Craig A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The purpose of the present study is to explore the possibility that the feeding story of John 6, which is made up of the multiplication of the loaves and fishes and the “eucharistic” discourse,¹ may constitute tradition that predates the Synoptic Gospels, where the feeding story is separate from the Eucharist.</p>
                     <p>It is natural to assume that the Fourth Evangelist has linked what is disparate in the Synoptics, but we might also wonder if in John 6 we have not a<italic>late</italic>combination of feeding miracle and eucharistic discourse but an<italic>early</italic>tradition that has been edited to reflect interest</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.17</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Jesus and the Galilean ‘Am Ha’arets:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fact, Johannine Irony, or Both?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Freyne</surname>
                           <given-names>Sean</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>139</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In discussing the historical plausibility or otherwise of episodes or speeches in the Fourth Gospel, a number of important interpretative decisions have to be taken. These methodological issues cannot be discussed in detail in this essay. My own opinion, as stated in my study of Galilee and the Gospels, is as follows: “The fact that Galilee enters the ironic patterns that the author (John) seeks to develop, shows just how important the memories associated with the region were to Christian self-understanding, even when there is no concern to develop a realistic narrative of that setting” (Freyne 1988, 131–32). In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.18</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Pool of Siloam:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Importance of the New Discoveries for Our Understanding of Ritual Immersion in Late Second Temple Judaism and the Gospel of John</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>von Wahlde</surname>
                           <given-names>Urban C.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>155</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The Pool of Siloam is one of the biblical sites adjacent to the Old City of Jerusalem that has been pointed out to visitors and pilgrims for centuries. It lies south of the Old City at the tip of the Ophel Ridge, in what is now the Arab village of Silwan. The pool is known locally by its Arab name, the Birkat Silwan. Visitors to the pool are directed to a fenced-in area near a Muslim school. A small, rusty sign identifies the place as the Pool of Siloam. In order to get near the pool itself, one must enter</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.19</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Overrealized Expulsion in the Gospel of John</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Klink</surname>
                           <given-names>Edward W.</given-names>
                           <suffix>III</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>When reading John 9, Martyn finds as blatantly anachronistic a key term in 9:22, ἀποσυνάγωγος (“from the synagogue”; also in 12:42 and 16:2a). Although in the narrative this term describes an event during Jesus’ earthly ministry, for Martyn (2003, 65) it is most certainly dealing with an event that could not have occurred until decades after Jesus’ life. Martyn is convinced that the first-century readers of the Fourth Gospel would have seen the “expulsion from the synagogue” term as an anachronistic insertion into the narrative. In many ways, the “expulsion from the synagogue” in 9:22 is the key to his</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.20</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Bethany Family in John 11–12:</title>
                     <subtitle>History or Fiction?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bauckham</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>185</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>According to the Gospel of John, Jesus counted among his close friends three siblings, Lazarus and his sisters Martha and Mary, who lived in the village of Bethany near Jerusalem. This essay is primarily concerned with the historicity of this family, but this can scarcely be separated from the historicity of the events in which they are involved in John’s narrative: the resuscitation of Lazarus by Jesus and the anointing of Jesus by Mary. It is true that the historicity of these events could be defended, while regarding the family as a Johannine invention. John, it might be argued, has</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.21</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>What’s in a Name?</title>
                     <subtitle>Rethinking the Historical Figure of the Beloved Disciple in the Fourth Gospel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Witherington</surname>
                           <given-names>Ben</given-names>
                           <suffix>III</suffix>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The environment in which the New Testament was written was both oral and rhetorical in character. Texts, especially religious texts, function differently in oral cultures that are 90 percent illiterate and in which even the texts that exist are oral texts, meant to be read aloud. These important insights, when coupled with the realization that orally delivered and rhetorically adept discourse and storytelling was at the heart of first-century culture, should long ago have led us to a new way of reading the Gospels themselves.</p>
                     <p>First, the telling of the story of Jesus was from the beginning crucial for the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.22</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>On Not Unbinding the Lazarus Story:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Nexus of History and Theology in John 11:1–44</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Tovey</surname>
                           <given-names>Derek M. H.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>213</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As I prepared this paper, a joke often came to mind of a traveler on his way to a city, finding himself lost in the countryside (perhaps I should say “boondocks”—we might imagine a traveler to Washington, D.C., somewhere in the Appalachian Mountains). He stops to ask directions of a local he finds leaning on a fencepost. “Tell me,” he asks, “how do I get to Washington, D.C.?” “Well,” comes the reply, “if I was going there, I wouldn’t start from here.”</p>
                     <p>The story of the raising of Lazarus must be one of the most problematic in the Fourth</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.23</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aspects of Historicity in John 5–12:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Response</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>225</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In responding to the eight essays in part 2 of this volume, I am impressed at the variety of approaches to aspects of historicity in the Gospel of John. Employing religious-anthropological, archaeological, contextual, and historical-critical studies, these essays cover the middle section of the Fourth Gospel, which includes three of Jesus’ four trips to Jerusalem and rising opposition from the Judean religious leaders. The one miracle narrated in all four canonical Gospels—the feeding of the five thousand—and its attending features makes John 6 the premier locus of Gospel-comparison analysis, yet the Lazarus story of John 11 has captured</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.24</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Introduction to Part 3:</title>
                     <subtitle>Aspects of Historicity in John 13–21</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John 13–21 covers the last week of Jesus’ ministry, following his entry into Jerusalem (12: 12–19), to include his last discourses with his followers (John 13–17), his arrest and trials (John 18–19), his crucifixion and burial (John 19), and his resurrection and appearances to his followers (John 20–21). Within John’s treatment of the Last Supper in John 13, Jesus does not institute the Eucharist as a meal of remembrance but washes the feet of his disciples. In John 14–16, Jesus foretells the sending of the Holy Spirit and prepares his followers for the challenges</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.25</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>John 13:</title>
                     <subtitle>Of Footwashing and History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Clark-Soles</surname>
                           <given-names>Jaime</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Prodigious are the questions generated by this passage (John 13:1–20), and only slightly less prodigious are the publications devoted to it. Textual, anthropological, theological, literary, and exegetical analyses abound; only the historical remains largely untouched. When the historical is mentioned, however, treatments most often refer to the history of the Johannine situation,<italic>not</italic>to the historical Jesus or the historicity of the underlying Johannine tradition. Of all the questions one could ask, we shall attend most closely in this essay to these two. (1) Is it historically plausible that Jesus washed the feet of his disciples? Why or why</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.26</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>John’s Last Supper and the Resurrection Dialogues</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>van Os</surname>
                           <given-names>Bas</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>271</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In an appendix to<italic>The Fourth Gospel and the Quest for Jesus</italic>, Paul Anderson (2006b, 193–95) proposes a phased development of the Johannine corpus:</p>
                     <p>(1) First, the Johannine tradition is formed around the Beloved Disciple. This tradition interacts with other developing Gospel traditions, such as those that would be used in the Synoptic Gospels, especially Mark’s.</p>
                     <p>(2) In response to the Gospel of Mark, and before Matthew and Luke were written, a first edition of the Gospel of John is written by the Johannine Evangelist; Q and Luke show dependence on the Johannine oral tradition.</p>
                     <p>(3) and (4) In</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.27</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Imitating Jesus:</title>
                     <subtitle>An Inclusive Approach to the Ethics of the Historical Jesus and John’s Gospel</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Burridge</surname>
                           <given-names>Richard A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>From earliest days, John has been viewed as the “spiritual gospel” (πνευματικὸν εὐαγγέλιον), while the “external facts” (actually, “the bodily things” (τὰ σωματικὰ) were preserved in the Synoptics (a saying originally attributed to Clement of Alexandria by Eusebius,<italic>Hist. eccl.</italic>6.14.7). Thus John has been seen as relatively late and Hellenistic, and primarily theological, while the Synoptics were seen as earlier and more Jewish, and therefore, according to this argument, more historical. Not surprisingly, then, John has been neglected in the various quests for the historical Jesus. Nowhere is this contrast more obvious than with regard to the ethical teaching</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.28</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>The Historical Plausibility of John’s Passion Dating</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Matson</surname>
                           <given-names>Mark A.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>291</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The question of the historical value of material in the Fourth Gospel rests on two concerns that always lurk behind the discussions in the SBL group focusing on John, Jesus, and history. The first is the foundational question of how we evaluate the Gospels, or really any ancient writing, for “historical” material. That is, we must deal with the always-contentious issue of the criteria we use to determine Gospel materials’ historical value.¹ The second question is how we account for the stark differences between John and the Synoptics.² One cannot venture far into any consideration of John’s historical value without</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.29</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>At the Court of the High Priest:</title>
                     <subtitle>History and Theology in John 18: 13–24</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Bond</surname>
                           <given-names>Helen K.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>313</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Despite a general preference for the Synoptic Gospels, several features of John’s narrative have often commanded a certain historical respect: the lengthier ministry and its wider geographical location, the more complex relationship between Jesus and John the Baptist, the date of the crucifixion, and the passage that concerns us now—John’s Jewish interrogation of Jesus (Smith 1993, 252–67). C. H. Dodd argued in 1963 that John’s “account of the interrogation is drawn from some source, almost certainly oral, which was well informed about the situation at the time, and had contact with the Jewish tradition about the trial and</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.30</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>See My Hands and My Feet:</title>
                     <subtitle>Fresh Light on a Johannine Midrash</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Garcia</surname>
                           <given-names>Jeffrey Paul</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>325</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The unique quality of the Doubting Thomas pericope in the Gospel according to John is further distinguished by its preserving the only explicit reference to Jesus’ nail wounds.</p>
                     <p>But Thomas, who was called the Twin, one of the twelve, was not with them when Jesus came. So the other disciples told him, “We have seen the Lord.” But he said to them, “Unless I see the mark of the<italic>nails</italic>in his hands, and put my finger in the mark of the<italic>nails</italic>and my hand in his side, I will not believe.” A week later his disciples were again</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.31</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Peter’s Rehabilitation (John 21:15–19) and the Adoption of Sinners:</title>
                     <subtitle>Remembering Jesus and Relecturing John</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Labahn</surname>
                           <given-names>Michael</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>John 21 may seem to be a surprising point of departure for a discussion about John and the historical Jesus.¹ Historical-critical scholarship, though challenged by conservative exegesis and/or by scholars using linguistic and narrative methods (e.g., Thyen 2005), still interprets John 21 as a later addition to the Gospel (e.g., Schnelle 2007a, 523–24). The judgment that John 21 has a secondary character is evident even in the more text-centered approaches of Francis Moloney (1998b, 545–47, 562–65) and Manfred Lang (1999, 294–95 n. 918).² So why take that chapter as a point of departure for raising the</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.32</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>John 21:24–25:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Johannine Sphragis</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Culpepper</surname>
                           <given-names>R. Alan</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>349</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In<italic>The Johannine School</italic>(Culpepper 1975), I examined John 21: 24– 25 for clues to the composition history and setting of the Fourth Gospel.<italic>In John the Son of Zebedee</italic>(Culpepper 1994), I studied it in the context of the growth of the tradition and legends about John. In this essay, I propose to look at its function in providing closure for the Gospel. The focus of this paper was prompted in particular by Howard M. Jackson and Richard Bauckham, who have recently offered readings of the last two verses of John that call for a reappraisal of their testimony</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.33</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aspects of Historicity in John 13–21:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Response</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>O’Day</surname>
                           <given-names>Gail R.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>365</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The eight essays in part 3 focus on John 13–21. Two essays are on John 13 (Clark-Soles, van Os), two on John 18 and 19 (Bond, Matson), one on John 20 (Garcia), two on John 21 (Labahn, Culpepper), and one is an overview essay (Burridge).</p>
                     <p>These essays can also be grouped according to the basic orientation with which the authors approach the question of historicity. Four of the essays approach the topic of historicity from the perspective of the historical plausibility of events narrated in Fourth Gospel (Clark-Soles, Garcia, Bond, Matson). The other four essays take as their starting</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.34</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Aspects of Historicity in the Fourth Gospel:</title>
                     <subtitle>Consensus and Convergences</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Anderson</surname>
                           <given-names>Paul N.</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>In reflecting upon the above treatments of aspects of historicity in the Fourth Gospel, a multiplicity of approaches and disciplines is here employed in getting at a common interest: the historical character of the Johannine tradition and ways in which it casts light upon the Jesus of history—his intentions, doings, teachings, travels, and receptions, as well as impressions, memories, interpretations, narrations, and writings about him in later settings. The division of the Gospel of John into three sections involving chapters 1–4, 5–12, and 13–21 works well as a means of dividing up the ministry of Jesus</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.35</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Epilogue:</title>
                     <subtitle>Whence, Where, and Whither for John, Jesus, and History?</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <contrib-group>
                     <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1" xlink:type="simple">
                        <name name-style="western">
                           <surname>Just</surname>
                           <given-names>Felix</given-names>
                        </name>
                     </contrib>
                  </contrib-group>
                  <fpage>387</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Where have we come from, where are we now, and where might we be headed with studies of the interrelationships between the Gospel of John and the historical Jesus? Readers of these first two volumes of collected essays, along with the many scholars who have attended sessions of the John, Jesus, and History Group over the past six years, are by now well versed in the discussions of the many complex questions surrounding the historicity of the Fourth Gospel. Yet it would be worthwhile for us briefly to reflect on the bigger picture and to consider the larger journey in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.36</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Works Cited</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>393</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.37</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Contributors</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>421</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.38</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Ancient Sources</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>427</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
      <book-part indexed="true" xlink:type="simple">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt16ptndz.39</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index of Modern Authors and Authorities</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>449</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
