<book xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      dtd-version="0.2"
      xml:lang="eng">
   <collection-meta>
      <collection-id collection-id-type="jstor">books</collection-id>
   </collection-meta>
   <book-meta>
      <book-id book-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg</book-id>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="call-number">GF21.034 1991</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Human ecology</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Wilderness areas</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Man</subject>
         <subj-group>
            <subject content-type="lcsh">Influence on nature</subject>
         </subj-group>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group>
         <subject content-type="lcsh">Philosophy of nature</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline">
         <subject>Philosophy</subject>
      </subj-group>
      <book-title-group>
         <book-title>The Idea of Wilderness</book-title>
         <subtitle>From Prehistory to the Age of Ecology</subtitle>
      </book-title-group>
      <contrib-group>
         <contrib contrib-type="author" id="contrib1">
            <name name-style="western">
               <surname>OELSCHLAEGER</surname>
               <given-names>MAX</given-names>
            </name>
         </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date>
         <day>24</day>
         <month>04</month>
         <year>0091</year>
      </pub-date>
      <isbn content-type="ppub">9780300048513</isbn>
      <isbn content-type="epub">9780300191271</isbn>
      <publisher>
         <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
         <publisher-loc>New Haven; London</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
      <permissions>
         <copyright-year>1991</copyright-year>
         <copyright-holder>Yale University</copyright-holder>
      </permissions>
      <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/j.ctt1cc2krg"/>
      <abstract abstract-type="short">
         <p>How has the concept of wild nature changed over the millennia? And what have been the environmental consequences? In this broad-ranging book Max Oelschlaeger argues that the idea of wilderness has reflected the evolving character of human existence from Paleolithic times to the present day. An intellectual history, it draws together evidence from philosophy, anthropology, theology, literature, ecology, cultural geography, and archaeology to provide a new scientifically and philosophically informed understanding of humankind's relationship to nature.</p>
         <p>Oelschlaeger begins by examining the culture of prehistoric hunter-gatherers, whose totems symbolized the idea of organic unity between humankind and wild nature, and idea that the author believes is essential to any attempt to define human potential. He next traces how the transformation of these hunter-gatherers into farmers led to a new awareness of distinctions between humankind and nature, and how Hellenism and Judeo-Christianity later introduced the unprecedented concept that nature was valueless until humanized. Oelschlaeger discusses the concept of wilderness in relation to the rise of classical science and modernism, and shows that opposition to "modernism" arose almost immediately from scientific, literary, and philosophical communities. He provides new and, in some cases, revisionist studies of the seminal American figures Thoreau, Muir, and Leopold, and he gives fresh readings of America's two prodigious wilderness poets Robinson Jeffers and Gary Snyder. He concludes with a searching look at the relationship of evolutionary thought to our postmodern effort to reconceptualize ourselves as civilized beings who remain, in some ways, natural animals.</p>
      </abstract>
      <custom-meta-group>
         <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>
                    lang
                </meta-name>
            <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
         </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
   </book-meta>
   <body>
      <book-part book-part-type="book-toc-page-order" indexed="yes">
         <body>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.1</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Front Matter</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>i</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.2</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Table of Contents</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>vii</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.3</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Preface</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>ix</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.4</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>xi</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.5</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER ONE</label>
                     <title>The Idea of Wilderness:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Paleolithic to Neolithic Culture</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>As the united states of america nears the twenty-first century, relatively little of its land remains unhumanized. The past ten thousand years show such humanization to be the norm across the world. Driven by metabolism and reproduction, humans have pressed nature into its role as provider of the resources to sustain burgeoning populations.¹ An alternative idea of wild nature as a<italic>source</italic>of human existence is gaining a public hearing. This idea questions the longentrenched civilized-primitive dichotomy, a bifurcation grounded in an assumption that the human story lies in our triumph over a hostile nature. The idea of nature as</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.6</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TWO</label>
                     <title>Ancient Mediterranean Ideas of Humankind and Nature:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Passage from Myth to History</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>31</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The prehistoric mediterranean world is sometimes characterized as “the first Eden” or “garden of God.”¹ The roots of the word<italic>Eden</italic>include the Babylonian<italic>eindu</italic>and the Hebrew<italic>Édhen</italic>, translated variously as paradise, plain, and hunting ground. The transition from a hunting-foraging way of life to<italic>agri</italic>-culture has often been associated with or identified as the so-called Fall.² In leaving the Paleolithic world for the Neolithic, humankind likely encountered a host of woes and travails unknown in its collective experience, not the least of which was work itself. Paleolithic peoples, existing in traditional ways established over untold millennia, lived in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.7</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER THREE</label>
                     <title>The Alchemy of Modernism:</title>
                     <subtitle>The Transmutation of Wilderness into Nature</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>68</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Throughout the middle ages human beings dreamed of transmuting common metal into precious gold through alchemy. Although this aspiration led to a handsome living for many an alchemist, employed by those who desired the proverbial something for nothing, the hope was never realized.<italic>Modernism</italic>—understood as a historical movement that begins with the Renaissance and extends to the present—is in this sense analogous to alchemy, for through science, technology, and liberal democracy modern people hoped to transform a base and worthless wilderness into industrialized, democratic civilization. Modernism, like the classicism of antiquity, thus continued the humanization of wild nature</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.8</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FOUR</label>
                     <title>Wild Nature:</title>
                     <subtitle>Critical Responses to Modernism</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Since the publication of Descartcs’s<italic>Discourse on Method</italic>(1637) and<italic>Meditations</italic>(1641) and Newton’s<italic>Principia Mathematica</italic>(1687), the mechanistic model has dominated natural science, The Cartesian-Newtonian paradigm enjoys cognitive hegemony in the modern world, displacing any aesthetic, religious, or philosophical claim to insight or knowledge. And long before the social sciences emerged, such thinkers as Thomas Hobbes and Adam Smith were modeling their treatises on the structure of political and economic society on the mechanistic paradigm, attempting to capture in human affairs what was being achieved in natural science: theoretical elegance and precision leading to predictive knowledge and causal control.</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.9</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER FIVE</label>
                     <title>Henry David Thoreau:</title>
                     <subtitle>Philosopher of the Wilderness</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Henry david thoreau cuts a most unusual figure in the fabric of American life, for he died largely unknown and unrecognized by his peers, perceived as a satellite orbiting an Emersonian center of gravity.¹ Today Thoreau’s reputation has largely eclipsed Emerson’s. The older transcendentalist is viewed more as a popularizer of European ideas than as a progenitor of a unique philosophy. Although Emersonian transcendentalism is moribund, Thoreau’s ideas yet animate reflection on the human condition and are recognized as crucial to the birth of a distinctively American idea of wilderness. He was in the vanguard of the nineteenth-century criticism of</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.10</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SIX</label>
                     <title>John Muir:</title>
                     <subtitle>Wilderness Sage</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>172</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Posterity has treated John Muir well, for the richness of his intellectual and institutional legacy continues to grow. In two decades, and especially in the ten years since the Muir archives were opened, the traditional view that he merely reiterated the tired truths of transcendentalism has been abandoned. A case can be made that he stands intellectually with Henry David Thoreau and Aldo Leopold as a thinker whose work yet exerts major influence on contemporary American ideas of wilderness. In instrumental terms, Muir is the father of the American conservation (now preservation) movement; his influence is most visibly manifest in</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.11</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER SEVEN</label>
                     <title>Aldo Leopold and the Age of Ecology</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Aldo leopold, the third giant of wilderness philosophy, is, a thinker whose ideas outline the living context of the idea of wilderness. Like Thoreau, he helped to define an intellectual framework within which to formulate questions involving the concept of wild nature. And like Muir, he was instrumental in founding an organization dedicated to wilderness preservation; the Wilderness Society remains a potent legacy, forming with Muir’s Sierra Club an effective advocacy for wildlife protection. But unlike Thoreau or Muir, Leopold could find a “path with a heart” that legitimated his life’s work. He became what is today termed a wilderness</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.12</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER EIGHT</label>
                     <title>The Idea of Wilderness in the Poetry of Robinson Jeffers and Gary Snyder</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>This chapter focuses on the idea of wilderness in the poetry of Robinson Jeffers and Gary Snyder, consequently ignoring other writers and poets whose work also reflects that concept. The selection of Jeffers and Snyder delimits an otherwise impossibly large field, and there is some reason to think that the choice is sound since “ecological consciousness seems most vibrant in the poetic mode. The poetic voices of Jeffers and Snyder, so rare in modern poetry but frequently found in primal people’s oral tradition, are a virtual cascade of celebration of Nature/God and being.”¹ We have already argued that Modernism—or,</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.13</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER NINE</label>
                     <title>Contemporary Wilderness Philosophy:</title>
                     <subtitle>From Resourcism to Deep Ecology</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>Contemporary ideas of wilderness are implicit Within activities as diverse as the legislative and judicial decisionmaking processes, policy implementation, and philosophical speculation. Ideally, some distinct idea might cut across this array of subjects and unite them along a continuum, much as the principles of liberal democracy unite diverse elements of the body politic. As Samuel Hays observes, environmentally oriented inquiry has not led “to a single system of thought such as social theorists might prefer, and it would be difficult to reduce its varied strands to a single pattern” ¹ Typically, however, those concerned with the idea of wilderness offer</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.14</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <label>CHAPTER TEN</label>
                     <title>Cosmos and Wilderness:</title>
                     <subtitle>A Postmodern Wilderness Philosophy</subtitle>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>320</fpage>
                  <abstract>
                     <p>The anomalies of modernism, that paradigm for thought and action upon which the contemporary world rests, are reflected throughout the conceptual spectrum of chapter 9. Yet paradigmatic revolution—a profound change in consciousness, however foolish that idea seems—is in the wind, and humankind may be on the brink of a postmodern age. Of course such qualifiers as anti-or posttend to obscure the central issue: Modernism.¹ Crucially, the idea of wilderness appears to undergird a new paradigm for understanding humankind as embodying natural process grown self-conscious. The wilderness paradigm might be viewed as only an outgrowth of the environmental movement</p>
                  </abstract>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.15</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Notes</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
            <book-part>
               <book-part-meta>
                  <book-part-id book-part-id-type="jstor">j.ctt1cc2krg.16</book-part-id>
                  <title-group>
                     <title>Index</title>
                  </title-group>
                  <fpage>461</fpage>
               </book-part-meta>
            </book-part>
         </body>
      </book-part>
   </body>
</book>
