<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3591443</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/427313</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR850201</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A Correlational Model of Comparative Theology</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Hugh</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Nicholson</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Coe College</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>April 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>85</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2005.85.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>191</fpage>
         <lpage>213</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2005 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/427313"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>By now it is a commonplace to assert that in today’s ever‐shrinking world religious pluralism is no longer simply a theoretically known fact but is rather a matter of lived experience. In fact, for most Christian communities pluralism emerged as an experienced reality some time ago. Yet the practice and conceptualization of Christian theology is only slowly and sporadically beginning to reflect the awareness of the theological significance of the claims of meaning and truth of the world’s religions. The discipline of “comparative theology,” as defined by Francis X. Clooney as the rereading of one’s own tradition in light of other traditions, remains a vaguely understood and marginal discipline within theological studies.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>In spite of its hesitant beginnings, however, theologians like Clooney and David Tracy regard comparative theology as the future of theology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>Indeed, given that the theological questions raised by the fact of religious pluralism are present in the historical situation in which theological reflection takes place today, there is a sense in which the modifier “comparative” is redundant, for it merely singles out for special emphasis a dimension of contemporary theological reflection that is intrinsic to the theological enterprise as such.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>
      </p>
      <p>The seeds of religious pluralism in the contemporary theological situation have the potential to transform traditional Christian theology from within. According to Paul Knitter, the pluralistic situation demands a conception of the relations between the world’s faiths that is radically new. Knitter’s proposal of a “unitive pluralism of religions” suggests a sort of kaleidoscopic vision of religious interpenetration in which every religion is present in the self‐understanding of every other without, however, the religions becoming confused.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>Our awareness of the sociology of knowledge, however, gives us reason to suspect that there are intrinsic limits to this kind of religious interpenetration. The dependence of religious ideas on specific social processes for their plausibility limits the flow of these ideas.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>More often than is usually acknowledged, religious doctrines are formed in response to specific questions arising out of religious practice.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>A tradition’s intellectual beliefs regarding the nature of reality are correlated to its particular way of life in such a way that the former make sense only in the context of the latter. A community’s cognitive beliefs are therefore apt to leave an outsider—one who does not share that community’s distinctive way of life—with an impression of otherness, even if the dependence of these beliefs on alien modes of social interaction is rarely so absolute as to render them unintelligible. The situation with respect to religious ideas stands in contrast to the propagation of scientific knowledge, which, by virtue of its relative independence from specific social/practical contexts,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>has the ability to pass through sociological barriers with relative ease. For this reason, one would not expect the theological revisions called forth by the new pluralism, as substantial as these are likely to be, to be quite as thoroughgoing as those undergone by the tradition in meeting the challenge of modernity.</p>
      <p>A comparative theology that acknowledges this correlation of religious ideas with religious activity favors an “inclusivist” understanding of the relationship between the home tradition and others.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>To the extent that religious beliefs are correlated with specific forms of religious praxis, the theologian cannot help but think about religious reality in the terms set by his or her own tradition. This alliance with an inclusivist position certainly does not mean, however, that comparative theology assumes the unchangeability of the home tradition as that tradition encounters other cultures and faiths. One could in fact argue that this presupposition has already been abandoned by mainstream Christianity. According to Karl Rahner, the abandonment of the presumption of unchangeability defines the transition from the Western church to a truly world church, a process that was inaugurated for the Catholic Church by Vatican II.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>The inclusivism of a theology that acknowledges and affirms the changes that a tradition undergoes in interreligious encounter could be termed a “dynamic” inclusivism, as opposed to the more familiar “static” inclusivism characterized by the presumption of unchangeability. This important qualification of the concept of inclusivism points to a feature of comparative theology that distinguishes it from the older, a priori “theology of religions,” namely, its reliance on specific comparisons. Clooney, whose attention to the details of compared traditions is exemplary, insists that comparative theology, as a truly constructive theological enterprise, takes place only after, and in light of, specific comparisons.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>Yet, although the particular character of a given exercise in a Christian comparative theology will depend greatly on the particular choice of materials—whether Hindu, Islamic, or Buddhist—brought into conversation with the Christian tradition, it remains a worthwhile task to formulate a general conceptual model of comparative theology. If nothing else, such an effort, by demonstrating the continuity between comparative theology and more established theological models, effectively challenges the presumption that comparative theology is a marginal, optional, and perhaps, for some, even suspect theological endeavor.</p>
      <p>The above‐mentioned concept of “dynamic inclusivism” provides a promising basis upon which to construct such a model of comparative theology. This concept embodies two theological claims that, although standing in tension with one another, together define the mainstream Christian position with regard to other religious traditions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref>The first is the normative status of Jesus Christ in defining authentic religious experience (or, given more forceful theological expression, the central role of Christ in mediating salvation). The second is the need to recognize the operation of God’s grace outside the boundaries of visible Christianity, as well as the possibility, implied by this recognition, of mutual enrichment through interreligious dialogue.</p>
      <p>To see how a comparative theology might best meet these two demands, I find it helpful to understand comparative theology in terms of what David Tracy calls a revised correlational model of theology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>Tracy builds on Paul Tillich’s conception of the method of correlation, according to which the task of the theologian is to correlate Christian answers to the existential questions arising out of the contemporary situation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref>Unlike Tillich, however, Tracy clearly acknowledges the fact that the situation often provides answers of its own to the human predicament.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref>This acknowledgment is vital for our purposes, for it allows us to recognize the presence of non‐Christian religions—which do, of course, provide their own answers—within the theological situation. That the situation contains its own answers means that the relation between situation and tradition is better thought of in dialectical rather than unilateral terms. Thus, according to Tracy, theology consists in the establishment of mutually critical correlations between the claims of the Christian tradition and those of the historical situation. The theologian reflects on the various ways in which the tradition and the situation affect each other—where they reinforce each other and where they critique each other. The arrows of interpretation go in both directions: the situation and its claims to religious meaning and truth are critically interpreted in light of the Christian tradition, and the Christian tradition is interpreted according to the questions and concerns arising out of the situation.</p>
      <p>In the first two sections of this essay, I shall discuss, respectively, each of these interpretive movements, specifically as they relate to the presence of non‐Christian religious beliefs and practices in the contemporary theological situation. In the third and final section I shall argue that the inclusion of non‐Christian beliefs and practices among the materials for explicit theological reflection calls into question the common understanding of apologetics as a secondary and extrinsic theological task. When the religiously pluralistic character of the theological situation is fully acknowledged, the correlational model suggests that Christian identity is actively constructed in a dialectical process of comparison and contrast with other traditions,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>and that, moreover, apologetically motivated representations of the religious “other” are invariably shaped by a prior concern to establish Christian identity. When made explicit, these implications expose as an illusion a presumption that belongs to the very nature of traditional apologetics, namely, that the “objective” differences noted by apologetics simply confirm an already‐established conception of Christian identity. In thus demystifying the apologetic project, the correlational model of theology discussed in the first two sections implies a conception, presented in the third, of comparative theology as the replacement of traditional apologetics.</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>For Clooney’s conception of comparative theology, see, e.g., his<italic>Theology after Vedanta</italic>(Albany: SUNY Press, 1993), 4–14, or “Comparative Theology: A Review of Recent Books (1989–1995),”<italic>Theological Studies</italic>56, no. 3 (September 1995): 521–23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>See the concluding sentence of Tracy’s article “Comparative Theology,” in<italic>Encyclopedia of Religion</italic>, 16 vols. (New York: Macmillan, 1987), 14:454: “Any theology in any tradition that takes religious pluralism seriously must eventually become a comparative theology.” Clooney gives a more qualified assessment of the future of comparative theology in “Comparative Theology: A Review of Recent Books,” 550.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>See Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedanta</italic>, 6.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Paul F. Knitter,<italic>No Other Name</italic>(Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1985), 7–16.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>For the concept of plausibility structure, see, e.g., Peter L. Berger,<italic>The Sacred Canopy</italic>(New York: Anchor, 1990), 45–51.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>For the argument that much of a tradition’s intellectual activity relates to questions regarding religious praxis, see Thomas P. Kasulis, “Philosophy as Metapraxis,” in<italic>Discourse and Practice</italic>, ed. Frank Reynolds and David Tracy (Albany: SUNY Press, 1992), 169–95.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>The exclusion of metaphysical concerns affords scientific knowledge a certain degree of autonomy with respect to particular social practices, as compared to the knowledge constitutive of a religious worldview that retains a tighter connection with a specific, communally shaped way of life. This modest assertion regarding the relative autonomy of scientific, as compared to religious, knowledge need not imply a more questionable claim regarding the culturally independent and ahistorical universality of scientific reason.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Clooney allies comparative theology with an inclusivist theology of religions. See Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedanta</italic>, 194–95, and “Reading the World in Christ: From Comparison to Inclusivism,” in<italic>Christian Uniqueness Reconsidered</italic>, ed. Gavin D'Costa (Maryknoll, NY: Orbis, 1992), 63–80.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Karl Rahner, “Toward a Fundamental Theological Interpretation of Vatican II,”<italic>Theological Studies</italic>40 (1979): 717. See also Knitter,<italic>No Other Name</italic>, 18–20.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Clooney, “Comparative Theology: A Review of Recent Books,” 522.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>This approach to other religions was set forth in the Second Vatican Council but has been adopted in its basic outlines by other Christian traditions. The acceptance of the Catholic model by other mainstream Christian denominations justifies Knitter’s term “the mainline Christian model” to refer to this general approach. See Knitter,<italic>No Other Name</italic>, 135.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>For a general statement of the revised correlational model of theology, see David Tracy,<italic>Blessed Rage for Order</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1996), chap. 3. Tracy applies this theological model specifically to religious pluralism in “Comparative Theology,” 447–48, 452–54.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Tracy,<italic>Blessed Rage for Order</italic>, 45–46.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>Ibid., 46.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>For an argument for the essentially relational nature of Christian identity, see Kathryn Tanner,<italic>Theories of Culture</italic>(Minneapolis: Fortress, 1997), 114–16.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>Interpreting the World in Terms of the Tradition</title>
         <p>The Christocentric requirement can best be understood in terms of the first of the above‐mentioned interpretive movements. The world of contemporary experience is interpreted in light of the claims of the tradition. Thus, for example, the human predicament (for which Tillich asserts Christianity provides the answers) will itself be cast in terms of the Christian message; contemporary questions will be formulated in light of Christian answers. Theologians like George Lindbeck (building on the work of Hans Frei) and Tracy appeal to contemporary theories of literary reference to understand this capacity of a religious tradition to shape human experience.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref>According to such theories, the reference of a text stands in front of it, namely, in the world this text opens up for the reader. Thus the Christian “text”—consisting of the classic texts of the Christian tradition, founded upon, but not restricted to, the Christian Bible—projects a domain of meaning in which Christians are to locate—and thereby to redefine—their own experiences of reality.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>The traditional notion of the imitation of Christ, for example, can be fruitfully understood in terms of this concept of “intratextuality.” Personal suffering acquires redemptive significance for a Christian when it is experienced as an imitation of Christ’s suffering; to suffer as a Christian is to be imaginatively present with Christ in his agony.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref>According to George Lindbeck, the primary task of the theologian is to extend the domain of meaning projected by the Bible to the whole of reality.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The extratextual reality to be incorporated into the world opened up by the religious “text” includes, of course, those non‐Christian religions that are present in the historical situation of the contemporary Christian.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>These will thus be understood, according to this model of theological reflection, in terms of a distinctively Christian worldview. The intratextual method of theology thus lends itself to an inclusivist model of comparative theology.</p>
         <p>This inclusivist understanding of theology, according to which other faiths are critically interpreted in light of a prior set of Christian beliefs, receives support from a central tenet of modern hermeneutical theory. Exposing the Enlightenment’s myth of the autonomous interpreter, Hans‐Georg Gadamer recognizes the positive—indeed, the indispensable—role of the interpreter’s prejudgments in the act of understanding. Any historical fact—that is to say, any product of human activity whose meaning, unlike that of the physical data of natural science, is constitutive of its very reality<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>—will either be understood in terms of the concerns and expectations of the interpreter or else in only a degenerative (and derivative) sense as a dead, “merely historical” fact. Any act of genuine understanding thus reflects the historical situation of its interpreter.</p>
         <p>Unfortunately, Gadamer’s case against the Enlightenment “prejudice against prejudice,” while representing an important first step in the direction of a viable cross‐cultural hermeneutical theory, still does not address the very real problem of distortion in cross‐cultural study. For the one feature of historical understanding that ensures the hermeneutical productivity of “prejudice” in Gadamer’s theory is largely absent in cross‐cultural understanding. What distinguishes those prejudices that are productive of understanding from those that lead to misunderstanding is the derivation of the former from the tradition of which the text to be interpreted is a part.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>This derivation guarantees a level of continuity between the questions the interpreter brings to the traditionary text and those for which the text was originally the answer.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref>In other words, the text itself has played a role in constituting the tradition that has influenced the interpreter’s questioning. This continuity establishes a topic of common concern that is the precondition for an authentic conversation between text and interpreter. In contrast to those prejudices that constitute one’s belongingness to tradition, invalid prejudices fail to transcend the subjectivity of the interpreter and are therefore discontinuous with any legitimate meaning offered by the traditionary text. Such idiosyncratic prejudices will therefore distort one’s interpretation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>Now it is precisely the feature of these subjective prejudices that renders them unfit for intracultural understanding, namely, their lack of a connection with the tradition of which the text is a part, that characterizes all prejudices, traditionary and idiosyncratic alike, when it comes to the interpretation of a culturally foreign text. The vast body of Christian apologetic literature, both past and present, testifies to this tendency of cultural prejudice to distort the meaning of culturally foreign religious facts.</p>
         <p>To counter this tendency, the pioneers in the phenomenological study of religion announced the methodological principle of<italic>epoche</italic>, that is, the bracketing of the scholar’s prior religious commitments. Yet for scholars like Gerardus van der Leeuw and Mircea Eliade the<italic>epoche</italic>principle does not signify a naive attempt to retrieve an Enlightenment ideal of detached objectivity modeled after the natural sciences. The phenomenologists insisted upon the involvement of the interpreter in the act of religious understanding.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref>The very concept of a phenomenon (“that which appears”) implies the involvement of the subject to whom this religious datum appears.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref>The subjective element in the interpretive act is precisely what renders one sensitive to the religious meanings in the historical material one studies. The<italic>epoche</italic>principle thus does not intend to exclude those presuppositions constitutive of the interpreter’s subjectivity but rather only those a priori attitudes that lead to the imposition of value judgments on religious phenomena. The very conception of the phenomenological study of religion as an approach distinct from both theological apologetics and historical specialization thus presupposes a distinction between, on the one hand, the presuppositions productive of religious understanding and, on the other, the a priori attitudes that impose distorting value judgments. Yet a wholly satisfactory solution to this problem of distinguishing valid presuppositions from tendentious a priori attitudes has been, to my knowledge, elusive. The solution certainly does not coincide with that of distinguishing valid from invalid prejudices in Gadamerian hermeneutics. As we saw above, the solution in that case depended on the notion of belonging to a tradition, a notion that is irrelevant here.</p>
         <p>Perhaps the concept of intratextuality provides the key to solving this problem. The hermeneutical model presupposed in this concept emphasizes the receptivity of the interpreter and, in doing so, draws attention to precisely that feature of hermeneutically productive prejudices that distinguishes them from a priori judgments, namely, their capacity for change. Paul Ricoeur captures the essence of this hermeneutical model when he writes that “to understand is not to project oneself into the text but to expose oneself to it.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref>In the context of the<italic>epoche</italic>principle, understanding is perhaps understood less as an act of empathy, suggesting the active participation of the interpreter in the subjective state of the author, than as an act of sympathy, whereby one renders oneself receptive to the particular experiential resonances set up by the text, resonances homologous to, but not identical with, those experienced by the original addressees. In other words, understanding presupposes a willingness to have one’s attitudes and outlook shaped by the mode of being‐in‐the‐world projected by the text.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref>What enables presuppositions to be productive of understanding, then, is their plasticity, their capacity for transformation, and it is this capacity that distinguishes them from the a priori attitudes that are willfully maintained in the midst of interreligious encounter.</p>
         <p>Understanding the hermeneutical problem in terms of textual interpretation enables us to do something that did not appear as a possibility in Gadamer’s hermeneutics, namely, to extend the conversational model of understanding to the radically other.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref>A textual model of hermeneutics such as Paul Ricoeur’s, by moving to the center of hermeneutical reflection the idea of the autonomy of the written text with respect to both its original context and that of its interpreter, recognizes the experience of difference as an essential and productive component in the interpretive process.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref>It does this in a more obvious way than does Gadamer’s theory, with its emphasis on the experience of belonging to a common tradition. According to David Tracy, who applies a similar understanding of hermeneutics to the problem of interreligious encounter, the recognition of the other as other implies an awareness of a hitherto undisclosed existential possibility.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">31</xref>Since the capacity to project possibilities belongs to the very nature of the self, such an encounter with the other enlarges one’s own self‐understanding. But this expansion of the self represents at the same time a deepening of the self, for often what enables one to recognize the other as possible are homologous cultural experiences, previously forgotten or repressed, that are lifted above the threshold of consciousness in the act of recognition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">32</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Of course, not all of the possibilities revealed in interreligious encounter are compatible with one’s religious identity. The normative claims that, together with the practices with which they are correlated, define that identity will ultimately decide whether a given possibility is a theologically viable possibility. At this point the normative theological judgments that were suspended in order to allow the religious other to present itself to our understanding reassert themselves. An approach to the religious other governed by the<italic>epoche</italic>principle eventually gives way to theology proper. The former approach—represented by the complex of disciplines falling under the rubric of “the study of religion”—represents a constitutive, though only provisional, moment within the larger project of comparative theology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">33</xref>But what renders the detour through interreligious understanding theologically significant is the conviction that one’s home tradition will be understood differently at the end of the process than it was at the beginning, thanks to the real changes undergone by the self in the moment of interreligious encounter.</p>
         <p>The foregoing description of interreligious encounter makes sense if we regard the notions that define religious identity as formal regulative principles that admit a degree of variation in the experiential “substance” of religious understanding. This conception of religious doctrines as regulative principles allows us finally to distinguish with precision the normative theological judgments that are suspended in the act of interreligious understanding from the hermeneutically productive presuppositions that are not. We can regard the former as formal criteria of religious identity and the latter as the modes of experience and understanding to be judged by—and modified in accordance with—such criteria.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">34</xref>These remarks support George Lindbeck’s understanding of a religion as a comprehensive interpretive framework that shapes the way its adherents understand and experience reality.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">35</xref>This conception of religion thus provides a helpful model for understanding the dynamics of interreligious encounter. The encounter with another religious tradition exposes religious experience and understanding to alternative structuring schemata, thereby occasioning creative rearrangements of the ways in which reality is known and experienced. The restructured patterns of experience and understanding nevertheless can, given the flexibility of a given religious structure vis‐à‐vis the experiential materials to be structured, be reassimilated to the original interpretive scheme.</p>
         <p>We have seen that the same feature of human experience presupposed in the intratextual method, namely, the self’s capacity to be shaped by a religious tradition, represents the key for understanding the problem of cross‐cultural hermeneutics. I can only interpret the religious other by allowing the religious other to interpret me. Now a critical number of such encounters will have a noticeable effect on the tradition of which I am a bearer.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">36</xref>Here we find ourselves having already crossed over into the subject matter of our next section, thus testifying to the difficulty of containing our description of the dynamics of theological reflection within the linear structure of a systematic presentation.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>See George A. Lindbeck,<italic>The Nature of Doctrine</italic>(Philadelphia: Westminster, 1984), 113–24; Tracy,<italic>Blessed Rage for Order</italic>, 49–52, 72–79.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Lindbeck,<italic>The Nature of Doctrine</italic>, 116–17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>See Louis Dupré,<italic>The Deeper Life</italic>(New York: Crossroad, 1981), 62–66; Lindbeck,<italic>The Nature of Doctrine</italic>, 118.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>Lindbeck,<italic>The Nature of Doctrine</italic>, 117.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>See Clooney, “Reading the World in Christ,” 67–72, for the use of Lindbeck’s concept of intratextuality to describe the inscription of other religions into a Christian context.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>See, e.g., Hans‐Georg Gadamer,<italic>Truth and Method</italic>, trans. Joel Weinsheimer and Donald G. Marshall (New York: Continuum, 1989), 285.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Ibid., 298.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>The question can be understood as a prejudice whose validity has been suspended in the encounter with the traditionary text. See ibid., 299.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>See Jürgen Habermas’s paraphrase in “A Review of Gadamer’s<italic>Truth and Method</italic>,” in<italic>The Hermeneutic Tradition from Ast to Ricoeur</italic>, ed. Gayle L. Ormiston and Alan D. Schrift (Albany: SUNY Press, 1990), 222.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>See, e.g., Douglas Allen,<italic>Structure and Creativity in Religion: Hermeneutics in Mircea Eliade’s Phenomenology and New Directions</italic>(Paris: Mouton, 1978), 84–90.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Eric J. Sharpe,<italic>Comparative Religion: A History</italic>(La Salle, IL: Open Court, 1986), 231–32.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Paul Ricoeur, “Hermeneutics and the Critique of Ideology,” in Ormiston and Schrift, eds.,<italic>The Hermeneutic Tradition from Ast to Ricoeur</italic>, 327.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>This passivity of the interpreter of a religious text corresponds to that of the original revelatory experience. See Allen,<italic>Structure and Creativity in Religion</italic>, 181.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>David Tracy credits Mircea Eliade’s “hermeneutics of creativity” with such a capacity. See David Tracy,<italic>Dialogue with the Other</italic>(Louvain: Peeters Press, 1990), 65.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Ricoeur, “Hermeneutics and the Critique of Ideology,” 324–25. (See also the helpful editors’ introduction to Ormiston and Schrift, eds.,<italic>The Hermeneutic Tradition from Ast to Ricoeur</italic>, 23–24.) Ricoeur appeals to the concept of distantiation in order to recognize a critical element in the interpretive act, thereby mediating between Gadamer’s hermeneutics of tradition and Habermas’s critique of ideology. Here we put the distantiation concept to quite a different use, namely, to shed light on the problem of cross‐cultural religious understanding.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>David Tracy,<italic>Plurality and Ambiguity</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1987), 20, 93.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Tracy cites as an example of this phenomenon Eliade’s rediscovery of the archaic roots of Western culture through his encounter with India (<italic>Dialogue with the Other</italic>, 62–63).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>See Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedanta</italic>, 7.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>See Lindbeck,<italic>The Nature of Doctrine</italic>, 79–84.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>Ibid., 80.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>So long as the number of mutually transformative interreligious encounters remains below a certain critical threshold, the tradition as a whole will remain unaffected. Such was Paul Ricoeur’s assessment (in 1967) of the relationship between Western culture and the great cultural traditions of the East (<italic>The Symbolism of Evil</italic>[Boston: Beacon, 1967], 22–23). Ricoeur argues that East and West have not yet effectively encountered each other in such a way that the experiences of India and China have a place in the cultural memory of the West. Such encounters as have taken place for certain individuals and groups nevertheless “have remained episodic for our culture as a whole” (23). Of course, the unevenness (from a sociological point of view) of Christianity’s encounter with other religions complicates the judgment of whether religious pluralism has begun to transform radically the Christian tradition as a whole. The conception of comparative theology presupposes, however, that such mutually transformative encounters have indeed taken place, at least for significant portions of the Christian community.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>The Transformation of Tradition in a Pluralist Context: Definition and Defamiliarization</title>
         <p>Now we turn to that other interpretive movement within the project of comparative theology as understood on the correlational model. The dominant interpretive movement from the tradition to the world incorporates a countermovement from the world to the tradition. The interpreted reacts upon the interpreter.</p>
         <p>One of the ways in which a religiously pluralistic situation can react upon a tradition is through conflict. A theological challenge will force a religious community to define (or redefine) itself. In a very real sense, the doctrinal shape of a religious tradition reflects the various views it has rejected in the course of its history. This is the mode of interreligious encounter that of course dominates much of Christian history. Most of the doctrines that sustain the identity of the Christian community are the products of conflict.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">37</xref>
         </p>
         <p>That the official doctrines whose function is to express the distinctiveness of the community vis‐à‐vis others have a basis in preexisting attitudes, orientations, and practices should not prevent us from acknowledging the real changes that a tradition undergoes in defining itself. The formulation of doctrines in response to a theological challenge does not leave the underlying social reality of the religious community unchanged. Inasmuch as the very existence of a social group includes a subjective element—that is, a social group fully comes into being only when it is aware of itself as such—the doctrines that communicate a community’s sense of identity to itself (and others) exercise a genuinely creative function. Out of a diffuse and inchoate sense of belonging to a tradition, one often shared by others, a religious community forges through its doctrines a sense of itself as a distinctive religious body. Religious doctrine shares with political speech the power to establish—to call into existence—a social group.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">38</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The analogy with political speech, supported by the observation that a community’s official doctrines are the products of controversy, suggests that the ability of these doctrines to define and sustain a sense of identity might be their most basic function. The curious fact that theologically trivial or obscure points often attain tremendous doctrinal importance suggests that doctrines derive their significance more from their effectiveness in defining the identity of a community than from their putative correspondence to metaphysical reality. The life‐and‐death importance attached to the cognitively obscure difference between the Nicene<italic>homoousios</italic>and the semi‐Arian<italic>homoiousios</italic>exemplifies this idea that doctrinal differences derive much of their original significance from the dynamics of social and political struggle. Mundane political discourse represents the limit case of this phenomenon, allowing us to see its basic features with stark clarity. The political slogan or label has meaning only relationally, its political use having effaced much of the intrinsic cognitive content of its words.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">39</xref>This neutralization of semantic or descriptive meaning allows these words more effectively to take on emotionally charged connotations from the political context and thus to serve as effective means for shaping and directing public sentiment. While the political analogy carries the obvious danger of reductionism if pressed too far, an acknowledgment of the political dimension of theological debate nevertheless sheds light on the way certain theological doctrines are able to hold tremendous religious significance in spite of—or perhaps precisely because of—their informational vacuity.</p>
         <p>The effectiveness of doctrine in forming communities appears to depend, however, on a partial or complete concealment of this sociopolitical function. The outward form of religious doctrines as descriptive statements of objective reality gives the impression that the association of a doctrine with a particular social group is merely accidental. The formation of a religious community appears to be merely symptomatic of the recognition of the propositional truth of a given set of doctrines. This concealment of the community‐forming intent of religious doctrines can perhaps be regarded as an instance of the broader social phenomenon Peter Berger terms “reification,” that is, the apprehension of social reality as grounded in the very nature of things rather than as a product of human activity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">40</xref>Understood in this way, the surface grammar of doctrine conceals the human origin of doctrinal formulations—and therefore that of the institutional processes they regulate—by suggesting that these reflect the very nature of reality. The understanding of doctrines primarily as performative expressions of communal identity implies that classical doctrines have a mythological aspect, in the sense that their appearance as simple representations of objective reality conceals the more complex expressive and regulative dimensions of their meaning.</p>
         <p>A recognition of the social function of doctrine, by freeing us from the obligation to take theological doctrines at face value as descriptive statements about metaphysical reality, removes a potent obstacle to the very idea of comparative theology. If theological doctrines are construed primarily as informative propositions about objective reality, then the claims to truth of the world’s religious traditions become mutually exclusive. An exclusively propositionalist understanding of doctrine leaves the comparative theologian with little else to do than argue for the cognitive superiority of Christian truth claims over against those of other religious communities. Under the burden of such a naive conception of doctrine, comparative theology degenerates into a crude and uninteresting apologetics. The assumption that doctrines can be nothing more than informative propositions forces one to choose between two unacceptable alternatives, namely, either to discount the importance of religious doctrine altogether, and thereby, by implication, to underestimate the importance of religious community, or else to deny, against our nobler religious instincts, that members of other religious communities can have anything of theological significance to teach us. We thus see that comparative theology favors a nonpropositional (i.e., either regulative or expressivist) theory of doctrine, much as it lends itself to a broadly defined inclusivist theology of religions.</p>
         <p>The recognition of an expressive or performative function of doctrine underneath the ostensible descriptive sense not only represents the negative condition for a comparative theology, as we have just seen, but also reveals one of the more interesting ways that comparison can further theological understanding. An acknowledgment of the fact that doctrines express religious identity justifies our regarding them as characterizations (albeit indirect ones) of religious communities. This means that doctrines, like all characterizations, unavoidably conceal some aspects of a tradition by highlighting others. I would like to suggest that comparison can liberate these doctrinally suppressed aspects by temporarily displacing the familiar characterizations by which a tradition like Christianity has traditionally defined itself.</p>
         <p>This displacement of the familiar concepts of religious self‐understanding can be fruitfully understood in terms of the aesthetic concept of “defamiliarization.” According to Victor Shklovsky, the main purpose of art is to counteract the tendency of practical life to make perception automatic and unconscious.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">41</xref>The pursuit of a goal encourages an economizing of perceptive effort with respect to the objects serving as means to that goal, so as to prevent an undue preoccupation with the means from interfering with the realization of the goal. Concepts, which function as schematic abbreviations of reality, are the means by which we are able to deal with objects with a minimum of perceptive effort.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">42</xref>A pragmatic attitude, by imparting a dynamic quality to our involvement with the world, promotes and sustains the conceptualization of reality. By deliberately slowing down the perceptual process, art reverses the process whereby concepts are generated from pragmatic intentionality, thus liberating objects from the familiar concepts of what they are.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">43</xref>The defamiliarization of reality through art allows the percipient to experience reality in its full texture; the work of art reveals the qualities of a thing that were suppressed by the concept. In a similar way, the defamiliarization of a religious tradition, by breaking through the polished surface of official doctrine, reveals previously unacknowledged dimensions of religious thought and experience.</p>
         <p>Comparison functions as a means of defamiliarization by having the strangeness of the religious other reflect back upon the home tradition. In forcing us to construe the familiar in terms of the unfamiliar, comparison, to quote Jonathan Z. Smith’s paraphrase of Shklovsky’s defamiliarization concept, “makes the familiar seem strange in order to enhance our perception of the familiar.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">44</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Following up on Francis Clooney’s insightful work on the comparative reading of religious texts,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">45</xref>I would like to suggest that we can best appreciate the cognitive power of comparison by looking at the comparative process in terms of contemporary theories of metaphor. Metaphor brings together two terms previously kept apart by established classificatory schemes.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">46</xref>The cognitive dissonance produced by the juxtaposition of categorically dissimilar terms calls forth from the interpreter an additional degree of cognitive effort.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">47</xref>By closing off the path of least cognitive resistance that is the literal meaning, metaphor forces us to give a new meaning to the words whereby the terms are reconciled to each other.</p>
         <p>According to Paul Ricoeur, the abolition of the literal interpretation in the metaphorical statement gives rise to a reinterpretation of reality itself.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">48</xref>Recalling Aristotle’s paradoxical claim that tragic poetry pre‐sents the essence of human action through the creation of a fictitious plot or<italic>muthos</italic>(that<italic>mimesis</italic>and<italic>muthos</italic>are brought together in the activity of tragic<italic>poesis</italic>),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">49</xref>Ricoeur maintains that the reinterpretation called forth by metaphorical discourse is at once imaginative and imitative, fresh and creative, and yet true to the reality that is metaphorically described.</p>
         <p>Understood on the model of metaphor, comparative theology is a creative, constructive activity that is at the same time faithful to the home tradition that it redescribes. This conception of comparative theology as a “poetic” activity that redescribes the tradition through an innovative construction of meaning represents the key, I believe, to understanding how a Christian comparative theology is able to reconcile a sincere openness to the claims of other religions with an uncompromising Christocentrism. We may cite Martin Luther King Jr.’s well‐known encounter with the thought of Gandhi as a paradigm for such a possibility. King credited Gandhi with revealing to him the possibility of extending the ethical teachings of Jesus into the realm of political action.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">50</xref>Viewing the Sermon on the Mount through the lens of Gandhi’s concept of satyagraha revealed the full breadth of the gospel teaching. Gandhi’s life reflected a dimension of Jesus’s life and teaching that had been obscured by more familiar patterns of interpretation. King’s willingness to learn from the follower of another religious path thus led to a deeper understanding of, and a renewed commitment to, the teachings of Christianity.</p>
         <p>By affirming the constructive aspect of comparison and its heuristic value, comparative theology avoids falling into the trap of casting an imaginatively constructed link as a natural or historical connection in a vain effort to lend “scientific” legitimacy to the former.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">51</xref>Thus disencumbered of the scientific prejudice that would tempt us into assuming a preexisting, objective foundation for every illuminating parallel, comparative theology is not committed to any dubious assumptions regarding a culturally independent experience of reality allegedly shared by the world’s faiths in order to justify its comparisons. Nor is its field of application restricted to those traditions for which there are established historical links.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">52</xref>Far from constituting a metalevel of discourse that simply records and analyzes past historical encounters, comparative theology itself represents a constitutive moment in an ongoing process of cross‐cultural transformation. Whether the imaginatively forged links of comparative theology overcome their arbitrary character and attain historical reality depends on whether they are supported by larger, historical forces through which the compared cultures effectively encounter each other. Without this support, these tenuous, imaginative links remain historically inert, confined to the mind of the scholar.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">53</xref>With it, they function performatively in the context of an effective encounter in the course of which the insights of one tradition become a constitutive part of another.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Lindbeck,<italic>The Nature of Doctrine</italic>, 75.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>See Pierre Bourdieu,<italic>Language and Symbolic Power</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1991), 236, 248–51, and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>Ibid., 184–85.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>Peter L. Berger and Thomas Luckmann,<italic>The Social Construction of Reality</italic>(New York: Anchor, 1967), 89–92.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Victor Shklovsky, “Art as Technique,” in<italic>Russian Formalist Criticism: Four Essays</italic>, ed. L. T. Lemon and M. J. Reis (Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1965), esp. 10–12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>Ibid., 12.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>Ibid., 12–13.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Jonathan Z. Smith,<italic>Imagining Religion: From Babylon to Jonestown</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1982), xiii.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>See Clooney, “Reading the World in Christ,” 67–72, and<italic>Theology after Vedanta</italic>, 156–83, esp. 171–75.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Paul Ricoeur on Biblical Hermeneutics</italic>, ed. John Dominic Crossan (Missoula, MT: Scholars Press, 1975), 78–79.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>Ibid., 231.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Ibid., 235.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>The Rule of Metaphor</italic>, trans. Robert Czerny (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1977), 244–45.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>See Clayborne Carson, ed.,<italic>The Papers of Martin Luther King, Jr.</italic>, vol. 4:<italic>Symbol of the Movement, January 1957–December 1958</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 2000), 296, 355, 478.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>As Jonathan Z. Smith insightfully observes, this tendency to assimilate the work of the imagination to science has the unhappy result of comparison becoming, not science, but a kind of magic (Smith,<italic>Imagining Religion</italic>, 21–22).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>See Clooney,<italic>Theology after Vedanta</italic>, 154: “Comparison forges a link which was not previously there, a link which (usually) cannot be justified on the basis of historical connections or of similarities so striking that they compel comparison.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>See Ricoeur on the arbitrary and premature character of the comparisons undertaken by the science of religion (<italic>Symbolism of Evil</italic>, 22–23).</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Comparative Theology and the Demystification of Traditional Apologetics</title>
         <p>Here in this final section I would like to situate this conception of comparative theology historically by reflecting on its relationship with the older apologetic theology that in many ways was its precursor. In keeping with the principle of “clarification by contrast,” a comparison of the two will further reveal the defining features of the conception of comparative theology that I have presented in this essay.</p>
         <p>Once again, we can begin by referring to the pioneering work of Francis Clooney. Clooney has argued that comparative theology replaces traditional apologetics as the defining mode of interreligious theological encounter and yet retains an apologetic dimension. As a confessional enterprise, comparative theology still finds it necessary sometimes to critique the theological positions of other faith communities.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">54</xref>And yet a serious engagement with other theological traditions reveals the specious nature of many of the contrasts through which traditional apologetics has argued for the uniqueness of Christianity. As Clooney’s most recent work on interreligious theological reasoning demonstrates, many of the theological concepts and arguments that were previously thought to be unique to the Christian tradition can in fact be found in other theological traditions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">55</xref>By invalidating the facile contrasts of traditional apologetics, comparison challenges the Christian theologian to examine the Christian tradition more carefully in order to discern what truly makes this tradition unique. We can infer that for Clooney the “well‐informed” apologetics that survives comparison exists in a more nuanced and attenuated form than its predecessor. Perhaps reflecting a concern to appeal to as wide a theological audience as possible, Clooney’s conception of the relationship between the apologetic tradition and comparative theology nevertheless emphasizes the continuity between the two. Clooney’s reflections imply that comparative theology subsumes apologetics in such a way that the latter survives with its basic nature intact, albeit with a greatly diminished role.</p>
         <p>I would like to conclude this essay by suggesting a model for understanding the relationship between apologetics and comparative theology that builds on Clooney’s general idea that comparative theology replaces apologetics while retaining an apologetic dimension. And yet, while adhering to the basic guidelines set by Clooney’s position, the model I propose differs in that it places greater emphasis on the aspect of discontinuity between comparative theology and traditional apologetics. I shall argue that comparative theology’s relationship to apologetics is better understood, not as a relation of subsumption, but rather as one of sublation, implying an element of negation. Comparative theology presupposes the negation of apologetics as apologetics is traditionally understood. An apologetic element is indeed preserved in comparative theology but only in a radically altered form.</p>
         <p>The thesis that comparative theology presupposes the sublation of traditional apologetics entails two subclaims. The first of these is that the objective contrasts apologetics draws between faith communities give expression to an underlying religious attitude that is more basic. A desire to express communal loyalty takes the form of establishing the unique identity of that religious community. The determination of communal identity is in turn achieved through the formulation of contrasts between the respective teachings of the home community and its rivals. In other words, apologetics can be analyzed into two elements, namely, the objective representations of rival teachings, on the one hand, and what is expressed through these representations, namely, a concern with establishing communal identity, on the other. A corollary to this analysis is that apologetics is like myth in that a concealment of its underlying expressive intent belongs to its very nature such that it is fundamentally transformed when this expressive component is recognized as such. The second claim is that our current knowledge of the complexity and internal diversity of religious traditions has revealed the generalizations upon which interreligious contrasts are based to be conceptual constructs that reflect the interests of the individual or group making the comparisons. This knowledge thus makes it increasingly difficult for apologetics to conceal its underlying concern with establishing identity. Unable to execute its characteristic function of concealment, traditional apologetics gives way to comparative theology.</p>
         <p>The analysis of apologetics that divides it into expressive and representational components is not immediately obvious. Ostensibly, the defense of the faith against theological challenges presupposes the prior establishment of a community’s identity. The concern to establish religious identity thus appears to be extrinsic to the apologetic enterprise. On a deeper level, however, religious identity is something that must be continually maintained and expressed,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">56</xref>and the contrasts drawn between one’s own community and others constitute one of the forms this expression of identity takes. That a concern to maintain religious identity is intrinsic to apologetics becomes clear when we acknowledge the continuity between apologetics and the formation of doctrine. To the extent that a basic function of doctrine is to delimit the cognitive boundaries of a religious community, there is an intrinsic connection between a community’s doctrines, themselves products of conflict, and the continuing apologetic enterprise of defending these doctrines against new challenges. A community of faith establishes its identity in and through theological dispute, both in the primary mode of doctrinal formation and in the secondary mode of doctrinal defense.</p>
         <p>The foregoing analysis of apologetics presupposes that the intent to establish communal identity is primary while the objective contrasts through which this is achieved are secondary.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">57</xref>This priority of the concern to preserve communal identity becomes most apparent in those cases where rival religious communities have a great deal in common. There the urge to distinguish one’s community from the other is forced to exploit trivial differences between the two. The triviality of the objective differences betrays an underlying, a priori motivation to establish the uniqueness of one’s community.</p>
         <p>As mentioned above, it belongs to the very nature of apologetics to conceal the spirit of partisanship that motivates it. Apologetics makes the case for the superiority of its own truth claims to the extent that it succeeds in presenting objective standards of reason as the deciding factor. The successful apologetic argument, to borrow a simile from Heidegger, obliterates traces of its origins like a passageway that destroys itself. In this respect, apologetics is continuous with the classical theological project of demonstrating the fittingness of the contingent particulars of Christian faith such that these appear to follow logically from general theological principles. All theological rationalism seeks to overcome the raw contingency of the historical particulars of a tradition of faith. In the case of apologetics, however, there are aspects of today’s theological situation that render this concealment of contingency virtually impossible. A modern awareness of the limits of rationalism—two principal sources of which are the Marxist critique of ideology and the psychological concept of rationalization—renders it difficult to ignore the underlying interests determining the direction and shape of theological argument. Moreover, the modern explosion of knowledge of the history of religions has called into question the factual accuracy of many of the interreligious comparisons of traditional apologetics. Thus a postmodern awareness of the limits of reason together with new doubts about the validity of the objective comparisons of traditional apologetics have rendered transparent the underlying partisan motives of apologetic theology. Given the modern tendency to dichotomize the experiential and the sociopolitical aspects of religion and to relegate the latter to the realm of the profane, an apologetics with its partisan core thus exposed is apt to be rejected as a particularly distasteful form of theology. Thus doubts regarding the factual accuracy of its representations coupled with an aversion to the crude partisanship that lies at its core have led to the demise of apologetics as a credible intellectual discipline within mainstream theological studies today.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">58</xref>
         </p>
         <p>An increase in knowledge and religious sensitivity has thus revealed the representations of the religious “other” in opposition to which Christianity has traditionally defined itself to be little more than projections of an underlying desire to establish religious identity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">59</xref>Thoughtful comparison exposes this basic need to establish religious identity by invalidating many of the representations through which this need has been at once expressed and concealed. We might say that comparative theology represents the demythologization of apologetics, where demythologization is understood in Rudolf Bultmann’s sense as the recognition of an expressive function underneath an appearance of objective description. So just as Bultmann sought to demythologize the New Testament by explicating the mode of being‐in‐the‐world expressed through a mythical world picture,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">60</xref>so too the comparative theologian recognizes the expressive intent beneath the often questionable comparisons of traditional apologetics. The analogy with Bultmann’s demythologization project calls attention to a point about this conception of comparative theology that brings it into line with Clooney’s, namely, that it does not imply an outright rejection of apologetics. Comparative theology can be regarded as the attempt to salvage what is legitimate in apologetics, namely, the desire to preserve the integrity of a particular religious community by establishing its cognitive boundaries. This conception of comparative theology as a demythologized apologetics thus acknowledges the legitimacy of a sociopolitical dimension to religion. Through judicious comparisons, comparative theology brings into relief the defining features of the Christian community. Yet this aspect of comparative theology differs from traditional apologetics in that it distinguishes a desire to define the Christian faith from a perceived need to refute the teachings of other faith communities. To the extent that comparative theology succeeds in this, its comparisons will be free of the tendentiousness that characterizes the contrasts of traditional apologetics.</p>
         <p>The apologetic project can be compared to rites of institution in that it establishes a social difference—one that becomes part of a group’s self‐understanding—by calling attention to a difference in a preexisting state of affairs.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">61</xref>Apologetic theology exploits objective differences between religious traditions in order to establish a community’s sense of its uniqueness. The “demythologization” of apologetics reveals a gap between the social differences constitutive of a community’s sense of identity and the objective differences upon which these are founded. Now, an underlying intent to express communal loyalty takes the form of an oppositional stance in a situation of theological challenge. This oppositional attitude then determines which differences will be incorporated into the group’s self‐understanding. An obliteration of the distinction between social and objective difference, however, creates the illusion that the oppositional attitude plays no active role in the production of communal identity, that it merely follows an awareness of objective difference as an inevitable consequence. One of the dangers of traditional apologetics, then, is for a simple awareness of objective differences between religions to compel an oppositional stance, even when the identity of the home tradition is not threatened. A confusion of social for objective difference allows the directionality from attitude to observation to reverse itself such that the simple awareness of differences between communities evokes an oppositional attitude. By dispelling the illusion that makes opposition an automatic reaction to objective difference, comparative theology frees itself of the false obligation to assume an oppositional stance toward other traditions.</p>
         <p>In today’s situation of radical pluralism, an open attitude toward traditions for which there are objective differences is not only possible but, I would argue, necessary. To appreciate this claim, it is necessary, first of all, to acknowledge a distinction between, on the one hand, the understanding of itself that a community presents to others and, on the other, that held by its own adherents.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">62</xref>John Henry Newman describes this distinction with typical eloquence: “Defenders of Christianity naturally select as reason for belief, not the highest, truest, the most sacred, the most intimately persuasive, but such as best admit of being exhibited in argument; and these are commonly not the real reasons in the case of religious men.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">63</xref>The depth and vitality of a tradition depends on maintaining such a “two‐dimensional” religious self‐understanding. The temptation to define one’s religion in purely oppositional terms threatens to suppress those reasons that are “the most intimately persuasive.” When one’s opposition to other religious communities wholly determines one’s religious self‐understanding, religion degenerates into an expression of identity politics. Yet the danger of an oppositional stance toward other traditions leading to such a one‐dimensional religious understanding is not serious when theological challenges are more or less peripheral to a religious community as a whole. In such a situation of “peripheral” pluralism, a community can get away with an oppositional or exclusivist attitude toward other traditions. A core of genuine self‐understanding will remain relatively unaffected by the polemics taking place at a community’s outer limits.</p>
         <p>When an exclusivist attitude is carried into a situation of radical pluralism, however, the danger of a tradition's unwittingly impoverishing itself becomes quite real. With an awareness of rival claims of religious meaning and truth pressing in on every side, there is a tendency to exaggerate those features of one’s tradition that establish difference and to ignore or even disavow those that happen to be shared by others. In this way a pluralistic situation forces distinctions that were once internal to a tradition to be projected outside of it. One could cite as a relatively trivial but illustrative example of this phenomenon the hackneyed contrast between the logical, analytical West and the intuitive, mystical East. This contrast actually originates from within the Western tradition. It appeared, for example, in efforts to define romanticism over against Enlightenment rationalism or the ethos of the American South versus that of the North. When the contrast between the analytical West and the mystical East is allowed to define Western culture, one is tempted into forgetting that Western culture is as much the tradition of Plotinus, Schleiermacher, and Beethoven as it is of Aristotle, Descartes, and Newton. A tradition’s understanding of itself thus becomes stylized to the extent that it allows itself to be defined by such a contrast.</p>
         <p>A situation of radical pluralism combined with an automatic instinct to define oneself in oppositional terms thus threatens to turn a tradition inside out. In overdefining itself in this way, a theological tradition suppresses those internal theological tensions that, like the creative tensions of metaphor that generate new dimensions of meaning, are productive of theological insight. Tensions that once could be readily found within the tradition are now apparent—at least initially—only outside of it. A theological tradition that has unintentionally suppressed sources of creative theological tension within itself in an effort to define itself vis‐à‐vis others will be forced now to cross interreligious boundaries in order to reappropriate such tensions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">64</xref>This generation of theological insight from tensions spanning religious boundaries is precisely the aim of the defamiliarization procedure outlined above. Defamiliarization thus functions as an antidote to the tendency toward hyperdefinition that results from a situation of radical pluralism.</p>
         <p>Defamiliarization presupposes a severing of the automatic conjunction between the awareness of religious difference and a defensive stance toward the religious other. The demythologization of apologetics that results from the new pluralism at the same time represents the condition for the possibility of the means, namely, defamiliarization, for countering its ill effects. Thanks to its ability to dissociate a concern for religious identity from a defensive attitude toward the religious other, comparative theology is able to modulate between definition, which establishes a sense of communal identity, and defamiliarization, which restores to a tradition the theological ambiance—the reflective space opened up with the relaxation of polemical pressure—needed for its depth and vitality.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>Francis X. Clooney, S.J.,<italic>Hindu God, Christian God</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 2001), 11.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>In the final chapter of<italic>Hindu God, Christian God</italic>, Clooney concludes that “almost all of what counts as theological thinking is shared across religious boundaries” (165).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>This is true of belonging to any social group (e.g., a nation or an ethnic group). According to Ninian Smart, “Belonging to a group involves performatively acknowledging the mark [that defines that particular group]” (“Religion, Myth, and Nationalism,” in<italic>Religion and Politics in the Modern World</italic>, ed. Peter Merkl and Ninian Smart [New York: New York University Press, 1983], 18). See also Bruce Lincoln,<italic>Discourse and the Construction of Society</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1989), 23.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>Lewis Coser’s concept of “non‐realistic” conflict (<italic>The Functions of Social Conflict</italic>[Glencoe, IL: Free Press, 1956], 48–55 and passim) is helpful for understanding this notion of the priority of the need to affirm communal identity over objective conflicts. In contrast to “realistic” struggles motivated by actual conflicts of interest, nonrealistic conflicts derive from an underlying need to maintain the cohesion of a social group. The actual matter of contention is more or less accidental in a situation of nonrealistic conflict. Coser, following Georg Simmel, notes that nonrealistic conflict is more apt to occur with respect to groups in which members participate with their entire personalities (58, 67ff.). Religious communities would represent the paradigmatic form of this type of social group. Of course, actual religious conflicts would involve both realistic and nonrealistic elements.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>58</label>
               <p>A fact duly acknowledged by Paul Griffiths in “An Apology for Apologetics,”<italic>Faith and Philosophy</italic>5, no. 4 (October 1988): 399.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
               <label>59</label>
               <p>See David Tracy’s analysis of the “projected otherness” of religious groups with which Christianity has historically come into contact, most notably the Jews (<italic>Dialogue with the Other</italic>, 49–50). John B. Henderson’s comparative study of heresy (<italic>The Construction of Orthodoxy and Heresy</italic>[Albany: SUNY Press, 1998]) supports this idea of the projective nature of traditional characterizations of rival religious communities by demonstrating the constructive character of the comparative schemata through which religious traditions have established their identities.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
               <label>60</label>
               <p>Rudolf Bultmann,<italic>The New Testament and Mythology and Other Basic Writings</italic>, ed. and trans. Schubert M. Ogden (Philadelphia: Fortress, 1984), esp. 9–15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
               <label>61</label>
               <p>Bourdieu,<italic>Language and Symbolic Power</italic>, 118–21. See also Anthony P. Cohen,<italic>The Symbolic Construction of Community</italic>(London: Tavistock, 1985), 117, as well as Lincoln,<italic>Discourse and the Construction of Society</italic>, 9.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
               <label>62</label>
               <p>See Cohen,<italic>Symbolic Construction of Community</italic>, 74, for a discussion of the contrast between, on the one hand, the symbolic simplicity of the “face” a community presents to the outside world and, on the other, the symbolic complexity of itself as an object of internal discourse.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
               <label>63</label>
               <p>John Henry Newman, “Implicit and Explicit Reason,” in<italic>Fifteen Sermons Preached before the University of Oxford</italic>(Westminster, MD: Christian Classics, 1966), 271.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
               <label>64</label>
               <p>This idea of the deliberate recovery of theological tensions by crossing religious boundaries can be understood in terms of the ecumenical concept of the complementarity of conflicting doctrinal formulations. Opposing doctrinal formulations are regarded as complementary expressions of a theological truth so profound as to be irreducible to any single formulation. For the ecumenical use of the complementarity concept, see, e.g., Avery Dulles, “Paths to Doctrinal Agreement: Ten Theses,”<italic>Theological Studies</italic>47 (1986): 44–45.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
