<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">symbinte</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Symbolic Interaction</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">01956086</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15338665</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">si.1999.22.2.121</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/si.1999.22.2.121</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Text and Temporality: Patterned-Cyclical and Ordinary-Linear Forms of Time-Consciousness, Inferred from a Corpus of Australian Aboriginal and Euro-Australian Life-Historical Interviews</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib rid="cor1"
                     contrib-type="author"
                     corresp="yes"
                     xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Warren D.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>TenHouten</surname>
               </string-name>
               <aff>University of California, Los Angeles</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <author-notes>
            <corresp id="cor1">Direct all correspondence to: Warren D. TenHouten, Department of Sociology, University of California, P. O. Box 951551, Los Angeles, CA 90095-1551.</corresp>
         </author-notes>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>August</month>
            <year>1999</year>
            <string-date>1999</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>22</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>si.1999.22.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>121</fpage>
         <lpage>137</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Society for the Study of Symbolic Interaction</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>1999</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/si.1999.22.2.121"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>It is argued that autobiographical texts, such as life-historical interviews, provide the richest possible source of information about a person's temporality and a culture's historical past. It is proposed that time-consciousness can be inferred from such texts. To this end, ethnographic and other studies of Australian Aboriginal time-consciousness were used to construct a seven-part model of patterned-cyclical time-consciousness. Turning these seven attributes of patterned-cyclical time-consciousness into their opposites yields seven features of one-dimensional, ordinary-linear time-consciousness, thereby establishing a structured temporal polarity. A lexical-level, content-analytic methodology, Neurocognitive Hierarchical Categorization Analysis (NHCA), is introduced, in which folk-concepts of time from<italic>Roget's International Thesaurus</italic>were used to construct wordlist indicators for 9 of the 14 definitional components. Then, using NHCA for a comparative analysis of texts consisting of life-historical interviews, earlier results of an empirical study were brieflv re-presented. Australian Aborigines, compared to Euro-Australian controls, used a significantly smaller proportion of words for an index of ordinary-linear time but a higher proportion of words for an index of patterned-cyclical time, indicating a time-consciousness that is primarily patterned-cyclical rather than linear. Females were less linear and more patterned-cyclical than males in both cultures. These cross-cultural results contribute predictive validity to the proposed polarity of time-consciousness. Implications for the culture-and-cognition paradox and its resolution in dual-brain theory are addressed.</p>
         </abstract>
         <counts>
            <page-count count="17"/>
         </counts>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
