<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="misc">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">revuetudslav</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50014667</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Revue des études slaves</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Institut d'études Slaves</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00802557</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">2117718X</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">43272117</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>IN MEMORIAM</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>AUX CRÉATEURS DISPARUS</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Jack</given-names>
                  <surname>Feuillet</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Marie</given-names>
                  <surname>Vrinat-Nikolov</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2010</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>81</volume>
         <issue>2/3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40129183</issue-id>
         <fpage>321</fpage>
         <lpage>326</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Centre d'études slaves et Institut d'études slaves, 2010</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/43272117"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Until about 2005, it was hard to find any publication about literature during the communist era or any important work concerning this period. Since then, this astonishing silence has given way to the publication in Bulgaria of several novels and hybrid writings. In the meantime occured not only literary, but also political and social events which changed the issue: isn't the real problem in Bulgaria today no longer the institutional, generational, historiographical or literary silence, but the dilemna between the collective or individual responsability? To cope with these problems, the author takes into account both the works of Paul Ricoeur concerning the excess of memory and the excess of oblivion, the blocked memory, manipulated memory, abusively controlled or obligated memory, and two emblematic books concerning the communist past as seen in the State Security files: The Watched Man by Vesko Branev, and Surveillance and Conditioning: the literary prose of the State security by Žerminal Čivikov. Ako flo 2005 r. JiHTepaTypHmrr kphthk MOHceme m ce nyzjH 3anjo 6i&gt;jirapcKaTa jihtcparypa Bee ome npeMtJinaBa KOMyHHCTHneckoto MHHajio, 3 a m o see ome jinncBa 3HanHMa TBOp6a 3a TOBa MHHajio, to orroraBa H3JM3 0Xa peflHIja pOMaHH H TBOp6 H C XH6pHaeh )KaHp. Me^cAyBpeMeHHO ce cjiynnxa jiHTepaTypHH, HO H nO JIHTHH eCKH H COUHaJIHH ct»6hth«, kohto npeHacoHHxa KaTO ne jih npo6jieMaTHKaTa. H 3 rjie ^ a , cera npoGjieMa-THHHO e He TOJIKOBa MT»JIHaHHeTO - HHCTHTy- UHOHaJIHO, CeMeHHO-nOKOJieHHeCKO, HCTOpHOrpa(J)CKO, jiHTepaTypHO h t. h. - kojikoto AHJieMaTa Me&gt;K,zjy KOJieKTHBHa h h h /jh b h - ayajiHa 0Tr0B0pH0CT. ToBa mchho me 6i&gt;fle aHajiH3HpaHO b HacToamara cranM, kohto ce n030BaBa, o t e^Ha CTpaHa, Ha pa3BHBaHHTe o t IToji PHKbop noHOTHH 3a n p eK O M e p n a n aM em h n p e K O M e p m m o j i k o n aM em , 3a m o p M 0 3 e u a naMeT, M a n u n y n u p a n a naMeT h 3a d b JU fc eH a naMeT; o t apyra CTpaHa, Ha ^Be KHHrn, eM- 6jieMaTHHHH 3a OTHOUieHHeTO KT»M MHH3JIOTO, OTpa3eHO b ^ocneTaTa Ha flipHcaBHa cnryph o c t - Cjiedenmm noeex oт ecejiHH BpaHeB h Ha6juodeHue u pa3pa6omm: Xydootcecmeenama npo3a na JJ-bpotcaena cmypnocm ot ҖepMHHaji чиbиkob.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>fre</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
