<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerhistrevi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The American Historical Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00028762</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19375239</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/ahr.111.4.1221</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Reviews of Books</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>Canada and the United States</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Jason C.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Bivins</surname>
               </string-name>
               <aff id="a1">North Carolina State University</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>October 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>111</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>526084</issue-id>
         <fpage>1221</fpage>
         <lpage>1222</lpage>
         <product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>David S.</given-names>
               <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
               <surname>Gutterman</surname>
            </string-name>.<source>Prophetic Politics: Christian Social Movements and American Democracy</source>.:<publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name>.<year>2005</year>. Pp. xii, 222. $34.95.</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2006 American Historical Association. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>American Historical Association</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/ahr.111.4.1221"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>There is much ado about religion and American politics. Political scientist David S. Gutterman has written an engaging but somewhat limited study of the “prophetic” impulse as a window onto the relation between religion and politics. He compares Billy Sunday, Martin Luther King, Jr., Promise Keepers (PK), and Call to Renewal (CTR), focusing on their readings of Exodus. It is an intriguing project, yet there are questions about its distinctiveness and about Gutterman's attentiveness to the study of religion.</p>
      <p>The central claim is that religious narratives shape sociopolitical positions, a commonplace observation that Gutterman embellishes by asserting “that this religiosity often takes on a prophetic cast” (p. 49). Such assertions, however, are also quite common in studies of American religion and politics (think of Perry Miller, Robert Bellah, and Sacvan Bercovitch) and they would benefit from a more precise articulation of the relation between religion and politics. While he adroitly ranges over political material (especially in his insightful use of Hannah Arendt and Paul Ricoeur), Gutterman's grasp of other subjects is sometimes shaky. He claims that his approach displaces “the common view of the status of religion in American political culture” (p. 3), yet the two conventional methods he names—jurisprudential/Constitutional or policy‐oriented studies—scantly exemplify the range of understandings in either the academy or public life. Gutterman cites Alexis de Tocqueville as exemplifying a distinct “third mode of scholarship” (p. 3) that, in contrast to “a functional approach to American religiosity” (p. 8), underscores the importance of religion in American culture. Such functionalism may dominate political science, but this is far from the case in religious studies, history, or American studies, where the significance of religion is a given.</p>
      <p>Beyond this, Gutterman provides good historical accounts of each movement (although the most recent scholarship is not always cited), yet his feel for the nuances of his case studies' religiosity could be strengthened. At times he invokes antiquated or contested categories: “mainstream Protestantism” (p. 52), “religious revivalism” (p. 2), or “culture wars” (p. 134). Further, while Exodus is clearly an important narrative, it is perplexing that Gutterman focuses relatively little on each group's Christology. One might usefully explore the centrality of Mark or Acts to CTR, or of Galatians to King, for example.</p>
      <p>Gutterman pairs Sunday with King, focusing on their sermons and speeches. His readings are sharp and detailed, and his solid historiography sits alongside the work of David Chappell or Clifford Putney. The chapters on PK and CTR are well written but contain misunderstandings of each group's political orientations. Gutterman briefly outlines PK's declension narrative involving the breakdown of the “nuclear family”; but this begs for further comparative work, as he does not engage the 1970s architects of this narrative (e.g. Richard Viguerie), nor does he make sufficient use of literature on gender and religion. He also mishandles some of PK's political complexities, asserting that PK “has a political vision, and proclaims a political theology” (p. 99) even as its members see “no reason for democratic politics” (p. 125). In fact, PK do not dismiss politics altogether; politics are simply seen as serving a different purpose than evangelism. In other words, the relations among oft‐used terms like “politics,” “democratic politics,” and “political theology” are at times imprecisely articulated.</p>
      <p>Gutterman also overstates CTR's comfort with democratic politics and insufficiently acknowledges Jim Wallis's long‐standing ambivalence about political language. The relationship between Sojourners' exilic position and CTR's politics is far more complicated than Gutterman suggests. Further, his assertion elsewhere that PK and CTR draw energy “away from the public sphere” (p. 164) is just as misleading. These groups are uncomfortable with conventional political activity, but, as Gutterman surely knows, there are multiple public spheres in which political will is established.</p>
      <p>Ultimately it is at times unclear what is gained in making these comparisons or if such analysis “enhances our understanding of the relationship between religious narratives and politics” (p. 92). What precisely is revealed in grouping these movements together, other than that political crisis invites prophetic criticism? Gutterman carefully unpacks the readings of shared Biblical texts, and he skillfully details contextual and interpretative differences. But one wishes he had gone beyond these descriptive endeavors to construct a more nuanced account of the relationship between religion and politics and, more importantly, of the specifically religious grounds of the activism he examines. While Gutterman can be theoretically deft—in exploring the relation between narrative and politics (p. 21) or garden/wilderness metaphors (p. 47)—he is not fully engaged with the literature on political religion, often citing unrepresentative figures like William Connolly or Stephen Carter. He is a sharp writer with an eye for interesting problems and material. I applaud his engagement with important issues and also the ambition of his thinking. But his central categories require further explication, and this book speaks to the need for more conversations across disciplines.</p>
   </body>
</article>
