<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">40207381</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/589948</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR00437</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Place of the Soul in Augustine and Proust: Amorous Memory versus Neuroscience</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Gian</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Balsamo</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">American University, Cairo</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2008</year>
            <string-date>October 2008</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>88</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>522216</issue-id>
         <fpage>439</fpage>
         <lpage>465</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2008 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/589948"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>Premise</title>
         <p>A discussion of the soul as the traditional seat of selfhood is justified in light of the fact that neuroscientists are gradually colonizing the notions and concepts pertinent to spiritual discourse. In<italic>Synaptic Self</italic>, for instance, Joseph Le Doux reminds us that in<italic>King John</italic>Shakespeare defines the brain as the “soul’s frail dwelling.” And then he goes on to remark: “A few minutes with my mother, a devout Catholic with Alzheimer’s disease, makes it painfully clear just how fragile the soul dwelling is.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>In imitation of the Freudian investigation of the unconscious through the analysis of its deficiencies and dysfunctions, Le Doux is implying that an expeditious way of determining what the soul is consists of looking at patients who have lost their mental faculties. A keen observer of the disconnection between introspective gaze and external action, Saint Augustine might see the soundness of Le Doux’s vantage point; the feebleness caused by a terminal illness, in the specific case of his mother Monnica, is described in Augustine’s<italic>Confessions</italic>as provoking a “defectum animae,” a privation of soul—in modern terms, Monnica undergoes a swooning or a fainting whereby her consciousness drifts away from the people and things around her (<italic>Confessions</italic>8.9, 9.11).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>And when Proust describes “the kind of beast” that his protagonist Marcel finds in the bed of his dying grandmother, an unrecognizable woman blinded by pain and unable to recognize her own kin, he is intimating that Marcel’s maternal grandmother also, like Augustine’s mother, is being robbed of the major identifying token of her conscious self. “But if the being that turned and tossed in my grandmother’s bed was just a beast,” wonders Marcel, “where had my grandmother gone?”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>Indeed, where does the soul of Marcel’s grandmother, or of Le Doux’s and Augustine’s mothers, go when it leaves the body?</p>
         <p>If “compassion is incomprehensible without mourning,” as Martha Nussbaum maintains in<italic>Upheavals of Thought</italic>, mourning, Proust intimates, is unjustified when inspired by the demise of a beast oblivious of herself and her beloved ones.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>Our three authors mourn because they are in a condition of compassionate reciprocity with the subject of their grief; they know that this same subject, this same<italic>person</italic>—were they to reverse roles, and become themselves the oblivious, the departed or departing one—would remember and mourn them. The soul is the conventional locus of this reciprocity. The following discussion probes this locus, the space of this reciprocity, as it is circumscribed in the writings of Augustine, Proust, and current neuroscience; it advocates in conclusion the thesis, Proustian in nature, that the soul may be most profitably understood as our altruistic, mutual dimension of self‐instantiation.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>Joseph Le Doux,<italic>Synaptic Self</italic>(New York: Penguin, 2002), 15.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>All translations from Augustine’s<italic>Confessions</italic>are mine, from the Latin text in Augustine,<italic>Confessions</italic>, trans. William Watts (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2000). I have occasionally modified translations from William Watts; from<italic>Saint Augustine’s Confessions</italic>, trans. Henry Chardwick (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998); and from Garry Wills’s translation of Book 10 of the<italic>Confessions</italic>, found in his<italic>Saint Augustine’s Memory</italic>(New York: Viking, 2002). References to the<italic>Confessions</italic>are given parenthetically in the text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Marcel Proust,<italic>Le Côté de Guermantes</italic>, in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>(Paris: Gallimard Quarto, 1999), II.i, 1006 (Roman numerals designate part and chapter, followed by the page number). All translations from<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>are mine.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Martha C. Nussbaum,<italic>Upheavals of Thought: The Intelligence of Emotions</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001), 590.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Volition, Neuroscience, and Transcendence</title>
         <p>By borrowing a line from Shakespeare, Le Doux smuggles into his text the notion that the seat of the soul is in the brain. According to this “scientific” or empiricist view, Marcel’s wondering about the location of the token of individuality that malady and death remove from the body is illegitimate: if the soul is a function of one’s gray matter, one may safely assume that after death it putrefies together with one’s brain—in the same tomb, in the same space. Hence, the soul of Marcel’s ailing grandmother would not have gone any place new or different; nor would it go there after death. The neuronal clusters that make this woman’s behavior recognizable to her own family, and the clusters, in turn, that remind her conscious self of the identity of her own kin, are simply misfiring; eventually they’ll die off altogether.</p>
         <p>The alternative or speculative view, derived from the ancient Egyptian, Sumerian, Greek, and Christian traditions, is that human beings are endowed with a durable soul inherent in, yet distinguishable from, the body, the permanent<italic>ikon</italic>or reflection of a transitory<italic>idolon</italic>. This soul inheres in the body and at death survives it in a transcendental space—or should I say, in a transcendental dimension rather than a space, since, regardless of how interior to the physical body the place of the soul is, the afterlife of the soul corresponds, in all these archaic traditions, to the immaterial locus of a metaphysics.</p>
         <p>This essay probes the validity of a third alternative to oppose the empiricist and metaphysical views. For our ancestors, the human being was endowed with the intangible faculties of memory, intelligence, and volition, faculties unperceivable to sense experience, unyielding to the known laws of cause‐and‐effect, yet capable of affecting concretely the world of sensible phenomena; I am thinking, for instance, of the mystery of the Egyptian Pharaoh’s continued existence after death in the memory of his subjects, who could only come to terms with the endurance of his legacy (written edicts and various orally transmitted commands) by turning his own son into a reincarnation. As the invisible causes of tangible effects, the faculties of memory, intelligence, and volition were considered mysterious, mystic, transcendental; they served to identify a human being (a man, principally) independently from the body’s physical appearance, as an individual, a self destined to actively survive, in memory and in deed, the extinction of the body.</p>
         <p>Most neuroscientists’ objection to this archaic view would be that memory, intelligence, and volition are not the invisible causes of visible effects. In fact, it is universally agreed that we will soon fully master the imaging technology needed to scan and map out the neural pathways that mobilize the parts of the brain corresponding to events related to remembrance, understanding, feeling, and decision making. And to the extent that neurophysiology can demonstrate that the realm of our supposedly intangible faculties may be ultimately reduced to “neuronal architectures,” wouldn’t the notion of an immaterial soul become redundant and dispensable?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>Why keep toying with the delusion that the identifying token of our conscious self transcends physical space?</p>
         <p>The reason why some sort—perhaps a new,<italic>soft</italic>sort—of transcendence of physical space and physiological function may be of relevance nowadays is that neuroscience does not explain human volition in terms of individual perfectibility but rather in terms of genetic endowment and epigenetic rules. It does not tell us what we should want but rather what the genetically and culturally acquired norms clustered in our brain will make us want. It therefore reduces individual choice to a matter of “selective advantage.” Jean‐Pierre Changeux, a pioneer of neuroscience, argues, for instance, that by being coded in the neural networks of individuals, certain “instructions for socially appropriate behavior” prevent them from engaging in antisocial conduct.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Neuroscience explains in sum individual volition, a mental function or faculty that was traditionally attributed to the transcendental soul, by reduction, that is, in terms of neuronal structures of genetic or epigenetic derivation. Yet, the neuroactivity of these structures is not propositional; that is, it is not lived through affectively in the first person, nor does it display itself in narrative terms; it can only be mapped propositionally from a third‐person perspective. As an example of this sort of descriptive mapping—applied to the simpler process of perception, though, not to volition—Gerald Edelman formulates propositionally a cat’s perceptual map with the following sentence: “Cerebellum and basal ganglia active in pattern [q], premotor and motor regions active in pattern [r], and subcorticalities in visual maps active in patterns x, y, and z.” The specific terminology adopted in this paratactic, third‐person description is irrelevant to our discussion, of course. (But for the sake of correct representation, it is important to emphasize the inclusiveness of the term “pattern,” repeated several times: it is a recent discovery of neuroscience that an external stimulus may pattern the same perceptual output in an individual brain [and<italic>a maggior ragione</italic>in distinct brains] even when it triggers the interaction of different neurons and neuronal groups. In this regard, Edelman defines the term<italic>degeneracy</italic>as “the ability of structurally different elements of [the brain] to perform the same function or yield the same output.”)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>Relevant to our discussion is the idea that the propositional mapping of a human being’s decision making would have to recur to an analogous, third‐person parataxis and catalogue of patterns, as those adopted in the cat example (admittedly enriched to a degree of inclusiveness—of neuronal clusters pertinent to perception, memory, attention, intention, prediction, mood, etc.—far beyond the threshold of current neurological knowledge).</p>
         <p>
            <italic>À la limite</italic>, even my own first‐person, self‐conscious, and affective response to the neuroactivity provoked in my brain by a given set of circumstances is a neuronal phenomenon; as such, it may be propositionally mapped on the basis of brain imaging—but not better by me than by any neuroscientist reading my brain scans. Neuroscience makes us dispassionate spectators of a conative performance that we not only care passionately about, but are the protagonists of. Regardless of how precisely my and my neighbor’s brain scans image the neuroactivity corresponding to our decision making, and regardless as well of how unaware both of us are of the distinctive patterns in our brain’s degeneracy, it remains that my and my neighbor’s respective participation in the spectacles of these neuroactivities differ in kind. I conceive of myself (and narrate myself) as the protagonist of my own intentions and the spectator of my neighbor’s. The degree of personal freedom whereby I cope with the constraining necessities imposed on my intentions by external circumstances is the negative carbon copy of the degree of necessity whereby I cope with my neighbor’s personal freedom in dealing with his or her own constraints. I consider myself accountable for my actions and emotions in inverse proportion to the constraints imposed on my intentions; I consider myself accountable for my neighbor’s actions and emotions in direct proportion to my ability to affect the constraints imposed on his or her intentions. And I consider my conscious reaction to the stimuli received from my neighbor’s and my external circumstances as efficacious in “steering [my] nervous system,” to adopt William James’s terminology in<italic>Principles of Psychology</italic>, rather than a mere reflection of the causal effects exercised by my brain’s neuronal firings on my actions and decisions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In other words, it seems to me that the neuroscientific approach is still unequipped to fully colonize the affective intangibles of human volition. It still sends us back to a dimension of personal accountability that transcends physiology—a soft transcendence, not necessarily metaphysical, but certainly not empiricist either.</p>
         <p>Augustine relegates the rational aspects of scientific thinking to the soul’s<italic>ratio</italic>, that is, our faculty of analysis and synthesis (<italic>De ordine</italic>2.11.30;<italic>De diversis quaestionibus ad Simpl</italic>. 2.2.3), and contrasts rationality with intelligence (<italic>intelligentia</italic>), the soul’s faculty to acquire wisdom (<italic>sapientia</italic>) and act accordingly (<italic>De Trinitate</italic>12.3.3, 12.12.19;<italic>De ordine</italic>2.30;<italic>De immortalitate animae</italic>10.17). Rationality is instrumental; unless guided by intelligence, it is not affectively accountable. In the moral universe of Augustine’s subordination of human affection and family responsibility to religious devotion, for instance, the individual who despairs at the disruption, the “privation of solace” (deserabar tam magno eius solacio) brought about in his daily life by the demise of a dear one who used to “serve” him or her (servitus ab illa mihi), acts rationally (i.e., in self‐interest) yet unintelligently; on the contrary, the individual who, regardless of personal inconvenience, rejoices at his or her dear one’s assumption in heaven, acts irrationally yet intelligently (i.e., affectively or, in this specific case, altruistically) (<italic>Confessions</italic>9.12).</p>
         <p>As an evolutionary science, neuroscience understands human volition as dependent on constraints of selective advantage that are not considered by the laws of physics; at the same time, it postulates that the genetic and epigenetic conative drives determined by these constraints are coded in a brain that obeys the laws of physics.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>It is a science sui generis: faced with a certain firing of neurons in an individual brain, it may determine rationally, that is, analytically and synthetically, whether this brain’s response to the given stimulus is rational or irrational. Yet, the rationalistic paradigm itself is not intrinsic to neuroscience per se. Neuroscience’s sole firm criterion of evaluation is the logic of selective advantage, that is, an epochal, transpersonal teleology whose consequences may be gauged only a posteriori; it is impossible to judge a priori if an individual’s action, be it in self‐interest or self‐abnegation, promotes the selective advantage of the species; at best, one can gauge its greater or smaller consistency with behavioral patterns that occurred in previous instances of demonstrated selective advantage. Recent studies of neuroeconomics demonstrate, for instance, that irrational behavior dictated by fear or greed—affective emotions—may on occasion be economically more profitable than the rational behavior dictated by neoclassical theory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>In this regard, it seems to me that Changeux’s application of selective advantage to the sort of socially appropriate behavior that, in the scheme mentioned above, would be coded in the neural networks of individuals, is simplistic and misconceived, based on a Rousseauian notion of social contract that is hardly coincident with the principles of selective advantage. To make one crucial example, international terrorism may be of selective advantage to its proponents even when it entails the self‐destruction of many of them and is seen as antisocial by a majority of peoples and cultures on the planet—yet we have no way of knowing in advance.</p>
         <p>Finally, when it comes to evaluating not just the rationality but, as more impellent according to Augustine, the wisdom or lack thereof in a manifestation of human volition (say, in an individual brain’s conative response to a given stimulus)—when it comes, that is, to switching from<italic>ratio</italic>to<italic>intelligentia</italic>—neuroscience must import its evaluative criteria from other disciplines, be they jurisprudence, ethics, history, economics, chemistry, and so forth. As long as this remains the case, we are compelled to further probe the tradition that assigns significant influence in our decision making to a conscious self that is not the docile puppet of genetic and epigenetic norms.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Jean‐Pierre Changeux,<italic>The Physiology of Truth: Neuroscience and Human Knowledge</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press/Belknap, 2004), 75.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Ibid., 150–51.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Gerald M. Edelman,<italic>Wider than the Sky: The Phenomenal Gift of Consciousness</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 2004), 43–45, 50.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Cited in ibid., 84.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>See Gerald M. Edelman and Giulio Tononi,<italic>A Universe of Consciousness: How Matter Becomes Imagination</italic>(New York: Basic, 2000), 215–16.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>See John Cassidy, “Mind Games,”<italic>New Yorker</italic>, September 18, 2006, 30–37.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Love and Self‐Abnegation in Augustine</title>
         <p>When Augustine defines Monnica’s swoon in terms of a “lack,” a “privation,” or even a “defection” (defectum) of the soul, he is adhering to the Ciceronian (and, more broadly speaking, pagan) terminology that identifies in any living being an animal, a creature vivified by an<italic>anima</italic>. Cicero talks of<italic>animalia inanimaque</italic>, that is, of the two distinct realms of the living things that the soul vivifies, and the inanimate things that instead have no life altogether.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">11</xref>When she faints, Monnica manifests neither less nor more than a fainted beast, a diminution or absence of this living force. This is what Augustine means. Monnica is<italic>subtracta a presentibus</italic>, removed from her surrounding—a removal that may be interpreted as subjective and objective, to the extent that, as the above‐cited passage from Proust’s description of Marcel’s dying grandmother may suggest, her oblivion of the son who stands by her side must be likely compounded with Augustine’s reluctance to identify her inert body with the fullness of her identity.</p>
         <p>In the view of Henri Bergson, an eminent anticipator of modern neuroscience, Monnica would be momentarily experiencing a highly abnormal level of “distraction” from the ordinary concerns of human life: she cannot<italic>animadvertere</italic>, address the focus of her attention to things of immediate concern to herself. To the chagrin of his acquired cousin Marcel Proust, according to whom, as will be discussed, the experience of distraction could, on special occasions, induce a deeper cognition of certain facets of one’s own self, Bergson maintained that the “attention to life,” constantly projected toward the next moment of decision making, is inherent in our genetic constitution. It is important to stress that this “attention to life” was to Bergson a specific evolutionary trait, an endowment “of the species,” whose diminution, in cases for instance of déjà vu experiences, was symptomatic of some sort of mental pathology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">12</xref>In other words, the Bergsonian individual—which may be taken as an ancestor of the individual hypostatized by neuroscience—is impoverished, deprived in his or her self‐expression, by any occurrence of inattention to life. By contrast, Augustine’s negative formula—<italic>defectum animae</italic>, “a deficiency of the soul”—invites us to identify a loss of consciousness merely with a decrease in the vital force that humans share with animals. We must look deeper into the classical legacy behind the semantic simplifications of the English word “soul.”</p>
         <p>In Augustine’s writings<italic>anima</italic>can be roughly identified with<italic>spiritus</italic>(spirit), a term broadly embracing, as in the above example of Pharaoh’s surviving memory, but more generally as in the pagan/Ciceronian views on the vivification of animal life, all the undetectable and unexplainable causes of organic vitality.<italic>Animus</italic>is a special portion of<italic>anima</italic>, but such a special portion that it shares with the realm of spirit little more than its transcendental character. The notion of<italic>animus</italic>is where Augustine draws the line differentiating animals from humans. The most potent activity or faculty of<italic>animus</italic>is<italic>mens</italic>(<italic>De Trinitate</italic>15.7.11), and in fact on occasion Augustine identifies one with the other (<italic>De civitate Dei</italic>7.23).<italic>Ratio</italic>(rationality) and<italic>intelligentia</italic>or<italic>intellectus</italic>(intelligence, intellect) are intrinsic to<italic>mens</italic>, as well as<italic>memoria</italic>and<italic>voluntas</italic>(memory, will);<italic>ratio</italic>is the seat of the ability to distinguish and connect sense perceptions (<italic>De ordine</italic>2.11.30);<italic>intellectus</italic>is the seat of the ability to undertake an enlightened quest for truth (<italic>Tractatus in Ioannis Evangelium</italic>15.4.19;<italic>De Trinitate</italic>1.6.12, 4.2.4;<italic>De ordine</italic>2.2.5, 9.26).<italic>Scientia</italic>(science) results from the use of<italic>ratio</italic>;<italic>sapientia</italic>(wisdom) results from the use of<italic>intellectus</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">13</xref>Moreover, the first specification of<italic>mens</italic>is self‐awareness or self‐knowledge (<italic>De Trinitate</italic>9.12.18)—subjectivity, in other words: a self‐knowing subject is the presupposition, the anchoring ground of any knowing, remembering, purposeful activity on the part of<italic>mens</italic>.</p>
         <p>Terminological precision is important here. What are we talking about when we talk of the Augustinian<italic>mens</italic>? If Augustine could dismiss in an equally cavalier way the diverse hypotheses that<italic>mens</italic>is air, or fire, or brain (<italic>De Trinitate</italic>10.10.13), it would be anachronistic nowadays to refute the notion that the seat of<italic>mens</italic>is in the mind, and the mind, in turn, when either remembering, understanding, feeling, or willing something, is a faculty or an endowment germane with the neural firings of the human brain—more immediately, say, than with the beating of the heart or the pumping of the lungs.</p>
         <p>Germane yet not identical. Even neuroscience stops short of identifying tout court the brain with the self‐knowing mind. According to the Nobel‐prize recipient Gerald Edelman, the brain’s neuronal firing does not cause (nor is it caused by) first‐person consciousness; it is simply reflected in it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">14</xref>Neuroactivity converts an occurrence in the world into a “unitary output” in the brain—this neuronal output is completely independent of self‐awareness. As it engenders this “unitary output,” neuroactivity “entails” or “implicates” or “reflects” immediately (with no detectable temporal gap) the “integrated scene” of the subject’s awareness of the same occurrence in the world. Edelman calls this conscious staging of the occurrence at hand a “phenomenal transform,” and he makes it dependent on all of the subject’s memories of past experiences, directly or indirectly related to the occurrence at hand; this integrated and conscious mental scene is anchored around the subject’s “feeling of self.” Finally, the integrated scene is collapsed into the subject’s propositional mental activity, that is, the subject’s first‐person, intentional attending to the occurrence at hand, as well as his or her linguistic attribution of meaning to it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">15</xref>
         </p>
         <p>When it comes to the relative independence of the human mind from the physical brain, Edelman’s scheme of perception and apprehension does not diverge significantly from Augustine’s indifference to the physical logic of cause‐and‐effect or, more precisely, of organization and function. Augustine’s scheme of sense impression makes the perceptive functions of the five senses depend on their specific organization (<italic>Confessions</italic>10.8), just like Edelman’s scheme makes the mental apprehension of sense perception depend on the sensory‐ and psychomotor organization of the brain. Augustine leaves behind the realm of cause‐ and‐effect no sooner than sense impression engenders a sensation in the mind, the seat of self‐awareness; this sensation engenders, by the self’s willful concentration on it, an<italic>imago</italic>or<italic>similitudo</italic>(image, simile) of the sensation in memory, and subsequently an intellectual understanding of it (<italic>De quantitate animae</italic>25.48;<italic>De Trinitate</italic>11.9.16). Analogously to Augustine, Edelman elides the conventional separation between organization and function as soon as, by “phenomenal transform,” the subject of perception enters the self‐reflective stage of a subject aware both of itself and of the scene in front of it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">16</xref>At this stage, Edelman explains the coordination of mental apprehension and subjective awareness by the noncausal notion of “implication” or “reflection.”</p>
         <p>In Augustine there is an outside and an inside of the mind; the former is circumscribed by the sensible world external to the human body, and inclusive of the body’s epidermal surface, where most of the functions of the senses are located; the latter is the seat of a self more durable than the body and independent of outward appearance. The inside of the mind coincides with the “I as soul” (ego animus) (<italic>Confessions</italic>10.6) and is the seat of intentionality; the moment a sensible impression crosses the threshold of perception and becomes mentally apprehensible, its absorption in memory and intelligence depends on the self’s purposeful application of<italic>intentio</italic>(intentional attention) to it (<italic>De Trinitate</italic>11.2.2, 11.3.6). In Edelman too one can identify an outside of the condition of self‐awareness, circumscribed by the sensible world, that is perceptible by the senses and apprehensible by the brain, and an inside of the condition of self‐awareness, or an interior yet indeterminate locus of self‐awareness.</p>
         <p>The principal difference that I want to stress here between the Augustinian mind and the mind postulated by neuroscience is that the coordination of outside and inside, in other words the interplay between the passivity of perception and the activity of attention, intervenes earlier in the former than in the latter. In Augustine, individual attention takes to orchestrating apprehension and remembrance as soon as a sensible impression touches one of the five senses. Edelman instead, in agreement with William James’s claim that “the thoughts … are the thinker,” believes that the self of “the first person is simply present” to the neuronal unfolding of thoughts but not an intentional witness to it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">17</xref>Edelman postpones the coordinated operations of cortical organization and intentional attention to the stage when the integrated mental scene is collapsed into the subject’s propositional mental activity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">18</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The second important difference is that attention in Edelman displays itself in the mere guise of a utilitarian attending to individual goals, analogous with Bergson’s animalistic, instinctive “attention to life”; in other words, Edelman confines the act of attention to one’s self‐serving reaction to nonconscious neuroactivity. By contrast, attention in Augustine displays itself in multiple guises, each of them correspondent to a different stage in the perfectibility of the individual self. When focused on using what is to be used (<italic>utendis uti</italic>) in order to achieve a goal or obtain a result, attention coincides with the most instrumental or rationalistic configuration of individual will. When focused on the fruition of things, goals, or results that are an end in themselves (<italic>fruendis frui</italic>), attention coincides with desire (<italic>De diversis quaestionibus ad Simpl.</italic>qq. 83, q. 30)—with<italic>intelligent</italic>desire, one could say, keeping in mind’s Augustine’s distinction between<italic>ratio</italic>and<italic>intelligentia</italic>. When focused on intimacy with God as the ultimate object of desire, attention coincides with love (<italic>De Trinitate</italic>11.2.4‐5;<italic>De musica</italic>6.8.21).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">19</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Whether it manifests itself as purpose, desire, or love, Augustinian attention is a direct expression of the negative or positive thrust of the individual’s quest for his or her optimal self. As a consequence of this consideration, one could say that Augustine promotes a transformative notion of the soul, based on the premise that an individual is not endowed with a permanent soul; more specifically, one could submit that to Augustine an individual’s sense of personal continuity, which derives from the coordinated exercise of memory (<italic>memoria</italic>) of the past, attention (<italic>contuitus</italic>) to the present, and anticipation (<italic>expectatio</italic>) of the future (<italic>Confessions</italic>11.20),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">20</xref>does not punctually correspond with the continuity of an unchangeable soul. Modeled on the trinitarian theology of Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, Augustine’s three‐layered rubric of personal continuity is informed, rather, by a principle of perfectibility.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">21</xref>The supreme moral paradigm of the Augustinian soul consists of<italic>fruendis frui et utendis uti</italic>, that is, of purposefully using what is to be used in order to enjoy the fruition of that which is good per se, hence delectable to the soul (<italic>se ipsa delectata</italic>)—(<italic>De Trinitate</italic>10.10.13).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">22</xref>The Augustinian soul thereby constantly redefines itself in terms of its more or less virtuous<italic>desiderata</italic>and meritorious intentions.</p>
         <p>The inside of the Augustinian mind is conventionally defined in terms of inwardness, and inwardness, which should never be confused with interiority, corresponds to the purposeful motion of an introspective gaze. Augustine’s introspective gaze functions in a specular way, by conveying the reflection of what it sees. Introspection plunges purposefully, attentively inside itself, and at the heart of itself it recognizes the reflection of its own intentions.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>Ferruccio Calonghi,<italic>Dizionario Latino‐Italiano</italic>(Turin: Rosenberg &amp; Sellier, 1969), 185.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Henri Bergson,<italic>L’énergie spirituelle</italic>(Geneva: Skira, 1946), 138–42.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>For all this terminology, see Michele Federico Sciacca’s detailed dissertation in “Introduzione—Filosofia,” in Sant’Agostino,<italic>La Trinità</italic>, trans. Giuseppe Beschin (Rome: Città Nuova, 2003), lxvii‐cxiv, esp. lxxxiii n. 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>Edelman,<italic>Wider than the Sky</italic>, 82–84. Contrary to Edelman, William James believed that some sort of feedback loop enabled consciousness to have an “efficacious” influence on the workings of the cerebral cortex.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>Ibid., 8, 49, 61, 77–79, 82, 85, 125. Regarding Edelman’s hypothesis that an order of implication or reflection (rather than of traditional causality) links propositional mental activity to its source in neuroactivity, it is interesting that Paul Ricoeur, without explicit mention of Edelman, traces the origin of the trope of reflection back to Plato’s<italic>Theaetetus</italic>, where Socrates establishes the complex connection between the<italic>eidolon</italic>, which corresponds in neuroscience to the perceived occurrence in the world, the<italic>eikon</italic>, which corresponds to the neuroactivity triggered by perception of the<italic>eidolon</italic>, and the<italic>tupos</italic>, which corresponds to the mnemonic preservation of the original perception in the<italic>mneme</italic>of affective remembrance or in the<italic>anamnesis</italic>of intentional recall. See Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, trans. Kathleen Blamey and David Pellauer (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004), 421–26.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>In his discussion of the semantic improprieties inherent in certain views currently adopted by neuroscientists, Ricoeur questions the legitimacy of the elision of the conventional separation between neural organization and neural function. See Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, 421–26.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>Cited in Edelman,<italic>Wider than the Sky</italic>, 133–34.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>See Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, 421–26.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>See Sciacca, “Introduzione—Filosofia,” lxxvi.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>Brian Stock,<italic>Augustine the Reader: Meditation, Self‐Knowledge, and the Ethics of Interpretation</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press/Belknap, 1996), 13, 222.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>Augustine wrote of this trinitarian analogy in the<italic>Confessions</italic>(13.11) and at greater length in<italic>De Trinitate</italic>(10.11.17–10.12.19; 14.6.8–14.13.17). A variety of authors has recently commented upon it. See Colleen Jaurretche,<italic>The Sensual Philosophy: Joyce and the Aesthetics of Mysticism</italic>(Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1997), 63–64; Brian Stock,<italic>After Augustine: The Meditative Reader and the Text</italic>(Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2001), 21–22, 55–56; Stock,<italic>Augustine the Reader</italic>, 236.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Beschin, translator's note in Sant’Agostino,<italic>La Trinità</italic>, 415 n. 4.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Augustinian Intentionality</title>
         <p>“Of you, God, I know that which I ignore of myself. And certainly we can only gaze into the enigma for now as though through a mirror, not yet (<italic>nondum</italic>) face to face” (<italic>Confessions</italic>10.15). This often‐cited pronouncement is at the heart of Augustine’s notion of individual intentionality. It alludes to the Pauline trope of reflection from the first letter to the Corinthians, with the difference that Paul talks of a futural time (<italic>tunc autem</italic>), a time at the end of time, when he will see God’s love “face to face” (13.12‐13), without the aid of sermons and prophecies. Augustine talks instead of the futural time when, equally without the aid of Scripture, he will see his own will coincide with God’s love. The mirrorlike, distorting barrier, separating Augustine’s flawed intentions from the intentions that one day will be reflected in his soul’s identity with God’s “face” (vultus) (<italic>Confessions</italic>9.4), should eventually fade away. For the time being, in order to promote the attainment of this future saintly identity for himself, his introspection reminds him of what he knows of God’s will; this is an imprecise remembrance triggered by Scripture, but above all by the “amorous memory” (amantem memoriam) left in his mind by the “gaze of trepidation” (in ictu trepidantis aspectus) whereby he underwent, in a couple of occasions narrated in his<italic>Confessions</italic>, an instant of mystical intimacy with God (<italic>Confessions</italic>7.17, 9.10).</p>
         <p>Paul’s trope of reflection is metonymic, based on the relation of affinity between effect and contiguity: one day Paul will see divine love with the same clarity whereby he sees the face of a man standing in front of him, while for now he sees it in the hazy reflection of Scripture—just as a primitive bronze mirror shows him at best an imprecise reflection of his own face. On the contrary, Augustine’s trope of reflection is metaleptic, based on multiple transpositions of meaning.</p>
         <p>Augustine’s intentions (being changeable and perfectible) remain opaque when he inquires about them within himself, while God, who is able to look into his mind’s hidden recesses with greater immediacy (and who knows the future as well), is perfectly cognizant of them. Similarly, Scripture, whose meaning is the punctual expression of God’s will, enables Augustine to know certain traits of God’s will, but only on condition that he vivify Scripture’s inert letters, which per se are murderers of meaning (<italic>Confessions</italic>6.4), by means of the “amorous memory” of God that he holds within his mind. Hence, the “enigma” intrinsic to Augustine’s mirror is cracked in the middle by the asymmetry between God’s boundless<italic>sapientia</italic>and Augustine’s laborious acquisition of limited and transient knowledge. When Augustine searches for “the interiors of [God’s] words” (<italic>Confessions</italic>11.2) within the mirror of Scripture, literal and allegorical mediation, enhanced in interpretive power by his “amorous memory” of God, allows him a partial and imprecise apprehension of that divine will which, a few centuries earlier, was plainly embodied, as love, in the person of Jesus (<italic>Confessions</italic>11.2); yet, the more amorously Augustine searches in the mirror of Scripture, the less imprecise is what he finds.</p>
         <p>From Paul’s simple metonymic analogy with the primitive technology of reflection, Augustine has elaborated a complex metalepsis of reflection. In the “enigma” of his mirror of reflection, purposive agency speculates upon its own nature by measuring the gap that separates it from God’s will. Augustine cannot undertake the task of knowing his own wishes without comparing them with those of the God of Scripture; one day “in the face of God” (who knows Augustine’s wishes better than he ever will) “his own darkness will shine like noontime” (<italic>Confessions</italic>10.15). The condition sine qua non for a perfect knowledge of his own will, and for Augustine not to remain in “darkness” as concerns what he truly wants is self‐abnegation: he must make his will identical with God’s will, whose proper name is love. In gazing at divine will as reflected in the mirror of Scripture, he must learn to see the coincidence of his own and Jesus’s face.</p>
         <p>The mirror of Scripture is thereby the indispensable complement to the mirror of Augustine’s introspection. Gregorius came to this conclusion in<italic>Moralia in Job</italic>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">23</xref>where he compacts Augustine’s allusion to the<italic>speculum</italic>as follows: “One could say that Sacred Scripture faces the eye of the mind in the guise of a mirror, so that in it our inner face may be seen.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">24</xref>
         </p>
         <p>As I said above, beyond depending on the interplay of self‐probing and scriptural exegesis, Augustine’s self‐knowledge is also a reflection of the changeableness and perfectibility of his individual self. Within the limiting scope of his doctrine of free will, one could say that the more Augustine’s individual intentions strive to coincide with love, the better he gets to know himself; and the better he knows himself, the more dispensable the mirror of introspection and the letter of Scripture become to him. Metaphor, allegory, symbol, and trope are necessary as long as Augustine’s will diverges from love; this dissimilarity with love makes it necessary that he should use scriptural exegesis to acquaint himself as well as he can with God’s love, and then strive in self‐abnegation to fill the gap between his intentions and God’s love—which is the gap between his own face and Jesus’s. But in the incorruptible body that will be given to him (and to all the saints) at the end of time, his “resemblance to God will be perfect,” and his face, like the face of Jesus, will be the punctual manifestation of God’s love (<italic>De Trinitate</italic>14.17.23).</p>
         <p>This is a radical form of metaphysical transcendence: after the allegory of love will have become incorporated in the universe of creation at the end of time, even the most ordinary of mirrors will reflect it punctually because love will have become all‐pervasive, identical with reality. In mortal time, the trope of the mirror of introspection stands for the existential stratagem leading to Augustine’s antiutilitarian affirmation of choice over circumstance, fruition (<italic>fruendis frui</italic>) over usage (<italic>utendis uti</italic>), love over personal convenience. Only through the paradoxical expedient of such a transformative self‐denial may Augustine’s soul fully come into its own as the token of his personal identity.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>According to Mary Carruthers, Gregorius would be more precisely alluding to relevant passage from Augustine’s<italic>Enarrationes in Psalmo 103</italic>, ser. I, n. 4. See Mary Carruthers,<italic>The Book of Memory: A Study of Memory in Medieval Culture</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press), 329 n. 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Gregorius Magnus,<italic>Moralia in Job</italic>, in<italic>Patrologia cursus completus, series latina</italic>, ed. J.‐P. Migne (Paris, 1841–64), II.i, 75, 553d; my translation.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc5">
         <title>The Altruism of Love in Proust</title>
         <p>I mentioned above that Augustine disapproves, as unintelligent, of the feelings and manifestations of ordinary mourning. The day of Monnica’s death, when his son Adeodatus breaks into sob, Augustine shares his sorrow, yet he dries “the well of his own eyes” (oculi mei … resorbebant fontem suum usque ad siccitatem) by the “violent command of his<italic>animus</italic>” (violento animi imperio). His tears, had he shed them, would have been spent in mere regret for the “disruption” brought to his “habits” (ex consuetudine dirrupta) by the death of Monnica, who “served” him all his life. Yet, his<italic>anima</italic>is “wounded,” and the<italic>vita</italic>that his<italic>anima</italic>infuses him with is “almost torn to pieces” (quasi dilaniabatur). Augustine’s words suggest that the vitality of his body used to be vivified by Monnica’s soul—or, more precisely, that his and Monnica’s soul were indistinguishable from each other, fused into one (<italic>anima … una facta erat ex mea et illius</italic>) (<italic>Confessions</italic>9.12, 13).</p>
         <p>Also in the case of Marcel, the protagonist of Proust’s<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, the powerful experience of the merging of souls manifests itself with special intensity when death obstructs it. The most remarkable instance of soul merging in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>occurs during Marcel’s second visit to the sea resort of Balbec. At the Grand Hotel, where years before he stayed with his grandmother, Marcel is assigned the same room as on the occasion of his first visit. The night of his arrival, when he bends down to unlace his shoes, he is struck by the recollection of the stooping posture taken by his grandmother—before her death, a creature as devoted and solicitous as Monnica—to unlace his shoes the night of their arrival together. This recollection is fraught with ambivalence—made happy by the image of his grandmother’s tender attention to his every need, and made sad, even painful, by an oppressive sense of desertion.<disp-quote>
               <p>I could not understand and made an effort to endure the pain of this contradiction: on the one hand, an existence, a tenderness, surviving in me just as I had known them, that is, made for me; a love in which everything found its own punctual complement, its goal, its constant direction in me. … On the other hand, no sooner had I experienced this happiness again, as if it belonged to the present, than I felt it was obstructed by the certainty, spreading like a recurrent physical pain, of a void which had effaced my image of that tenderness, which had destroyed that existence, abolished retrospectively our mutual predestination, made of my grandmother, at the very moment when I found her again<italic>as in a mirror</italic>, a mere stranger.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">25</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>This memory initiates a metamorphosis in Marcel. He instantly loses sight of his present self (<italic>moi</italic>) and acquires a self pervaded by “a love in which everything finds its own punctual complement, its goal,” in him. This self is his “soul” (âme). More precisely, this self is the soul that, having existed in a condition of “mutual predestination,” of reciprocal fusion with the soul of his grandmother, he lost after her death: because of his indifferent mourning, the cohesion of his and his grandmother’s souls had faded gradually away and he had become a different self. Now he finds himself gazing, like Augustine, into an enigmatic “mirror.” This mirror does not reflect his own face but rather that of his grandmother, which appears to him an emblem of the unreflected face of his present self, like that of “a mere stranger.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">26</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In similar circumstances, as we just saw, Augustine accepts as a fact of life the mutual incoherence, brought about by death, between his and Monnica’s souls and awaits submissively the reunion that will follow his own death, when both he and Monnica will be endowed of the same body of divine love. Marcel, on the contrary, strives to reconnect right away, in the here‐and‐now, his soul with that of his grandmother. It is an urgent matter, for him; in spite of the physical absence imposed on his grandmother by death, he believes he can reactualize the cohesion of their two souls and renew thereby his past identification with his grandmother.</p>
         <p>Marcel understands that no preconceived notion of life and death, either materialistic or spiritualistic, may help him recover his “mutual predestination” with the soul of his grandmother. All he has to start from is “the originality of his pain”; he must “respect [it]” and follow therefore the logic, which death substituted to the cohesion of his and his grandmother’s souls, “of the mutual grafting in [him] of survival and nothingness.” This logic is bound to remain “incomprehensible” both to his “intelligence” and to his “faint‐heartedness” (which in this specific instance stands for an indolent facet of personal will). But it would be wrong to domesticate, as “intelligence and will” are eager to do, this incomprehensible logic by attributing the consolation of a life‐after‐death to his grandmother. His grandmother’s soul may only be resurrected via the resurrection of Marcel’s lost self, the self that was his soul at the time when his grandmother and he shared a “mutual predestination.” In order to attain the “resurrection” of his own self, Marcel evades the control of intelligence and volition by taking refuge in the world of sleep; and in “the organic depth … of his own viscera,” which stands here for the symbol of his own mortality, he finds the self that his grandmother’s death took away from him. “World of sleep in which our inner awareness, subordinated to the troubles of our organs, speeds up our heartbeat or our respiration, because the same dose of fright, of sadness, of remorse acts with a power a hundred times greater when thus injected into our veins; as soon as we start cruising on the black streams of our own blood as if on the sixfold coils of an inner Lethe, to travel the arteries of the buried city, tall solemn figures appear to us, approach us and then walk away, leaving us in tears.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">27</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Suzanne Nalbantian was the first critic to stress the relevance of this episode in the configuration of memory work in Marcel; her interpretation, however, which hinged on the presumption that all of Marcel’s emotions subsequent to his falling asleep could only decrease the intensity of his original reminiscence, goes in the opposite direction with respect to mine. Marcel’s crossing of the Lethe reverses the direction followed by the souls in Virgil’s underworld; these souls must cross into oblivion in order to be reborn into another body, while Marcel brings his lost “self” (the self that existed in a condition of “mutual predestination,” of reciprocal fusion with his grandmother) back to life by crossing the river backwards, into remembrance.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">28</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Marcel’s bodily interiors are translucid to the dreamer who, having divested himself of intelligence and volition, sails the feelings of “fright, sadness, remorse” that unconscious memory “injects in his blood stream.” The “mirror” that, at the instant when involuntary memory showed him the prostrated body of his grandmother, revealed to him the estrangement of his own soul from hers, is displaced by a new mirrorlike effect, that is, the oneiric “reflection” of the “painful synthesis” showing him that his grandmother’s annihilation is organismically grafted upon his own survival. Reborn, thanks to this dream, to the old self of his cohesion with his grandmother, to the old self of their two souls’ mutual fusion, Marcel is now conscious of carrying within his own soul “the diminished life” of his resurrected grandmother, “as pale as a memory.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">29</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>, in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, II.i, 1328; my emphasis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>II.i, 1327–28; II.ii, 1349.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Ibid., 1330.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Suzanne Nalbantian,<italic>Memory in Literature: From Rousseau to Neuroscience</italic>(New York: Palgrave, 2003), chap. 4, esp. 72–73. Virgil,<italic>Eneide</italic>, trans. Rosa Calzecchi Onesti (Turin: Einaudi, 1995), 6.748–51.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>II.i, 1329–30.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc6">
         <title>Filiation of Proust’s Introspection from Augustine</title>
         <p>I will now compare the mirror of introspection in Augustine with the mirror in which Marcel, having lost his identity with his grandmother’s soul, finds himself gazing at her face as if it were a stranger’s. This predicament is analogous to the inability to recognize himself in the mirror of inwardness experienced by Augustine. As we know, Augustine operates in a metaphysical logic wherein self‐recognition is conditional on self‐improvement: he can recognize his soul’s features in the mirror of introspection only on condition and to the extent that he turn his own will into the equivalent of divine love; a self‐abnegating form of cohesion brings about the full deployment of his identity with divine love, and that self‐abnegation, in turn, enhances the integrity of his self‐knowledge.</p>
         <p>At first Marcel neglects his grandmother’s death; in “deny[ing]” her, he “died to himself” by adopting an identity discordant with the amorous self that existed in “mutual predestination” with her soul.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">30</xref>When involuntary memory strikes him with the recollection of his grandmother’s solicitous gesture kneeling at his feet, and this vision returns to him his previous amorous self, he appreciates this old self’s superiority and would like to get it permanently back; this self is superior to the other selves, “which have succeeded one another in [him] since a while ago,” because it brings back to him his “veritable grandmother”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">31</xref>—neither an incidental simulacrum of remembrance, nor the “kind of beast”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">32</xref>turning and tossing in the bed of her agony (which “had only her name” and he “regretted so little”), but rather her “living reality.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">33</xref>This is perhaps the most emblematic instance in Proust’s novel when involuntary memory acts “the same way as love does.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">34</xref>The dream following this shock of recollection reveals to Marcel that he literally embodies that mutual predestination with his grandmother, which death seemed to have “effaced” forever.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">35</xref>
         </p>
         <p>As I said, Marcel can recover this past self only by a process of self‐resurrection; in order to revitalize his old self, he must resuscitate the cohesion of his and his grandmother’s souls. A double resurrection is at stake: the resuscitation of his past self entails a stoic gift of resuscitation for his grandmother’s soul, based on the precept that “the resurrection of the soul after death is perhaps [only] conceivable as a mnemonic phenomenon.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">36</xref>The authenticity of the self that Marcel wants to recover will be proportional to the degree of altruism whereby he is ready to rarefy his own present sense of identity, so as to bring it to merge with his “veritable grandmother.”</p>
         <p>In consideration of the fact that no direct influence may be traced from Augustine to Proust, I will now draw the line of filiation between their respective mirrors of introspection (and the transcendental logic of willful self‐improvement inherent in each one, respectively) by taking a coordinated detour into the discussions of self‐reflection found in two authors whose influence on Proust is unquestionable, namely Henri Bergson and Arthur Schopenhauer. As a theorist of memory and dream work, Bergson exercised an indubitable influence on his acquired cousin, Marcel Proust.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">37</xref>We will see that when it comes to the issues of individual willpower and self‐abnegation (both crucial to the discussion of love in Augustine), both Bergson and Proust were Schopenhauerian revisionists. And to the extent, as will be discussed, that Schopenhauer was in turn an Augustinian revisionist<italic>malgré soi</italic>, our excursus will close the circle of cultural influence by bringing face‐to‐face, if you will, Augustine’s and Proust’s respective mirrors of introspection.</p>
         <p>In<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>Marcel draws an analogy between the notions of soul, consciousness, and memory. In agreement with Henri Bergson, who declared in<italic>L’énergie spirituelle</italic>that “we do not forget anything,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">38</xref>Marcel is persuaded that there is in our soul “an unknown domain” where “all our interior wealth, our passed joys, all our pains” are stored and, when useless to our present concerns, kept dormant—in memory yet forgotten. Our “total soul” (âme totale) would be the repository of all the contents of our memory, both the active or remembered ones as well as those that the active ones push back, forgotten and dormant, into the “unknown domain.” This “total soul” has a merely “fictitious value,” hence, since it is made up of mutually irreconcilable memories, the active ones corralling the rest within a condition of temporary amnesia. The set of memories that prevails in our consciousness and grasps thereby our attention at a given time coincides with the self, the<italic>moi</italic>that we identify ourselves with at that time. At different times and given different “frames of sensations,” different sets of memories would prevail, and as a consequence we would identify with this or that different self.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">39</xref>
         </p>
         <p>One could say that, according to Marcel, our soul is divisible in multiple configurations, a variety of partial and irreconcilable souls, if you will, which are stored up in memory; as long as they are not actualized in consciousness, they remain virtual, inert, “sentenced to death” by the dominion “of a different self.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">40</xref>Marcel labors, as will be discussed, to help the best among these partial souls of his—those relating to his profoundest affections—to prevail over the rest.</p>
         <p>The mechanism of selective recollection described by Marcel is remarkably analogous with the trope of the pyramid adopted by Bergson in<italic>L’énergie spirituelle</italic>. According to Bergson, the mass of all the<italic>souvenirs</italic>stored in memory is like the immense basis of a pyramid; this mass “pushes up at each instant from the bottom of the unconscious” to reach the tip of the pyramid, that is, the level of conscious remembrance, yet our “attention to life” gives the primacy of attention only to the recollections “which may concur to present action.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">41</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In this binding of memory and experience lies a crucial difference, though, between Marcel’s and Bergson’s respective points of view. As discussed earlier, to Bergson the binding of memory with experience is constantly projected toward the next moment of decision making.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">42</xref>To Marcel, instead, surrendering to the utilitarianism of the “attention to life” may entail a renunciation of one’s most genuine selves. This sort of self‐betrayal occurs when one, surrendering to more pressing needs, neglects the emotions induced, for instance—to take the best‐known example—by the sensory perception experienced by Marcel in the episode of the madeleine.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">43</xref>To Marcel, the process of selective recollection needed to “resurrect” or re‐actualize the most valuable among our virtual selves functions in a deliberate mode of distraction or, to invert Bergson’s formula, of inattention to life.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">44</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The narrator of Proust’s aborted novel<italic>Contre Sainte‐Beuve</italic>praises the binding of present sensation and past remembrance as endowed with “a sort of … reality” that is superior “to the realities of … intelligence, passion, and feeling.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">45</xref>Bergson values the “harmony” between present sensation and its mnemonic equivalent because, in a mode of “attention to life,” it tells one how to handle present “circumstances” so as to optimize future ones.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">46</xref>On the contrary, Proust’s narrator declares that from the “impression” of this binding of past and present we may derive a nonutilitarian “pleasure”: a pleasure requiring that one disregard the spontaneous drives inherent in one’s attention and volition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">47</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Jean Santeuil, the protagonist of Proust’s eponymous and second aborted novel, may be considered a predecessor of Marcel in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">48</xref>The narrator of<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>refers to Jean’s “contemplation” as the practice, superior to “pleasure, thought, and memory,” which, willfully embraced, and fueled by imagination, gives us back our “soul” as an aggregate of the “relics of our life.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">49</xref>In this novel already, as he will later do in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, Proust postulates imagination as a faculty that, unable to apply itself directly either to present circumstances or to past memories,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">50</xref>“floats” around those past realities that are “captured” (prise) by present experience via the mediation of memory.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">51</xref>Although it adheres to Bergson’s principle of “harmonization” between present impression and analogous recollection,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">52</xref>Jean’s contemplation contradicts Bergson’s advocacy of a constantly transformative, hands‐on intervention on reality. When one talks of contemplation in Proust, in fact, obligatory reference must be made to Schopenhauer, whose influence on the French writer was certainly not inferior to Bergson’s.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">53</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The “aesthetic contemplation” promoted by Schopenhauer obstructs any active desire to change the world. In his dialogue on the question of the soul’s immortality, Schopenhauer advocates the attainment of a condition of “true indifference” to the world and to one’s own situation in it; this acceptation of “indifference” may be taken as a radical version of Marcel’s inattention to life in Proust’s<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>. Although Marcel’s distracted self is severely revisionistic with respect to Schopenhauer’s indifferent self, I submit that it is of Schopenhauerian derivation; this derivation sets it in diametrical opposition with respect to Bergson’s “attention to life.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">54</xref>While Bergson advocates an egoistic exercise of individual will as the unquestionable condition for one’s existence in the flow of time, Schopenhauer advocates a self‐denying purging of individual will leading to the subject’s “no longer stand[ing] in the stream of time.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">55</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Schopenhauer’s rejection of individual will’s self‐serving egoism bespeaks a greater concordance than he is willing to acknowledge between his views and Augustine’s avocation of the perfectibility of<italic>voluntas</italic>. As discussed, to Augustine the harder one’s individual intention strives to coincide with love, the better one gets to know oneself; and the better one gets to know oneself, the more diaphanous becomes the diaphragm separating one’s real self from its ideal reflection in the mirror of introspection. Self‐knowledge is self‐making in Augustine, and this self‐making consists of the transformative self‐denial whereby one purposefully modifies one’s own will until a coincidence is reached between desire and love. Schopenhauer accuses Augustine of “expressing in a naïve way” the role played by will in one’s self‐determination. According to Schopenhauer, when Augustine draws an analogy in<italic>De civitate Dei</italic>between “gravity [as] the motion of the body” and “love [as] the motion of the soul,” he is confusing the “real necessity” bestowed on both motions by the same cause, that is, by the self‐deployment of will in time and space, with the soul’s<italic>liberum arbitrium indifferentiae</italic>, that is, the undifferentiated free will whereby the soul, contrary to the body’s deterministic fate, chooses its own destiny.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">56</xref>There is no “undifferentiated free will,” hence no perfectible self in Schopenhauer; one either succumbs to the necessity of will’s self‐deployment or affirms one’s freedom by obstructing it, by boycotting it. Schopenhauer is an Augustinian reductionist<italic>malgré soi</italic>—a revisionist of Augustine’s avocation of the perfectibility of the self. Schopenhauer’s reductionism is reflected in the lack of direction intrinsic to his project of self‐emancipation from the dominion of will. In Augustine the obstruction of the instinctive drive of self‐interest is a figuratively upward movement (<italic>momentum</italic>), deriving its direction from the self‐abnegation, the weightlessness of love;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">57</xref>in Schopenhauer the obstruction of will’s self‐deployment is directionless, virtually nihilistic; it goes nowhere, or more precisely it plunges the will‐less self into nothingness, since all possible directions, in time and space, coincide with will’s own self‐deployment. One could say that the passivity of Schopenhauer’s asceticism, swaying between a passive contemplation of the world and a passive renunciation to it, is a subcase in the range of existential options offered to the individual self by Augustine’s belief in individual perfectibility.</p>
         <p>Jean Santeuil personifies a self‐denying subject who, inattentive to life, engages in forms of contemplation that, fueled by involuntary memory, channel him toward a Schopenhauerian form of existence “out of time” (hors du temps).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">58</xref>The exercise of involuntary memory is the solution that “tears [Jean] away from the condition of slavery to present time and pervades him with the impression of a permanent life,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">59</xref>bestowing on him a condition of Schopenhauerian “asceticism.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">60</xref>However, it is well known that in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>involuntary memory is no longer the “panacea,” as Joshua Landy has aptly pointed out, that solves the problems of Proust’s protagonist.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">61</xref>When Marcel tries to bridge the gap separating time lost from time regained, he must look beyond the expedients of a mnemonic technique. When it comes to involuntary memory, one could say that Marcel in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>operates in agreement with Augustine’s moral paradigm; he uses involuntary memory as an instrument (<italic>uti utendis</italic>) in order to attain a higher and more delectable good (<italic>frui fruendis</italic>), namely, the amorous altruism of his better self.</p>
         <p>In the episode of his grandmother’s dream, for example, the theory of involuntary memory is grafted onto the theory of dreams developed especially in<italic>Le Côté de Guermantes</italic>I and in<italic>À l’ombre des jeunes filles en fleurs</italic>II. In sleep Marcel’s<italic>moi</italic>“dies” and then, upon awakening, finds itself slightly modified by its dreams. Marcel recognizes himself by self‐recollection, yet it is a partially different self that he “remembers again,” when his memory “resurrects” it after the self‐forgetfulness of sleep. At first the “immersion” into a “leaden sleep” entails for Marcel a state, close to death, of radical absence from himself: “the attack of mental derangement that we call sleep” provokes in him a condition of complete self‐amnesia. In turn, this self‐amnesia gives him access to “the dark walls of that chamber which opens up on our dreams,” wherein “the drive to forget amorous sorrows works away incessantly.” Finally, thanks to his intrusion into this realm of constantly eroded remembrance, Marcel may disable the process of oneiric deterioration; he brings away with him “memories of dreams” that, although “shrouded in shadows” by the drive to forget, will become recognizable to him when the coincidence of some similar occurrence in the daytime will “strike them like a ray of light.” It is at the epiphanic stage of this “fortuitous” coming together of oneiric relic and present impression that the work of involuntary memory coalesces with the work of dreams. In the specific case of his grandmother’s dream, Marcel’s<italic>moi</italic>, after the deliberate rarefaction obtained in sleep, is resurrected as the self that used to exist in a condition of mutual cohesion with the soul of his grandmother.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">62</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The coordination of the work of involuntary memory with the work of dreams is the vehicle for Marcel’s recuperation of his amorous self. He renounces his current, self‐centered self for the altruistic self that embodies “the diminished life” of his resurrected grandmother.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">63</xref>I have used elsewhere the predicate of “altruism” to designate a project of self‐expression that incorporates alterity as its very raison d’être, arguing that genuine altruism is found in the expressions of human love.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">64</xref>In this perspective, one could say that Marcel’s strategy of amorous self‐discovery promotes at once the affirmation and the negation of personal will. Just as Schopenhauer’s rejection of the self‐serving egoism of individual will may be seen as revisionistic, and narrower in existential options, with respect to Augustine’s avocation of the perfectibility of<italic>voluntas</italic>in the amorous individual, so may Marcel’s commitment to the recuperation of his amorous self be seen as revisionistic with respect to Schopenhauer’s obstruction of will’s self‐affirmation. Marcel’s willful annihilation of his self‐centered<italic>moi</italic>is the diametrical opposite to will’s nihilistic destruction of the self; by renouncing his self‐centered<italic>moi</italic>, in fact, Marcel manages to salvage his altruistic self from the oblivion of unconscious memory, and thereby affirm it.</p>
         <p>Now that the ramified circuitry of cultural influence has brought face‐to‐face Augustine’s and Proust’s respective mirrors of introspection, we may see more distinctly how Augustine’s and Marcel’s respective notions of soul share the presumption that self‐knowledge depends on self‐improvement. The more he strives to make his desire coincident with God’s love, the better Augustine knows himself; the better he knows himself, the more superfluous his introspection becomes, because his historical self converges better and better with his own destined‐for‐paradise self. As to Marcel, the more he rarefies his self‐centered self and adopts in its stead the altruistic self that coincides with his grandmother’s love, the less he feels estranged from himself. In Augustine’s scheme one finds the classical elements of metaphysical transcendence. The full convergence between actual and aimed‐at self, hence the full elimination of the mirror of introspection, will occur in the afterlife, in the metaphysical body that will be allotted to Augustine as a saint—a body that will embody all the scriptural figures of redemption and salvation, making any mediation of reflexivity redundant to truth. In Proust’s scheme one may detect instead the elements of a soft transcendence—grafted on the laws of the organism. When involuntary memory acts “the same way as love does,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65">65</xref>retrieving for Marcel his (forgotten or discarded) amorous self, he is encouraged to engage in an organismic sort of introspection; by dropping into a comatose sleep that paralyzes the self‐serving drives of his intellect and will, the two faculties that would otherwise work in concert toward the rejection of this altruistic self, Marcel is enabled to surrender unconditionally to the unconscious memory of it. Even in this case, any mediation of reflexivity becomes redundant; the self that past affections have deposited in Marcel’s unconscious memory is literally indistinguishable from his own organism—it just needs to be retrieved by a deliberate plunge into it.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Marcel Proust,<italic>À l’ombre des jeunes filles en fleurs</italic>, in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, II, 569.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>II.i, 1327.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Le Côté de Guermantes</italic>II.i, 1006.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>II.i, 1327.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Le Côté de Guermantes</italic>I.i, 45.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>II.i, 1328.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Le Côté de Guermantes</italic>I, 813.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>See Roger Shattuck,<italic>Marcel Proust</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1982), 144; Richard Chassick, “The Search for the Authentic Self in Bergson and Proust,” in<italic>Psychoanalytic Approaches to Literature and Film</italic>, ed. Maurice Charney and Joseph Reppen (London: Associated University Presses, 1987), 19–36, esp. 19.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>Bergson,<italic>L’énergie spirituèlle</italic>, 93; my translation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>II.i, 1327.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>Ibid.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Bergson,<italic>L’énergie spirituèlle</italic>, 137, 183. Although Bergson does not provide a scientific explication of this motion of reciprocal “harmonization” between past memory and present situation, his description suggests the phenomenon analogous to what contemporary immunology and neuroscience call “binding”: the “harmonization” of past and present is permitted, that is, by a matching or recognition whereby a preexistent memory turns out to fit a present sense perception better than all other competing memories. For a definition of “binding,” see Massimo Piattelli‐Palmarini, “Evolution, Selection, and Cognition: From ‘Learning’ to Parameter Setting in Biology and in the Study of Language,”<italic>Cognition</italic>31 (1989): 1–44, esp. 15–17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>Bergson,<italic>L’énergie spirituèlle</italic>, 139.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>One such case of self‐betrayal occurs in the often‐cited episode of the trees of Hudimesnil. Riding on the carriage of Mme de Villeparisis, Marcel feels an unexplainable happiness at the sight of three trees; yet, try hard as he may, he cannot find a reason to his happiness. These trees, so strangely familiar, are perhaps a memory from childhood or from a dream, or a cryptic epiphany, or just an optical impression owing to eye fatigue. They seem to be asking of Marcel that he “return them to life”; he recognizes in their “naïve and passionate gesticulations the impotent regret of a dear person who, having lost the usage of words, feels he cannot tell us what we are unable to guess.” Having failed repeatedly to identify the source of his emotion, Marcel gives up puzzling over it, and at that precise moment he feels “as if he had just lost a friend,<italic>died to himself</italic>, denied a dead person, or misidentified a god.” Proust,<italic>À l’ombre des jeunes filles en fleurs</italic>II, 568–69; my emphasis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Ibid., 533.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>Marcel Proust,<italic>Contre Sainte‐Beuve</italic>, ed. Bernard de Fallois (Paris: Gallimard, 1954), 114; my translation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>Bergson,<italic>L’énergie spirituèlle</italic>, 137.<italic>Contre Sainte‐Beuve</italic>may be taken, albeit to a lesser extent than Proust’s previous aborted novel,<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>, as a preliminary draft of<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>. In a brief commentary of<italic>Contre Sainte‐Beuve</italic>, Pierre Clarac establishes the strict connection linking this early work to the<italic>Recherche</italic>. See “Notice,” in Marcel Proust,<italic>Contre Sainte‐Beuve (précédé de: Pastiches et mélanges, et suivi de: Essais et articles)</italic>, ed. Pierre Clarac (Paris: Gallimard, 1971), 819–29, esp. 827. However, on another occasion Clarac has written that “it is from<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>(and not from<italic>Contre Sainte‐Beuve</italic>) that the<italic>Recherche</italic>came out.” Pierre Clarac, “Notice,” in Marcel Proust,<italic>Jean Santeuil (précédé de: Les Plaisirs et les jours)</italic>, ed. Pierre Clarac (Paris: Gallimard, 1971), 980–86, quote on 983.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Contre Sainte‐Beuve</italic>, ed. Fallois, 114; my translation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Clarac, “Notice,” in Proust,<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>, 983. Apropos, it is significant that, in an episode of the novel’s section that bears the Stendhalean title, “<italic>De l’amour</italic>,” the character of Charlotte addresses Jean with the name “Marcel.” See Proust,<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>, 831. This is a revealing distraction on the part of the author who limits mention of the name Marcel to only two episodes in the entire<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>. Both episodes occur in<italic>The Captive</italic>. See Joshua Landy,<italic>Philosophy as Fiction: Self, Deception, and Knowledge in Proust</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004), 22; Marcel Proust,<italic>La Prisonnière</italic>, in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, 1658 (two repetitions of the name “Marcel”), 1720 (three repetitions).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>, 318, 399.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>In his notion of involuntary memory, Marcel corrects the Aristotelian principle that an object of the imagination that is imprinted in memory cannot coincide with the present experience of the object itself, because “there is no such thing as memory of the present.” Although he espouses the Aristotelian principle that “one can only imagine what is absent,” Marcel sees this principle as invalidated whenever the essential character of a presently experienced sensation coincides with that of a sensation imprinted in memory. In such an instance, one can enjoy the impression of the present sensation to the fullest; thanks to the intensifying “application” of one’s imagination of it, one enjoys, in other words, the impression that a sensation or event from the past is being concretely resuscitated in the here and now. This imaginative appreciation of the present throws one into the bliss of a dimension “emancipated from the order of time” (affranchie de l’ordre du temps) and makes one oblivious of or indifferent to the squalor of one’s “directly felt reality.” Aristotle, “On Memory,” in<italic>The Complete Works of Aristotle</italic>, ed. Jonathan Barnes, Bollingen Series LXXI‐2 (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press), 1: 714–20, quotes on 714–15; Marcel Proust,<italic>Le Temps retrouvé</italic>, in<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, 2266–67.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>, 318, 399.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>Bergson,<italic>L’énergie spirituèlle</italic>, 137.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>Anne Henry and Jean‐Jacques Nattiez have documented the influence exercised by Schopenhauer’s philosophy on Proust. Anne Henry,<italic>Marcel Proust: Théorie pour une esthétique</italic>(Paris: Klinsksieck, 1981), 45–97; Jean‐Jacques Nattiez,<italic>Proust as Musician</italic>, trans. Derrick Puffett (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), 78–87.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>Arthur Schopenhauer, “Immortality: A Dialogue,” in<italic>Studies in Pessimism: A Series of Essays</italic>, trans. T. Bailey Saunders, 4th ed. (London: Swan Sonnenschein &amp; Co., 1893; repr., St. Clair Shores, MI: Scholarly Press, 1976), 53–58; see Raymond Martin and John Barresi,<italic>The Rise and Fall of Soul and Self: An Intellectual History of Personal Identity</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 2006), 192.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>Arthur Schopenhauer,<italic>The World as Will and Representation</italic>, trans. E. F. J. Payne (New York: Dover, 1966), bk. 3, secs. 18, 38; translation modified.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>Ibid., secs. 24, 38, 55, 60, 68ff. Sec. 24, translation modified.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>Augustine,<italic>De civitate Dei</italic>11.28.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>58</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Jean Santeuil</italic>, 402.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn59">
               <label>59</label>
               <p>Ibid.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn60">
               <label>60</label>
               <p>Schopenhauer, “Immortality: A Dialogue,” 53–58.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn61">
               <label>61</label>
               <p>Landy,<italic>Philosophy as Fiction</italic>, 102.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn62">
               <label>62</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Le Côté de Guermantes</italic>I, 812–13. See also Proust,<italic>À l’ombre des jeunes filles en fleurs</italic>II, 644–45.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn63">
               <label>63</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Sodome et Gomorrhe</italic>II.i, 1329–30.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn64">
               <label>64</label>
               <p>Gian Balsamo, “Figural Literalism: Metaphor, Altruism, and Alterity in Dante and Caterina da Siena,"<italic>Exemplaria</italic>18, no. 1 (2006): 1–30, esp. 9–10.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn65">
               <label>65</label>
               <p>Proust,<italic>Le Côté de Guermantes</italic>I.i, 45.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc7">
         <title>Conclusion: Amorous Memory, Mourning, and Reciprocity</title>
         <p>In the present article I have undertaken the examination of individual volition in Augustine, the church father who introduced the idea of “free will” (liberum arbitrium) in religious discourse. Augustine’s portentous contribution to the discussion of volition as a token of identity and a reflection of self‐awareness consists of the identification of desire with love. To Augustine, our soul (<italic>animus</italic>) is not a constant and immutable attribute, but the expression of a perfectible self, which wills its own optimal instantiation when it desires first and foremost to love. After discussing Augustine, I proceeded to examine the different way whereby Marcel, the protagonist of<italic>À la recherche du temps perdu</italic>, curbs his own conscious volition, which he considers an incurable source of personal egoism, in order for his better self to surrender to the love buried in his unconscious memory.</p>
         <p>In both Augustine’s and Marcel’s experience, it turns out that the loss of a dear person may entail a loss of self, a sense of personal diminution—the subtraction of a crucial element in one’s purposeful self‐instantiation in the world. In the context of a different discussion, Ricoeur remarks aptly that the death of a loved one “constitutes a genuine amputation of oneself to the extent that the relation with the one who has disappeared forms an integral part of one’s identity.” We saw that Augustine copes with such a loss of identity by way of a detour into the desire of divine love and seeks his own better self through a self‐abnegating identification with this divine love. Marcel reacts instead to such a loss of identity by way of a detour into the materiality of his own mortality and seeks his own better self through a self‐denying identification with the love that the dear one’s death has left imprinted in his organism. In both cases, death’s “radical heterogeneity in relation to … desire” is exorcised by desire itself. The relevant difference between Augustine’s and Marcel’s respective forms of mourning is that the former reflects the metaphysical transcendence intrinsic to a more ancient notion of soul, while the latter’s reflects the soft transcendence of an embodied notion of soul that, however organismic in nature, bridges the gap separating merely genetic and epigenetic responses to mourning from the autonomy of one’s self‐instantiation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">66</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The mourning strategies adopted respectively by Augustine and Marcel suggest that the death of the beloved may teach us how to disrupt the foundation of self‐reflexivity upon which, as we saw with regard to the split selves of Augustine and Marcel, we tend to erect our own identity. In<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, Ricoeur advocates a mourning strategy equivalent with a similar goal. At first, he says, the death of the beloved brings about “a genuine amputation of oneself.” But then the experience of mourning entails “internalization,” a new level of personal identification for both the love object, lost to death, and our own self as a subject predicated on affections that now manifest themselves in absentia. This new self‐identification, in turn, trains us in the “anticipation” of our own futural self as predicated on the “plurality” that death will one day bestow on us in the memory of our dear ones.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67">67</xref>This is the equivalent of the compassionate reciprocity with the subject of one’s grief that, as mentioned in my opening remarks, justifies the state of mourning, or, in Nussbaum’s words, makes compassion “comprehensible.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">68</xref>
         </p>
         <p>In light of this discussion, we may now go back to the question that introduced the foregoing arguments. Where does the soul of Joseph Le Doux’s mother go when it leaves the body? My soft‐transcendental answer, Proustian in nature, is that it goes, or more exactly it remains, where it should be in the first place, namely, in the organismic memory that mourning “injects in [her son’s] blood stream.” It is the embodied token of his self’s altruistic identification in the loved one.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn66">
               <label>66</label>
               <p>Ricoeur,<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, 358–59.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn67">
               <label>67</label>
               <p>See ibid., 357–61.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn68">
               <label>68</label>
               <p>Nussbaum,<italic>Upheavals of Thought</italic>, 590.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
