<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">sciefictstud</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Science Fiction Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SF-TH Inc.</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00917729</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23276207</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">sciefictstud.38.1.0115</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5621/sciefictstud.38.1.0115</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>ARTICLES-SPECIAL ISSUE ON SLIPSTREAM</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Material Entanglements: Steven Hall’s<italic>The Raw Shark Texts</italic>as Slipstream Novel</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>N. Katherine Hayles</string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2011</year>
            <string-date>March 2011</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">38</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">sciefictstud.38.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>115</fpage>
         <lpage>133</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2011 SF-TH Inc.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5621/sciefictstud.38.1.0115"/>
         <abstract>
            <title>ABSTRACT</title>
            <p>Characterizing the slipstream genre, Bruce Sterling locates it between mainstream and science fiction; it “sets its face against consensus reality” and makes us feel “very strange.” A strong slipstream candidate is Steven Hall’s<italic>The Raw Shark Texts</italic>(2007). Manifesting as a distributed literary system, the text has as its core a print novel, but other internet and real world sites also contain fragments or “negatives.” One of the text’s two villains, Mycroft Ward, has transformed into an online database; a posthuman subjectivity, he appropriates “node bodies” that upload their information and download new instructions. This separation of content (online database) from form (node body) is, according to Alan Liu, one of the primary characteristics of postindustrial knowledge work. To this extent, Hall positions his narrative not only against databases but also against knowledge that is, in Liu’s terms, autonomously mobile, transformable, and automated, having lost its material instantiation and been pulverized into atomized bits of information. The text’s second villain—a “conceptual shark,” the Ludovician—represents the complete fusion of form and content; the typographical symbols used to describe the shark also comprise its flesh in verbal and graphic representations. The text thus positions its protagonist, Eric Sanderson, as caught between twenty-first-century forms of knowledge and the implosion of signifier into signified. In this sense, the novel functions as a parable for the contemporary human condition, looking toward a posthuman future but incarnated within an ancient biological heritage.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="r1">
            <mixed-citation>Ambrose, Stanley H. “Paleolithic Technology and Human Evolution.” Science 291.5509 (2 March 2001): 1748-53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r2">
            <mixed-citation>Deacon, Terrence W. The Symbolic Species: The Co-Evolution of Language and the Brain. New York: Norton, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r3">
            <mixed-citation>Doyle, Arthur Conan. “The Adventure of The Bruce-Partington Plans.” 1912. The Case-Book of Sherlock Holmes. Hertfordshire, UK: Wordsworth Editions, 1993. 765-82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r4">
            <mixed-citation>Genette, Gérard. Narrative Discourse: An Essay in Method. 1972. Trans. Jane E. Lewin. Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP, 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r5">
            <mixed-citation>Hall, Steven. The Raw Shark Texts. Edinburgh: Canongate, 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r6">
            <mixed-citation>Hall, Steven. The Raw Shark Texts. Toronto: HarperPerennial Canada, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r7">
            <mixed-citation>Hayles, N. Katherine. “Narrative and Database: Natural Symbionts.” PMLA 122.5 (Oct. 2007): 1603-1608.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r8">
            <mixed-citation>Hayles, N. Katherine. Writing Machines. Cambridge, MA: MIT, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r9">
            <mixed-citation>Hui, Barbara Lok-Yin. Narrative Networks: Mapping Literature at the Turn of the Twenty-First Century. PhD Dissertation. University of California, Los Angeles. 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r10">
            <mixed-citation>Lacan, Jacques. “The Instance of the Letter in the Unconscious.” 1966. Écrits: The First Complete Edition in English. Trans. Bruce Fink, in collaboration with Héloïse Fink and Russell Grigg. New York: Norton, 2006. 412-43.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r11">
            <mixed-citation>Lefebvre, Henri. The Production of Space. 1974. Trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith. London: Blackwell, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r12">
            <mixed-citation>Liu, Alan. Local Transcendence: Essays on Postmodern Historicism and the Database. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r13">
            <mixed-citation>Mangen, Anne. The Impact of Digital Technology on Immersive Fiction Reading: A Cognitive-Phenomenological Study. Saarbrücken, Germany: VDM, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r14">
            <mixed-citation>Manovich, Lev. The Language of New Media. Cambridge, MA: MIT, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r15">
            <mixed-citation>Pressman, Jessica. “The Aesthetic of Bookishness in Twenty-First Century Literature.” Michigan Quarterly Review 48.4 (Fall 2009): 465-82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r16">
            <mixed-citation>Pynchon, Thomas. Gravity’s Rainbow. New York: Viking, 1973.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r17">
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur, Paul. Time and Narrative, Volume 1. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r18">
            <mixed-citation>Sterling, Bruce. “Slipstream.” SF Eye #5. 1989. Online. 22 Nov. 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r19">
            <mixed-citation>Universes of Max Tegmark, The. Website of Max Tegmark, Professor of Physics, MIT. Online. 15 Dec. 2010.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r20">
            <mixed-citation>Wardrip-Fruin, Noah. “Surface, Data, Interaction and Expressive Processing.” A Companion to Digital Literary Studies. Ed. Susan Schreibman and Ray Siemans. Oxford: Blackwell, 2008. 163-82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
