<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mexistudestumexi</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Mexican Studies/Estudios Mexicanos</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">07429797</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15338320</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4141892</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/msem.2004.20.2.327</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <series-title>Articles</series-title>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>La historia en México (1984-2004)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <surname>Matute</surname>
                  <given-names>Álvaro</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
		          <month>08</month>
            <year>2004</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2004</string-date>
	        </pub-date>
         <volume>20</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>msem.2004.20.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>327</fpage>
         <lpage>342</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>©2004 by the Regents of the University of California. All rights reserved. Please direct all requests for permission to photocopy or reproduce article content through the University of California Press’s Rights and Permissions website, at www.ucpress.edu/journals/rights.htm.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/msem.2004.20.2.327"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article was intentionally written as a sort of conversation with Luis González to whom it is dedicated. It is full of references to his writings and his ideas. Instead of providing a list of historical writings produced in Mexico since 1984, the essay examines the institutional framework in which Mexican historiography is produced and the relationship between institutions and the writing of history. Another goal is to consider the entry into the profession of new generations of historians and, with them, the enormous variety of historical subjects that constitute the new fields of historical research. Finally, the author considers the contrast between the new interpretations and the unwillingness of a public, molded by an official history, to accept them.</p>
            <p>Más que hacer un recorrido a través de la vasta producción historiográfica mexicana de los últimos 20 años (1984-2004), el artículo pretende analizar las condiciones de desarrollo institucional a partir de las cuales se ha desenvuelto dicha producción historiográfica. Los sistemas de evaluación desarrollados a partir del Sistema Nacional de Investigadores cobran un papel relevante. Asimismo, se pone énfasis en el surgimiento de las nuevas generaciones de historiadores, en los nuevos temas que se han incorporado a los tradicionalmente tratados y en el contraste entre las nuevas propuestas de los historiadores provenientes de los resultados de las investigaciones y las interpretaciones a que han dado lugar y la resistencia del público, moldeado por la inercia de la historia oficial. El artículo está deliberadamente planteado con títulos y elementos de don Luis González, a cuya memoria está dedicado.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
