<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">modernphilology</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="ucp-id">mp</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Modern Philology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00268232</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15456951</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/656448</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MP108102</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Animals, Poetry, Philosophy, and Dante's<italic>Commedia</italic>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Brenda Deen</given-names>
                  <x> </x>
                  <surname>Schildgen</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of California, Davis</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>August 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">108</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">653501</issue-id>
         <fpage>20</fpage>
         <lpage>44</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2010 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/656448"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <verse-group>
         <verse-line>All is allegory, says my Philip. Each creature is key to all creatures. A dog sitting in a patch of sun licking itself, says he, is at one moment a dog and at the next a vessel of revelation.</verse-line>
         <attrib>(J. M. C<sc>oetzee</sc>,<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>)</attrib>
      </verse-group>
      <sec>
         <title>INTRODUCTION: THE CURRENT INTEREST IN THE STATUS OF ANIMALS</title>
         <p>J. M. Coetzee, the Nobel Prize–winning South African novelist, has increasingly deliberated on animals, human responsibility for them, and the relationships between humans and animals. In<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>, he presents “the lives of animals” as the obsession of his main character, an aging contemporary novelist.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">1</xref>The novel addresses an important ethical issue for our own times: what are the feelings of animals and how does the capacity of animals to feel affect how human beings can or ought to relate to other creatures?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">2</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The two chapters that specifically deal with animals, “The Lives of Animals One: The Philosophers and the Animals” and “The Lives of Animals Two: The Poets and the Animals,” reprint the two lectures Coetzee himself gave as the fictional author Elizabeth Costello at the Princeton Tanner Lectures in 1997–98. By moving these talks into the novel<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>, Coetzee makes the fictional environment the space to discuss animals, animal rights, and human responsibility. Because his main character is nearing death, he connects the animal rights discussion to the human capacity to think about death, particularly our own death, and to the “sympathetic imagination” that similarly gives us the ability to imagine the emotions of others, including nonhuman creatures.</p>
         <p>Coetzee's interest in animal rights parallels the radical redirection of intellectual and philosophical approach to the status of animals. For example, Charles Magel's bibliography on animals cites only ninety-four books treating the moral status of animals up to 1970, with thousands of books having appeared since that time.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">3</xref>This development, some argue, represents a reconsideration of the Western world's hierarchy of creatures that has always placed “man” at the apex.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN4">4</xref>In the face of the rapid disappearance or the annihilation of up to 60 percent of nonhuman animal species in the next decades, it perhaps should not surprise us that many contemporary writers have put creatures in the foreground of their literary endeavors.</p>
         <p>Among the philosophical works ruminating on the question of animals, we find Jacques Derrida's<italic>L'animal que donc je suis</italic>(The animal that therefore I am), considered the philosopher's “extraordinary contribution to a rethinking of the animal question.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN5">5</xref>Cary Wolfe's<italic>Zoontologies</italic>, representing Descartes, Kant, Heidegger, Lacan, and Levinas on animals; Giorgio Agamben's<italic>The Open;</italic>and<italic>Animal Philosophy</italic>, collecting Nietzsche, Heidegger, Derrida, and Cixous, among others, together demonstrate philosophers' interest in animals.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN6">6</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Thus, in taking up animal rights issues, novelists like J. M. Coetzee, Paul Muldoon, A. S. Byatt, and Witi Ihimaera show the current intellectual and artistic engagement with the ethical relevance of human relationships to animals and with what animal identity reveals about our own humanity. To explore the animal question, Coetzee's novel scrutinizes the traditional dichotomy between poetry and philosophy to argue that poetry can surpass or sidestep the limitations of dominant ideologies, attitudes, or even habits of thought in any given time period. Coetzee's novelist argues that poetry might have the power to overturn hegemonic philosophical systems that relegate animals to their traditionally lower than human status in the chain of being.</p>
         <p>This dichotomy between poetry and philosophy, first articulated by Plato, persists to modern times, as when Martin Heidegger restates the position in<italic>Was ist das—die Philosophie?</italic>(What is philosophy?): “Between these two—thought and poetry—reigns a hidden relationship because both are given to the service of language and give themselves to it. Between them, however, there persists at the same time a deep abyss, for ‘they live on separate mountains.’”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN7">7</xref>More recently, while confronting Heidegger's polarity between poetry and philosophy, Alain Badiou has written that after Hegel, “poetry assumed certain of philosophy's functions,” although not all poetry nor the work of all the poets is philosophic poetry or poetic philosophy. Badiou restricts the list to a few poets. (Among these, he names Hölderlin, Mallarmé, Rimbaud, Trakl, Pessoa, Mandelstam, and Celan.)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN8">8</xref>This radical division between poetry and philosophy, one that separates the affective and the cognitive, fails to recognize the way in which poetry itself, through metaphor and simile (or poetic discourse), unifies or attempts to unify the affective and the cognitive, the object and the subject, and in so doing, questions the assumed division between poetry and philosophy. Badiou's brief essay suggests, in fact, that the poetry that assumed philosophy's function or took over where “philosophy falters” is “a locus of language wherein a proposition about being and about time is enacted.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN9">9</xref>Badiou is speaking of a particular moment in the nineteenth century, but it can be argued that poetry from other eras may share similar features. Examining how poetry represents nonhuman creatures offers us a means to see that although philosophers may have underestimated or categorized the creature world to suit their particular thought system, poetic language may have simultaneously contested these same philosophical positions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
         <title>ANIMALS IN THE MIDDLE AGES</title>
         <p>Animals (in this essay referring to all self-moving species, including insects, birds, and fish as well as mammals), as a dominant source for metaphor, simile, allegory, and symbol, abound in literature of all eras. In the Middle Ages, as Jacques Le Goff wrote some forty-odd years ago in<italic>Medieval Civilization</italic>, animals were the subject of constant attention and reflection.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN10">10</xref>A recent spate of books, all published since 1999, includes<italic>Micrologus</italic>, Jacques Voisenet's<italic>Bêtes et hommes dans le monde médiéval</italic>(Beasts and man in the medieval world),<italic>L'animal exemplaire au Moyen Âge</italic>(The exemplary animal in the Middle Ages), Francesco Zambon's<italic>L'alfabeto simbolico degli animali</italic>(Symbolic alphabet of animals), David Salter's<italic>Holy and Noble Beasts</italic>, and<italic>Aristotle's Animals in the Middle Ages and Renaissance</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN11">11</xref>What has emerged is a recognition of the complexity and diversity of the treatment and role of animals in the medieval imagination.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN12">12</xref>Rather than simple allegory or moral exempla, particularly after Michael Scot's thirteenth-century translation of Aristotle's<italic>De animalibus</italic>(On animals),<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN13">13</xref>animal representation could include, often in a single case, empirical knowledge, theology, philosophy, politics, and cosmology as well as poetic or artistic ornamentation.</p>
         <p>Whether in sacred or profane contexts, medieval animals presented with empirically observed traits may be themselves symbols, allegories, metaphors, or similes. As symbolic communication, they can become the means to bring affective and cognitive knowledge and experience together. Reaching back to biblical images, we see that animals can be actors for God, as the locusts of the eighth plague of Egypt (Exod. 10:12) or the whale in Jonah (Jon. 1:17). They may represent the divinity as a lion (Isa. 31:4; Hosea 5:14, 13:8); a hovering bird (Isa. 31:5); a panther (Hosea 13:7); a leopard (Hosea 13:7); a bear (Hosea 13:8); or even a worm (Ps. 22:6). In medieval iconography, they may represent Christ (as the pelican or the lamb), the lion as king, and the eagle as empire; they may be creatures without reason (as the wolf); they may be wonders; they may be footprints or vestiges of the immanent presence of the creator (as in Franciscan theology).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN14">14</xref>The same animal with the same traits—the lion or eagle, for example—may take on completely different meanings in different contexts. But what is most important in all cases is that the creature as image conveys meaning. It is rarely mere ornamentation. In this respect, contemporary discussions of nonhuman creatures—by Derrida and Agamben, for example—continue the medieval assumption that nonhuman creatures both as beings and as images reveal something, thus sharing the idea that animals both as “beings” and as “signs” might convey both cognitive and affective knowledge.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN15">15</xref>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
         <title>ANIMAL IMAGERY IN DANTE'S<italic>COMMEDIA</italic>
         </title>
         <p>This essay argues that although the<italic>Commedia</italic>adheres to the philosophical tradition from Aristotle to Aquinas on the place of animals in the hierarchy of being, and the poet adopts conventional animal typologies, he nonetheless presents both the philosopher's and the poet's view of creatures. Some of the animals in Dante's<italic>Commedia</italic>appear as allegories or as similes and metaphors, whose precise meaning, although still subject to discussion, nonetheless conveys a relatively transparent meaning, as the three beasts in<italic>Inferno</italic>1, whose specific significance may be debated, but who clearly represent a hindrance to the pilgrim's progress and therefore signify diverse types of spiritual and moral danger.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN16">16</xref>However, the animals, as similes or metaphors, can become wonders: they may be shadows of the act of the creator, and as such they reveal the poet's knowledge of the natural world and provide an insight into his views about nonhuman creatures. In certain moments of heightened imagery, Dante's poem moves us out of the purely philosophical world and into the existential animal world. This does not mean that Dante overthrows the Aristotelian hierarchy of creatures but that, on some occasions, his animal similes disrupt this presumed order to present animal being-ness as outside hierarchies and philosophical systems.</p>
         <p>I propose here that Elizabeth Costello's idea—that poets differ from philosophers on animals—suggests an approach to literature in which literary language may be seen to convey a meaning neither intended nor limited by the time in which it was written. In other words, poetic language invites readers to contemplate how the knowledge it conveys differs from purely philosophical discourse even while it may be presenting itself as philosophical discourse. Metaphorical language may remove readers and the poets themselves from their own temporal, cultural, and philosophical horizons, moving the poetic work itself into a space of heuristic contemplation and apprehension beyond or outside their own political, social, philosophical, and cultural environments. In Dante's case, we may see that some of his metaphors and similes make it possible for the poet to probe the limits of Aristotelian hierarchies, even of Christian mainstream metaphysical orthodoxy, and thus to incarnate or make present the theological vision of the poem.</p>
         <p>I also want to take seriously Coetzee's author's idea of animals as “vessels of revelation,” the idea that the allegory implicit in the life cycle of frogs (<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>, 216–18) or in the dog sunning himself (<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>, 229) evokes some “timeless” sign in the animal world. Despite Coetzee's “postmetaphysical” and nonreligious framework, this view hints at a transcendent reality in the immanent natural world that the poet makes present through language, as in Francis of Assisi's poetic theology in the “Cantico di frate sole” (Canticle of brother sun), often titled “Cantico delle creature” (Canticle of the creatures). Probably more studied than any other work of the patron saint of the environment, the poem is a cosmic liturgy praising all of creation: “Laudato sie, mi Signore, cun tutte le tue creature” (Praised be you, my Lord, with all your creatures).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN17">17</xref>The poem's praise of creation or created things proves to be a “poetics” for humans' reconciliation with their own animal or created being-ness.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN18">18</xref>This is similar to what Derrida recognized as drawing humans to animals because of our mutual capacity to suffer, our vulnerability to death, and therefore our potential communion with other creatures in<italic>L'animal que donc je suis</italic>. Dante, because of his canonical status, because he belongs to a long past<italic>weltanschauung</italic>, because he adheres to Aristotelian philosophical views on ethics and on animals, and because many scholars have pounded him into his temporal niche, emerges as an excellent poet with whom to test the theory of animal images as “timeless.”</p>
         <p>Dante's animals (whether described via metaphor or simile or actually making an appearance) seem to break down into three categories: symbolic or allegorical creatures in the tradition of<italic>Physiologus</italic>that may be fantastic or real, like the three beasts of<italic>Inferno</italic>1 or the Griffin (<italic>Purgatorio</italic>2.29–32); similes and metaphors in which actions of humans or the dead are compared to animals; and images classified through an organizational structure that separates air, land, and water creatures. Since he had many resources for animal discussions—fables, encyclopedias, natural philosophy, Aristotle, Franciscan theology—it comes as no surprise that his animal imagery follows philosophical conventions and features a repertoire of traditional symbols, whether in their Christian, ancient Roman, or fabulist contexts, including lambs (Christ as lamb [<italic>Paradiso</italic>17.33] or pelican [<italic>Paradiso</italic>25.113]), wolves (<italic>Inferno</italic>1.49), lions, eagles (Christ as a bi- natured lion-eagle [<italic>Purgatorio</italic>2.29–32]), doves (<italic>Inferno</italic>5.82) , or fox (<italic>Inferno</italic>27.75), and frog and mouse (<italic>Inferno</italic>23.6). In figuring human corruption as bestial, Dante adopts an Aristotelian legacy; allegory and Aristotelian ethics coincide here. In both cases animal figures offer the tool to present a philosophical or theological position whereby the allegory reinforces the conventional and static hierarchy of creatures.</p>
         <p>Earlier studies of Dante's animals have inventoried the creatures,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN19">19</xref>analyzed the beast allegories,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN20">20</xref>and scrutinized the poet's frequent use of bird imagery.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN21">21</xref>An Italian entomologist, Giorgio Celli, and an Italian psychologist, Antonella Venturelli, have introduced a modern environmental approach to the poem in a recent article.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN22">22</xref>This article, together with another on bee symbolism, offers new perspectives on how we might talk about Dante and nonhuman creatures.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN23">23</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Analyzing the<italic>Commedia</italic>as three ecosystems, Celli and Venturelli argue that of the three canticles,<italic>Inferno</italic>has the greatest biodiversity (52 percent), followed by<italic>Purgatorio</italic>(30 percent) and<italic>Paradiso</italic>(18 percent).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN24">24</xref>These environmentalist observations reverse the traditional hierarchical views; they show that Dante's domain of the miscreant dead features the greatest range of creatures, including mammals, birds, reptiles, fish, insects, and other invertebrates, as well as fantastic creatures. Dante's choices appear to follow an Aristotelian ethical system that associates sin with the strata of the animal kingdom closest to the ground or with wild and untamed creatures. The ecosystem of the whole<italic>Commedia</italic>appears to reinforce the Aristotelian hierarchy of creatures. With regard to fantastic creatures,<italic>Inferno</italic>has twenty-three;<italic>Purgatorio</italic>, fourteen, all symbolic or allegorical; and in<italic>Paradiso</italic>, we find angels, the risen, and only symbolic forms of transcendent being.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN25">25</xref>Nonetheless, Celli and Venturelli specifically note that even though Dante's chain of being descends from humans to lower creatures in the order common to his times, he nonetheless observed natural phenomena with surprising exactness.</p>
         <p>Dante's capacity to observe animals becomes clearer in his metaphors and similes than through the animals that actually appear in the poem, as the iconographic eagle in<italic>Paradiso</italic>or the three beasts of<italic>Inferno</italic>1. It would be difficult to classify the poem's allegorical animals as metaphors; most function as metonymies, whereby the animals stand for something else—the heavenly eagle, for example, for the justice of God—so they are therefore a symbolic substitution for what they represent and do not bring to the fore latent connotations in the vehicle or the tenor, a trait Paul Ricoeur has argued characterizes the power of the metaphor.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN26">26</xref>Earlier, Enzo Melandri emphasized the unexpected, flexible, and creative uses of analogy and suggested that analogy's ability to bring forth latent connotations is precisely its heuristic, evocative, and synthetic power in contrast to allegory, which, although founded on analogy, is not in itself an analogical concept.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN27">27</xref>
         </p>
         <p>As Ricoeur elaborates it, “metaphor” as a semantic process has the power to transfer sentiments, so that in its poetic function, metaphor stretches the power of the double sense (sign and signified, vehicle and tenor, subject and predicate, or principal subject and modifier) from the cognitive to the affective.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN28">28</xref>Melandri also associates this approach with Max Black, who himself takes inspiration from I. A. Richards, who writes, “When we use a metaphor we have two thoughts of different things active together and supported by a single word, or phrase, whose meaning is a resultant of their interaction.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN29">29</xref>He identifies this same conception as more brilliantly developed in Arthur Koestler's<italic>The Act of Creation</italic>, in which the metaphor's “bisociation” brings forth many other composite phenomena than those initially found in the analogy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN30">30</xref>Of Dante and the Bible, Ricoeur writes, “Si la métaphore consiste à parler d'une chose dans les termes d'une autre, ne consiste-t-elle pas aussi à percevoir, penser ou sentir, a propos d'une chose, dans les termes d'une autre?” (If metaphor consists in speaking of a thing in the terms of another, does it not consist also in perceiving, thinking or feeling, about one thing in the terms of the other?)<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN31">31</xref>In other words, metaphor offers us this “insight”—to perceive, think, feel, even perhaps be or become like another. It allows us to experience entrance into the other, in a sense capturing a rapturous condition of mankind beyond or before hierarchies, dichotomies, and binaries. Identifying this approach to metaphor with post-Cartesianism and Heidegger, Melandri, like Badiou, calls this the “sympathy” aspect of the hermeneutics of the analogy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN32">32</xref>
         </p>
         <p>But the animals that actually appear in Dante's poem function as a type of allegorical equation rather than as analogy. For example, the eagle as poetic image does not reveal anything new or surprising about eagles, or, indeed, about the justice of God. Nor do the three beasts in<italic>Inferno</italic>1 reveal anything about the behavior of these creatures or about the specific sins they represent. Rather, they enact a pattern of allegory that Erich Auerbach links to the classical past in contrast to what he identifies as Dante's “figural” allegories. For Auerbach, “Virgil,” as an example, is “not an allegory of an attribute, virtue, capacity, power, or historical institution. He is neither reason nor poetry nor the Empire” to which the simplified nineteenth-century notion of allegory had reduced him. Auerbach's understanding of allegory makes Virgil “a<italic>figura</italic>of the fulfilled truth that the poem reveals, and this fulfillment is more real, more significant than the<italic>figura</italic>.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN33">33</xref>In the static-type allegory of the three beasts of<italic>Inferno</italic>1 or the eagle of<italic>Paradiso</italic>, real creatures have become personifications. This pattern resembles what Fredric Jameson has defined as allegory in his discussion of a Balzac novel (<italic>La cousine Bette</italic>) where “realistic characters” little by little become possessed and devolve into personifications. In Dante, these animal beings are already personifications in the same way that his bi- natured creatures that lord over various sections of hell (Minos, Geryon, centaurs) are personifications. Jameson argues that characters that turn into personifications lack individual existence or personality as they become equated with some notion of the universal—in other words, they become abstractions.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN34">34</xref>Similarly, the animals that Dante turns into personifications lack particular features other than their stereotyped traits, and thus they lose their species individuality to their abstract or universal symbolic meaning. In Auerbach's understanding of Dante's system of allegory, however, the figure becomes evocative and heuristic, leading beyond itself to contemplation of its connection to past, present, or fulfilled time. This essay argues that Dante's animal similes and metaphors that show close observation of nature, even if only for the duration of the simile or metaphor, suspend the Aristotelian hierarchy of creatures and present the immanent fullness of being of the creature world. But rather than pointing forward or back in time, as in Auerbach's theory of<italic>figura</italic>, these images suspend time; in fact, they make all time fully and immanently present.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
         <title>DANTE, ARISTOTELIAN PHILOSOPHY, FRANCISCAN THEOLOGY, AND ANIMALS</title>
         <p>One cannot deny that Dante adopts the philosophical tradition that asserts human superiority over animals because of the rational intellect and the possession of free will (<italic>Paradiso</italic>5.19–25).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN35">35</xref>Aristotle's<italic>Nicomachean Ethics</italic>divides the qualities of character to be avoided into three kinds: vice, moral weakness, and brutishness. Explaining brutishness as the reduction of the human to a beast, Aristotle argues that the opposite to brutishness is “superhuman virtue, a kind of heroic and divine excellence.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN36">36</xref>Thus, Aristotle posits a continuous line for humans going from brutishness (most like animals) to superhuman (most like gods). In Dante's time, the Dominicans continued this Aristotelian tradition, with Albertus Magnus providing what has been characterized as a theory of zoological anthropocentrism.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN37">37</xref>Animals' ability to participate in “man's rational way of living” allows Albert to rank animals according to the degree of their resemblance to man, but man, made in the image of God, is the perfect and most dignified creature. However, Albert does not conclude with this simple hierarchy of beings, for in introducing the Aristotelian idea that something marvelous (<italic>mirabile</italic>) resides in all natural things, he links all natural things as continuous with one another rather than in a binary opposition as man versus nature, animal versus human, and so on.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN38">38</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Dante restates the view of human versus beast in canto 11 of the<italic>Inferno</italic>when Virgil explains the three domains of hell:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line> le tre disposizion che 'l ciel non vole,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>incontenenza, malizia, e la matta</verse-line>
            <verse-line> bestialitade.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(<italic>Inferno</italic>11.81–83)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[the three dispositions which Heaven wills not: incontinence, malice, and mad bestiality.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Linking “bestialitade” (bestiality) with the worst aspects of human behavior, he insists that this most malignant of sins “è de l'uom proprio male” (is man's unique evil) (<italic>Inferno</italic>11.25). Equating sin with perversion of the unique trait of the human—reason—also reduces malicious humans to the bestial, and thus animals and animalistic behavior furnish the most common image to describe sinners in the<italic>Commedia</italic>.</p>
         <p>The three allegorical beasts of<italic>Inferno</italic>1.32–49—the leopard, lion, and she-wolf—like the serpentine Geryon, or the batlike, wormlike image of Satan, constitute a static idea of “fallen nature.” Continuing this association of the loss of the rational faculty with bestial (i.e., sinful) behavior, the lovers in<italic>Inferno</italic>5 are likened to flocks of birds moved by instinct (5.40–49, 82–87); the gluttons are like ravenous dogs (6.14, 19, 28); the avaricious bark like dogs (7.43); and the angry will become like pigs in slime (8.50). The “mille anime distrutte” (thousand ruined souls) are like frogs before an enemy (9.76–79), and the foul stench of the Epicureans (10.136, 11.4–5) reminds us of their animal bodies. Fraud itself, though a fantastic animal, figures as a mammalian serpentine “fiera con coda aguzza” (beast with pointed tail) (17.1). Flatterers, like pigs with muzzles (18.104), are reduced to the bestial. Dante gives a litany of snakes and serpents to describe the thieves in canto 25 (25.4–9, 19–24, 49–141). The falsifiers in the eighth circle are like hogs sinking their tusks into each other (30.27–29), and the traitors, like ravenous dogs, pursue their cannibalistic desires while evoking the image of animals gorging in the wild (33.1, 8, 78). Satan's appearance is likened to a “vispistrello” (bat) (34.49) and to a “vermo” (worm) (34.108), and he has the hair of an animal (34.75, 80). These images follow an uncontroversial philosophical and poetic convention, inspired by the ancient fabulist tradition as epitomized in<italic>Physiologus</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN39">39</xref>
         </p>
         <p>This language of unredeemed animal nature returns to the poem in<italic>Purgatorio</italic>and<italic>Paradiso</italic>when Dante refers to political disorder or ecclesiastical corruption. Probably the most powerful example occurs in<italic>Purgatorio</italic>14, when, indicting the corruptions of the cities in the Arno Valley in Tuscany, Guido del Duca, a repentant sinner, likens its people and their actions to wild animals:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line>ond’ hanno sì mutata lor natura</verse-line>
            <verse-line> li abitator de la misera valle,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> che par che Circe li avesse in pastura.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Tra brutti porci, più degni di galle</verse-line>
            <verse-line> che d'altro cibo fatto in uman uso,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> dirizza prima il suo povero calle.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Botoli trova poi, venendo giuso,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> ringhiosi più che non chiede lor possa,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> e da lor disdegnosa torce il muso.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Vassi caggendo; e quant’ ella più ’ngrossa,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> tanto più trova di can farsi lupi</verse-line>
            <verse-line> la maladetta e sventurata fossa.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Discesa poi per più pelaghi cupi,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> trova le volpi sì piene di froda,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> che non temono ingegno che le occùpi.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Io veggio tuo nepote che diventa</verse-line>
            <verse-line> cacciator di quei lupi in su la riva</verse-line>
            <verse-line> del fiero fiume, e tutti li sgomenta.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Vende la carne loro essendo viva;</verse-line>
            <verse-line> poscia li ancide come antica belva;</verse-line>
            <verse-line> molti di vita e sé di pregio priva.</verse-line>
            <verse-line>Sanguinoso esce de la trista selva;</verse-line>
            <verse-line> lasciala tal, che di qui a mille anni</verse-line>
            <verse-line> ne lo stato primaio non si rinselva.</verse-line>
            <attrib> (<italic>Purgatorio</italic>14.40–54, 58–66)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[Wherefore the dwellers in the wretched valley have so changed their nature that it seems as though Circe had them at pasture. Among filthy hogs, fitter for acorns than for any food made for human use, it first directs its feeble course. Then, coming lower, it finds curs more snarling than their power warrants, and from them it scornfully turns away its snout. It goes on falling, and the more it swells, the more does the accursed and ill-fated ditch find the dogs turned to wolves. Then, after descending through many a deep gorge, it finds foxes so full of fraud that they have no fear that any trap may take them.… I see your grandson who becomes a hunter of those wolves on the bank of the savage stream, and he strikes them all with terror; he sells their flesh still living, then slaughters them like worn-out cattle: many he deprives of life, himself of honor. Bloody he comes forth from the dismal wood: he leaves it such that in a thousand years from now it will not rewood itself as it was before.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Starting with the distinction between mankind and beasts, the description of the people in the Arno Valley spirals down from domestic to wild creatures as Dante's river descends from pigs to doglike creatures, and the wider the river the more the people become like wolves, until finally they are more akin to foxes; but still worse occurs, for the speaker predicts that a “hunter” will attack these wolves but turn himself into such a slaughtering beast that a thousand years must pass before the forest can return to its pristine state. Thus, Dante likens civil and political chaos—the result of human malice—to particular kinds of bestial behavior in a descending order from domesticated to wild animals, but the worst of these is the predatory beastlike human.</p>
         <p>Putting predatory creatures at the bottom of the scale based on a metaphorical or symbolic insight is not particularly startling. These kinds of metaphors are what Ricoeur (following Max Black) would identify as based on “common associations.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN40">40</xref>Quintessentially Aristotelian in its presuppositions, the linking of human bestiality with unethical action also follows the convention installed in the fabulist tradition of likening cruel and rapacious humans to wild animals. Invective like this occurs throughout<italic>Purgatorio</italic>and<italic>Paradiso</italic>, where one of the most common distinctions is between the domestic herd and the wild in images of sheep/goats and wolves (<italic>Purgatorio</italic>27.76–86;<italic>Paradiso</italic>9.131–33, 25.5–6, 27.55).</p>
         <p>Besides the Aristotelian tradition, Franciscan theology offered Dante, as a lay Franciscan himself, another theory of creatures that focuses on the idea of immanence in nature.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN41">41</xref>Following Francis, the Franciscans bring “creation” to the foreground as the incarnate reality of God's continuing presence in the world. For the Franciscan theologian Bonaventure, nature is everything that exists that is not God but is made by God.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN42">42</xref>Although adhering to the Aristotelian tradition that man is the rational creature, Bonaventure also discusses how Francis greeted a large flock of birds “as if they were endowed with reason” (eas velut rationis participles salutavit).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN43">43</xref>Bonaventure states the fundamental principle of Franciscan spirituality—that the natural phenomena of the world reveal their creator, even, one could say, make their creator immanently present: “Creatures are shadows, echoes and pictures of that first, most powerful, most wise and most perfect Principle, of that eternal Source, Light, Fulness, of that efficient, exemplary and ordering Art. They are vestiges, representations, spectacles, proposed to us and signs divinely given so that we can see God.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN44">44</xref>
         </p>
         <p>For Bonaventure, following Augustinian prompts, Francis's life was like a return to the<italic>hortus deliciarum</italic>before humankind's lapse and separation from nature. In Francis's model relationship to God and nature, according to Bonaventure, God's creatures are brothers and sisters: “When he [Francis] considered the primordial source of all things, he was filled with even more abundant piety, calling creatures no matter how small by the name of brother and sister because he knew they had the same source as himself.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN45">45</xref>This position is radically different from the dichotomized man-animal opposition upheld in the philosophical tradition and that has, as Agamben argues, anthropomorphized animals and animalized man.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN46">46</xref>Because it is rooted in “affective and aesthetic experience,” this Franciscan-inspired theology is never purely intellectual, for it expresses the “sense of union with the being and life of Nature.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN47">47</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Taking account of these Franciscan views, we might ask whether the animal similes in Dante's poem invite us, his readers, to contemplate Coetzee's novelist's question, “Do we have something in common—reason, self-consciousness, a soul—with other animals?” (<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>, 79). Coetzee's novelist answers her own question with a theory about feelings and sympathy whereby humans have the capacity to share at times the being of another. “Sympathy,” Coetzee writes, “has everything to do with the subject and little to do with the object, the ‘another,’ as we see at once when we think of the object not as a bat (‘Can I share the being of a bat?’) but as another human being” (<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>, 79).</p>
         <p>In many of Dante's animal similes, the poet/pilgrim, or Beatrice, or angels become that other, share the being of the other, thus following the Franciscan tradition and intimating that, for the duration of the simile at least, what separates the human from the animal in a fixed hierarchy of creatures might be overcome at least poetically via an analogy that cuts off difference and replaces it with similarity in a moment of transcendent immanence or immanent transcendence. Following Emmanuel Levinas's understanding of transcendence, here transcendence finds itself in immanence, as the subject loses itself in the other.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN48">48</xref>This is an insight Dante himself hints at with several reflexive neologisms in<italic>Paradiso</italic>, as, for example, when the pilgrim Dante remarks to Folco of Marseilles, the Provençal poet with whom he converses, that he cannot “inyoumyself” as you “inmeyourself”: “Già non attendere’ io tua dimanda, / s'io m'intuassi, come tu t'inmii” (Surely I should not wait for your request, were I in you, even as you are in me) (<italic>Paradiso</italic>9.80–81). Both reflexive verbs are neologisms, and as transitive actions require the actor (in this case a pronoun) and the undergoer (the reflexive pronoun) to be filled by one entity, thus overcoming apparent alterities.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN49">49</xref>Dante the pilgrim makes clear that he cannot overcome that alterity like Folco has, who, as a resident of the heavenly sphere, has surpassed ordinary human binaries. But this becoming the other remains, as in Levinas's ethical system, the ultimate purpose of the pilgrim's journey.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN50">50</xref>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
         <title>POETRY AND CREATURES: THE ANIMAL SIMILE IN THE<italic>COMMEDIA</italic>
         </title>
         <p>Dante's use of the animal simile brings nonhuman and human creatures together, either as analogies, through the breakdown of sign and signified, or in a process whereby “the other”—in this case a nonhuman creature—is the “locus of transcendence” that actually “calls into question the<italic>I</italic>in its existence as a being for itself,” as Levinas posits. For in Levinas's understanding of alterity and transcendence, the “I” paradoxically finds within itself “the other as such.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN51">51</xref>This parallels what Badiou argues in “The Age of Poets.” In this poetic process, time collapses, as the eschatological future and the prelapsarian past exist in the eternal present of the actions of nonhuman creatures.</p>
         <p>Setting aside the numerous references to falcons and falconry that have long been recognized as suggesting Dante's acquaintance with the birds, with hunting, and possibly with Frederick the Second's<italic>De arte venandi cum avibus</italic>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN52">52</xref>let us look at the metaphors and similes in which he shows his knowledge of creatures. Through poetry, in contrast to philosophy—and even if this were not his purpose—Dante can potentially think his “way into the existence of a bat or a chimpanzee or an oyster, any being,” as J. M. Coetzee describes the power of poets in<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>(80). Poetry, in other words, is a means whereby the subject can radically transcend itself in relation to the world of creatures.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN53">53</xref>This argument, of course, rests on the precise status or function of these similes or analogies in the poem.</p>
         <p>Whether or not the poets themselves agreed, for classical rhetoricians simile and metaphor function almost exclusively as forms of ornamentation. In the Aristotelian, Ciceronian, or Quintilian rhetorical tradition, metaphor is mere “substitution,” a way to see likeness between two distinct phenomena, a language trick, and a graceful addition to the poem.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN54">54</xref>According to the rhetoricians, metaphor, simile, and neologism in this tradition function primarily to increase aesthetic appeal. Despite this position, as one scholar of ancient rhetoric has highlighted, in fact, metaphor had more functions in ancient poetry. Among these we might include (<italic>a</italic>) to clarify, (<italic>b</italic>) to render sensual immediacy, and (<italic>c</italic>) to link the vehicle with unexpected associations.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN55">55</xref>Still, as Auerbach highlighted about classical<italic>figura</italic>, these features keep the image within a tropological function because none are associated with semantics. But a number of Dante's nonhuman creature images are different. The examples of a few that he has adapted from his Latin sources can suffice here. Dante's snake and serpent images in<italic>Inferno</italic>25.69–141, derived from Lucan's<italic>Pharsalia</italic>and Ovid's<italic>Metamorphoses</italic>, do much more than characterize the terrain, as in Lucan.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN56">56</xref>Ovid's serpent image shares a moral valence with Dante, for the image characterizes the entanglement of passion as Hermaphroditus falls to the lure of Salmacis: “But she wrapped herself around him, as a serpent / Caught by an eagle, borne aloft, entangles / Coils around head and talons, or as ivy / Winds round great oaks, or an octopus extends / Its prey within its tentacles.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN57">57</xref>In this instance, the melding into the other presents itself as a distortion and an aberration, as a devolution, both in Ovid and in Dante. But Dante appropriates this classical textual legacy with its moral judgment, however, to support his law of<italic>contrapasso</italic>, moving the imagery far beyond the two dimensions of ornamentation and moral censure. Dante's analogy between the thieves and the behavior of snakes and serpents becomes one of his visionary means to dramatize the poem's cosmological<italic>lex talionis</italic>. Virgil's analogy between Aeneas's men secretly preparing to leave Carthage in<italic>Aeneid</italic>4 compares the sailors to ants storing up for winter in methodical and organized haste;<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN58">58</xref>in contrast, for Dante the “schiera bruna” (dark band) of ants in<italic>Purgatorio</italic>26.34, likening the lovers to an orderly ant community (discussed below), conveys multiple meanings. The Virgilian image gives a parallelism in action while ornamenting the description, but Dante's density of significance moves beyond parallelism and analogy because of the semantic and, in Dante's case, theological element of medieval symbolism.</p>
         <p>Breaking from classical pastoral, as one might expect in Hell, Dante's world of nature in<italic>Inferno</italic>includes frogs (9.76, 22.26, 22.33); worms (3.69, 6.22, 34.108); flies, fleas, and wasps (3.66, 17.51); lizards (25.79); snails (25.132); mosquitoes, flies, and fireflies (26.28–29); and bats (34.34–50). These comparisons involve observations of nature in which the vehicle of the simile exists by itself as well as in analogy to the tenor. One of the most powerful examples of this occurs in<italic>Inferno</italic>26. To describe the lights he sees below in the bolgia of the false counselors, Dante chooses the following epic simile:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line>Quante 'l villan ch'al poggio si riposa,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> nel tempo che colui che 'l mondo schiara</verse-line>
            <verse-line> la faccia sua a noi tien meno ascosa,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>come la mosca cede a la zanzara,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> vede lucciole giù per la vallea,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> forse colà dov’ e’ vendemmia e ara.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(<italic>Inferno</italic>26.25–30)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[As many as the fireflies which the peasant, resting on the hill—in the season when he that lights the world least hides his face from us, and at that hour when the fly yields to the mosquito—sees down along the valley, there perhaps where he gathers the grapes and tills.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Here, we have a quotidian picture from the perspective of the peasant who watches the passage from flies to mosquitoes at dusk and the time of fireflies in the middle of summer. The simile describes the scene in the present (or eternal) tense, thus emphasizing the repetitive ongoing action of the peasant, the insects, and the sun that lights the world. The creatures, linked to the peasant in a symbiotic relationship, signal the time of day and year, revealing the predictability and order in nature to him. The insects, on the other hand, at least in this setting, are indifferent to humans, about which I will say more later. In other words, these creatures are so predictable, because of their interconnectedness with the drive and pull of other natural forces, that the peasant can measure time through them. The creatures follow both nature's and divine rhythms, “L'amor che move il sole e l'altre stele” (The love which moves the sun and the other stars) (<italic>Paradiso</italic>33.145). This picture illuminates a moment in the annual almanac, in which nature persists oblivious to humans although the human (“villan”) possesses the knowledge to read nature's signs. Thus detached from the tenor, the simile shows how creatures reveal and communicate their natural knowledge and points to nature's order and vigor.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN59">59</xref>But as a vehicle, it also tells us about the lights Dante the pilgrim sees below. Together with the tenor, the simile's scene highlights the stark differences among (1) the peasant's simple natural knowledge; (2) the pilgrim's flawed knowledge, for he mistakenly likens the flames below to fireflies; and (3) in contrast to the perennial insight and knowledge of the “villan,” Ulysses' presumptuous desire to master knowledge of the natural world.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN60">60</xref>Furthermore, the poet's simile unsettles the hierarchy of creatures, pitting the peasant's natural knowledge against Ulysses' superior intellect and will that challenges natural boundaries and costs him his eternal life.</p>
         <p>Similes like this function both as equation or analogy and to describe a natural phenomenon that draws attention to itself as indifferent to humans and as an end, an entity with its own incarnate viability. In<italic>Purgatorio</italic>26, several similes describe the lovers of both preferences, likening the lovers to ants, to birds, and to fish: “così per entro loro schiera bruna/ s'ammusa l'una con l'altra formica, / forse a spïar lor via e lor fortuna” (thus within their dark band one ant touches muzzle with another, perhaps to spy out their way and their fortune) (26.34–36); “Poi, come grue ch'a le montagne Rife / volasser parte, e parte inver’ l'arene, / queste del gel, quelle del sole schife” (Then, like cranes that should fly, some to the Riphaean mountains and others toward the sands, these shy of the frost, those of the sun) (26.43–45); “Poi, forse per dar luogo altrui secondo / che presso avea, disparve per lo foco, / come per l'acqua il pesce andando al fondo” (Then, perhaps to give place to another following close behind he vanished through the flames like a fish that goes through the water to the bottom) (26.133–35). In the medieval context, ants, fish, and birds are common images for prudent community (ants) and for the human soul (birds and fish), so these choices follow a conventional pattern.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN61">61</xref>
         </p>
         <p>However, while it could be argued that these similes function allegorically to show the loss of rational faculty to instinctual drives that explains the condition of the sinners in this circle, and while the similes do indeed describe the actions of the sinners, the vehicles in the similes are not just analogies. Rather, they function as microscopic views of the natural world of creatures and as part of the natural order of Dante's created universe: existing alone, they become sign, signified, and signifying, indifferent to humans or even to their place in the order of creatures; and, like all other creatures, in their immanent presence they perform and participate in a vast cosmic dance. Again, as Agamben puts it, describing animal captivation, the animal possesses a “more spellbinding and intense openness than any kind of human knowledge,” yet “it is closed in a total opacity.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN62">62</xref>Animals—in this case, ants, fish, and birds—lacking consciousness of themselves as selves are captivated within themselves and by instinct and needs. This captivation, according to Agamben, following Heidegger, makes the world opaque to the nonhuman creature, yet this “captivation” also allows the animal to be “open” to the world, as vestige or footprint of a living divine presence. In this understanding of the ontology of the animal, we recognize that the animal is not in the postlapsarian human strife-ridden condition, trapped between being and nonbeing (consciousness and finitude). Rather, the animal exists in a state of obliviousness about the cares and anxieties that plague human consciousness. With the similes functioning heuristically, we then see the lustful in<italic>Purgatorio</italic>26, who are harnessing their recalcitrant desires, to aspire to this state possessed by nonhuman creatures and epitomized by the unconscious action of ants. In one sense the condition of the blessed, like that of the ants, is fullness of being, outside consciousness.</p>
         <p>Demonstration of how this notion works in Dante becomes even clearer when we examine the animal similes in<italic>Paradiso</italic>. These overwhelmingly are bird images, with the major exception of the bee simile that occurs in canto 31. Unlike the bird similes in<italic>Inferno</italic>5, where the birds as flocks are likened to the windblown lovers, the bird similes in<italic>Paradiso</italic>invariably describe the purposeful action of lone birds. Furthermore, in contrast to many similes and metaphors in<italic>Paradiso</italic>that seem to attenuate the relationship between what is figured and the language to express it,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN63">63</xref>in the case of these similes, the vehicle—sign and signifier of the immanent action—makes the natural event itself an “opening” to the “fullness of being” of the animal world. For example, in describing the action of the iconographic Eagle (<italic>Paradiso</italic>19 and 20), Dante makes its movement parallel to both a circling stork in the wild who has just fed her chicks and simultaneously the just-fed chick who looks up at the mother. With the verbs in the eternal tense (the present), this image likens the maternal symbiosis with the chicks as eternal actions to the movement of the symbolic eagle, itself an allegory standing for imperial masculinity and divine justice. Together (vehicle and tenor), they are both animal and transfigured human, male and female, mother and child, abstract and concrete:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line>Quale sovresso il nido si rigira</verse-line>
            <verse-line> poi c'ha pasciuti la cicogna i figli,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> e come quel ch'è pasto la rimira;</verse-line>
            <verse-line>cotal si fece, e sì leväi i cigli,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> la benedetta imagine.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(<italic>Paradiso</italic>19.91–95)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[As the stork circles over her nest, when she has fed her young, and as the one that she has fed looks up to her, such became (and I so raised my brows) the blessed image.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Here, via simile, Dante makes the observable action of the nonhuman creature in the natural world parallel the actions of the blessed, as it evades being a mere sign; in its immanence, it becomes analogous to the blessed in their transcendent condition, the living proof of the order and harmony of creation in which creatures “share the being of another,” as Coetzee's character puts it.</p>
         <p>Likening the eagle's speech to a bird's song, Dante gives another example in the following canto in which nonhuman creatures and blessed humans are analogous. Here he suggests that we can know “blessedness” through a bird's song. Thus, with the present tense emphasizing eternal action (“si spazia” [soars], “tace” [silences], “sazia” [satiates]) the lark sings and then falls silent because, like the blessed, it satisfies its desires within itself:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line>Quale allodetta che ‘n aere si spazia</verse-line>
            <verse-line> prima cantando, e poi tace contenta</verse-line>
            <verse-line> de l'ultima dolcezza che la sazia,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>tal mi sembiò l'imago de la ‘mprenta</verse-line>
            <verse-line> de l'etterno piacere.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(<italic>Paradiso</italic>20.73–77)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[Like the lark that soars in the air, first singing, then silent, content with the last sweetness that satiates it, so seemed to me the image of the imprint of the Eternal Pleasure.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Here, in an exemplary type of analogy, the mother lark's soaring, singing, contentment, and lapsing into silence express the fulfillment of being of the “enheavened” souls. They have become in their transcendent blessedness the same as the lark in the immanent natural world, whose actions are eternal, unlike those of Dante the poet, whose tense for himself is actually the remote or completed past: “tal mi sembiò” (so it seemed to me). Furthermore, the lark, sated with its own song, is also indifferent to humans, as in Agamben's argument about the animal status. Here again, Dante uses a description of immanent nature as analogous to transcendent blessedness, a sublime example of nature's detachment from the will and desire of humans. With the simile celebrating this animal blessedness, Dante suggests that nonhuman creatures resisted or avoided the fall from grace, and that the actions and being of nonhumans offer us a view into the prelapsarian condition of unconscious blessedness.</p>
         <p>Yet another example of this pattern occurs in the following canto, where in a six-line simile, Dante makes the early morning rising of jackdaws akin to the action of angels going up and down the ladder of ascent:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line>E come, per lo natural costume,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> le pole insieme, al cominciar del giorno,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> si movono a scaldar le fredde piume;</verse-line>
            <verse-line>poi altre vanno via sanza ritorno,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> altre rivolgon sé onde son mosse,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> e altre roteando fan soggiorno;</verse-line>
            <verse-line>tal modo parve me che quivi fosse</verse-line>
            <verse-line> in quello sfavillar che 'nsieme venne,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> sì come in certo grado si percosse.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(<italic>Paradiso</italic>21.34–42)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[And, as by their natural custom, the daws move about together, at the beginning of the day, to warm their cold feathers, then some fly away not to return, some wheel round to whence they started, while others wheeling make a stay: such movements, it seemed to me, were in that sparkling, which came in a throng, as soon as it smote upon a certain step.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Again, and this is critical to the argument here, the tense to describe the actions of the birds is the present—“si movono” (move together), “vanno via” (fly away), “rivolgon” (wheel around), “fan” (make)—the tense that conveys eternal action, meaning that the creatures are outside historical time, outside teleological time, and outside human time. In contrast, Dante's observations are in the completed past, just as his memory of the vision of the angels is. The memory stays vivid only through the analogy to the continuous action of the daws in the immanent world of nature.</p>
         <p>In a parallel example, a nine-line simile that is also an aubade, Dante has Beatrice gaze toward the zenith like a mother bird waiting for the sun to rise so she can feed her chicks:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line>C<sc>OME</sc>
               <sc>L'AUGELLO</sc>, intra l'amate fronde,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> posato al nido de’ suoi dolci nati</verse-line>
            <verse-line> la notte che le cose ci nasconde,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>che, per veder li aspetti disïati</verse-line>
            <verse-line> e per trovar lo cibo onde li pasca,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> in che gravi labor li sono aggrati,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>previene il tempo in su aperta frasca,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> e con ardente affetto il sole aspetta,</verse-line>
            <verse-line> fiso guardando pur che l'alba nasca;</verse-line>
            <verse-line>così la donna mïa stava eretta.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(<italic>Paradiso</italic>23.1–10)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[As the bird, among the beloved leaves, having sat on the nest of her sweet brood through the night which hides things from us, who, in order to look upon their longed-for aspect and to find the food wherewith to feed them, wherein her heavy toils are pleasing to her, foreruns the time, upon the open bough, and with glowing love awaits the sun, fixedly gazing for the dawn to break; so was my lady standing, erect.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Once again the tense is the present for the actions of the bird, emphasizing its eternal action, while the imperfect is the narrative time for Dante's memory of Beatrice's actions. With the echo of Richard of St. Victor's discussion of birds and contemplation,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN64">64</xref>here Beatrice becomes the nonhuman creature, a bird, pregnant with love, waiting so she can feed her brood. In eternal animal anticipation and delight, she expects the dawn, an allegorical reference to resurrection and new life, as the bliss of animal being renders this mystical anticipation.</p>
         <p>Reworking Virgil's<italic>Georgics</italic>4, Dante here offers a concrete example of how his Christian use of analogy radically differs from the classical mode when he compares angels to the bees, who give what Virgil had called the “caelestia dona” (gift of heavens).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN65">65</xref>
            <italic>Georgics</italic>4 begins by describing how the bees operate and also how humans can husband them, likening the bees to warriors who come to the defense of their king (4.76–77), and who in their battles achieve great glory (4.4–7). While the analogy is decorative, it too reveals the prevailing military values of the Romans in the first century, even if Virgil's effusive lyricism about pastoral life offers a countervailing ideology (4.8–67 and 4.116–24, for example). In contrast, Dante's analogy moves beyond human social or philosophical systems and into the realm of attenuated significance or meaning to emphasize the transformed heavenly condition:</p>
         <verse-group>
            <verse-line>ma l'altra, che volando vede e canta</verse-line>
            <verse-line> la gloria di colui che la 'nnamora</verse-line>
            <verse-line> e la bontà che la fece cotanta,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>sì come schiera d'ape che s'infiora</verse-line>
            <verse-line> una fïata e una si ritorna</verse-line>
            <verse-line> là dove suo laboro s'insapora,</verse-line>
            <verse-line>nel gran fior discendeva che s'addorna</verse-line>
            <verse-line> di tante foglie, e quindi risaliva</verse-line>
            <verse-line> là dove 'l süo amor sempre soggiorna.</verse-line>
            <attrib>(<italic>Paradiso</italic>31.4–12)</attrib>
         </verse-group>
         <boxed-text position="float">
            <p>[But the other host—who, as it flies, sees and sings His glory who enamors it and the goodness which made it so great—like a swarm of bees which one moment enflower themselves, and the next return to where their work acquires savor—was descending into the great flower which is adorned with so many petals, and thence re-ascending to where its love abides forever.]</p>
         </boxed-text>
         <p>Here, once again we find a collection of verbs in the present, some both reflexives and neologisms, which simultaneously render eternal action and linguistic impossibility (because of the neologisms) while eliding the difference between the actor and action: “s'infiora” (enflower themselves), a neologism; “si ritorna” (return themselves); “s'insapora” (ensavors itself), a second neologism; “s'addorna” (adorns itself); “risaliva” (re-ascends), and “soggiorna” (abides). With the reflexives and the present tense, Dante emphasizes the perpetual movement of angels as they sing God's praises; with the linguistic play of the neologisms he conveys the impossibility of actually describing them; and by likening them to their analogy in the created world, bees, he also heightens our awareness that in the actions of bees we can see something of the divine realm in our world of nature. This focus on the detail of creaturely action, through the verbs and this observable natural environment, once more overcomes the separation between the transcendent and the immanent, sign and signified, vehicle and referent, with the analogy hinting that alterity can become sameness or, as Badiou puts it, poetry's melding with philosophy allows it to bond object and subject and to overcome the rupture between what would otherwise be two modes of discourse.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN66">66</xref>
         </p>
         <p>There is a history for this reverence for the honeybee in Christianity: going back at least to Ambrose in the fourth century, the honeybee appeared in the Christian baptism liturgy. Virgil's likening of the bee to an immortal soul (<italic>Georgics</italic>4:220–27) was recited almost verbatim when the Paschal candle, made of beeswax and used at baptism, was lit.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN67">67</xref>Traditionally, bee imagery shows up to characterize monarchy, the church (“apis est ecclesia” [the bee is the church]), community, and labor.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN68">68</xref>For Dante's period, probably the most important source for bee lore was Thomas of Cantimpré's<italic>Bonum universale de apibus</italic>(The universal good of bees) (1200–1270), a text that explores, in the Dominican learned tradition, both the natural and moral characteristics of the creatures. Thomas, who closely observes the social and natural life of bees, still maintains that bee life parallels the ideal religious community, for following Ambrose's commentary on the<italic>Hexaemeron</italic>(<italic>PL</italic>14) and his<italic>De Virginibus</italic>(<italic>PL</italic>16:210D–1A), it associates bees with community work, with a hierarchical structure, and with virginity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN69">69</xref>Yet, although the philosophical and theological underpinnings of Virgil's analogy and Thomas's discussion differ, the analogy remains very similar in that it posits a one-to-one arbitrary equation.</p>
         <p>However, the Aristotelian topos of the “sagacity of bees,” found in Bartholomeus Anglicus, Albertus Magnus, Vincent of Beauvais, and Thomas Aquinas, was adopted to signify the wonder of nature.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN70">70</xref>Thus, whether in their natural environment, as parallel to an idealized monastic setting, or linked with the “celestial realm,” bees, as the least animal-like creatures who were deemed closest to the heavenly sphere, offered Dante an image for an idealized golden age, an eschatological future already realized in the natural world. Dante's transfigured golden age, however, is not in the past but in the immanent present of the actions of bees, which as nonhuman creatures most like angels, and as poetic vehicles, make transcendence visible in the immanent world of nature. But there is more here, because Dante's use of the nonhuman animal simile places the immanent creature outside itself, and knowledge of self, and makes this a condition of blessedness to which humans might aspire. This has both an aesthetic and heuristic function because it poses a question about the philosophical boundaries that place man above all other creatures. The fact that the poet chooses insects, bees, birds, or fish and avoids mammals (except of course the lamb) as his vehicles to convey this insight suggests these creatures are more analogous to this “blessed” condition than wolves or other predatory creatures. Mammals, in Dante's bestiary, tend to fall easily into the static allegory/personification realm, in step with the “common association” notion of the metaphor, whereas Dante's similes with insects, bees, birds, or fish show how a close observation of nature can become the poetic means for making the immanent transcendent and the transcendent present in the immanent.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <fn>
            <p>I wish to express enormous gratitude to my colleague, Professor Juliana Schiesari, whose own work inspired me to think about the status of animals. Also, thanks to the three anonymous readers for<italic>Modern Philology</italic>, who really read and reread this piece with a microscopic lens. Finally, very special thanks are owed to Joshua Waggoner, PhD candidate in comparative literature, University of California, Davis, for his conscientious and careful scrutiny of all the textual and secondary references at the final stages.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN1">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>J. M. Coetzee,<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>(New York: Viking, 2003), hereafter cited parenthetically. The phrase “the lives of animals” comes from the title of Coetzee's Princeton Tanner Lectures, collectively published as<italic>The Lives of Animals</italic>, ed. Amy Gutman (Princeton University Press, 1999).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN2">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>For an extended discussion of the novel and the animal question, see Brenda Deen Schildgen, “No Bounds to the Sympathetic Imagination in J. M. Coetzee's<italic>Elizabeth Costello</italic>,”<italic>Critical Comparative Studies</italic>2 (2005): 323–36.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN3">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>See Peter Singer, preface to<italic>Animal Philosophy: Essential Readings in Continental Thought</italic>, ed. Matthew Calarco and Peter Atterton (London: Continuum, 2004), xii; Charles Magel,<italic>Keyguide to Information Sources in Animal Rights</italic>(Jefferson, NC: McFarland, 1989).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN4">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>Richard Sorabji,<italic>Animal Minds and Human Morals: The Origins of the Western Debate</italic>(London: Duckworth, 1993).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN5">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>Jacques Derrida,<italic>L'animal que donc je suis</italic>, ed. Marie-Louise Mallet (Paris: Galilée, 2006); David Wood, “Thinking with Cats,” in Calarco and Atterton,<italic>Animal Philosophy</italic>, 129.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN6">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>Cary Wolfe, ed.,<italic>Zoontologies: The Question of the Animal</italic>(Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2003); Giorgio Agamben,<italic>The Open: Man and Animal</italic>, trans. Kevin Attell (Stanford University Press, 2004).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN7">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>Martin Heidegger,<italic>Was ist das—die Philosophie?</italic>(Tübingen: Günther Neske Pfullingen, 1956), 45, my translation. Unless otherwise noted, all translations are my own.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN8">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>Alain Badiou, “The Age of Poets,” in<italic>Manifesto for Philosophy</italic>, trans. and ed. Norman Madarasz (Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 1999), 69.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN9">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>Ibid.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN10">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>Jacques Le Goff,<italic>Medieval Civilization, 400–1500</italic>, trans. Julia Barrow (New York: Blackwell, 1989), 561. Le Goff's work originally appeared as<italic>La civilization de l'Occident medieval</italic>(Paris: Arthaud, 1964).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN11">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>Nathalie Blancardi et al., eds.,<italic>Micrologus: Il mondo animale</italic>, 2 vols. (Florence: Edizioni del Galluzzo, 2000); Jacques Voisenet,<italic>Bêtes et hommes dans le monde médiéval: Le bestiaire des clercs du Ve au XIIe siècle</italic>(Turnhout: Brepols, 2000); Jacques Berlioz and Marie Anne Polo de Beaulieu, eds.,<italic>L'animal exemplaire au Moyen Âge: Ve–XVe siècles</italic>(Presses Universitaires de Rennes, 1999); Francesco Zambon,<italic>L'alfabeto simbolico degli animali: i bestiari del medioevo</italic>(Milan: Luni, 2001); David Salter,<italic>Holy and Noble Beasts: Encounters with Animals in Medieval Literature</italic>(Woodbridge: Brewer, 2001); Carlos G. Steel, Guy Guldentops, and Pieter Beullens, eds.,<italic>Aristotle's Animals in the Middle Ages and Renaissance</italic>(Leuven University Press, 1999).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN12">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>See Jacques Voisenet,<italic>Bestiaire Chrétien: L'imagerie animale des auteurs du Haut Moyen Âge</italic>(Toulouse: Presses Universitaires du Mirail, 1994); Joyce E. Salisbury,<italic>The Beast Within: Animals in the Middle Ages</italic>(New York: Routledge, 1994); L. A. J. R. Houwen, ed.,<italic>Animals and the Symbolic in Mediaeval Art and Literature</italic>(Groningen: Forsten, 1997);<italic>Le monde animal et ses representations au Moyen-Âge (XIe–Xve siècles): Actes du XVème congrès de la société des historiens médiévistes de l'enseignement supérieur public</italic>(Université de Toulouse–Le Mirail, 1985); and Janetta Rebold Benton,<italic>The Medieval Menagerie: Animals in the Art of the Middle Ages</italic>(New York: Abbeville, 1992).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN13">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>For a discussion of this work, see Aafke M. I. van Oppenraay, “Michael Scot's Arabic-Latin translation of Aristotle's Book on Animals,” in Steel, Guldentops, and Beullens,<italic>Aristotle's Animals</italic>, 31–43.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN14">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>See Bonaventure,<italic>Itinerarium mentis in Deum</italic>, in<italic>Opera omnia</italic>, ed. Aloysii Lauer, 10 vols. (Florence: Collegii S. Bonaventurae, 1882–1902), 5:299; Eloi Leclerc,<italic>The Canticle of Creatures: Symbols of Union; An Analysis of St. Francis of Assisi</italic>, trans. Matthew J. O'Connell (Chicago: Franciscan Herald, 1977).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN15">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>Agamben,<italic>Open</italic>, 73.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN16">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>All quotations from<italic>Inferno</italic>,<italic>Purgatorio</italic>, and<italic>Paradiso</italic>are from Dante Alighieri,<italic>The Divine Comedy</italic>, trans. with commentary by Charles S. Singleton, Bollingen Series 80 (Princeton University Press, 1970–75), hereafter cited parenthetically by canticle, canto, and line number(s).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN17">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>St. Francis of Assisi,<italic>Il cantico di frate sole</italic>, ed. Vittore Branca (Florence: Olschki, 1965), 83. English translation from<italic>Francis and Clare: The Complete Works</italic>, trans. Regis J. Armstrong and Ignatius C. Brady (New York: Paulist, 1982), 38.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN18">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>For a full development of this idea in St. Francis's poem, see Leclerc,<italic>Canticle of Creatures</italic>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN19">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>Oscar L. Kuhns,<italic>The Treatment of Nature in Dante's “Divina commedia”</italic>(London: Arnold, 1897).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN20">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>Aldo S. Bernardo, “The Three Beasts and Perspective in the<italic>Divine Comedy</italic>,”<italic>PMLA</italic>78 (1963): 15–24.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN21">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>Teresa Gualtieri, “Dante's Cranes and the Pilgrimage of Poetic Inspiration,”<italic>Rivista di Studi Italiani</italic>13 (1995): 1–13; David B. Comer, “‘Quali colombe’—Doves, Venus, and the Holy Ghost: A Brief Speculative Note on<italic>Inferno</italic>V.82–87,”<italic>South Atlantic Quarterly</italic>71 (1972): 496–503; Daniela Boccassini,<italic>Il volo della mente: Falconeria e sofia nel mondo mediterraneo; Islam, Federico II, Dante</italic>(Ravenna: Longo, 2003).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN22">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>Giorgio Celli and Antonella Venturelli, “Gli animali nella<italic>Divina commedia</italic>(tra fantasia e realtà),” in<italic>Dante e la scienza</italic>, ed. Patrick Boyde and Vittorio Russo (Biblioteca Classense di Ravenna, 1995), 109–17.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN23">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>Albert L. Rossi, “The Poetics of Resurrection: Virgil's Bees (<italic>Paradiso</italic>XXXI, 1–12),”<italic>Romanic Review</italic>80 (1989): 305–24.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN24">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>Celli and Venturelli, “Gli animali,” 113.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN25">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>Ibid, 110–12.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN26">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>La métaphore vive</italic>(Paris: Éditions du Seuil, 1975), 126.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN27">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>Enzo Melandri,<italic>La linea e il circolo: Studio logico filosofico sull’ analogia</italic>(1968; repr., Macerata: Quodlibet, 2004), 29–34, 703–8; on allegory, 76–78.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN28">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>Ricoeur,<italic>Métaphore vive</italic>, 252.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN29">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>I. A. Richards,<italic>The Philosophy of Rhetoric</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1936), 93. See also Melandri,<italic>Linea e il circolo</italic>, 531–33; Max Black,<italic>Models and Metaphors: Studies in Language and Philosophy</italic>(Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1962), 38.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN30">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>Arthur Koestler,<italic>The Act of Creation</italic>(New York: Macmillan, 1964), 67.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN31">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>Ricoeur,<italic>Métaphore vive</italic>, 109.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN32">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>See Melandri,<italic>Linea e il circolo</italic>, 549–80.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN33">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>Erich Auerbach, “Figura,” in<italic>Scenes from the Drama of European Literature</italic>(Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1984), 70–71.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN34">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>See Fredric Jameson, “<italic>La cousine Bette</italic>and Allegorical Realism,”<italic>PMLA</italic>86 (1971): 252–53.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN35">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>Gary Matthews, “Augustine and Descartes on the Souls of Animals,” in<italic>From Soul to Self</italic>, ed. M. James C. Crabbe (London: Routledge, 1999), 89–107.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN36">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>Aristotle,<italic>Nicomachean Ethics</italic>, trans. Martin Ostwald (Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill, 1962), 7.1145a, 7.1150a.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN37">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>Guy Guldentops, “Albert the Great's Zoological Anthropocentrism,” in Blancardi et al.,<italic>Micrologus</italic>, 1:218–19.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN38">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>Aristotle,<italic>On the Parts of Animals I</italic>–<italic>IV</italic>, trans. James G. Lennox (Oxford: Clarendon, 2001), 1.5.645a; Albertus Magnus,<italic>De animalibus</italic>(Washington, DC: Catholic University of America Press, 2008).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN39">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <italic>Physiologus</italic>, trans. Michael Curley (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1979).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN40">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>Ricoeur,<italic>Métaphore vive</italic>, 114; Black,<italic>Models and Metaphors</italic>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN41">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>Nick Havely,<italic>Dante and the Franciscans: Poverty and the Papacy in the “Commedia”</italic>(Cambridge University Press, 2004).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN42">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>Antonio M. di Monda, “Natura e sopranatura in S. Bonaventura,” in<italic>San Bonaventura maestro di vita Francescana e di sapienza Cristiana</italic>, ed. A. Pompeii, in<italic>Atti del congresso internazionale per il VII centenario di San Bonaventura da Bagnoregio</italic>, 2 vols. (Rome: Pontificia Facolta’ Teologica “San Bonaventura,” 1976), 2:57.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN43">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>Bonaventure, “Life of Saint Francis,” in<italic>Bonaventure</italic>, trans. Ewert Cousins (New York: Paulist, 1979), 294, and “Legenda Sancti Francisci,” in Lauer,<italic>Opera omnia</italic>, 8:504–64.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN44">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>“Quod omnes creaturae istius sensibilis mundi animum contemplantis et sapientis ducunt in Deum aeternum, pro eo quod illius primi principii potentissimi, sapientissimi et optimi, illius aeternae originis, lucis et plenitudinis, illius, inquam, artis effientis, exemplantis et ordinantis sunt<italic>umbrae</italic>,<italic>resonantiae</italic>et<italic>picturae</italic>, sunt<italic>vestigia</italic>,<italic>simulacra</italic>et<italic>spectacula</italic>nobis ad contuendum Deum proposita et<italic>signa</italic>divinitus data” (Bonaventure,<italic>Itinerarium mentis in Deum</italic>, 302); translation from Bonaventure, “The Soul's Journey into God,” in Cousins,<italic>Bonaventure</italic>, 76.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN45">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>“Consideratione quoque primae originis omnium abundantiori pietate repletus, creaturas quatumlibet parvas<italic>fratris</italic>vel<italic>sororis</italic>appellabat nominibus, pro eo quod sciebat, eas unum secum habere principium” (Bonaventure, “Legenda Sancti Francisci,” 527); translation from Bonaventure, “Life of Saint Francis,” 254–55.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN46">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>Agamben,<italic>Open</italic>, 58.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN47">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>Leclerc,<italic>Canticle of Creatures</italic>, 12.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN48">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>Emmanuel Levinas, “Philosophy and Transcendence,” in<italic>Alterity and Transcendence</italic>, trans. Michael B. Smith (New York: Columbia University Press, 1999), 3–37.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN49">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>For a discussion of neologisms and reflexives in<italic>Paradiso</italic>, see Brenda Deen Schildgen, “Dante's Neologisms in the<italic>Paradiso</italic>and the Latin Rhetorical Tradition,”<italic>Dante Studies</italic>107 (1989): 101–19.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN50">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>For expansion on Dante, Levinas, and “otherness,” see William Franke, “The Ethical Vision of Dante's<italic>Paradiso</italic>in Light of Levinas,”<italic>Comparative Literature</italic>59 (2007): 209–27.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN51">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>Pierre Hayat, preface to Levinas,<italic>Alterity and Transcendence</italic>, xiv.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN52">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>
               <italic>The Art of Falconry: Being the “De arte venandi cum avibus” of Frederick II of Hohenstaufen</italic>, trans. and ed. Casey A. Wood and F. Marjorie Fyfe (Stanford University Press, 1961).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN53">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>See Franke, “Ethical Vision,” 210–11.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN54">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>See<italic>Aristotle on Rhetoric: A Theory of Civic Discourse</italic>, trans. George A. Kennedy (New York: Oxford University Press, 1991), 1405a; Aristotle,<italic>Poétique</italic>, ed. and trans. J. Hardy (Paris: Société d'édition les belles lettres, 1965), 1457b; Cicero,<italic>De oratore</italic>, trans. Harris Rackham (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1968), 3.37; Quintilian,<italic>Institutio oratoria</italic>, ed. and trans. H. E. Butler (1920; repr., Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1989), 5.14.34–35.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN55">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>Doreen Innes, “Metaphor, Simile, and Allegory as Ornaments of Style,” in<italic>Metaphor, Allegory, and the Classical Tradition</italic>, ed. G. R. Boys-Stones (Oxford University Press, 2003), 7–27; see also Richards,<italic>Philosophy of Rhetoric</italic>; Murray Krieger,<italic>A Reopening of Closure: Organicism against Itself</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1989).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN56">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>See Lucan,<italic>The Civil War (Pharsalia)</italic>, bks. 1–10, trans. J. D. Duff (London: Heinemann, 1928), 9.763–76, 790–97; and Ovid,<italic>Metamorphoses</italic>, ed. R. J. Tarrant (Oxford University Press, 2004), 4.373–79, 576–80, 586–89.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN57">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>“Denique nitentem contra elabique uolentem / implicat, ut serpens, quam regia sustinet ales / sublimemque rapit (pendens caput illa pedesque / alligat et cauda spatiantes implicat alas), / utue solent hederae longos intexere truncos, / utque sub aequoribus deprensum polypus hostem / continet ex omni dimissis parte flagellis” (Ovid,<italic>Metamorphoses</italic>4.361–67). English translation from Ovid,<italic>Metamorphoses</italic>, trans. Rolfe Humphries (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1955), 4.361–65.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN58">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>See Virgil,<italic>Aeneidos</italic>, bk. 4, ed. R. D. Williams (Oxford: Clarendon, 1960), lines 398–407).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN59">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>Agamben,<italic>Open</italic>, 59–60.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN60">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>For an extensive discussion of the simile and its implications for reading<italic>Inferno</italic>26 and the Ulysses episode, see Margherita Frankel, “The Context of Dante's Ulysses: The Similes in<italic>Inferno</italic>XXVI, 25–42,”<italic>Dante Studies</italic>104 (1986): 99–119; see also Richard H. Lansing,<italic>From Image to Idea: A Study of the Simile in Dante's “Commedia”</italic>(Ravenna: Longo, 1977), 111–23.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN61">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>Baudouin Van den Abeele, “L'allégorie animale dans les encyclopédies Latines du Moyen Âge,” in Berlioz and de Beaulieu,<italic>Animal exemplaire au Moyen Âge</italic>, 123–43.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN62">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>Agamben,<italic>Open</italic>, 59.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN63">
            <label>63</label>
            <p>John Freccero, “Introduction to<italic>Paradiso</italic>,” in<italic>Dante: Poetics of Conversion</italic>, ed. Rachel Jacoff (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1986), 209–20.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN64">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>Richard of St. Victor, “Caput XLIV: De quanto virtutum culmine contingat in ima vitiorum corruere,” from<italic>De eruditione interioris hominis</italic>, in<italic>Patrologia cursus completus, series Latina</italic>, 221 vols. (Paris, 1841–64), 196:44.1340–41. References to this series are given in the text hereafter as<italic>PL</italic>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN65">
            <label>65</label>
            <p>Virgil,<italic>Georgics</italic>, ed. R. A. B. Mynors (Oxford: Clarendon, 1990), 4.1, hereafter cited parenthetically. On the reworking of Virgil, see Rossi, “The Poetics of Resurrection.”</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN66">
            <label>66</label>
            <p>Badiou, “Age of Poets,” 72.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN67">
            <label>67</label>
            <p>Marie-Thérèse Zenner, “From Divine Wisdom to Secret Knowledge: The Cosmology of the Honeybee in the Church Calendar,” in Blancardi et al.,<italic>Micrologus</italic>, 1:114–15; Nadia Pollini, “Les propriétés des abeilles dans le<italic>Bonum universale de apibus</italic>de Thomas de Cantimpré (1200–1270),” ibid., 1:261–96.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN68">
            <label>68</label>
            <p>Zenner, “From Divine Wisdom,” 104.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN69">
            <label>69</label>
            <p>Thomas of Cantimpré,<italic>Bonum universale de apibus</italic>, trans. Henri Platelle (Paris: Brepols, 1997).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn fn-type="other" id="FN70">
            <label>70</label>
            <p>Guy Guldentops, “The Sagacity of Bees: An Aristotelian Topos in Thirteenth-Century Philosophy,” in Steel, Guldentops, and Beullens,<italic>Aristotle's Animals</italic>, 296.</p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
