<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">man</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j100268</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Man</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>journal-series-title</meta-name>
               <meta-value>New Series</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00251496</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2801348</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Fieldwork, Reciprocity, and the Making of Ethnographic Texts: The Example of Maurice Leenhardt</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>James</given-names>
                  <surname>Clifford</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>9</month>
            <year>1980</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>15</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>i330145</issue-id>
         <fpage>518</fpage>
         <lpage>532</lpage>
         <page-range>518-532</page-range>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 1980 Royal Anthropological Institute</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2801348"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Maurice Leenhardt's ethnographic work in New Caledonia spanned nearly half a century, from 1902-1948. The first part of this field research is described and analysed, as background to his later anthropological writings. Leenhardt's specific position as a missionary-ethnographer is discussed, its advantages and disadvantages weighed. A liberal missionary perspective is found, in this case, to be conducive to a portrayal of cultural process. Leenhardt's translation methodology and his relations with key informants are detailed. Transcription, the means by which ethnographic texts are constituted by more than a single subject, is speculatively extended to ethnographic practice generally. Field research may be seen as a collective, reciprocal endeavour through which textualised translations are made. This viewpoint calls into question common notions of description, interpretation and authorship in the writing of ethnography.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
