<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Journal of Speculative Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0891625X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15279383</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil.26.2.0102</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0102</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A Philosophical History of the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy?</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>David Carr</string-name>
               <aff>Emory University and New School for Social Research</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">26</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jspecphil.26.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>102</fpage>
         <lpage>107</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0102"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>“You're a philosopher of history—say something philosophical about the history of SPEP.” So said Tony Steinbock (or words to that effect) when I asked him what he had in mind for this panel. OK, here goes.</p>
      <p>The philosophy of history was classically conceived as a form of theodicy—justifying God's ways to man, as Milton put it. Saint Augustine is considered by some to be the father of the philosophy of history, though the term itself was apparently invented by Voltaire. And Augustine didn't use the faux-Greek word<italic>theodicy</italic>either, which wasn't invented until the time of Leibniz. But he thought of it this way. The Roman Empire had recently converted to Christianity and should have been flourishing and increasing in glory. Instead it was rapidly declining and falling before his very eyes. This didn't make sense. What was wrong?</p>
      <p>Not to worry, said Augustine. Things may be pretty grim in the city of man, but in the city of God, all would be put right, or rather, already had been, from all eternity.</p>
      <p>Fifteen hundred years later, Hegel called his philosophy of history a theodicy. History is a slaughter bench, he said, in which the good seemed to suffer, the evil to triumph. Could we find reason or even meaning in this sorry panorama? But reason is cunning, he claimed, and is working to produce good out of evil, freedom out of oppression. The city of God is not beyond the world but is emerging in history itself. In fact, it is really at hand, and philosophy can show us this.</p>
      <p>What does all this have to do with the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP)? Well, the scene in philosophy looked like a slaughter bench to some of us in the 1950s and 1960s. There is nothing so intolerant as a movement that is just taking off, and so it was with analytic philosophy in those years. Imported from prewar Vienna and Cambridge, it took root in the United States with the fervor of the newly converted. Yet another revolution in philosophy, said Richard Rorty, world-weary as always, even in his early years, in the introduction to his 1967 collection<italic>The Linguistic Turn</italic>. He predicted it would suffer the fate of earlier revolutions (he listed Husserl's among them), and he was right. But that message was drowned out by the busy applications of the new approach. Analyzing language using the tools of logic, trying to achieve precision by aping the sciences it admired and envied, it subjected to disdain and derision those who didn't go along. It was not only those inspired by recent German and French philosophy who suffered this treatment: the whole history of philosophy was declared irrelevant, unless it could be mined for well-formed arguments that could be translated into logical symbols. The devotees of this philosophical persuasion soon consolidated their control of major departments and hardened into a powerful establishment.</p>
      <p>There were pockets of resistance, however, including two departments represented on this panel, Northwestern and Yale, and these provided much of the impetus for founding a new society named after phenomenology and existentialism. It was an act of rebellion, and if analytic philosophers thought of themselves as revolutionaries, the founders of SPEP were anything but counterrevolutionaries or reactionaries. They had their own revolution to foment.</p>
      <p>Bob Scharff and Ed Casey can talk about Northwestern, where they were students. I can say a bit about Yale, since I was a graduate student there. Many of my teachers were resisting the analytic onslaught. There were scholars of Hume and Kant (Charles Hendel and George Schrader); metaphysicians in the grand Whiteheadian mode (Paul Weiss and Nathaniel Lawrence); Brand Blanchard, a late advocate of a sort of Bradleyian idealism; and students of American Pragmatism like John Smith and Richard Bernstein. All soldiered on, in an atmosphere in which what they were doing was considered nonsense. But Carl Hempel and Arthur Pap and Charles Stevenson had also been at Yale, followed by Wilfred Sellars and Norwood Russell Hanson. It proved to be a combustible mixture, and when I returned from a Fulbright year in Paris, in 1963, a major blowup had occurred. Sellars and two gifted logicians, Alan Anderson and Nuell Belknap, had decamped to the unlikely destination of Pittsburgh, where they and others founded a major center of analytic philosophy and philosophy of science. And John Wild had come to Yale from Northwestern. Russ Hanson took himself out, tragically, by flying his World War II biplane into a mountain—he was a stunt pilot in his spare time. George Schrader, who became my<italic>Doktorvater</italic>, had discovered Heidegger in Germany. Others were tolerant, if not partisans, like John Smith and Richard Bernstein. That left Yale as one of the centers of Continental philosophy, at least for a while. It remained combustible, however. Talk about a slaughter bench! The Bernstein tenure case of 1964, ostensibly about publish or perish, brought out student demonstrators and made the national press. Over the next ten years many innocent lambs were led to that particular slaughter bench, up to and including members of this very panel. The Yale administration, suffering from an inferiority complex and unwilling to be different, couldn't stand to be told it was out of line with Harvard and Princeton, so the analytic establishment asserted itself. SPEP never again met at Yale, after those early years. Eventually the department crashed and burned, like Hanson's biplane, going into receivership in the 1980s. Some of us could not resist a<italic>frisson</italic>of<italic>Schadenfreude</italic>.</p>
      <p>But I'm getting ahead of myself. A clueless graduate student, I wandered onto this pockmarked battlefield in 1964, when I learned that the third SPEP meeting would be held at Yale. (An aside here: if the first meeting was in 1962, shouldn't we be celebrating in 2012? Maybe the first meeting was really in 1961. In any case, I wouldn't know, because I wasn't there.) Some of my fellow graduate students and I were puzzled and wondered what to expect. We thought of phenomenology, and especially existentialism, as rather antiestablishment currents, and the idea of an academic conference devoted to them seemed incongruous. I remember Chip Dallery wondering if there would be an “existentialist smoker.” Some of you may find this hard to believe, but “smoker” was the name given to the evening receptions at conferences like the American Philosophical Association (APA) in those days. The word perfectly encapsulated the hugely male-dominated, tweed-jacketed, pipe-smoking atmosphere of the era. We wondered: Would there be black sweaters and black berets instead of tweeds and Gauloises instead of pipes? Maybe we even enjoyed thinking of ourselves as outsiders and thought the idea of founding a society was too much like imitating the ways of the APA and other establishment groups. We didn't understand the politics of academia or feel the need for establishing ties with like-minded philosophers elsewhere. But that just shows how naive we were.</p>
      <p>In the event, SPEP did seem to be made up of oddballs and outsiders in those early years. In 1964 it was a bit larger than the twenty or thirty souls that Ed Casey describes in his paper, but not by much. The leadership was a diverse bunch: Aron Gurwitsch, gruff and insistent on rigor and clarity, the embodiment of the old-school European professor. His presence made me aware, for the first time, I think, of the existence of the New School for Social Research, that amazing institution where I would later teach and am teaching now. John Wild, with the fervor of the recent convert himself, was eager to convert others. According to one tale, possibly apocryphal, an undergraduate student reported that he kept talking about a place called “Lebensville” and saying we ought to go back there. Herbert Spiegelberg, sweetest of men, had earned the respect and gratitude of all for publishing his two-volume<italic>The Phenomenological Movement</italic>, which had appeared in 1960. George Schrader, slowly abandoning Kant for Heidegger. Bill Earle, a very smooth talker—that's all I remember. Erwin Straus, who in his old age exemplified, every time he stood up to speak, the epic struggle of our species to attain the upright posture. Dreyfus, Todes, Lingus, Schrag, and Edie were the Young Turks in that group. We graduate students, still looking on curiously from the sidelines at that point, slowly got a sense of the great learning and intellectual integrity of our elders and also eventually picked up the excitement of being an embattled minority struggling for survival and recognition.</p>
      <p>And so it began, at least for me. At the second Yale meeting, in 1968, Edie and Schrader pressed me into service as “secretary”—I believe that was the title then—and I started planning the next meeting. Such was my success that after assembling a tentative program and sending it around, Bert Dreyfus called in the middle of the night from the West Coast to tell me he wouldn't cross the street, much less the country, to attend such a boring meeting. Help arrived, for both me and SPEP, in the form of a postdoc in Europe, which allowed me to dump the planning of the 1969 meeting back in Jim Edie's lap. This may have had something to do with the fact that SPEP decided it needed two secretaries rather than one, and that's how I got teamed up with Ed Casey, starting the tandem arrangement that remains, with upgraded titles, of course, in place today.</p>
      <p>Over the course of an academic career that involved many ups and downs, and many dislocations, SPEP has remained a constant, a place of refuge almost, where I could be recognized and accepted. Many friendships were formed and continued there, and after a time the possibility of seeing friends became a major reason for attending. It's strange that SPEP can seem like a fixed place to which one returns again and again, even though it is a movable feast held each year in a different place. In a certain sense arriving at SPEP each year is “getting back into place,” to plagiarize a well-known phenomenologist, even though we may be in Philadelphia, Chicago, New York, or even (if we can find it) Penn State. Its heart and soul, of course, remains the exchange of ideas built around a common tradition: ideas, texts, philosophers. As important in the history of SPEP has been the appearance among us of some of the most important European philosophers of these last fifty years: We were too late to lure Heidegger, Sartre, and Merleau-Ponty to our shores, but we heard Gadamer, Arendt, Ricoeur, Habermas, Derrida, and many more.</p>
      <p>Over the years SPEP outgrew campus meetings and moved into convention hotels, just as it seemed to outgrow phenomenology and existentialism, leading to a big discussion, sometime in the eighties I believe, over whether to rename it the Society for Continental Philosophy. This, of course, was the second dispute about the naming of the society. Bob Scharff tells us about the first dispute in his paper, when the original title could have resulted in SEPP rather than SPEP. The second proposal could have changed us from SPEP to SCP. I was involved in those discussions, I believe, as a member of the Executive Committee, but I don't remember why the original name was retained. Maybe because SCP would have been too hard to pronounce. Certainly phenomenology and existentialism never disappeared from the scene, so maybe it was thought that we would have to adopt an acronym like SPEPPMCTHF. Our society got much bigger as well as more complex compared with its humble origins, in an incremental growth and transformation we didn't always notice if we attended every year.</p>
      <p>But just the other day I got a kind of Rip van Winkle testimony from my friend Dick Howard, of Stony Brook, who apparently hasn't attended SPEP since the twenty-fifth anniversary meeting in Toronto. He's here for a panel tomorrow, and he sent me an e-mail, from which I quote, in part, with permission: “Just have been looking at SPEP program—it's extraordinary how it's grown and the diversity of things going on there. A ‘victory’ that at the same time comes with a diversification that perhaps gives more breath than depth? History will judge.” So there you have it! The judgment of history! SPEP flourishes today, a major force in American philosophy, and its “victory” seems to justify and redeem in retrospect all those early struggles, the slaughter bench of the early days, the courage and prescience of that small band of outsiders and oddballs. It makes a good story, as history always should: the triumph of the little guys over enormous odds. In Hegelian terms, reason exercised its cunning and brought about results unforeseeable, almost unimaginable, in those far-off days of 1962—or was it 1961? In philosophical terms, history has rendered its judgment.</p>
      <p>Is SPEP the city of God? This would be going too far. Not even the theological turn in French Phenomenology would make this claim. Dick Howard already threw in a troubling question: “diversification that perhaps gives more breadth than depth?” he asked. And there are plenty more troubling questions. SPEP is now a big operation. It has committees and subcommittees, multiple simultaneous sessions, blind review. All these developments are signs, perhaps inevitable ones, of its success, but all have familiar downsides: bureaucratization, diversification for its own sake, what Habermas would call<italic>Unübersichtlichkeit</italic>. This is what happens when outsiders become insiders, the antis become their own sort of establishment. You can't blame some of us for feeling nostalgic for our long-lost innocence, even though we all know—you don't have to be a philosopher of history to know this—that we can't go there. History has rendered a judgment, but Dick Howard said, “History<italic>will</italic>judge.” That's one problem with history: It's always rendering judgments, but they are never final. You'd have to be at the end of history for that, and despite the claim of some philosophers, we aren't there yet. The slaughter bench of history looks very different today from the early 1960s, but it's still in some ways a slaughter bench. So how will the SPEP of the early twenty-first century look to the philosopher-historians of 2061—or is it 2062?</p>
   </body>
</article>
