<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">polishreview</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Polish Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00322970</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">polishreview.58.1.0015</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5406/polishreview.58.1.0015</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Olga Stanisławska's<italic>Charles de Gaulle Roundabout</italic>: Raw Facts and the Danger of Finalizing Narratives</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Kosmala</surname>
                  <given-names>Kinga</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>15</day>
            <month>06</month>
            <year>2013</year>
            <string-date>2013</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">58</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">polishreview.58.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>15</fpage>
         <lpage>28</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2013 by the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/polishreview.58.1.0015"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Olga Stanisławska's reportage book<italic>Rondo de Gaulle'a</italic>[Charles de Gaulle Roundabout] was published in 2001 by Wydawnictwo Twój Styl in Warsaw. The book describes one woman's yearlong journey across Africa, from Casablanca, to Morocco, through Mauritania, Mali, Niger, Nigeria, Chad, Cameroon, Guinea, Congo, Zaire, and Uganda to Nairobi, Kenya. Stanisławska writes about the political, economic, and social issues of numerous African countries. She describes the painful issue of modern-day slavery in Mauritania, the dramatic fate of the Tuareg nation, and recent conflicts in Chad. The book's narrative sometimes merges with objectified, newspaper-style news, but more often ventures into a solipsistic memoir and a warm and sensual portrayal of the various communities the author visits. Stanisławska's actual journey across Africa is complemented by her emotional and literary voyage from the paradise-like plains of the Saharan desert countries to the hellish depths of the jungle in the Congo. She frames her journey, or rather "travels," from Karen Blixen's<italic>Out of Africa</italic>(a self-created paradise) to Joseph Conrad's<italic>Heart of Darkness</italic>(a self-imposed hell). Both of Stanisławska's journeys–physical and literary–provide a captivating platform for studying her narrative as an unending and deeply empathic encounter with another human being. In<italic>Charles de Gaulle Roundabout</italic>there is a visible tension between the author's need to tell a story and her anxiety that in doing so she may (mis)treat people and turn them into fictional characters, that is, make their stories finite.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Adam Zachary Newton, Narrative Ethics (Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1995), 19.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Emmanuel Levinas, On Thinking of the Other: Entre nous, trans. Michael B. Smith and Barbara Hershav (New York: Columbia University Press, 1991), 14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 309.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Newton, Narrative Ethics, 45</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Jacques Lacan, "Seminar on 'The Purloined Letter,'" Yale French Studies 48 (1972): 38-72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Quoted after Geoffrey Galt Harpham, Getting It Right: Language, Literature, and Ethics (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992), 167.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>"Słoń a sprawa polska" [Elephant and the Polish cause], Maciej Wilamowski, Konrad Wnęka, and Lidia A. Zyblikiewicz, Leksykon polskich powiedzeń historycznych [The lexicon of Polish historical proverbs] (Kraków: Wydawnictwo Znak, 1998).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Olga Stanisławska, Rondo de Gaulle'a [Charles de Gaulle Roundabout] (Warsaw: Wydawnictwo Twój Styl, 2001), 10</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mary Louise Pratt, Imperial Eyes: Travel Writing and Transculturation (London: Routledge, 1992), 137.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Homi Bhabha, "Culture in Between," in Multicultural States: Rethinking Difference and Identity, ed. David Bennet (London: Routledge, 1998), 24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Roy Wagner, The Invention of Culture (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1981), 4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Masud Zavarzadeh, The Mythopoeic Reality: The Postwar American Nonfiction Novel (Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1976), 53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Friedrich Nietzsche, "On Truth and Falsity in Their Extramoral Sense," trans. M. Mugge, vol. 48 of Philosophical Writings, ed. E. Grimm and C. Molina y Media (New York: Continuum, 1995), 97.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Arthur Rimbaud, "The Sleeper in the Valley," Collected Poems (fragment quoted by Stanisławska), trans. Oliver Bernard (New York: Penguin Classics, 1962).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Harpham, Getting It Right.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Quoted after ibid., 163.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 164.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Ricoeur, Time and Narrative, trans. Kathleen McIaughlin and David Pellauer (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1984), 41.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Stanisławska, Rondo de Gaulle'a, 86.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See http://www.ancient-hebrew.org/27_holy.html.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Stanisławska, Rondo de Gaulle'a, 169.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Theroux, "Introduction" to Graham Greene's Journey Without Maps (New York: Penguin Classics, 2006).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>When Stanisławska wrote the book in 1997, she could not have known that the 2007 Kenyan elections and the rival political parties would bring a disastrous situation to that country.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gayatri Spivak, The Spivak Reader: Selected Works of Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak, ed. Donna Landry and Gerald MacLean (New York: Routledge, 1996), 24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 269-70.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Anne Cubilié, "Cosmopolitanism as Resistance: Fragmented Identities, Women's Testimonial and the War in Yugoslavia," in Critical Ethics: Text, Theory and Responsibility, ed. Dominic Rainsford and Tim Woods (New York: St. Martin's Press, 1999), 273.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Charles de Gaulle Roundabout, "Beznadziejna jest utopia map, absurdalna nieprzystawalność słów i rzeczy… . Pisać to przedawać rzeczywistość, żeby wkroczyć w krainę słowa. Pomiędzy słowem a rzeczą zieje przepaść. Ta przepaść, która tak przeraźliwym absurdem jawi się przy rondzie de Gaulle'a."</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
