<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">jeducthourevupen</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50010353</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>The Journal of Educational Thought (JET) / Revue de la Pensée Éducative</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Faculty of Education, University of Calgary</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00220701</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23767086</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Envisioning Technological Literacy in Science Education: Building Sustainable Human-Technology-Lifeworld Relationships</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>MIJUNG</given-names>
                  <surname>KIM</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>WOLFF-MICHAEL</given-names>
                  <surname>ROTH</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2008</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>42</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23762745</issue-id>
         <fpage>185</fpage>
         <lpage>206</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/23767086"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Present discourses on technology education are taking a positive and value-neutral approach with utilitarian and vocational overtones. The discourses generally lack discussions of human agency and human responsibility for techno-scientific activities and technological literacy. To support the emergence of a collective civic literacy, we argue in this text that technology education needs to take up critical and value-acknowledging aspects with emphasis on building sustainable relationships among human beings, technology, and lifeworld. To understand the relationship between human agency and modern technology, we examine the nature of technology in the dimensions of technology as causality and technology as a relationship of lifeworld. Discussing Martin Heidegger's perspectives on the causalities of technology, we question how the nature of technology situates human beings in power-related relationships to the world. Understanding technology as process and relationship of lifeworld, the paper extends its discussion of the responsibility of a dialectical human-technology-lifeworld relation based on a socio-technical and ethico-moral framework of technology. By recognizing human responsibility of and for modern technology, we outline a critical and reflective approach to technological literacy. The approach challenges the position of current approaches to technology in the attempt to provide a foundation for a contemporary pedagogy of technological awareness and values. Aujourd'hui, les discours en matière d'enseignement de la technologie sont en train de prendre une orientation positive et dépourvue de jugement de valeur comportant des connotations utilitaristes et professionnelles. En général, les discours n'ouvrent pas assez de discussions sur l'action humaine et la responsabilité humaine dans les activités technico-scientifiques et dans l'alphabétisme technologique. Dans ce papier, afin de renforcer l'éclosion de l'alphabétisme civique collectif, nous ouvrons le débat sur le fait que l'enseignement de la technologie a besoin d'aborder des aspects critiques et de valeur reconnue avec un accent mis sur la construction durable des relations chez les êtres humains, dans la technologie et dans la vie mondiale. Dans le but de comprendre les relations entre l'action humaine et la technologie moderne, nous analysons la nature de la technologie en tant que causalité et en tant que relation de la vie mondiale. Nous discutons des perspectives de Martin Heidegger sur les causalités de la technologie. Nous posons des questions sur la manière que la nature de la technologie situe les êtres humains dans les relations basées sur le pouvoir face au monde. Nous assimilons la technologie comme processus et comme relation de la vie mondiale. L'article élargit les propos sur la responsabilité dune relation dialectale humaine technologie/vie mondiale, fondée sur une structure de technologie sociotechnique et éthico morale. En reconnaissant la responsabilité humaine de et pour la technologie moderne, nous soulignons une démarche critique et réfléchie de l'alphabétisme technologique. La démarche remet en question la position des approches actuelles vers le chemin de la technologie afin d'apporter une base à une pédagogie contemporaine de sensibilisation et de valeurs technologiques.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="d7857e138a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e145" publication-type="other">
(Roth, 2006</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>REFERENCES</title>
         <ref id="d7857e161a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e165" publication-type="other">
Abram, D. (1996). The spell of the sensuous. New York, NY: Random House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e172a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e176" publication-type="other">
Bakhtin, M. M. (1993). Toward a philosophy of the act. Austin, TX:
University of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e186a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e190" publication-type="other">
Franklin, U. (1992). The world of technology. Concord, ON: Anansi.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e197a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e201" publication-type="other">
Fourez, G. (1997). Scientific and technological literacy as a social practice.
Social Studies of Science, 27, 903-936.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e212a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e216" publication-type="other">
Heidegger, M. (1954). The question concerning technology. In D.F. Krell
(Ed.), Martin Heidegger: Basic writings from being and time (1927) to
the task of thinking (1964) (pp. 283-318). New York, NY: Harper &amp; Row
Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e232a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e236" publication-type="other">
Ihde, D. (1990). Technology and the lifeworld: From garden to earth.
Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e246a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e250" publication-type="other">
Kroker, A. (2004). The will to technology and the culture of nihilism:
Heidegger, Nietzsche, and Marx. Toronto, ON: University of Toronto
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e263a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e267" publication-type="other">
Latour, B. (1993). We have never been modern. Cambridge, MA: Harvard
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e277a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e281" publication-type="other">
Latour, B. (1999). Pandora's hope: Essay on the reality of science studies.
Cambridge, MA: Harvard University press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e291a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e295" publication-type="other">
Mayor, F. (1999). Science and power today and tomorrow. In F. Mayor &amp; A.
Forti (Eds.), Science and power (pp. 137-169). Paris, France: UNESCO
Publishing.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e309a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e313" publication-type="other">
McGinn, R. (1991). Science, technology, and society. Englewood Cliffs, NJ:
Prentice-Hall.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e323a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e327" publication-type="other">
Mol, A. &amp; Law, J. (1994). Regions, networks and fluids: Anaemia and social
topology. Social Studies of Science, 24, 641-671.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e337a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e341" publication-type="other">
Nancy, J.-L. (2000). Being singular plural. Stanford, CA: Stanford
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e351a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e355" publication-type="other">
Rees, W. (2002). Globalization and sustainability: Conflict or convergence?
Bulletin of Science, Technology and Society, 22(4), 249-268.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e365a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e369" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. (1992). Oneself as another. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e379a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e383" publication-type="other">
Roth, W.-M. (2006). Learning science: A singular plural perspective.
Rotterdam, NL: Sense.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e394a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e398" publication-type="other">
Roth, W.-M. (in press). Toward a dialectical notion and praxis of scientific
literacy. Journal of Curriculum Studies.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e408a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e412" publication-type="other">
Roth, W-M. &amp; Barton, A. (2004). Rethinking scientific literacy. New York,
NY: RoutledgeFalmer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e422a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e426" publication-type="other">
Roth, W.-M., &amp; Lee, Y.J. (2006). Contradictions in theorizing and
implementing "communities. Educational Research Review, 1, 27-40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d7857e436a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d7857e440" publication-type="other">
Sismondo, S. (2004). An introduction to science and technology studies.
Maiden, MA: Blackwell Publisher.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
