<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">complitstudies</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Comparative Literature Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00104132</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15284212</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">complitstudies.51.1.0018</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/complitstudies.51.1.0018</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Poetry Is Theft</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Rachel Galvin</string-name>
               <aff>Johns Hopkins University</aff>
            </contrib>
            <bio xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple">
               <p>
                  <sc>rachel galvin</sc>is an Andrew W. Mellon Postdoctoral Fellow at the Humanities Center of the Johns Hopkins University. She holds a PhD in Comparative Literature from Princeton University. Her work appears in Boston Review, Jacket 2, Los Angeles Review of Books, Modernism/modernity, MLN, and The Wallace Stevens Journal, as well as in volumes such as War and The Blackwell Companion to Translation Studies. She is an Associate Editor for Literature of ASAP Journal: A Scholarly Journal of the Association for the Study of the Arts of the Present. She is also the author of a book of poems, Pulleys &amp; Locomotion, and Hitting the Streets, a translation from the French of Raymond Queneau.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">51</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">complitstudies.51.1.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>18</fpage>
         <lpage>54</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/complitstudies.51.1.0018"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article explores poetic practices of copying and recycling that follow a “cannibalistic” logic. Taking a cue from theories of literary relationality elaborated by Edward Said, Haroldo De Campos, Oswald De Andrade, Édouard Glissant, Jorge Luis Borges, and Marcus Boon, I examine innovations in the work of poets such as Mónica de la Torre, Timothy Donnelly, Terrance Hayes, Mark McMorris, Haryette Mullen, M. NourbeSe Philip, and Wendy Walker. While it is unusual to read North American poetry in connection with postcolonial and Latin American literary theory, my article's method enacts the same kind of poetic circuit that I am interested in exploring. Seeking to build on recent comparative approaches to twentieth-century poetry I argue that tracing dialogues and conceptual affinities across linguistic and regional boundaries is crucial for understanding the development of experimental poetics in the American Hemisphere.</p>
         </abstract>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd>poetry</kwd>
            <kwd>comparative poetics</kwd>
            <kwd>copying</kwd>
            <kwd>cannibalism</kwd>
            <kwd>capitalism</kwd>
            <kwd>Latin American literature</kwd>
            <kwd>North American Literature</kwd>
         </kwd-group>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>
         <disp-quote content-type="epi">
            <p>For some time, the devouring jaws of these new barbarians have been chewing up and “ruining” a cultural heritage that is ever more planetary.</p>
            <attrib>—Haroldo De Campos</attrib>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote content-type="epi">
            <p>Le plagiat est nécessaire. Le progrès l'implique. (Plagiarism is necessary. Progress implies as much.)</p>
            <attrib>—Comte De Lautréamont (pseudonym of Isidore-Lucien Ducasse)</attrib>
         </disp-quote>
         <disp-quote>
            <p>Oscar Wilde: I wish I had said that.</p>
            <p>James McNeill Whistler: You will, Oscar, you will.</p>
         </disp-quote>“To write, today, in both Europe and Latin America will mean, more and more, to rewrite, to rechew,” declares Haroldo De Campos in his essay “Anthropophagous Reason: Dialogue and Difference in Brazilian Culture.”<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>1</sup>
         </xref>In calling for a literature that devours other literatures rather than imitating them, he is riffing on a founding document of Latin American letters, the 1928 “Cannibalist Manifesto” (“Manifesto Antropófago”). In the manifesto, Brazilian modernist Oswald De Andrade writes, “I am only concerned with what is not mine. Law of Man. Law of the cannibal”<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>2</sup>
         </xref>(“Só me interessa o que nao é meu. Lei do homem. Lei do antropófago”).<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>3</sup>
         </xref>The poetics of cannibalism have pointed politico-aesthetic implications: ingesting and devouring describe the ludic recombination of preexisting cultural elements—or what might be called, more neutrally, innovation through engagement with tradition. At the same time, it constitutes an aggressive program for the construction of a national poetics that draws at will from the world's cultural heritage. De Campos and De Andrade specifically imagine this literary combinatorics, or recycling, as mediated through the body of the writer. Even as the traditionally denigrated figure of the cannibal or New World barbarian—an ignoble savage—has been energetically reclaimed by Latin American artists and intellectuals, the activity of cultural re-mastication empowers the colonial or subaltern culture as “a conquering agent unexpectedly capable of transformations that affect both self and other.”<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>4</sup>
         </xref>What does this concept mean for twentieth-century poetic procedures? Is an allusion to Shakespeare a cannibalization of the Bard? What if the allusion is slightly distorted, as in the famous line from De Andrade's manifesto, “Tupi or not Tupi, that is the question,” which names an indigenous Indian population in an English line included in a manifesto that is otherwise written in Brazilian Portuguese? De Andrade's act of cultural devouring may seem to be merely tongue-in-cheek, multilingual wordplay, but how does it fit with his aim to rewrite Brazilian literary tradition?</p>
      <p>Following cultural cannibalism's provocative, anti-mimetic proposition further still, is this incorporation total, or does it leave leftovers or expel a by-product? How should we characterize the relationship between a new poem and a precursor text when a writer feeds a line from a Shakespearean sonnet through an online anagram program, as U.S. poet K. Silem Mohammad has done, so that the result is identical to Shakespeare's on the level of the letter, but not at all semantically? In his ongoing project called<italic>Sonnagrams</italic>, Mohammad recombines lines to form new poems that respect the sonnet's traditional conventions of meter and rhyme.<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>5</sup>
         </xref>What kind of game is he playing, and is it the same one De Andrade was playing almost a century ago? How are these games different from other allusions, quotations, and appropriations of, say, Shakespeare's<italic>Tempest</italic>, whose character Caliban appears as a stand-in for the colonial subject in texts by writers throughout the Americas, particularly in the Caribbean, from Martinican Aimé Césaire (<italic>Une tempête</italic>) and Cubans Roberto Fernández Retamar (<italic>Caliban</italic>) and Antonio Benítez-Rojo (<italic>Repeating Island</italic>), to the poetry of Barbadian Kamau Brathwaite and St. Lucian Derek Walcott?<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>6</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>To phrase these questions differently, instead of seeing the literary canon as a<italic>source</italic>—a point of origin that engenders progeny, reiterations, borrowings, and references—cultural cannibalism proposes that later texts absorb, devour, or radically re-author earlier works. In this article, I wish to trace a modest segment of what Edward Said has called “the whole field of other possible relationships between writings.”<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>7</sup>
         </xref>He describes the “adjacency” between texts as a nonlinear alternative to imagining sequentiality or dynastic linkages between texts, since a text “imitates no spatial or temporal object.”<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>8</sup>
         </xref>I aim to show that radical re-authoring occurs, in myriad forms and to myriad effects, by examining contemporary North American poetry that re-theorizes literary tradition as a part of its critique of sociohistorical matrices of power.<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>9</sup>
         </xref>My analysis will move through the century and across languages used throughout the American hemisphere to explore how subversive copying indicates the fissures in notions of property and subjectivity. I am interested in how poets appropriate literary capital through constrained recombination, recycling, and playful appropriations of language. These poetic texts are particularly concerned with displacement (of people, language, ideas, property) and the bundle of myths surrounding the concept of origin, both metaphorically and experientially.</p>
      <p>At times, poets cite, rewrite, and name other poets as a way to accrue cultural capital to their own texts in a way that is deeply self-conscious of power imbalances. Copying may be considered usurpation, as De Campos argues: “The polytopical polyphonic planetary civilization is, I believe, under the devouring sign of translation<italic>lato sensu</italic>. Creative translation—‘transcreation’—is the most fruitful manner of rethinking Aristotelian<italic>mimesis</italic>which has marked Western poetics so profoundly; of rethinking this concept not as a passive-oriented theory of copy or reflex, but as a usurping impulse in the sense of a dialectic production of differences out of sameness.”<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>10</sup>
         </xref>The poets I am interested in here transcreate: they cut up and recontextualize language of many sorts, play with proper names and mistaken identities, and imagine the cannibal as a figure of resistance to the colonial matrix of power, with its accompanying regime of language and capitalist consumption. Adapting the argument set out by Marcus Boon in his comparative study of the philosophy and cultural theory that underpins copying in the age of globalization,<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>, I suggest that various twentieth-century poetic practices of copying articulate a politics that is “not only resistant to the dominant logic of late capitalism, but … [goes] far beyond the banalities of ‘subculture,’ or the disturbing impasses of indigenous cultures that find themselves caught between assimilation and forcible insertion into contemporary IP regimes as commodified signifiers of otherness.”<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>11</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Taking a cue from Boon—as well as theories of literary relationality and cultural recycling elaborated by De Campos, De Andrade, Édouard Glissant, and Jorge Luis Borges—offers a way to think about contemporary North American poetic innovations that is nonlinear, somatic, and messy, and alert to the decolonizing impulse in that poetry. I wish to offer an alternative to models of “uncreative” or “conceptual writing,” or the model of “the anxiety of influence,”<xref rid="r012" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>12</sup>
         </xref>and to show that recombinatory poetics are much more than mere games, as has recently been claimed.<xref rid="r013" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>13</sup>
         </xref>By bringing theories of poetic relationality from throughout the Americas together with contemporary poetry written in English, I aim to continue and expand the scope of comparative, transnational reconceptualizations of twentieth-century poetry that include the important efforts of Jahan Ramazani, Brent Hayes Edwards, and Matthew Hart.</p>
      <p>This article begins by considering a set of nonhierarchical models for poetic making, primarily, cannibalism and Glissant's Relation. These conceptual models theorize the relationality that undergirds playful procedures of recombination, copying, plagiarism—in short,<italic>copia</italic>. Copia, the root of the word “copy,” I will use throughout as an umbrella term for procedures of recombination, following Boon's use of the term as a general category.<xref rid="r014" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>14</sup>
         </xref>As Boon glosses, copia balances between the Latin term, which originally means “abundance, plenty, multitude” (referring to the Roman goddess of plenty and increase), and the modern sense linked to decrease (“theft or deterioration of an original”).<xref rid="r015" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>15</sup>
         </xref>This tension will be important as I consider the making and unmaking that are part of creative composition. After briefly discussing cannibalism and Relation, I explore some of the philosophical and aesthetic underpinnings of concepts of copying and originality in the Americas. In the second half of the paper, I assemble an archive of recent, experimental poetry written by poets including Mónica de la Torre, Terrance Hayes, Timothy Donnelly, Mark McMorris, Haryette Mullen, M. NourbeSe Philip, and Wendy Walker, showing that their procedures can be understood as following a cannibalistic logic of displacement as it engages discourses of power.<xref rid="r016" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>16</sup>
         </xref>“Cannibalistic logic” is a logic of copia. It seeks radical mixing (of genres, registers, sociolects), abundant reformulation, and reimagining, and in the process re-authors its “source” texts. Unlike contemporary poetry that has been called “uncreative” or “conceptual,” this archive offers a provocative rethinking of cultural and sociopolitical power, colonization's legacy of race-based oppression, and the ways in which global capital is a form of institutionalized appropriation.</p>
      <p>It may seem unusual to read contemporary North American poetry with postcolonial, Caribbean, and Latin American literary theory, but in doing so, my method enacts the same kind of poetic circuit that I am interested in exploring. Dialogues across linguistic and regional boundaries are crucial for the development of experimental poetics in the American hemisphere during the twentieth century; and on the level of biography, some of the poets I will discuss here grew up in the Caribbean or Mexico before living in the United States or Canada. Ramazani, in his analysis of transnational poetics, presses on “displacement” as crucial to the postcoloniality of metaphor and the metaphoricity of postcoloniality: “Dislocations of meaning, defamiliarizing incongruities, linguistic hybridity, and consciousness of sameness in difference are integral to both postcoloniality and the very structure of metaphor.”<xref rid="r017" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>17</sup>
         </xref>Although Ramazani's focus is on poetry from former British Commonwealth countries, his assertion is also germane to the poetry of the Americas. By pointing out that both metaphoricity and postcoloniality are imagined “in terms of the movement, transference, or alienation of discourse from one place to another, a movement that involves not only a one-way shift but inevitably a bidirectional hybridization,”<xref rid="r018" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>18</sup>
         </xref>Ramazani offers an argument for reciprocal literary relationality that strikingly recalls Cuban anthropologist Fernando Ortiz's influential notion of sociocultural “transculturation.” In 1940, Ortiz adapted the anthropological concept of “acculturation”—which implies the acquisition of one culture by another, from the initial uprooting of a previous culture (deculturation) to the subsequent creation of new cultural phenomena (neoculturation)—to formulate the more dialectical “transculturation.”<xref rid="r019" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>19</sup>
         </xref>Angel Rama, who adapts Ortiz's concept to apply it to literature, stresses that “selection and inventiveness … must always be part of the mix in any case of cultural plasticity.” A community “will necessarily<italic>invent new things through a combinatory system</italic>that matches the cultural system's own autonomy.”<xref rid="r020" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>20</sup>
         </xref>Although he does not mention Ortiz or Rama, Ramazani's “bidirectional hybridization” intimates a similarly multidirectional, combinatorial process that is useful as a scholarly method and a way to conceive of literary relationality.</p>
      <p>I am proposing the cannibalistic logic of poetic displacement as an alternative to the concept of “uncreative writing” that has begun to gain currency among North American poets and scholars. Kenneth Goldsmith has argued, along with Marjorie Perloff, Craig Dworkin, and Brian Reed, that a key tendency in late twentieth- and early twenty-first-century poetry is that of “information management.” This tendency is characterized by the “rhetoric of the Internet search result,” which Dworkin glosses as “a collage of unpredictably discontinuous and truncated quotations, with certain words repeated and emphasized.”<xref rid="r021" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>21</sup>
         </xref>More than a period style, argues Reed, it is a “period ethos,” and he identifies as twenty-first-century “appropriation poetries” those that redirect language (somewhat like an Aikido master re-channels energy). Reed writes, “Today's poet … stands outside in a data-storm, and she clings to the few language scraps she is able to rescue as they blow by.”<xref rid="r022" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>22</sup>
         </xref>He likens this composition process to the strumming of a harp in Herman Melville's declaration in<italic>Battle-Pieces</italic>: “I seem, in most of these verses, to have but placed a harp in a window, and noted the contrasted airs which wayward winds have played upon the strings.”<xref rid="r023" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>23</sup>
         </xref>This lovely comparison aims at an anti-subjective origin for poetry, but ends up reifying the guiding consciousness of the person who thought to place a harp (that consummate lyric symbol) in a window, or to stand outside in a storm.</p>
      <p>According to the arguments put forward by Perloff, Dworkin, Goldsmith, and Reed, the recontextualization of language is a marker of “taste” or aesthetic judgment, and therefore a sign of genius. Perloff writes, “<italic>According to taste</italic>: it is important to remember that the citational or appropriative text, however unoriginal its actual words and phrases, is always the product of choice—and hence of individual taste.”<xref rid="r024" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>24</sup>
         </xref>In this interpretation, the appropriation of language becomes the reassertion of individuality and authority. Goldsmith terms this “self-expression,” “emotion,” and “authorship” in<italic>Uncreative Writing</italic>. Perloff argues, “If the new ‘conceptual’ poetry makes no claim to originality—at least not originality in the usual sense—this is not to say that<italic>genius</italic>isn't in play. It just takes different forms.”<xref rid="r025" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>25</sup>
         </xref>The rhetoric of Perloff and Goldsmith's claims is fascinating. Viewing the recontextualization of language as a marker of “taste” or aesthetic judgment is a hoary basis for authority. Attributing the act of recontextualizing to “genius” reinforces the fetish of authenticity that reigns in late capitalist society<xref rid="r026" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>26</sup>
         </xref>and is a clear manifestation of the metaphysics of origin.<xref rid="r027" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>27</sup>
         </xref>By “metaphysics of origin,” I refer to the central epistemic issue that creates a theology of “the new, the creative, the true” in the West, following Françoise Meltzer's analysis in<italic>Hot Property: The Stakes and Claims of Literary Originality</italic>. Meltzer shows that the idea of literary originality functions within an economy of displacement: that is, the idea of “origin” itself is continually displaced so as “to clothe its status as invention, or myth.”<xref rid="r028" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>28</sup>
         </xref>Said has identified a similar phenomenon that he calls the “imperative connection” between the idea of a beginning and the “aboriginal human need to point to or locate a beginning.”<xref rid="r029" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>29</sup>
         </xref>Twentieth-century notions of private property, patriarchy, and sovereignty are deeply intertwined with the metaphysics of origin, Meltzer writes:<disp-quote>
            <p>While it is no surprise that a culture of late capitalism should be so obsessed about the limits and boundaries of private property, we seem to be increasingly haunted by an odd anxiety every time the idea of originality is at issue … Underlying these convictions is another series of beliefs: in the individual and his—and I mean<italic>his</italic>—sovereignty; in a patriarchal hegemony as dominating culture and metaphysics; in a concomitant feminine economy as eternally secondary, unable by definition to partake of an originary model; in private property and the exclusionary systems that ensue; in manual work as a valid labor and product, to which writing remains a destabilized and ambiguous correlative.</p>
            <p>Finally and inevitably, the belief in originality and the possessiveness it entails engender the prose and economy of paranoia: paranoia in the “creators,” whose fear of being robbed masks a more basic anxiety that originality may be impossible and illusory.<xref rid="r030" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>30</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>
      </p>
      <p>Poetic cannibalism, in contrast, seeks to overturn the matrix of power undergirding notions of literary primacy and to cultivate compositional procedures based in radical mixing. It is less invested in maintaining the myth of lyric subjectivity (a nineteenth-century construction that was codified through the reading methods of twentieth-century critics), according to which the persona and subjectivity of the artist are determining factors in the work of art and its guarantor of significance.<xref rid="r031" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>31</sup>
         </xref>As we will see in the next section, it is a provocative rethinking of cultural and sociopolitical power dynamics.</p>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title>Tropes of Poetic Relation in the Americas</title>
         <p>Of plagiarism, little new can be written. In fact, the preceding line is lifted entirely and set without quotation marks from Hillel Schwartz's<italic>The Culture of the Copy</italic>.<xref rid="r032" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>32</sup>
            </xref>Which raises the question: Is the only difference between citation and theft that wily set of quotation marks? What is the relationship between the citation and its new context (my article)? Since intellectual and artistic theft are not transhistorical concepts, but are construed differently at different times and in different places,<xref rid="r033" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>33</sup>
            </xref>how can we understand the concept of “authorship”? Although contemporary poetic recycling is being trumpeted as a new method, and has the allure of nowness as it engages with digital processes, information management, and the rhetoric of the Internet search, it is an age-old strategy. Poetic plagiarism and appropriation are found in the constraints of Oulipo, surrealist aleatory juxtaposition, romanticism, early modern imitation, and further back to the Greeks. Just think of the cento, a classical poetic form that can be traced to the first few centuries of the last millennium, which is made up entirely of lines from other texts (at first, lines from Homer were particularly popular as fodder for recombination). The cultural currency of copia, however, differs based on time and place—just as ideas of authorship, originality, and work (as activity and object) are construed differently. Cast positively, cultural recycling may be viewed as homage, pastiche, parody, or ludic recombination; on the flip side, it engages in deception, forgery, theft, plagiarism, hoax, usurpation. In both of these interpretations of the politics of form, discourses of power are in play.<xref rid="r034" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>34</sup>
            </xref>Form itself may be neutral, as many have argued,<xref rid="r035" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>35</sup>
            </xref>but its situation in time and space endow it with social vision and political charge. Who decides when a text is playing appropriately, that is, by the rules, and when does it appropriate someone else's work? Is writing in fact work? “Is it ‘really’ manual work, and, if so, can its product, the text, be owned by the laborer?” asks Meltzer in<italic>Hot Property: The Stakes and Claims of Literary Originality</italic>.<xref rid="r036" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>36</sup>
            </xref>She links the legislation of copyright and what she terms the “metaphysics of origin” to culturally determined definitions of labor and property, all of which are predicated on a dualist philosophy. What does copia loosen in the dualist worldview, what does it set free, what does it skirt, what does it hem in?</p>
         <p>“We cannot actually live in a world without mimesis,” writes Boon, asserting that despite its stigma, imitation has always shaped human cultures and communities.<xref rid="r037" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>37</sup>
            </xref>Drawing from philosophy, law, and aesthetic and cultural theory, Boon's<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>argues that copying is an organic activity—not just humans but all forms of life copy—and that culturally, it is regulated based on historically contingent ideologies and regimes of power. By comparing the framing of copying and the reception of copying strategies across regions and across the century, such as between the Latin American vanguard and contemporary North American experimental poetics, we can see that there are radical differences that shed light on the sociohistorical situations in question. The reclaiming of copia is often part of the radicalization of subaltern communities,<xref rid="r038" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>38</sup>
            </xref>as it challenges the myth of authenticity and colonialism's legacy of racism, destabilizes signs of racial and cultural priority, and renders the national no longer “naturalizable.”<xref rid="r039" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>39</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Poets throughout the Americas have sought tropes for their relation to other cultures, reinterpreting and reappropriating the very action of borrowing or condition of belatedness by which cultures of the Americas have historically been described. These tropes are a way of engaging the “problem of mirror culture,” as Brazilian theorist Roberto Schwarz calls it in<italic>Misplaced Ideas</italic>. In light of practical issues of inequity in Latin America, Schwarz evaluates interventions against the “commonplace idea” of the “primacy of origins” by philosophers including Jacques Derrida and Michel Foucault (who rethink hierarchy as “an infinite sequence of transformations” with no first or last). While Schwarz sees “exciting” potential in “attacking the coordinates” of authorship, influence, and originality—which would help to discredit “that romantic correspondence between individual heroism, masterly execution and collective redemption which imbues the nationalist schemas with their undeniable knowledge-value and potential for mystification”<xref rid="r040" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>40</sup>
            </xref>—he nonetheless expresses skepticism about the pragmatic solutions that might be derived from such theory.</p>
         <disp-quote>
            <p>It remains to be seen whether this conceptual break with the primacy of origins would enable us to balance out or combat relations of actual subordination. Would the innovations of the advanced world suddenly become dispensable once they had lost the distinction of originality? … If theory remains at this level, it will continue to suffer from the same limitations, and the radicalism of an analysis that passes over efficient causes will become in its turn largely delusive. The inevitability of cultural imitation is bound up with a specific set of historical imperatives over which abstract philosophical critiques can exercise no power.<xref rid="r041" ref-type="fn">
                  <sup>41</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>
         <p>These historical imperatives, as Schwarz calls them, condition the range of poetics developed in the American hemisphere in the twentieth century. While writers in the Americas may seem to respond to the same concerns that the French articulate in various theories of intertextuality (Kristeva, Barthes, Riffaterre, Ricoeur), it is clear that the social, political, and aesthetic concerns surrounding poetic procedures of copia (allusion, quotation, parody, pastiche) in the Americas during this period are radically different from those in Europe because of inequities in development and geopolitical power. Analysis of those differences requires a hemispheric approach to poetry that evaluates literature from the Americas according to models of relation that originate in the Americas. This is not to make the nonsensical claim that a given region must be studied according to the theories produced in that region. Rather, I want to emphasize that many conceptual models for racial, ethnic, national, and linguistic relationality that arise in the Americas are formulated by writers whose own work provides poetic instantiations of or negotiations with those models, and thus illuminates the sociohistorical matrix of power that gives rise to those poetic strategies and imbues them with meaning. These models provide context for the idea of cannibalism, which is intimately intertwined with many of them.</p>
         <p>The twentieth century saw a shift from a theorization of Manichean tropes of relationality to organicist tropes.<xref rid="r042" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>42</sup>
            </xref>Manichean tropes emphasize binary oppositions and reconciliations, such as that of acculturation,<italic>mestizaje</italic>, and<italic>métissage</italic>. These include some of the interstitial definitions offered by postcolonial theory, which tend toward a model of hybridity; Fernando Ortiz's and Angel Rama's concepts of transculturation; Jahan Ramazani's hybrid muse; Derek Walcott's “divided to the vein”; the “double consciousness” of W. E. B. Du Bois; and Kamau Brathwaite and many others' use of the oppositional figure of Caliban (an anagram for the nexus of terms “Carib” and “Cannibal”). In contrast, organicist tropes such as cannibalism (<italic>antropofagia</italic>) offer more fluid models for conceiving of the relationship between peoples and between texts. They challenge the metaphysics of origin by offering nondirectional and nonhierarchical understandings of relationality: for example, Glissant's<italic>Relation</italic>, Deleuze and Guattari's rhizome, Jorge Luis Borges's deliberate anachronism,<xref rid="r043" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>43</sup>
            </xref>Paul Gilroy's theorization of “stereophonic” cultural forms in the black Atlantic, and Brent Hayes Edwards's<italic>décalage</italic>(which emphasizes the inassimilable in the otherwise binary structure of African “diaspora”). In Glissant's formulation,<italic>Relation</italic>is a nonhierarchical mode of interdependence, such that “each and every identity is extended through a relationship with the Other.”<xref rid="r044" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>44</sup>
            </xref>Glissant builds on Deleuze and Guattari's notion of the rhizome: “an enmeshed root system, a network spreading either in the ground or in the air, with no predatory rootstock taking over permanently. The notion of the rhizome maintains, therefore, the idea of rootedness but challenges that of a totalitarian root.”<xref rid="r045" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>45</sup>
            </xref>For Glissant, rather than a circuit between center and periphery, the peripheries may interchange with one another, so that<italic>Relation</italic>takes multifarious, shifting trajectories. These models of nonhierarchical networks of mutual sustenance and connection are distinctly mobile. Rather than valorizing primacy, they avoid what Emily Apter calls the “moral ecology of roots” as a metaphor.<xref rid="r046" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>46</sup>
            </xref>Rather than an inversion, overturning, appropriation, or incorporation, they acknowledge inextricability.</p>
         <p>In this vein, Borges elaborates a theory of an organic, nonlinear relationship between new literature and older literature. He draws from T. S. Eliot's “Tradition and the Individual Talent” while departing from it in a key way. Instead of judging new works according to the standards set by literary monuments of the past, Borges undoes this hierarchy in temporality and cultural capital, arguing that new texts necessarily change the way we read old texts and construct tradition. A contemporary Latin American writer such as himself is thus envisioned as making a crucial contribution to the Western tradition as a whole, changing the way readers approach the Greek classics, for example.<xref rid="r047" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>47</sup>
            </xref>Borges bears out this idea not only in his short stories, but also in “Eternity and T. S. Eliot,” where he patches together sentences from different sections of Eliot's work and “created the Eliot he needed,” as Juan De Castro writes, through free translation and loose appropriation of Eliot's texts.<xref rid="r048" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>48</sup>
            </xref>Borges expands on this idea in “Kafka and His Precursors,” where he writes, “The fact is that each writer creates his precursors. His work modifies our conception of the past, as it will modify the future.” Instead of positing a continuum between authors past and authors present, Borges turns Eliot's notion on its head.<xref rid="r049" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>49</sup>
            </xref>In another well-known story, “Pierre Menard, Author of the<italic>Quixote</italic>,” a twentieth-century writer desires to write<italic>Don Quixote</italic>and so copies it over, word for word, in the process re-authoring the text and making it radically new for readers in his own century.<xref rid="r050" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>50</sup>
            </xref>Alan Pauls has shown that in Borges's fiction, originality is always located<italic>elsewhere</italic>, and the narrator is a contrabandist, parasite, or vampiric figure who relays, transmits, translates, and echoes that original source. If we substitute “cannibalism” for “vampirization” in the following statement, Pauls's argument about Borgesian “parasitic” figures holds: they take vampirization to its ultimate consequences, Pauls writes, “until when drunk with someone else's blood, they betray their species and produce something new.”<xref rid="r051" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>51</sup>
            </xref>Borges's deliberate anachronism is envisioned as an appropriation of the other that occurs through violent, bodily consumption.</p>
         <p>The above-mentioned organicist models of Borges, Glissant, and others offer alternative, non-dualist ways of conceptualizing the relations between cultures and poetries. They operate on multiple levels. On the level of literary history and with regard to tracking formal innovation, Relation offers an alternative to a rooted or Manichean model of exchange; on the level of procedure and reference within the text, as we examine specific instances of cultural recycling; and on the meta-level of interrogating scholarly methods and selection of objects of study. The choice of model can potentially participate in what Walter Mignolo would call “epistemic disobedience,”<xref rid="r052" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>52</sup>
            </xref>or a refusal to maintain and reinforce the hierarchies of the colonial matrix of power.</p>
         <p>As I will show in what follows, contemporary North American writers are participating in a cannibalistic logic as they write poems demonstrating a keen awareness of being embedded in networks of Relation. Their poems re-author source texts, such that their new texts carry the re-routings of older texts with them, as well as the vast entourage of translations and allusions to those earlier texts. They deliberately play upon the anxiety associated with plagiarism, which is linked to the notion of a sovereign textual subject: a subject that “purports to double mimetically the authoritative and self-contained subjectivity of the author,”<xref rid="r053" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>53</sup>
            </xref>or what has been commonly called the lyric “I.”</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>The Epidermis of Sincerity</title>
         <p>An alternative optic on contemporary writing becomes available if we look back to Latin America nearly one hundred years ago. At the same time as the “Cannibalist Manifesto” was being written and circulated in Brazil, the polemic surrounding the reception of the Spanish-speaking poetic vanguard clustered around three major issues: the significance of technique; the existence of genuine novelty in avant-garde poetry; and creative sincerity and profundity.<xref rid="r054" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>54</sup>
            </xref>Consider, alongside the “Cannibalist Manifesto,” another, earlier founding document of Latin American letters, a short text by José Martí. Martí, an originator of<italic>modernismo</italic>and a revolutionary leader in the Cuban struggle for independence, introduced a late nineteenth-century volume of his poems with a prose piece that declares, “These are my verses. I borrowed them from no one.”<xref rid="r055" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>55</sup>
            </xref>He continues:<disp-quote>
               <p>None of them has emerged from my mind, warmed over, artful and beautified; they have come like tears springing from the eyes or blood spurting out from a wound…. I did not stitch together bits of this and that, but cut deep into myself. These poems emerged written not in academic ink but in my own blood. Whatever I place on view here I once have seen (<italic>I</italic>have seen it: me), and I have seen much more, which fled before I could copy its features. From strangeness, singularity, haste, and hoarding, I wrest my visions, and any fault was my own, for I have made them rise up before me as I copy them. I am responsible for the copy. I found some garments that were torn and others that were whole, and I wore these colors. I know they are not worn out. I love difficult sonorities and sincerity, even when it may seem brutal. All that they have to say I know and have confirmed for myself. I have sought to be loyal, and if I sinned I feel no shame at having sinned.<xref rid="r056" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>56</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>Martí invokes Aristotelian mimesis as crucial to the writing of a poem: in this tale of literary composition, the writer filters reality and imagination and copies his perceptions onto the page. Yet the process of “copying” does not introduce any falsehood or deception. Quite to the contrary, Martí stakes out a poetics of sincerity and authenticity rooted in his own physical person, springing from his “own blood” rather than intellectual abstraction or a hodgepodge of combinatoric procedures. Martí states that the writer himself serves as his own warrant of truth, his own guarantor, because he has acquired knowledge through sensory experience (“<italic>I</italic>have seen it: me”).<xref rid="r057" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>57</sup>
            </xref>Similarly, twenty years later in her “Decalogue of the Artist,” Chilean poet Gabriela Mistral imagines poetic composition as a bodying forth in maternal terms: “Darás tu obra como se da un hijo: restando sangre de tu corazón” (“You shall bring forth your work as a mother brings forth her child: out of the blood of your heart”).<xref rid="r058" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>58</sup>
            </xref>Anatomic, telluric, and organic tropes are a hallmark of vanguardist claims for Latin American literature and culture of this period, and particularly those that (even when avoiding cultural nationalism and seeking internationalism) stake out the exceptionality of the Americas, portraying the continent as energetic and new.<xref rid="r059" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>59</sup>
            </xref>Sincerity—mediated through the authenticity of the writer's body—is necessary for “false erudition” and “the imported book” of European origins to fall away, according to Martí. The<italic>criollo</italic>(a Latin American of European descent), representing a racial and cultural mixing that is the product of colonial history, moreover, cedes to the<italic>mestizo</italic>in the fashioning of a national poetic tradition.<xref rid="r060" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>60</sup>
            </xref>At heart, Martí and Mistral defend subjectivity as the guarantor of poetry's quiddity.</p>
         <p>In an infamous 1927 article, “Contra el secreto profesional” (“Against Professional Secrets”), Peruvian poet César Vallejo uses a similar metaphor to criticize the “false and epidermic” pan–Latin Americanism of Mistral, as well as the modish cosmopolitanism of other<italic>vanguardista</italic>writers (including Borges). Echoing Emile Zola's “J'accuse,” Vallejo writes, “Acuso, pues, a mi generación de continuar los mismos métodos de plagio y de retórica de las pasadas generaciones, de las que ella reniega” (“I accuse, then, my generation of continuing the very same methods of plagiarism and rhetoric used by the past generations that they repudiate”).<xref rid="r061" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>61</sup>
            </xref>In direct opposition to the academicized poetic formulas borrowed from European Surrealism, Vallejo advocates particular elements of the Romantic ethic (notions of inspiration, honesty, authenticity, emotion, and the human), yet without drawing on its aesthetic. Vallejo's own poetry grows in part from an investigation of the linguistic function of “I,” that stuttering, fragmented convergence of energies. His poetry is not subjective, per se—it is an investigation of the<italic>possibility</italic>of subjectivity. His poems are shaped by a concern with the plasticity of language and the process of writing, ludic maneuvers, and a mix of registers (colloquial speech, and Peruvianisms romp with arcane scientific vocabulary) as he fashions a poetic form that corresponds to his sense of the contemporary.</p>
         <p>Since the push for “authentic” literary culture and autonomous literary production must above all be read in national terms, it is useful to recall Rama's assertion that from the 1700s to the present, the slogan of Latin American writers has been “Be independent!” Calls have been made for ethnic, geographic, cultural, and local literary forms free of European elements. Rama identifies three main impulses that have driven literary innovation—independence, originality, and representation—and traces these aesthetic values to the romantic perception of America as “glaringly different from its mother societies, given its distinctive physical environment, its diverse ethnic makeup, and its difference in terms of development when compared to the only model of progress—Europe.”<xref rid="r062" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>62</sup>
            </xref>For the poetry of the Americas to be original, it simply must be true to its own particularity—or so it would seem.</p>
         <p>In the United States, Ralph Waldo Emerson envisioned a “representative” poet of genius, who would “chaunt our own times and social circumstance,” cleaving closely to the lived experience of American nature and American society by “singing” America (just as Walt Whitman would claim to do) (“The Poet,” 1844).<xref rid="r063" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>63</sup>
            </xref>For Emerson, American geography and “our own times” make a particular formal demand of the poet (“it will not wait long for metres”). So does local culture. Cuban poet Nicolás Guillén said that he was “searching for a national poetry” in his turn to the<italic>son</italic>, a Cuban musical style that combines African and Spanish elements, as a structuring element for his poems.<xref rid="r064" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>64</sup>
            </xref>In a similar vein, Langston Hughes in 1926 urged black poets to turn to the spirituals and jazz of the “common people,” which “furnish a wealth of colorful, distinctive material for any artist because they still hold their own individuality in the face of American standardizations.”<xref rid="r065" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>65</sup>
            </xref>James Weldon Johnson would echo Hughes in his 1931 preface to<italic>The Book of American Negro Poetry</italic>, calling “genuine folk stuff” the “unfailing sources of material for authentic poetry.”<xref rid="r066" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>66</sup>
            </xref>Authenticity is widely imagined as residing in mimetic relation to land, the body, and autochthonous culture.</p>
         <p>Copying becomes the original sin within this framework, such that “the ubiquitous stamp of ‘inauthenticity’ came to be seen as the most authentic part of the national drama, its very mark of identity,” as Schwarz has noted with regard to Brazilian literature.<xref rid="r067" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>67</sup>
            </xref>Moreover, the demand for authenticity posits an unattainable norm of “an organic, reasonably homogeneous national culture with popular roots.”<xref rid="r068" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>68</sup>
            </xref>The concept of local particularity and independence is predicated on a series of problematic postulates concerning inspiration, originality, and totality: literary creation ex nihilo; a “pure” literature; and inevitably, a remainder that resists incorporation or that is produced by the process of copying or digesting.<xref rid="r069" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>69</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s03">
         <title>Take Note: The Fashion of Footnotes</title>
         <p>Meltzer notes that terms such as “origin” and “displacement” are heavily freighted in the administrative language of immigration, forming the “machinery of political repression.”<xref rid="r070" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>70</sup>
            </xref>She indicates that the tropes invite further study in relation to “any minority discourse/dominant culture dialectic,”<xref rid="r071" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>71</sup>
            </xref>but does not pursue this line. It is here that I would like to pick up and adapt her notion of the metaphysics of origin to my analysis of twentieth-century recombinatory and cannibalistic poetic procedures and their theorization in the Americas. The displacement or deterritorialization of literary texts and their fragments has an analog in the movement of peoples from the Old to the so-called New World, the language of mastery and domination, and tropes of emancipation and vengeful incorporation. Therefore, while the formal strategies of a poetics of copia are part of literary making from ancient times, the theories by which copia is understood in the twentieth century have arisen within the sociohistorical reality of migration integral to the colonial matrix of power, which in turn depends on capitalism.<xref rid="r072" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>72</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Literary strategies such as footnoting and citation create relationality (in Ramazani and De Campos's sense). Citation practices are always bound up with questions of authority. In her theorization of intertextuality, influence, and imitation, Mary Orr offers the broader term “cultural recycling,” distinguishing between “unvoiced forms” (paraphrase, variant, translation) and more appropriative forms. Critique is inherent to cultural recycling, she notes: it has the practical function of “(re-)evaluation by means of comparison, counter-position and contrast.”<xref rid="r073" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>73</sup>
            </xref>She consequently identifies quotation and allusion as significant strategies for asserting authority. The quotation is always suggestively metonymic, with its “focusing and crystallizing function,” so that the part always sends back to the whole: “An utterance that verifies, authorizes, transports and redefines meanings across time and national boundary, quotation and its accomplice, allusion, name borrowing practices for very specific ends, whether authentication of or separation and autonomy from authorities.”<xref rid="r074" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>74</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Citation is particularly potent for bridging. Even as it connects, it always recalls its displaced status. “Quotation is a constant reminder that writing is a form of displacement,” observes Said. “For although quotation can take many forms, in every one the quoted passage symbolizes other writing as encroachment…. As a rhetorical device, quotation can serve to accommodate, to incorporate, to falsify (when wrongly or even rightly paraphrased), to accumulate, to defend, or to conquer—but always, even when in the form of a passing allusion, it is a reminder that other writing serves to displace present writing.”<xref rid="r075" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>75</sup>
            </xref>Quotation is a “vigorous mechanism of displacement,” Antoine Compagnon agrees. “It's even more powerful than surgery.”<xref rid="r076" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>76</sup>
            </xref>Contemporary descriptions of citation and the displacement it effects in experimental poetry are vivid and dynamic. In addition to the aforementioned uncreative writing (Goldsmith), there is Tan Lin's “plagiarism,” Sergio Waisman's “creative plagiarism,”<xref rid="r077" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>77</sup>
            </xref>Haryette Mullen's “recyclopedia,”<xref rid="r078" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>78</sup>
            </xref>and various critical descriptions of “syncretic poetics,”<xref rid="r079" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>79</sup>
            </xref>“fragmentary collages that channel surf,”<xref rid="r080" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>80</sup>
            </xref>and the “apotheosis of ‘contaminated language.’”<xref rid="r081" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>81</sup>
            </xref>Some definitions stress the racial, political dimensions of self-fashioning and the “hunger for new forms,” as Kevin Young calls it. Young writes of “counterfeit culture,” which he defines as “the ways in which black writers create their own authority in order to craft their own, alternative system of literary currency and value, so to speak, functioning both within and without the dominant, supposed gold-standard system of American culture…. For the black author, and even the ex-slave narrator, creativity has often lain with the lie—<italic>forging</italic>an identity, ‘making’ one, but ‘lying’ about one too.”<xref rid="r082" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>82</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Poetry has come a long way since T. S. Eliot's endnotes documenting his citations and sources in<italic>The Waste Land</italic>first troubled his readers. Or has it? Endnotes are common currency in back margins of poetry books published today in North America. They archive and index their sources in a quasi-scholarly fashion, assiduously referencing their source documents or offhandedly alluding to “inspiration” from textual and non-textual sources they have “drawn from,” “appropriated,” are “indebted to,” “borrow from,” or which they “adapt.”<xref rid="r083" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>83</sup>
            </xref>In a send-up of this fashion, Mónica de la Torre and Terence Gower's<italic>Appendices, Illustrations &amp; Notes</italic>consists solely of such “back matter,” featuring a “Recommended Reading” section of faux sources on the last page.<xref rid="r084" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>84</sup>
            </xref>The framing apparatus is an index (pun intended) of an authoritative hand—be it the writer's or the editor's.</p>
         <p>The citation of sources is a common procedure employed by contemporary experimental poetry of varying levels of constraint. Witness the documentary impulse driving Mark Nowak's<italic>Shut Up Shut Down</italic>, Natasha Tretheway's<italic>Native Guard</italic>, Van Jordan's<italic>MACNOLIA</italic>,<xref rid="r085" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>85</sup>
            </xref>and Claudia Rankine's<italic>Don't Let Me Be Lonely</italic>; the dismemberment of a legal decision in M. NourbeSe Philip's<italic>Zong!</italic>which she breaks down to the phonemic level, yet includes in an appendix in its original form; and the excerpting of legal documents in Vanessa Place's<italic>Statement of Facts</italic>. A politically motivated, cut-and-splice method joins officious official language with pop culture in poems by Timothy Donnelly and Geoffrey G. O'Brien that mash up the USA Patriot Act with Bruce Springsteen's “Born to Run” (Donnelly) and Jean Genet's<italic>Querelle</italic>(O'Brien). Their constraints vary in strictness. Donnelly wrote “The Last Dream of Light Released from Seaports” from a repertoire of words “selected from successive pages” of the Patriot Act and combined with Springsteen's 1975 hit song, but he does not specify the method further, and in several of his other endnotes states that terms were selected “randomly.”<xref rid="r086" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>86</sup>
            </xref>For his part, O'Brien composed “They Met Only in the Evenings” using only words that appear in the Patriot Act, with one word per line replaced with a word from Genet. The political statement made by both poems stems as much from the fact that the Patriot Act itself is a document that imposes constraints on public activities (and redraws the boundaries between what is private and what is public) as from the re-authoring and re-contextualizing that takes place through the cut-up method. The fear of official language machines and the effects of duplicating and grafting recur throughout Donnelly's book. “We become like those who seek to destroy us,” he writes in a line borrowed from a 2006 misquote of a 1946 telegram from U.S. diplomat George Kennan.<xref rid="r087" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>87</sup>
            </xref>The poem is aware of its own citation of outworn rhetoric, indicating the anxiety that even as establishment language is sent up, it is included in the poem and therefore ultimately constitutive of it.</p>
         <p>Other poets use endnotes to make visible the constraints that structure their poems, in a mode reminiscent of the Oulipian penchant for texts that thematize or otherwise lay bear their constraints. In four of the poems in<italic>Lighthead</italic>, African American poet Terrance Hayes borrows the form of the<italic>pecha kucha</italic>, a Japanese business presentation in which “a presenter narrates or riffs on twenty images connected to a single theme for twenty seconds at a time.”<xref rid="r088" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>88</sup>
            </xref>Hayes directs the reader out of his book and across media to a website (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xlink:href="http://www.pechakucha.org/">http://www.pechakucha.org/</uri>) for more information on the form; and he suggests Googling images of works by African American sculptor Martin Puryear that correspond to “Arbor for Butch.” “Coffin for Head of State” is written “after” the songs of Nigerian musician and composer Fela Kuti; and “Twenty Measures of Chitchat” draws on “conversational fragments.” In one section of “Twenty Measures,” titled “Landscape with Riot,” looting and cannibalism are described as modes of appropriation: “When the house windows were broken, I was one of the people / stepping in, then out again, with boxes and whole registers / of what belonged to me, with dream-swollen jewelry leashed / about my neck, with blood on my shirt and blood on my teeth.”<xref rid="r089" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>89</sup>
            </xref>The image of the speaker with bloodied teeth, appropriating commodities, appears amended in the following section (“The Imminent Till”) by the statement “Time is the real cannibal.” It is the violence of American racism that is cannibalistic in this portrayal. The title refers to Emmett Till, the fourteen-year-old African American boy from Chicago who was brutally murdered in Mississippi in 1955 for whistling at a white woman:<verse-group>
               <verse-line>Time is the real cannibal, mesmerizing even at face value,</verse-line>
               <verse-line>weighing down the stars, and the river holding the unlucky</verse-line>
               <verse-line>body attached to a cluster of fish, where the heart is</verse-line>
               <verse-line>so diluted the doctors wear gloves when they handle it.<xref rid="r090" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>90</sup>
                  </xref>
               </verse-line>
            </verse-group>Till's body was found in the Tallahatchie River, with a cotton gin fan tied around his neck with barbed wire. His death helped spark the civil rights movement. It inspired dozens of poems (from Langston Hughes to Marilyn Nelson), songs, and other artistic responses. Hayes's poem for Till invokes a host of other poems, contributing to their elegiac tradition, and the simple description of Till's fragile heart recalls Gwendolyn Brooks's “Last Quatrain of the Ballad of Emmett Till.”</p>
         <p>Hayes frequently uses recombination and assiduously designed constraints to link his poems to those of African American women poets who have preceded him. In<italic>Hip Logic</italic>, he includes as an epigraph a poem “made up of whole and partial lines in the index (under<italic>W</italic>) of<italic>The Collected Poems of<sc>audre lorde</sc>
            </italic>.”<xref rid="r091" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>91</sup>
            </xref>The collection also includes a sonnet entirely made up of the line “We sliced the watermelon into smiles” repeated fourteen times, and several odes. The bulk of the book is made up of a series of poems titled “A Gram of &amp;S,” based on the daily word game found in the puzzle section of newspapers. Hayes explains in a note, “I end each line with one of the eleven words derived from the title word, while abiding by the other rules of the game: 1. Words must be derived from four or more letters. 2. Words that acquire four letters by the addition of ‘s,’ such as ‘bats’ or ‘dies’ are not used. 3. Only one form of a verb is used.”<xref rid="r092" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>92</sup>
            </xref>In a more recent collection titled<italic>Lighthead</italic>, Hayes also uses constraints. Reading just the end words of “The Golden Shovel” in<italic>Lighthead</italic>gives the entirety of Gwendolyn Brooks's poem “We Real Cool”:<verse-group>
               <verse-line>When I am so small Da's sock covers my arm, we</verse-line>
               <verse-line>Cruise at twilight until we find the place the real</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
            <verse-group>
               <verse-line>Men lean, bloodshot and translucent with cool.<xref rid="r093" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>93</sup>
                  </xref>
               </verse-line>
            </verse-group>Brooks's poem has been literally re-authored, as has Elizabeth Alexander's “Ladders,” which emerges in the end words of Hayes' poem “The Last Train to Africa”<xref rid="r094" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>94</sup>
            </xref>in precisely the same way. Homage and lineage are inscribed directly into Hayes's poems, so that the reader cannot read one without the other. This incorporation of the precursor is more thoroughgoing than an onomastic reference or dedication: it literally reproduces the precursor poem. As Hayes's new poem circulates, Brooks's poem will always circulate along with it, encapsulated within it, living a special kind of afterlife through reiteration. In other poems, Hayes also responds to a precursor by writing<italic>against</italic>a “foe.” His poem for Wallace Stevens asks, “Who is not more than his limitations,” and makes its position explicit in the closing lines: “This song is for my foe, / the clean-shaven, gray-suited, gray patron / of Hartford, the emperor of whiteness / blue as a body made of snow.”<xref rid="r095" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>95</sup>
            </xref>But the poem also admits more softly its relation to the poet from Hartford and his “supreme fiction”: “I too, having lost faith / in language, have placed my faith in language. / Thus, I have a capacity for love without / forgiveness.” These lines dilate into a broader statement about the poetic speaker's relation to the historical wounds of racial oppression in the United States.</p>
         <p>Like Hayes's “Snow for Wallace Stevens,” “Thirteen Ways of Looking at Blackbird (After Wallace Stevens)” by Olive Senior, a Jamaican poet living in Canada, reimagines the blackbird as an enslaved African arriving in the Americas. In addition to the obvious constraint of following a thirteen-part, meditative structure, each of Senior's sections picks up and revises select elements from the corresponding sections of Stevens's poem. Where Stevens in section IV offers a non-dualist philosophy (“A man and a woman / Are one. / A man and a woman and a blackbird / Are one”), Senior's poem offers a more jagged portrait, in which Blackbird, arriving on a sugarcane plantation, “no longer knows / if he is man or woman or bird or simply is” (IV). Abased and enslaved, a “survivor of the crossing,” Blackbird is “the lucky one in three” (II), exhausted and without the luxury to contemplate in tranquility, as does Stevens's poetic speaker (“I was of three minds,” II). Senior's rewriting changes how we read Stevens. When turning back to Stevens, the reader will hear Senior's resonances. Senior doesn't call Stevens a “foe,” but the implicit comparison—her corrective to the narrative—makes clear her position as she inscribes America's violent history of slavery into Stevens's abstract reflection and poetic structure. (Her rewriting concords with Thylias Moss's “Reconsideration of the Blackbird,” in which she writes: “Problem: No one's in love with the blackbirds. / Solution: Paint them white, call them visions, everyone will want one.”)<xref rid="r096" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>96</sup>
            </xref>Hayes and Senior apply the principles of cannibalistic poetics to their rewritings of Stevens, and by metonymic extension, to their rewriting/writing into the blanks or white spaces of American poetics. They show that poetry is not impartial: it tells the history of national culture.</p>
         <p>Such twentieth-century poems claim trans-American affiliation to canonical poems even as they rewrite them critically, just as Langston Hughes responds to Walt Whitman in “I, Too, Sing America” and Jean Toomer does in “Blue Meridian.” But Hughes's poem borrows from while resisting Whitman, in which “every atom belonging to me as good as belongs to you.” In his ambivalent homage to Whitman's poetics of recombination, Hughes insists on a remainder. Racial difference means that something is left over or left out of the full-throated equation of self and other,<xref rid="r097" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>97</sup>
            </xref>as in the gesture Senior and Hayes both make in their responses to Wallace Stevens.</p>
         <p>“We were born to imitate,” writes Mark McMorris in “Aphrodite of Economy.” His collection<italic>The Blaze of the Poui</italic>is in complex dialogue with history, the history of language, and the idea of constraint and lacuna. McMorris's poems perform and reflect on the ways in which language bears a political charge:<verse-group>
               <verse-line>History chokes on a rag of kerosene</verse-line>
               <verse-line>the fuse is lit down a corridor of echoing images</verse-line>
               <verse-line>and one cannot shuffle the fulgurating words</verse-line>
               <verse-line>to nominate as aesthetics what time calls blood—</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
            <verse-group>
               <verse-line>…</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
            <verse-group>
               <verse-line>we were born to imitate, and that's the paradox</verse-line>
               <verse-line>of being from an offshore rock: how to put out</verse-line>
               <verse-line>the wide savagery when you're inside the beast</verse-line>
               <verse-line>that in other legends, as wolf, swallows the community</verse-line>
               <verse-line>in this one has left prints in the form of sugar cane</verse-line>
               <verse-line>that actually broaches a goddess of slave economy.<xref rid="r098" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>98</sup>
                  </xref>
               </verse-line>
            </verse-group>McMorris's fabricated sources underscore the problems inherent in the metaphysics of origin.<italic>Blaze of the Poui</italic>features “Fragments: Journal of a Voyage to Undiscovered Lands,” which is accompanied by a short prose piece announcing that the journal was found among Sir Walter Raleigh's affairs, edited some time after 1589, and then encountered again in a used bookshop on Connecticut Avenue in Washington, DC.<xref rid="r099" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>99</sup>
            </xref>The narrator of the “Journal” is a sixteenth-century explorer who writes of landing on a Caribbean island and meeting its inhabitants, the “Cannibals.” The cannibal reappears throughout McMorris's poems, he notes, “for the same reason I have other colonialist specters, mythical creatures, savages, barbarians—because they define an imaginary terrain and set up zones on the periphery for power to act against.”<xref rid="r100" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>100</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>As the incorporation and imitation of sources recalls, history's re-membrance is inextricable from dis-memberment, just as inspiration is rooted in the physical action of taking in breath. A cannibalistic poetics rips up history and nails it back together “with its viscera on the outside, all that glistening green truth showing in the rip marks.”<xref rid="r101" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>101</sup>
            </xref>The bricolage of poetic making, like building a golem, is everywhere depicted in cannibalistic poetry.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s04">
         <title>Typing, Outsourcing, and Forging Identities</title>
         <p>
            <disp-quote content-type="epi">
               <p>That's not writing, that's typing.</p>
               <attrib>—Truman Capote on Jack Kerouac</attrib>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote content-type="epi">
               <p>That's not writing, it's plumbing.</p>
               <attrib>—Samuel Beckett on William Burroughs</attrib>
            </disp-quote>Mexican poet Mónica de la Torre's “Doubles” in her 2008 collection<italic>Public Domain</italic>draws on an ephemeral, “low” genre, namely, the Listserv posting.<xref rid="r102" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>102</sup>
            </xref>“Doubles” comprises a fictionalized e-mail correspondence between de la Torre's namesakes, whose information she found on the Internet: “Hi! I am Monica de la Torre, but I am not your mother! I am Regional Student Representative for the #1 Region in the Nation, Region1!!”; “I am stripper, go-go dancer, performance artist and top model. Why do you want me?”<xref rid="r103" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>103</sup>
            </xref>The often hilarious, fictionalized e-mails took a disorienting leap out of the virtual when de la Torre first published the piece in an online journal,<italic>Words Without Borders</italic>. She explains in an author's note:<disp-quote>
               <p>I once saw my name posted on a listserve for people harboring the hope that Internet technology would finally lead them to find their disappeared loved ones. With this history-loaded search as the premise for<italic>Doubles</italic>, I came up with fictional email correspondence that weaved together the real identities of all the namesakes I could find on the web. The piece originally was published online: anyone searching for me or any other Mónica de la Torre inevitably came upon it. It so happened that one of the people who ended up reading<italic>Doubles</italic>online was the actual mother of the woman whose search inspired the piece. She got a hold of my email, and wrote to me with the certainty that I'd know how she could find her daughter. Years had gone by. I had no leads to offer; the email I had for the daughter was no longer valid.<xref rid="r104" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>104</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>The feedback loop of publication and response was significantly foreshortened by de la Torre publishing in an online journal. In a digital mise en abime, her poetic text was quickly repurposed in the same Web it reflected, in a poignant reminder of art's inseparability from history.</p>
         <p>Throughout “Doubles,” a concern with bilingualism and the national and linguistic identity implied by de la Torre's patronym are at issue. A transsexual model from Veracruz, Mexico, asks in a mix of Spanish and English, “Hablas español? Do you speak Espanish?” The orthography foregrounds the slippage from the spoken to the written in interlanguage (a sociolinguistic term referring to a variety of language “intermediate between the speaker's native language and the target language”).<xref rid="r105" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>105</sup>
            </xref>Another Mónica de la Torre complains, “Is this some sort of joke? Just because my name sounds Spanish doesn't mean that I am from Argentina. I am sick of receiving sales calls and junk mail in Spanish! What is this! If your last name is Hungarian does that mean that AT&amp;T will send you Hungarian promotional material?” Near the end of the piece, one Mónica de la Torre sends another Mónica de la Torre a poem in Spanish (since, she writes humorously, “from what could gather upon looking at your varsity's website, it looks like you might write poetry”). When the second Mónica complains that she can't read the poem because she doesn't speak Spanish, the first Mónica obliges by sending a translation. This is one place where the text winks at the reader, since the (real) de la Torre is an accomplished translator who has published a major anthology of contemporary Mexican poetry,<xref rid="r106" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>106</sup>
            </xref>and in fact translated the whole text of “Doubles” from Spanish.<xref rid="r107" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>107</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>But the vertiginous rings of (self-)translation expand one step further when the first Mónica also sends another, more disjunctive poem titled “Countdown by Mónica de la Torre,” which she claims someone else translated and she found on the Internet. It includes a line in Spanish from a well-known and much covered Mexican song, “Mi rival es mi propio corazón, por traicionero” (“My rival is my own heart, because it's treacherous”). The verse is a nod to the whole text's engagement with naming and identity, doubling and forging, and the uneven process of translation. Sometimes, the text insinuates, you become your own rival.</p>
         <p>But despite its humor, de la Torre's piece frames a serious response to the complex legacy of Argentina's dirty war and the dispersions of many sorts that it caused. The whole Listserv dialogue is initiated because of Mercedes Correche's search for her mother, Mónica de la Torre, who was most likely “disappeared” by the Argentine dictatorship in 1977 “after being accused of subversive activities.” The Argentine dictatorship specialized in rhetorically camouflaging its actions against citizens with layers of euphemism, such that the regime itself was referred to as a “special process,” and its method of kidnapping, torturing, and killing its enemies was called “disappearing” them. The dictatorship was marked by “censorship of texts and the persecution of people, when even the appearance of thinking was suspicious.”<xref rid="r108" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>108</sup>
            </xref>The national sense of language changed between 1976 and 1983: “Uncertainty, suspicion, oblique broaching of discourse, masking, fracturing, displacement of the great issues to one's own subjectivity, the search for a center located outside the immediate social milieu: such are the recurrent terms that critics use to identify these years of transition which, now, with the mediation of time, serve well to reflect the spirit of Argentine society during the years of dictatorship.”<xref rid="r109" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>109</sup>
            </xref>Crucially, de la Torre's narrator rewrites herself as a collectivity. The text offers a parable of multiple subjectivity and generic mixing, in which poems are born among layers of misdirection, and translation is always imperfect. A very real need to locate origins in a place where origins have been violently erased come together in the poetics of “Doubles,” which both acknowledges and resists origins. The literal search for origins, or lineage, coexists with the poet's resistance to the concept of authenticity. By retelling this encounter, de la Torre foregrounds the problem that Roberto Schwarz had pointedly articulated in<italic>Misplaced Ideas</italic>: how can conceptual wrangling with the metaphysics of origin affect actual conditions of sociohistorical domination and oppression?</p>
         <p>It is not new for poets to renovate the language of poetry by appropriating or sending up enervated, devalued language as a way to critique discourses of power. It may even be one of the oldest methods of literary innovation, considering the Roman appropriation of Greek literature. But some contemporary, experimental poets explicitly link mass production of capitalist consumer products and the logic of the copy<xref rid="r110" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>110</sup>
            </xref>to the production of art in a Benjaminian vein. De la Torre refers to the age of mechanical reproduction in an epigraph to “Photos While U Wait,” which she borrows from Jacques Barzun's introduction to Gustave Flaubert's<italic>Dictionary of Accepted Ideas</italic>: “The cliché, as its name indicates, is the metal plate that reproduces the same image mechanically without end.”<xref rid="r111" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>111</sup>
            </xref>Poems written under constraint and composed of recombined, appropriated text at times thematize the activity of appropriation itself as endemic to capitalism. The supermarket is a popular trope for the destruction of authenticity, disenfranchisement, and advertising's interpellation of the subject. A discursive tone dotted with imperatives mark these poems, as they echo the language of consumerism. African American poet Harryette Mullen's<italic>S*PeRM**K*T</italic>, included in her<italic>Recyclopedia</italic>, is structured according to the logic of supermarket aisles (“sort of like your shopping list”), and the missing letters in its title spell out<sc>u are</sc>, as in, “you are what you eat,” as Mullen explains in an author's note. “I was thinking about domestication, about the role of women, women as consumers, women having supposed power as consumers but also being disempowered in other ways…. You can't necessarily buy who you really want to be. You have to buy the available images,” she writes in an accompanying statement.<xref rid="r112" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>112</sup>
            </xref>Mullen, like Hayes, also connects her poetics to that of a woman poet predecessor. Her books<italic>Trimmings</italic>and<italic>S*PeRM**K*T</italic>, she explains, “correspond to the ‘Objects’ and ‘Food’ sections of Stein's<italic>Tender Button</italic>s. I share her love of puns, her interest in the stuff of life, and her synthesis of innovative poetics with cultural critique. However … I'm also interested in the collision of contemporary poetry with the language of advertising and marketing, the clash of fine art aesthetics with mass consumption and globalization, and the interaction of literacy and identity.”<xref rid="r113" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>113</sup>
            </xref>Mullen combines the language of marketing (“Check out this week's seasonal electric reindeer luz de vela Virgin Mary mark downs”)<xref rid="r114" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>114</sup>
            </xref>with descriptions of scenes found in a supermarket that intimate social and economic disenfranchisement: “Pyramids are eroding monuments. Embalmed soup stocks the recyclable soul…. Devoid of colored labels, the discounted irregulars.”<xref rid="r115" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>115</sup>
            </xref>Such lines encode, too, references to historical disenfranchisement (the “discounted” irregulars suggest the regiments of people of color enlisted in the U.S. Army during World War II). She explains, “My inclination is to pursue what is minor, marginal, idiosyncratic, trivial, debased, or aberrant in the language that I speak and write.”<xref rid="r116" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>116</sup>
            </xref>One of the central gestures of the poem is to echo corporate consumerism's interpellation of the individual shopper: “Aren't you glad you use petroleum? Don't wait to be told you explode. You're not fully here until you're over there. Never let them see you eat. You might be taken for a zoo. Raise your hand if you're sure you're not.”<xref rid="r117" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>117</sup>
            </xref>The flattening of what might be called “voice” or “style” into the recycling of recognizable discourses of power in consumerist society is part of Mullen's project.</p>
         <p>In a similar critique of language and consumerism, in<italic>Whole Foods</italic>, Marie Buck playfully fuses language from the company's website, an anarchist zine, and etymological dictionaries, so that “the hybrid form of<italic>Whole Foods</italic>contrasts with the grocer's rhetoric of uncorrupted organic wholeness and natural unmediated authenticity.”<xref rid="r118" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>118</sup>
            </xref>Her poems play on culinary exoticism and the branding and marketing of food products to indicate privilege and access: “Cheeses often reflect the character of their country of origin, so experimenting with different cheese can be a kind of exploration of a faraway place” (“Cheese”).<xref rid="r119" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>119</sup>
            </xref>In one poem titled “Authenticity,” Buck incorporates what appear to be instructions for caring for fruit with intimations about the process of poetic making: “Cutting and exposure to the air darkens the flesh. We stood in unheated squats having tooth and not being limp. We were more art than science. We gently rubbed our skin in a circular motion.”<xref rid="r120" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>120</sup>
            </xref>The process of slicing and selecting brings about a transformation that is “more art than science” in this self-reflective poem. But more immediately, “Authenticity” also calls to mind the exposé concerning Whole Foods cofounder John P. Mackey, who used a pseudonym to post more than 1,100 entries about his own company on Yahoo! Finance bulletin boards between 1999 and 2006. The food mogul's posts were often self-serving: “I like Mackey's haircut. I think he looks cute,” one 28 April 2000 post read. “You must not patronize any of WFMI's stores. Tattoos, piercings, unusual dress and interesting haircuts are everywhere in the stores. In comparison, Mackey looks like a model for Brooks Brothers!”<xref rid="r121" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>121</sup>
            </xref>The hypertrophied falseness of the supermarket comes to a head in Mackey's (im)posturing.</p>
         <p>Theft is a trope for the history of slavery and deracination in the Americas in Wendy Walker's mixed-genre, “long work in poetic nonfiction,”<italic>Sexual Stealing</italic>. Through a constraint by which she exclusively used language selected from a “predecessor text,” she subjected Ann Radcliffe's<italic>Mysteries of Udolpho</italic>to what she calls “mesostic selection” for the purpose of extracting “the latent discourse,” mixing it with images and other texts she found, such as planters' diaries, when researching subjugation on sugar plantations. She postulates that British gothic fiction “found the source of its horror in plantation slavery, specifically the sugar plantations of Jamaica and Santo Domingo.”<xref rid="r122" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>122</sup>
            </xref>Forced labor, and the appropriation of labor and libidinal objects, is thus thematized and enacted through Walker's procedure. Some lines she lifts entirely, such as a section from the diary of late eighteenth-century British planter Thomas Thistlewood, who recorded on 7 August 1770 how his slave Sally stole food, was tortured for it, and then attempted to run away:<verse-group>
               <verse-line>dusk of accents</verse-line>
               <verse-line>from trembled excursions</verse-line>
               <verse-line>lines</verse-line>
               <verse-line> sonnet to go</verse-line>
               <verse-line> steps all ah!</verse-line>
               <verse-line> sweet</verse-line>
               <verse-line> light'ning portrait</verse-line>
               <verse-line> all ah!</verse-line>
               <verse-line> conceal away!</verse-line>
               <verse-line> who would</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
            <verse-group>
               <verse-line>lines to being compelled</verse-line>
               <verse-line>painful</verse-line>
               <verse-line>she to presume</verse-line>
               <verse-line>away thoughts exercise</verse-line>
               <verse-line>indisposition fever</verse-line>
               <verse-line>a recovery advanced</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
            <verse-group>
               <verse-line>air provisions</verse-line>
               <verse-line>no torturing</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>As Sally steals everything left in the cookroom, and eats it if eatable,</p>
               <p>Phibbah had her tied with her hands behind her naked for the</p>
               <p>Mosquitoes to bite her tonight. She bawled out lustily, but before 9</p>
               <p>O'clock in the evening broke loose and ran away. I got up, and all hands</p>
               <p>Went to seek her. I caught her near the Rockholes, in ditto provision</p>
               <p>Ground. Her hands were tied up so tight that the string hurt her very</p>
               <p>Much. Brought her home and secured her for this night in the bilboes.</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>About 9 in the evening, Cum Sally<italic>(mea) Sup</italic>. Terr. In Rockhole provision ground. Thistlewood's Diary, Tuesday, August 7, 1770.<xref rid="r123" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>123</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>In a fragmented section that imagines Sally's internal monologue, and a brief, indented excursion into lyric flight, the reader is led to identify with Sally's subjectivity. Subsequently, the perspective shifts, and Thistlewood recounts what happened when Sally tried to flee. The last lines are evocative, but Walker does not provide a gloss on Thistlewood's schoolboy Latin, leaving it to the reader to decipher. His semi-encrypted note indicates that in a further degradation, he raped Sally when he caught her.<xref rid="r124" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>124</sup>
            </xref>The enigmatic code and quasi-bureaucratic accounting are more shocking than a lurid description might have been.</p>
         <p>Violent appropriation of sovereignty and the articulation of the experience of oppression are also at issue in M. NourbeSe Philip's<italic>She Tries Her Tongue, Her Silence Softly Breaks</italic>. Philip, a Canadian poet born in Moriah, Trinidad and Tobago, addresses the silencing and sexual assault of women in conjunction with colonial history in the Americas. The Ovidian figure of Philomela, who was raped and had her tongue torn out so that she could not relate what had happened to her, is central to<italic>She Tries Her Tongue</italic>. Persephone's search for Ceres is another major theme. Philip foregrounds the problem of “the mother tongue” as she reworks Ovidian myths with excerpts from invented didactic texts (such as language tests, which are akin to those of Theresa Hak Kyung Cha's<italic>Dictee</italic>or Myung-Mi Kim's<italic>Commons</italic>, both of which also problematize language acquisition as an engine of hegemony). Some invented texts offer recommendations for the treatment of slaves: “Edict II: Every slave caught speaking his native language shall be severely punished. Where necessary, removal of the tongue is recommended. The offending organ, when removed, should be hung on high in a central place, so that all may see and tremble” (“Discourse on the Logic of Language”).<xref rid="r125" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>125</sup>
            </xref>Philip destabilizes the notion of a linguistically unified Caribbean history by mixing genres and weaving the demotic with Latin citations, as McMorris notes: “It's difficult to tell at first glance whether or not the poet has invented her ‘quoted’ texts, and this keeps things unsettled, shadowy, and undecided. In the later poems of the book, where the imitation of other genres takes place, we hover between belief and doubt, unable without a quantity of research to separate the fabrication from the real. It's as if Philip wants to contaminate the library of Western disciplines—founded in the Latin language—by destroying our confidence in the truth of its texts.”<xref rid="r126" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>126</sup>
            </xref>As in Walker's sequence, a “quantity of research” is required. The reader's ability to ascertain the authority of the texts may be troubled, and the archive of Western culture may become “contaminated” in Philip's treatment, but as indicated in an epigraph from Ovid (translated by Dryden), “All Things are alter'd, nothing is destroyed.”<xref rid="r127" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>127</sup>
            </xref>Philip intersperses repurposed sections from Ovid's<italic>Metamorphoses</italic>—touchstones from the colonial epistemic regime—with lyric poems in “Over Every Land and Sea.” The name of the Ovidian translator she cites from, Mary M. Innes, is given at the foot of the page. The naming of translators is pointed, as it presents an assemblage of literary authorities that tango with invented snippets of texts. In Philip's collection, the procedure of cutting, grafting, transplanting, and mutilating texts is in direct dialogue with the theme of violent, physical mutilation of women's bodies and voices: “When transplanting, you may notice a gently ripping sound as the roots are torn away from the soil. This is to be expected: for the plant, transplanting is always a painful process.”<xref rid="r128" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>128</sup>
            </xref>Recombination intimates historical force, and historical pain, even as it is part of the process of restituting the lost utterance. Philip not only cannibalizes “predecessor texts,” but in a key reversal, her collection cannibalizes invented texts that stand for discursive authority within the colonial matrix of power (dictionaries, how-to guides, etc.). She cannibalizes ghosts, or proleptic imaginings of modes of discursive oppression that could have been. Just as discursive systems have appropriated subaltern voices—either supplanting them with violently imposed imaginings of what those voices could have been or erasing them entirely—Philip appropriates the “overaltern” voice (in De Campos's term) by sizing it to fit her own poetic project. In her 2008 book,<italic>Zong!</italic>named for a 1781 slave ship, Philip goes even further in the fragmentation of appropriated language. Working with the legal decision<italic>Gregson v. Gilbert</italic>, which documented the drowning of 150 slaves by the captain so that the ship's owners would collect insurance monies, she progressively strips language down to the phonemic level, so that utterances become a constellation of stuttering, drowning cries.<xref rid="r129" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>129</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Allusion and citation in Philip's<italic>She Tries Her Tongue</italic>explicitly works to harness cultural capital from the literary canon. As she puts it, her poems are squatters in the house of language: “We have been linguistic squatters, possessing adversely what is truly ours.”<xref rid="r130" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>130</sup>
            </xref>This appropriation is of a piece with what Oswald De Andrade and K. Silem Mohammad are about in their splicing of Shakespeare, which I mentioned at the outset. In<italic>Sonnagrams</italic>, Mohammad combines aleatory procedures with the strict observance of traditional meter and rhyme in his recombination of Shakespeare's sonnets. Somewhat like Pierre Menard's re-authoring of<italic>Don Quixote</italic>, Mohammad sought to create new poems that were “quantitatively equivalent to Shakespeare's poems,” although this meant they were equivalent only “at the most basic linguistic level: the letter.” Mohammad explains his combinatorial process: “I feed each of Shakespeare's 154 sonnets one line at a time into an internet anagram engine … thus generating a new list of words from each line … The textual output … gives me a bank of raw material.”<xref rid="r131" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>131</sup>
            </xref>A quatrain from sonnet #3 (“Look in thy glass, and tell the face thou viewest”) becomes:<verse-group>
               <verse-line>Go softly to the Disneyland Hotel,</verse-line>
               <verse-line>Its simulacral threshold grown sublime:</verse-line>
               <verse-line>The bedrooms all emit that new car smell,</verse-line>
               <verse-line>Like nothing else in bourgie Anaheim.<xref rid="r132" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>132</sup>
                  </xref>
               </verse-line>
            </verse-group>As Heather McHugh puts it, Mohammad offers an “anagram as scrupulous as it is full of slang and sass.”<xref rid="r133" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>133</sup>
            </xref>Mohammad notes that he's not interested in being “overtly influenced by Shakespeare's semantic content.”<xref rid="r134" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>134</sup>
            </xref>His re-authoring is, moreover, consciously situated within a tradition of anagrams (especially those of Ferdinand De Saussure) and rewritings of Shakespeare's sonnets (he names Ted Berrigan, Bernadette Mayer, Jen Bervin, Steve McCaffrey, and others). His “sonnagrams,” as he calls them, thus carry with them an entourage of other re-authorings, so that their network of references expands in time and space far beyond Shakespeare, in a web of poetic relations.<xref rid="r135" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>135</sup>
            </xref>Like Dante's<italic>Inferno</italic>they name names, mentioning Mohammad's contemporaries, experimental poets Kenneth Goldsmith and Christian Bök (“Now Kenny G. and Christian B. were sweethearts / Till Kenny had an uncreative thought,” sonnet #43),<xref rid="r136" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>136</sup>
            </xref>the Flarf poetry movement, and titles of pop culture works (movies, bands, etc.). They link back to myriad cultural appropriations and reiterations of Shakespeare, too, including De Andrade's “Cannibalist Manifesto” and his rewriting “Tupi or not Tupi, that is the question.” As one poem warns, reversing the Barthesian death of the author, “Although you feel the author's days are through, / The author in the end erases you.”<xref rid="r137" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>137</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>One poem, “After Shakespeare,” sounds particularly Shakespearean: it is the only poem in the set that draws exclusively from the Bard's lexical fields (“disloyal moon!”), so that its echoes emphasize the distance between the other sonnagrams and Shakespeare:<verse-group>
               <verse-line>For lovers oft from thee great boldness draw</verse-line>
               <verse-line>To do like acts of mutiny below;</verse-line>
               <verse-line>A tacit metamorphosis of law</verse-line>
               <verse-line>Informs their fervent antidote to woe</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
            <verse-group>
               <verse-line>(RP and F with WS [RP];</verse-line>
               <verse-line>[RP] PP with WH [VD]).</verse-line>
               <verse-line>———</verse-line>
               <verse-line>[Sonnet 37 (“As a decrepit father takes delight”)]<xref rid="r138" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>138</sup>
                  </xref>
               </verse-line>
            </verse-group>Leftover letters are one of the hazards of the anagram machine. Mohammad explains, “Each Sonnagram, including its title, is an anagram of a standard modern-spelling version of one of Shakespeare's Sonnets, containing exactly the same letters in the same distribution as the original. The title is composed last, using whatever letters are left over once I've assembled a working sonnet in iambic pentameter with an English rhyme scheme.”<xref rid="r139" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>139</sup>
            </xref>Some have read the leftover letters in the concluding couplet as presenting a false encryption for the reader, linking it to Shakespeare's mysterious dedication of his sonnets in 1609 to “Mr. WH.”<xref rid="r140" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>140</sup>
            </xref>The initials are also familiar to readers of modernist poetry: WS might stand in for William Shakespeare, but it might also refer to Wallace Stevens, just as WH are Auden's famous initials … But perhaps it is merely a trap to believe that decoding is possible. The point of the poem may be that knowledge of the canon, or intertextual expertise, leads only to dead ends. But if the leftover letters that stud the poem are read as recombinatory elements that follow the logic of DNA sequencing—so that language itself is a constant reproduction of combinatory possibility—the poem offers resistance to decoding and the idea of the body as legible.</p>
         <p>Yet the very title of the collection and its constituent poems,<italic>Sonnagrams</italic>, echoes the name of an obstetric ultrasound procedure that sends sound waves through the body, suggesting a sounding or reverberation that recurs to (imminent) birth as a trope for poetic making. In a sonogram, the length of time that an echo takes to return measures the depth of the body's tissue, which causes interference for the echo. In this vividly corporeal portrayal of poiesis, an alternative to the aggression of cannibalism, the poet turns an ear to his or her predecessors and their echoes filter through the poet's body, leaving the realm of sound to begin to form images.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s05">
         <title>Conclusion: “The Cannibals of Today Are the Hosts of Tomorrow”<xref rid="r141" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>141</sup>
            </xref>
         </title>
         <p>
            <disp-quote content-type="epi">
               <p>I love originality so much I keep copying it.</p>
               <attrib>—Charles Bernstein</attrib>
            </disp-quote>The above epigraph is the first line of Bernstein's “Manifest Aversions, Conceptual Conundrums, and Implausibly Deniable Links,” which continues in a florilegium of funny aphorisms.<xref rid="r142" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>142</sup>
            </xref>The poem puns on T. S. Eliot plus the language of economics: “<italic>Immature poets borrow. Mature poets invest</italic>”; “<sc>poetry wants to be free</sc>. (Or, if not, available for long-term loan)”; “I'm the derivative product of an originality that spawns me as it spurns me.” The history of poetry is a long history of poems composed by announcing poetic debts, such as Dante does in his address to Virgil in the opening canto of the<italic>Inferno</italic>: “First of all authors and master of me, / I borrowed from you and to you I owe a debt / For the music that's brought me success.” But Bernstein's “investing,” as an alternative for stealing and borrowing, offers a further valence for cannibalistic recombination. When a poet<italic>invests</italic>in another poet's work, he or she brings it forward into the future, sometimes literally, as Hayes's poem for Gwendolyn Brooks reproduces the full text of her poem “We Real Cool”; or as Philip does when repurposing citations from Ovid; or as Mohammad's<italic>Sonnagrams</italic>re-sequence the most fundamental linguistic elements of Shakespeare's sonnets. In fact, the latter's ultra-soundings may point to a gendered version of poetic generation, in the same way that Dante casts Virgil as a heroic woman, who swoops in and whisks the younger poet away from a perilous situation in Canto XXIII so that the elder poet protects the next.</p>
         <p>Tropes for poetic relationality proliferate and concatenate. And there is so much more to say. The topic of poetic copia is indeed so abundant as to suggest myriad forking paths of contemplation and investigation. Hidden within the present reflections are dozens of doors leading to other rooms of thought that this article unfortunately does not have the luxury to open. The poets of the Latin American neobaroque—including Argentines Néstor Perlongher, Osvaldo Lamborghini, and Arturo Carrera, Uruguyans Roberto Echavarren and Eduardo Milán, Cuban American José Kozer, and Peruvian Argentine Reynaldo Jimenez—are in deep dialogue with cannibalistic poetics, as De Campos argues in his analysis of “anthropophagous reason” (which he defines as a “ludic space of polyphony and of language in convulsion”).<xref rid="r143" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>143</sup>
            </xref>In the twentieth and twenty-first century there is also a suggestive plethora of poetic frauds, hoaxes, and impersonations—the Ern Malley hoax and Christopher Reid's<italic>Katerina Brac</italic>, to name just two. Multilingual poetics, with its play on shifting linguistic identities, interlanguage, and polyphony, presents another avenue that would be fruitful for exploration; as does new media poetics that makes use of digital technology. As cultural processes that mingle past and present texts, such cannibalistic poetry participates in a form of cultural philosophy<xref rid="r144" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>144</sup>
            </xref>that unseats dualistic notions of genius and non-genius, source and derivative, and argues implicitly or explicitly against the metaphysics of origin.</p>
         <p>There is quite a lot more to say, in fact. As we've seen, cultural cannibalism is a practice that is deeply embedded in and responsive to problems of power. It is crucial to situate discourses of authenticity and mimesis within history to uncover the ways in which poets have worked around and against those discourses. The question of contemporary experimental poetry's response to the abundance and waste of late capitalism, and how the cannibal figures within it, bears further exploration. Twentieth- and twenty-first-century readers must stay attuned to the omnipresence of cultural mastication, as De Campos calls it:<disp-quote>
               <p>The combinatory and ludic polyculturalism, the parodic transmutation of meanings and values, the open, multilingual hybridization [which] are the devices responsible for the constant feeding and refeeding of this “baroquizing” almagest: the carnivalized transencyclopedia of the new barbarians, where everything can coexist with everything. They are the machinery that crushes the material of tradition, like the teeth of a tropical sugarmill, transforming stalks and husks into bagasse and juicy syrup.<xref rid="r145" ref-type="fn">
                     <sup>145</sup>
                  </xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>The “new barbarians” are still at it: Consume, produce, repeat.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Haroldo De Campos, “Anthropophagous Reason: Dialogue and Difference in Brazilian Culture,” in<italic>Novas: Selected Writings</italic>, ed. Antonio Sergio Bessa and Odile Cisneros (Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 2007), 177.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Oswald De Andrade and Leslie Bary, “Cannibalist Manifesto,”<italic>Latin American Literary Review</italic>19.38 (1991): 38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Oswald De Andrade, “Manifesto Antropófago,” in<italic>A Utopia Antropofágica</italic>(Sao Paolo: Editora Globo, 1995), 47.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sara Castro-Klarén, “A Genealogy for the ‘Manifesto Antropófago'; or, The Struggle Between Socrates and the Caraïbe,”<italic>Nepantla: Views from the South</italic>1.2 (2000): 297.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>K. Silem Mohammad,<italic>Sonnagrams 1–20</italic>(Cincinnati, OH: Slack Buddha Press, 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a series of studies of the afterlives of<italic>The Tempest</italic>, see Peter Hulme and William H. Sherman, eds.,<italic>“The Tempest” and Its Travels</italic>(London: Reaktion Books, 2000).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Edward Said,<italic>Beginnings: Intention and Method</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1985), 20.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 10.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Art historians have recently developed this idea. Alexander Nemerov writes that W.H. Auden “modernizes” Breughel's<italic>Icarus</italic>without changing a brushstroke, rendering the sixteenth-century painting dramatically contemporary. See Nemerov, “The Flight of Form: Auden, Bruegel, and the Turn to Abstraction in the 1940s,”<italic>Critical Inquiry</italic>31.4 (2005): 789–93. Mieke Bal claims that certain twentieth-century works of art do just this to the work of Caravaggio. I am indebted to her arguments. See Bal,<italic>Quoting Caravaggio: Contemporary Art, Preposterous History</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2001), 3–5.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Haroldo De Campos, “Ex-centric's Viewpoint” (1997),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://myrtus.uspnet.usp.br/tradterm/site/images/revistas/v04n2/v04n2a03.pdf">http://myrtus.uspnet.usp.br/tradterm/site/images/revistas/v04n2/v04n2a03.pdf</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r011">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Marcus Boon,<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2013), 8–9. Boon elaborates this point later on in his book: “Subaltern, subcultural, and other marginal folk groups are scapegoated by global capitalism for criminal acts of reappropriation, but global capital is itself nothing other than institutionalized and legitimated appropriation on a vast scale” (212). Boon's book is available for free download in PDF format at<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.hup.harvard.edu/features/boon/">http://www.hup.harvard.edu/features/boon/</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r012">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kenneth Goldsmith,<italic>Uncreative Writing: Managing Language in the Digital Age</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 2011); Kenneth Goldsmith and Craig Dworkin, eds.,<italic>Against Expression: An Anthology of Conceptual Writing</italic>(Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 2011); Harold Bloom,<italic>The Anxiety of Influence: A Theory of Poetry</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1997); Marjorie Perloff, Unoriginal Genius: Poetry by Other Means in the New Century (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2010).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r013">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Calvin Bedient, “Against Conceptualism,”<italic>Boston Review</italic>(24 Jul. 2013).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r014">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Boon, “Copia, or the Abundant Style,” in<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>, 41–76. For a response to Bedient, see Galvin, “Lyric Backlash,” Boston Review (Feb. 2014).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r015">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 41–42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r016">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>In the larger project from which this article is drawn, Hemispheric Poetics, I also analyze twentieth-century Spanish, French, and Portuguese poetry written in the Americas.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r017">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Jahan Ramazani,<italic>The Hybrid Muse: Postcolonial Poetry in English</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2001), 75.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r018">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 73.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r019">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Fernando Ortiz,<italic>Cuban Counterpoint: Tobacco and Sugar</italic>, trans. Harriet De Onís (Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 1995) 102–3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r020">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Angel Rama,<italic>Writing Across Cultures: Narrative Transculturation in Latin America</italic>, trans. David Frye (Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 2012), 22 (emphasis added).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r021">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Craig Dworkin, “The Imaginary Solution,”<italic>Contemporary Literature</italic>48.1 (2007): 48.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r022">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Brian M. Reed, “In Other Words: Postmillennial Poetry and Redirected Language,”<italic>Contemporary Literature</italic>52.4 (2011): 782.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r023">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Cited in ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r024">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Marjorie Perloff,<italic>Unoriginal Genius: Poetry by Other Means in the New Century</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2010), 169.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r025">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r026">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Boon,<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>, 116.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r027">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Françoise Meltzer,<italic>Hot Property: The Stakes and Claims of Literary Originality</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1994).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r028">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid, 157.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r029">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Said,<italic>Beginnings</italic>, 4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r030">
            <label>30.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Meltzer,<italic>Hot Property</italic>, 5–6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r031">
            <label>31.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Gillian White, Lyric Shame: Producing the ‘Lyric’ Subject of Contemporary American Poetry (Harvard University Press, 2014) and Victoria Jackson, Dickinson's Misery: A Theory of Lyric Reading (Princeton University Press, 2005).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r032">
            <label>32.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Hillel Schwartz,<italic>The Culture of the Copy: Striking Likenesses, Unreasonable Facsimiles</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Zone Books, 1998), 311.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r033">
            <label>33.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Boon,<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>, 109–11.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r034">
            <label>34.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 122.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r035">
            <label>35.</label>
            <mixed-citation>David Caplan,<italic>Questions of Possibility: Contemporary Poetry and Poetic Form</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 2005), 14; Mutlu Konuk Blasing,<italic>Politics and Form in Postmodern Poetry: O'Hara, Bishop, Ashbery, and Merrill</italic>(New York: Cambridge University Press, 1995); Lawrence S. Rainey,<italic>Institutions of Modernism: Literary Elites and Public Culture</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1998).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r036">
            <label>36.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Meltzer,<italic>Hot Property</italic>, 5–6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r037">
            <label>37.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Boon,<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>, 243.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r038">
            <label>38.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 74.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r039">
            <label>39.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Homi K. Bhabha, “Of Mimicry and Man: The Ambivalence of Colonial Discourse,” in<italic>The Location of Culture</italic>, 2nd ed. (New York: Routledge, 1994), 85–92.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r040">
            <label>40.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Roberto Schwarz,<italic>Misplaced Ideas: Essays on Brazilian Culture</italic>(London: Verso, 1992), 6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r041">
            <label>41.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 6–7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r042">
            <label>42.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I use this term with reference to Frantz Fanon's analysis of the Manichean allegory that undergirds colonial logic. See<italic>The Wretched of the Earth</italic>, trans. Constance Farrington (New York: Grove Press, 1965).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r043">
            <label>43.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Marjorie Garber,<italic>The Use and Abuse of Literature</italic>(New York: Random House, 2012), 180.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r044">
            <label>44.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r045">
            <label>45.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Edouard Glissant,<italic>Poetics of Relation</italic>, trans. Betsy Wing (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1997), 11.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r046">
            <label>46.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Emily Apter,<italic>Continental Drift: From National Characters to Virtual Subjects</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1999), 32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r047">
            <label>47.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Juan E. De Castro,<italic>The Spaces of Latin American Literature: Tradition, Globalization, and Cultural Production</italic>(New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2008), 55.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r048">
            <label>48.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 54.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r049">
            <label>49.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r050">
            <label>50.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Nemerov takes Borges's stories as a lens through which to view inter-art relation: In “Menard's rendering of Cervantes is richer because the modern-day author has given the older text a newfound relevance. The original now refers to the present not merely allegorically—as a static and obsolete set of personifications—but in a more direct fashion: its antiquated language has been transformed into something itself made in the present and therefore immediately responsive to modern events.” Nemerov, “The Flight of Form,” 788.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r051">
            <label>51.</label>
            <mixed-citation>My translation: “Llevan la vampirización hasta sus últimas consecuencias, hasta que, embriagados de sangre ajena, traicionan la condición de sue specie y producen algo<italic>nuevo</italic>.” De Castro links Pauls's discussion of vampirism to Borges's rewriting of Eliot's idea of tradition. See Pauls,<italic>El Factor Borges</italic>(Barcelona: Anagrama, 2004), 107.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r052">
            <label>52.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Walter D. Mignolo,<italic>The Darker Side of Western Modernity: Global Futures, Decolonial Options</italic>(Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 2011), 116.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r053">
            <label>53.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Meltzer,<italic>Hot Property</italic>, 4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r054">
            <label>54.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mirko Lauer notes that<italic>vanguardista</italic>ideas of authenticity belied their own romantic roots. See Lauer, “Estudio Preliminar,” in<italic>La polémica del vanguardismo, 1916–1928</italic>(Lima: Fondo Editorial de la Universidad Nacional Mayor de San Marcos, 2001), 11–13.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r055">
            <label>55.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Although Martí most likely wrote the poems and this introduction in the early 1880s, they were not published until 1913.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r056">
            <label>56.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Jose Martí,<italic>Selected Writings</italic>, trans. Esther Allen (New York: Penguin, 2002), 57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r057">
            <label>57.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For discussion of the cultural turn toward the senses as the seat of knowledge and its effects on claims for authority made in the literature of war, see Rachel Galvin, “The Guilt of the Noncombatant and W. H. Auden's ‘Journal of an Airman,’” in<italic>War</italic>, ed. Laura Asche and Ian Patterson (Cambridge: D. S. Brewer for the English Association, forthcoming); Yuval Noah Harari,<italic>The Ultimate Experience: Battlefield Revelations and the Making of Modern War Culture, 1450–2000</italic>(Basingstroke: Palgrave Macmillan, 2008), 32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r058">
            <label>58.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Trans. Doris Dana, in<italic>Twentieth-Century Latin American Poetry: A Bilingual Anthology</italic>, ed. Stephen Tapscott (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1996), 80.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r059">
            <label>59.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Vicky Unruh,<italic>Latin American Vanguards: The Art of Contentious Encounters</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1994), 129–34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r060">
            <label>60.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Martí,<italic>Selected Writings</italic>, 290.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r061">
            <label>61.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“No se trata aquí de una conminatoria a favor de nacionalismo, continentalismo ni de raza. Siempre he creído que esas etiquetas están fuera del arte y cuando se juzga a los escritores en nombre de ellas, se cae en grotescas confusiones y peores desaciertos. Aparte de que ese Jorge Luis Borges, verbigracias, ejercita un fervor bonaerense tan falso y epidérmico, como lo es el latinoamericanismo de Gabriela Mistral y el cosmopolitismo a la moda de todos los muchachos americanos de última hora.”<italic>Variedades</italic>, no. 1001, Lima (7 May 1927); Cesar Vallejo,<italic>Crónicas de poeta</italic>(Caracas: Fundacion Biblioteca Ayacucho, 1996), 57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r062">
            <label>62.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Rama,<italic>Writing Across Cultures</italic>, 5.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r063">
            <label>63.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ralph Waldo Emerson,<italic>Collected Essays: Complete Original Second Series</italic>(Rockville, MD: Arc Manor, 2007), 26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r064">
            <label>64.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Cited in translator's introduction, Nicolás Guillén,<italic>Yoruba from Cuba: Selected Poems</italic>, trans. Salvador Ortíz-Carboneres (Leeds, UK: Peepal Tree, 2005), 17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r065">
            <label>65.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Langston Hughes, “The Negro Artist and the Racial Mountain,” in<italic>Let Nobody Turn Us Around: An African American Anthology</italic>, ed. Manning Marable and Leith Mullings (Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2009), 254.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r066">
            <label>66.</label>
            <mixed-citation>James Weldon Johnson, “Preface,” in<italic>The Book of American Negro Poetry</italic>, ed. James Weldon Johnson (New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1931), 3–8.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r067">
            <label>67.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Schwarz,<italic>Misplaced Ideas</italic>, 13.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r068">
            <label>68.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 11.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r069">
            <label>69.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Zita Nunes, Cannibal Democracy: Race and Representation in Literature of the Americas (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2008), for analysis of the “remainder” in cannibalism as a cultural metaphor.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r070">
            <label>70.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Meltzer,<italic>Hot Property</italic>, 163.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r071">
            <label>71.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r072">
            <label>72.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mignolo,<italic>The Darker Side of Western Modernity</italic>, xiv–xv.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r073">
            <label>73.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mary Orr,<italic>Intertextuality: Debates and Contexts</italic>(Cambridge, UK: Polity, 2003), 7.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r074">
            <label>74.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r075">
            <label>75.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Said,<italic>Beginnings</italic>, 22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r076">
            <label>76.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Antoine Compagnon,<italic>La seconde main; ou, Le travail de la citation</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 1979), 29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r077">
            <label>77.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sergio Waisman,<italic>Borges and Translation: The Irreverence of the Periphery</italic>(Lewisburg, PA: Bucknell University Press, 2005), 208.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r078">
            <label>78.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Harryette R. Mullen,<italic>Recyclopedia: Trimmings, S*PeRM**K*T, and Muse &amp; Drudge</italic>(Minneapolis, MN: Graywolf Press, 2006), vii.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r079">
            <label>79.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Vera Broichhagen, Kathryn Lachman, and Nicole Jenette Simek, eds.,<italic>Feasting on Words: Maryse Condé, Cannibalism, and the Caribbean Text</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Program in Latin American Studies, Princeton University, 2006).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r080">
            <label>80.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Craig Morgan Teicher, “Fault Lines,”<italic>Boston Review</italic>(1 Sept. 2007).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r081">
            <label>81.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r082">
            <label>82.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kevin Young,<italic>The Grey Album: On the Blackness of Blackness</italic>(Minneapolis, MN: Graywolf Press, 2012), 24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r083">
            <label>83.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Timothy Donnelly,<italic>The Cloud Corporation</italic>(Seattle, WA: Wave Books, 2010), 149, 150.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r084">
            <label>84.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Terence Gower and Mónica de la Torre,<italic>Appendices, Illustrations &amp; Notes</italic>(Santa Monica, CA: Smart Art Press, 1999), 53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r085">
            <label>85.</label>
            <mixed-citation>A. Van Jordan, MACNOLIA (New York, W.W. Norton and Co., 2004). Jordan's 2007<italic>Quantum Lyrics</italic>also includes a bibliography in addition to its endnotes.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r086">
            <label>86.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Donnelly,<italic>The Cloud Corporation</italic>, 149–50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r087">
            <label>87.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r088">
            <label>88.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Terrance Hayes,<italic>Lighthead</italic>(New York: Penguin, 2010), 94.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r089">
            <label>89.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r090">
            <label>90.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Terrance Hayes,<italic>Hip Logic</italic>(New York: Penguin, 2002), 40.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r091">
            <label>91.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r092">
            <label>92.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r093">
            <label>93.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Hayes,<italic>Lighthead</italic>, 6–8.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r094">
            <label>94.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 11.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r095">
            <label>95.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r096">
            <label>96.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Thylias Moss, “Reconsideration of the Blackbird,” in<italic>Honey, Hush! An Anthology of African American Women's Humor</italic>, ed. Daryl Cumber Dance (New York: Norton, 1998), 122–23.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r097">
            <label>97.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I am grateful to Lindsay Reckson for pointing out this connection.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r098">
            <label>98.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mark McMorris,<italic>The Blaze of the Poui</italic>(Athens: University of Georgia Press, 2003), 13.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r099">
            <label>99.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“No firm conjecture can rest upon the mixture of Latin and English in his commentary.” Ibid., 53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r100">
            <label>100.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mark McMorris, personal correspondence (4 Dec. 2012).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r101">
            <label>101.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Peter Carey,<italic>My Life as a Fake</italic>(London: Faber and Faber, 2003), 235.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r102">
            <label>102.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mónica de la Torre,<italic>Public Domain</italic>(New York: Roof Books, 2008), 83–97.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r103">
            <label>103.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 83.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r104">
            <label>104.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Author's note cited in<italic>Against Expression</italic>, ed. Dworkin and Goldsmith, 177.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r105">
            <label>105.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Peter Trudgill,<italic>A Glossary of Sociolinguistics</italic>(Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press, 2003), 65.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r106">
            <label>106.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mónica de la Torre and Michael Wiegers, eds.,<italic>Reversible Monuments: Contemporary Mexican Poetry</italic>(Port Townsend, WA: Copper Canyon Press, 2001).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r107">
            <label>107.</label>
            <mixed-citation>De la Torre radically revised the original translation that appeared in<italic>Words Without Borders</italic>when she collected the poem in<italic>Public Domain</italic>. The first translation is conspicuously wooden in what can only be a deliberately stilted rendering. The second is more compact and makes use of regular end rhyme. The smoother translation implies that the fictional Mónica has linguistic mastery of both languages and is a more accomplished hand at translating. Mónica de la Torre, “Doubles,”<italic>Words Without Borders</italic>(2 Feb. 2006),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://wordswithoutborders.org/article/doubles">http://wordswithoutborders.org/article/doubles</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r108">
            <label>108.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Jorge Perednik, “Nueva poesía argentina durante la dictadura (1976–1983),” in<italic>Nueva poesía argentina durante la dictadura (1976–1983)</italic>, ed. Jorge Perednik (Buenos Aires: Ediciones Calle Abajo, 1992), 9 (my translation).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r109">
            <label>109.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Fondebrider, Jorge. “Treinta años de poesía argentina.” In Tres decadas de poesía argentina 1976-2006, edited by Jorge Fondebrider. Buenos Aires: Libros del Rojas, 2006) 20. My translation.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r110">
            <label>110.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“The capitalist logic of the copy” is Boon's phrase. See<italic>In Praise of Copying</italic>, 36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r111">
            <label>111.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mónica de la Torre, “Photos While U Wait,”<italic>Zoland Poetry</italic>(n.d.),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.zolandpoetry.com/featured/delatorre/featured2.html">http://www.zolandpoetry.com/featured/delatorre/featured2.html</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r112">
            <label>112.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Harriet Mullen, “Conceptual Statement,” in<italic>I'll Drown My Book: Conceptual Writing by Women</italic>(Los Angeles: Les Figues Press, 2012), ed. Bergvall et al., 93.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r113">
            <label>113.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mullen,<italic>Recyclopedia</italic>, x.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r114">
            <label>114.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 68.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r115">
            <label>115.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 67.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r116">
            <label>116.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Harryette Mullen, “Imagining the Unimagined Reader: Writing to the Unborn and Including the Excluded,” in<italic>The Cracks Between What We Are and What We Are Supposed to Be: Essays and Interviews</italic>(Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press, 2012), 6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r117">
            <label>117.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mullen,<italic>Recyclopedia</italic>, 69.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r118">
            <label>118.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Introduction to Marie Buck, “from Whole Foods,”<italic>Against Expression</italic>, ed. Dworkin and Goldsmith, 121. See also Andrew Martin, “Whole Foods Executive Used Alias,”<italic>New York Times</italic>(12 Jul. 2007),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/12/business/12foods.html">http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/12/business/12foods.html</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r119">
            <label>119.</label>
            <mixed-citation>
               <italic>Against Expression</italic>, ed. Dworkin and Goldsmith, 121.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r120">
            <label>120.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid, Loc. Cit.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r121">
            <label>121.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Martin, “Whole Foods Executive Used Alias.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r122">
            <label>122.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Wendy Walker, “Conceptual Statement,” in<italic>I'll Drown My Book</italic>, ed. Bergvall et al., 123.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r123">
            <label>123.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 121.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r124">
            <label>124.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Trevor Burnard,<italic>Mastery, Tyranny, and Desire: Thomas Thistlewood and His Slaves in the Anglo-Jamaican World</italic>(Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2004), 221.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r125">
            <label>125.</label>
            <mixed-citation>M. NourbeSe Philip,<italic>She Tries Her Tongue, Her Silence Softly Breaks</italic>(Charlottetown, PEI, Canada: Ragweed Press, 1989), 58.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r126">
            <label>126.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mark McMorris, “Performance as Critical Practice: NourbeSe Philip's ‘Discourse on the Logic of Language’” (n.d.), 182–83.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r127">
            <label>127.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Philip,<italic>She Tries Her Tongue, Her Silence Softly Breaks</italic>, 83.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r128">
            <label>128.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ibid., 84.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r129">
            <label>129.</label>
            <mixed-citation>A similar method is used by Philip Metres in his<italic>The Abu Ghraib Arias</italic>(Denver: Flying Guillotine Press, 2011) to indicate the effects of torture on articulation.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r130">
            <label>130.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Philip,<italic>She Tries Her Tongue, Her Silence Softly Breaks</italic>, 20–21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r131">
            <label>131.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Author's note cited in<italic>Against Expression</italic>, ed. Dworkin and Goldsmith, 442–43.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r132">
            <label>132.</label>
            <mixed-citation>K. Silem Mohammad, “Poems,”<italic>Wags Revue</italic>(Summer 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r133">
            <label>133.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Heather McHugh, “Three Sonnagrams by K. Silem Mohammad,”<italic>The Stranger</italic>(5 Sept. 2012),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.thestranger.com/seattle/three-sonnagrams/Content?oid=14656745">http://www.thestranger.com/seattle/three-sonnagrams/Content?oid=14656745</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r134">
            <label>134.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Author's note cited in<italic>Against Expression</italic>, ed. Dworkin and Goldsmith, 443.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r135">
            <label>135.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mary Jo Bang's translation, or transcreation of a major work of world literature,<italic>Dante Alighieri's Inferno</italic>, similarly carries with it an “entourage” of preceding translations of the<italic>Inferno</italic>. See Galvin, “Looting,”<italic>Boston Review</italic>(1 Mar. 2013),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.bostonreview.net/poetry/rachel-galvin-looting">http://www.bostonreview.net/poetry/rachel-galvin-looting</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r136">
            <label>136.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mohammad,<italic>Sonnagrams 1–20</italic>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r137">
            <label>137.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“My, You Annoy Me, Funny Daddy Roy: Yes, You of Uneasy Eye (Eye of Yore),” in Mohammad, “Poems,” 18.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r138">
            <label>138.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mohammad,<italic>Sonnagrams 1–20</italic>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r139">
            <label>139.</label>
            <mixed-citation>K. Silem Mohammad, “Sonnagrams,”<italic>1913: A Journal of Forms</italic>51 (2011): 14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r140">
            <label>140.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sarah Case, “Songs and Sonnets: A Review of Peter Gizzi's ‘Threshold Songs’ and K. Silem Mohammad's ‘Sonnagrams 1–20,'”<italic>Jacket 2</italic>(9 Sept. 2012),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://jacket2.org/reviews/songs-and-sonnets">http://jacket2.org/reviews/songs-and-sonnets</uri>. Case calls these leftover letters a “sham puzzle.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r141">
            <label>141.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Mónica de la Torre, “Landscape Bleak,” Zoland Poetry (n.d.),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.zolandpoetry.com/featured/delatorre/featured2.html">http://www.zolandpoetry.com/featured/delatorre/featured2.html</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r142">
            <label>142.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Charles Bernstein, “Manifest Aversions, Conceptual Conundrums, and Implausibly Deniable Links,”<italic>Poetry</italic>(Feb. 2009),<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.poetryfoundation.org/poetrymagazine/article/182837">http://www.poetryfoundation.org/poetrymagazine/article/182837</uri>. The quotation in the subhead for this section comes from Torre, “Photos While U Wait.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r143">
            <label>143.</label>
            <mixed-citation>De Campos,<italic>Novas</italic>, 168.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r144">
            <label>144.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bal,<italic>Quoting Caravaggio</italic>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r145">
            <label>145.</label>
            <mixed-citation>De Campos, “The Alexandrian Barbarians: Planetary Redevouring,” trans. Odile Cisneros, in<italic>Novas</italic>, 174.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
