<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">comparatist</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50013777</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Comparatist</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of North Carolina Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01957678</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15590887</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26237237</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>ESSAYS</subject>
               <subj-group>
                  <subject>RE-ORIENTALISM: GERMAN INDOLOGY STUDIES BEYOND FOUCAULT AND GADAMER</subject>
               </subj-group>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Indo-German Connections, Critical and Hermeneutical, in the First World War</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>MCGETCHIN</surname>
                  <given-names>DOUGLAS T.</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Florida Atlantic University</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>MAY 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">34</volume>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26237226</issue-id>
         <fpage>95</fpage>
         <lpage>126</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2010 Southern Comparative Literature Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26237237"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adas, Michael. “Contested Hegemony: The Great War and the Afro-Asian Assault on the Civilizing Mission Ideology.” Journal of World History 15.1 (2004): 31–63.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alter, Stephen G. William Dwight Whitney and the Science of Language. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Anand, Mulk Raj. Across the Black Waters. Bombay: Kutub Publishers, 1955. [1940] Audoin-Rouzeau, Stéphane and Annette Becker. 14–18, Understanding the Great War. 1st American ed. Trans. Catherine Temerson. New York: Hill and Wang, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bagchi, Kaushik. “An Orientalist in the Orient: Richard Garbe’s Indian Journey, 1885–1886.” Journal of World History 14 (2003): 281–325.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Balfour, Michael Leonard Graham. The Kaiser and His Times. New York: Norton, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barooah, Nirode K. Chatto: The Life and Times of an Indian Anti-Imperialist in Europe. New Delhi: Oxford University Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barooah, Nirode K. India and the Official Germany, 1886–1914. Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 1977.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bernhardi, Friedrich Adam Julius von and Allen H. Powles. Germany and the Next War. London: Edward Arnold, 1912.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bose, Arun. Indian Revolutionaries Abroad, 1905–1922, in the Background of International Developments. Patna: Bharati Bhawan, 1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bose, Arun. Indian Revolutionaries Abroad, 1905–1927: Select Documents. New Delhi: Northern Book Centre, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bose, Sugata and Ayesha Jalal. Modern South Asia: History, Culture, Political Economy. 2nd ed. New York: Routledge, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bridgham, Frederick George Thomas. The First World War as a Clash of Cultures. Rochester: Camden House, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chandra, Bipan, et al. India’s Struggle for Independence. New Delhi: Penguin, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Collett, Nigel. Butcher of Amritsar: General Reginald Dyer. London: Hambledon Continuum, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Commonwealth War Graves Commission. “India and the Commonwealth War Graves Commission.” http://www.cwgc.org/admin/files/cwgc_india.pdf (accessed September 26, 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dallmayr, Fred R. ed. Beyond Orientalism. Albany: State University of New York Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davis, Mike. Late Victorian Holocausts: El Niño Famines and the Making of the Third World. London; New York: Verso, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Deutsch-Indischen Gesellschaft. Indien in Berlin: Festschrift Der Deutsch-Indischen Gesellschaft Berlin Aus Anlass Ihres 25jährigen Jubiläums. Berlin: Tastomat, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eksteins, Modris. Rites of Spring: The Great War and the Birth of the Modern Age. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ewers, Hanns Heinz. Indien und Ich. Munich: George Müller Verlag, 1911.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy M. Aryans, Jews, Brahmins: Theorizing Authority through Myths of Identity. Albany: State University of New York Press, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Figueira, Dorothy M. Translating the Orient: The Reception of Śakuntalā in Nineteenth-Century Europe. Albany: State University of New York Press, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fraser, Thomas G. “Germany and Indian Revolution, 1914–18.” Journal of Contemporary History 12.2 (1977): 255–72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fussell, Paul. The Great War and Modern Memory. New York: Oxford University Press, 1975.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ganeshan, Vidhagiri. Das Indienbild deutscher Dichter um 1900. Bonn: Bouvier Verlag, 1975.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Glasenapp, Helmuth von. Meine Lebensreise: Menschen, Länder und Dinge, Die Ich Sah. Wiesbaden: F. A. Brockhaus, 1964.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gordon, Leonard A. Brothers against the Raj: A Biography of Indian Nationalist Leaders Sarat and Subhas Chandra Bose. New York: Columbia University Press, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Günther, Lothar and Hans-Joachim Rehmer. Inder, Indien und Berlin: 100 Jahre Begegnung Berlin und Indien. 1. Aufl. ed. Berlin: Lotos Verlag, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hagen, Gottfried. “German Heralds of Holy War: Orientalists and Applied Oriental Studies.” Comparative Studies of South Asia, Africa and the Middle East 24.2 (2004): 145–62.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Halbfass, Wilhelm. India and Europe. Albany: State University of New York Press, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Halbfass, Wilhelm. “Special Comments.” Sanskrit and ‘Orientalism’: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai. New Delhi: Manohar, 2004. 237–44.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hay, Stephen. Sources of Indian Tradition. 2nd ed. Vol. 2: Modern India and Pakistan. New York: Columbia University Press, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herling, Bradley L. The German Gita: Hermeneutics and Discipline in the German Reception of Indian Thought, 1778–1831. New York: Routledge, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hopkirk, Peter. Like Hidden Fire: The Plot to Bring Down the British Empire. New York: Kodansha International, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inden, Ronald. Imagining India. Cambridge: Basil Blackwell, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jelavich, Peter. “German Culture in the Great War.” European Culture in the Great War: The Arts, Entertainment, and Propaganda, 1914–1918. Eds. Aviel Roshwald and Richard Stites. Studies in the Social and Cultural History of Modern Warfare. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1999. 32–57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Joll, James and Gordon Martel. The Origins of the First World War. 3rd ed. New York: Pearson Longman, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Keegan, John. The First World War. New York: Vintage, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">King, Richard. Orientalism and Religion: Postcolonial Theory, India and “The Mystic East.” New York: Routledge, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kontje, Todd. German Orientalisms. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kopf, David. “Hermeneutics versus History.” Orientalism: A Reader. Ed. Alexander Lyon Macfie. New York: New York University Press, 2000. 194–207.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kulke, Hermann and Dietmar Rothermund. A History of India. 4th ed. New York: Routledge, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leifer, Walter. India and the Germans: 500 Years of Indo-German Contacts. Bombay: Shakuntala Pub. House, 1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marchand, Suzanne. German Orientalism in the Age of Empire: Religion, Race, and Scholarship. New York: Cambridge University Press, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marston, Daniel and Chandar S. Sundaram. A Military History of India and South Asia: From the East India Company to the Nuclear Era. Westport: Praeger Security International, 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Masani, Zareer. Indian Tales of the Raj. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maugham, W. Somerset. Ashenden, or: The British Agent. New York: Doubleday, Doran and Co., 1941.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. Indology, Indomania, Orientalism: Ancient India’s Rebirth in Modern Germany. Madison: Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 2009.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. “Into the Centre of Sanskrit Study: Ancient Indian Studies and German Culture in Berlin and Leipzig in the Nineteenth Century.” Sanskrit and ‘Orientalism’: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai. New Delhi: Manohar, 2004. 197–229.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGetchin, Douglas T. “The Whitney-Müller Conflict and Indo-German Connections.” Mapping Channels Between Ganges and Rhein: German-Indian Cross-Cultural Relations. Eds.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jörg Esleben, Christina Kraenzle, and Sukanya Kulkarni. Newcastle upon Tyne, England: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2008. 29–50.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jörg Esleben, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai, eds., Sanskrit and ‘Orientalism’: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. New Delhi: Manohar, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Murti, Kamakshi. India: The Seductive and Seduced “Other” of German Orientalism. Westport: Greenwood Press, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref54">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Naoroji, Dadabhai. Poverty and Un-British Rule in India. 1st Indian ed. Delhi: Publications Division, Ministry of Information and Broadcasting, Government of India, 1962.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref55">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Northrup, David. “Migration from Africa, Asia, and the South Pacific.” The Oxford History of the British Empire: The Nineteenth Century. Ed. Andrew Porter. New York: Oxford University Press, 1999. 88–100.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref56">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Omissi, David E. Indian Voices of the Great War: Solders’ Letters, 1914–18. New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref57">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Orwell, George. Burmese Days. New York: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1974.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref58">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Otto, Rudolf. Die Urgestalt der Bhagavad-Gita. Tübingen: Mohr, 1934.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref59">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Otto, Rudolf and Frank Hugh Foster. India’s Religion of Grace and Christianity Compared and Contrasted. New York: Macmillan, 1930.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref60">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Otto, Rudolf, Bertha L. Bracey, and Richenda C. Payne. Mysticism East and West: A Comparative Analysis of the Nature of Mysticism. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1932.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref61">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Otto, Rudolf. West-Östliche Mystik. Gotha: L. Klotz, 1926. Papen, Franz von. Memoirs. Trans. Brian Connell. New York: Dutton, 1953.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref62">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pollock, Sheldon. “Indology, Power, and the Case of Germany.” Orientalism: A Reader. Ed. Alexander Lyon Macfie. New York: New York University Press, 2000. 302–23.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref63">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Poley, Jared. “Everything is India: Hanns Heinz Ewers, Indology and Women.” Sanskrit and ‘Orientalism’: Indology and Comparative Linguistics in Germany, 1750–1958. Eds. Douglas T. McGetchin, Peter K. J. Park, and Damodar SarDesai. New Delhi: Manohar, 2004. 361–82.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref64">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reventlow, Ernst zu. Indien: Seine Bedeutung für Grossbritannien, Deutschland und die Zukunft der Welt. Berlin: E. S. Mittler und Sohn, 1917.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref65">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricoeur, Paul. “Hermeneutics and the Critique of Ideology.” Hermeneutics and the Human Sciences. Ed. and trans. John B. Thompson. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993. 63–100.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref66">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Said, Edward. Orientalism. New York: Vintage, 1978.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref67">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Said, Edward. “Orientalism Reconsidered.” Orientalism: A Reader. Ed. Alexander Lyon Macfie. New York: New York University Press, 2000. 345–61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref68">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schwab, Raymond. The Oriental Renaissance: Europe’s Rediscovery of India and the East, 1680–1880. Trans. Gene Patterson-Black and Victor Reinking. New York: Columbia University Press, 1984. [1950].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref69">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sengupta, Indra. From Salon to Discipline: State, University and Indology in Germany, 1821–1914. Beiträge zur Südasienforschung. Bd. 198. Heidelberg: Ergon Verlag, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref70">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stache-Rosen, Valentina. German Indologists: Biographies of Scholars in Indian Studies Writing in German; with a Summary on Indology in German Speaking Countries. New Delhi: Statesman Press (Max Mueller Bhavan), 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref71">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Strobel, Margaret. White Women and the Second British Empire. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1991.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref72">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sumner, Ian. The Indian Army 1914–1947. Oxford: Osprey Publishing, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref73">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">VanKoski, Susan Christina. “The Indian Ex-soldier from the Eve of the First World War to Independence and Partition: A Study of Provisions for Ex-Soldiers and Ex-Soldiers’ Role in Indian National Life.” Ph.D. diss. Columbia University, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref74">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Washbrook, D. A. “India, 1818–1860: The Two Faces of Colonialism.” The Nineteenth Century. Ed. Andrew Porter. Vol. 3 in The Oxford History of the British Empire. New York: Oxford University Press, 1999. 395–421.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref75">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Welch, David. Germany, Propaganda, and Total War, 1914–1918: The Sins of Omission. New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref76">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williams, John Frank. Corporal Hitler and the Great War 1914–1918: The List Regiment. London; New York: Frank Cass, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref77">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zantop, Susanne. Colonial Fantasies: Conquest, Family, and Nation in Precolonial Germany, 1770–1870. Durham: Duke University Press, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
