<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">dialectica</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50010949</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Dialectica</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Blackwell-Wiley Publishing</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00122017</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">17468361</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">42969056</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Is there Irrationality in the Existence of a Plurality of Philosophical Theories</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Ruth Barcan</given-names>
                  <surname>Marcus</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1985</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>39</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40115211</issue-id>
         <fpage>321</fpage>
         <lpage>328</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/42969056"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>In this paper some claims of Professor Ricoeur are challenged. (1) It is pointed out on historical grounds that counter to Professor Ricoeur's claim, most past philosophies are displaced, or ignored. The surviving canon is small and very selective. There is, therefore, substantial agreement on the large corpus which is rejected. (2) It is also argued that Professor Ricoeur's contrast between philosophy and the sciences is too sharp since in the history of modern sciences there are always conflicting theories existing in parallel. However, it is the case that in philosophy standards of "acceptability" are looser and not the rigorous ones of science. A philosophical theory may be appreciated for the problems it discloses, the richness and subtlety of its arguments, its strategies and the like despite acknowledged failings. Appreciation of incompatible theories is not irrational. (3) The claim is rejected that the seeming irrationality is resolved by viewing each system as wholly autonomous. (4) The apparent restriction of philosophy by Professor Ricoeur to global systems is also questioned. L'auteur conteste quelques affirmations du prof. Ricoeur. (1) Elle montre, sur des bases historiques, que beaucoup de philosophies passées sont écartées ou ignorées. Le canon retenu est petit et très sélectif. Il y a donc un accord substantiel quant au vaste corpus qui est rejeté. (2) Elle montre aussi que le contraste que le professeur Ricoeur établit entre philosophie et sciences est trop abrupt, puisqu'il y a toujours eu, dans l'histoire de la science moderne, des théories opposées qui coexistaient. Toutefois, il est vrai qu'en philosophie, les standards d' «acceptabilité» sont plus lâches et diffèrent de ceux, plus rigoureux, de la science. Une philosophie peut être appréciée pour les problèmes qu'elle pose, pour la richesse et la subtilité de ses arguments, ses stratégies ou d'autres choses semblables et ceci en dépit de ses insuffisances notoires. Il n'est pas irrationnel d'apprécier des théories incompatibles. (3) Elle rejette la thèse selon laquelle le fait de considérer chaque système comme totalement autonome supprime l'irrationalité. (4) Elle conteste enfin la restriction — apparemment faite par le professeur Ricoeur — de la philosophie à des systèmes globaux. Es werden einige Behauptungen von Professor Ricoeur in Frage gestellt. (1) Es wird gezeigt, dass aus historischen Gründen entgegen Ricoeurs Behauptung die meisten vergangenen Philosophien tatsächlich verdrängt oder ignoriert werden. Der überlebende Kanon ist gering und selektiv. Deshalb gibt es eine wichtige Übereinstimmung hinsichtlich des grossen Korpus', der verworfen wird. (2) Es wird argumentiert, dass Ricoeur den Kontrast zwischen der Philosophie und den Wissenschaften zu extrem sieht, da in der Geschichte der modernen Wissenschaften immer rivalisierende Theorien nebeneinander existiert haben. Es stimmt allerdings, dass die Massstäbe für Akzeptierbarkeit in der Philosophie lockerer sind als die strengen der Wisschenschaft. Eine philosophische Theorie mag wegen der Probleme, die sie entwickelt, wegen des Reichtums und der Subtilität ihrer Argumente, ihrer Strategien etc. gewürdigt werden, obschon sie anerkanntermassen versagt hat. Die Würdigung unvereinbarer Theorien ist nicht irrational. (3) Die scheinbare Irrationalität kann nicht dadurch aufgelöst werden, dass jedes System als völlig autonom betrachtet wird. (4) Es wird ebenfalls Ricoeurs Einschränkung der Philosophie auf globale Systeme in Frage gestellt.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d13744e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d13744e114" publication-type="other">
P. Feyerabend, "How to Defend Society Against Science," Scientific Revolutions edited
by I. Hacking, Oxford, 1981, p. 60.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d13744e124a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d13744e131" publication-type="other">
L. Laudan, "A Problem Solving Approach to Scientific Progress," ibid, p. 153.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d13744e138a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d13744e145" publication-type="other">
Philipp Franck, Modern Science and its Philosophy, Prentice Hall, 1957, P. 191 for ref-
erences and texts.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d13744e155a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d13744e162" publication-type="other">
Ibid, p. 188.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d13744e170a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d13744e177" publication-type="other">
Philosophy and the Mirror of Nature, Princeton, 1981 p. 168.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
