<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/651708</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR1277</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Last Night: Ritualized Violence and the Last Instructions of 9/11<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Margo</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Kitts</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Hawaii Pacific University</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>July 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>90</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>651998</issue-id>
         <fpage>283</fpage>
         <lpage>312</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2010 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/651708"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>*</label>
               <p>Hector Avalos invited my first draft of this essay for a regional American Academy of Religion meeting in Chicago in 2006. I developed it further because he, Mark Juergensmeyer, Eftychia Stavrianopoulou, Wendy Doniger, Scott Noegel, Pamela Stewart, and a few other colleagues encouraged it, in contrast to those who were offended by its comparative premises. My gratitude to them and also to the editors and critical reviewers for the<italic>Journal of Religion</italic>, who made me aware of a vaster literature on suicide terrorism, which I have summarized in the notes.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>For the student of religion and war, the last instructions to the suicide bombers of 9/11 offer little that is new. The purification of warriors, prayer, oath swearing, even the prebattle slaughter of victims—here ostensibly the flight attendants<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>—may be found in the preparations for religious wars from ancient times, especially in Western traditions. Comparable behaviors performed in comparable situations suggest comparable ritual logic. This essay will explore the ritual logic in the last instructions, focusing on the rituals of the last night.</p>
      <p>For support, my essay relies on the classical ritual theory of Stanley Tambiah to grasp the persuasive force of the instructions as drawn from the iconic reconfiguration of primordial paradigms understood to be established at the founding of the Islamic order. Relying on theories by James Fernandez, Paul Ricoeur, and Roy Rappaport, I argue that the metaphorical transformation of these ritual participants into players in primordial dramas is accomplished through ritual strategies that heighten the communicational register and bind the actors to a dense metaphorical domain. Further, I attempt to show that some elements of the instructions for the last night add up to a highly sanctified “liturgical order,” although this notion is modified slightly from that of Roy Rappaport, who coined the term.</p>
      <p>It bears emphasizing that no knowledgeable person considers the 9/11 bombers or these instructions as representing the heart of Islam, the word itself connoting peace and submission. One of the aims of this essay is to show, rather, that the ritualized dimensions of these instructions reflect relatively common behaviors found also within Christian, biblical, and even older warring traditions.</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>Bruce Lincoln,<italic>Holy Terrors</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2003), 10. See discussion of this act by Tilman Seidensticker in “The Instructions Given in the Spiritual Manual and Their Particular Interpretation of Islam,” in<italic>The 9/11 Handbook</italic>, ed. Hans G. Kippenberg and Tilman Seidensticker (London: Equinox, 2006), 19–27, esp. 25.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>Ritual Performances and Liturgical Orders</title>
         <p>Catherine Bell, Valerio Valeri, James Fernandez, Roy Rappaport, and Stanley Tambiah are just a handful of established theorists who have promoted the idea that the performances we call “rituals” have as their final effect a form of communication. For Stanley Tambiah, ritual performances communicate certain paradigms of behavior that are recognized by an audience at an iconic level. As Tambiah sees it, pattern recognition is the very foundation of ritual communication, and the patterns that rituals communicate may be understood as “iconic analogues” of primordial acts. By “iconic analogue,” Tambiah appears to rely on American philosopher Charles Peirce: an icon is a sign bearing a relationship to an object in the way that a map bears a relationship to a territory. The territory is fuller than the map, but one can understand the map as lifted, as it were, from the territory but referring back to it and indeed invoking it<italic>pars pro toto</italic>. Some ritual performances, then, lift a kind of iconic analogue from actions conceived as occurring primordially, invoking them<italic>pars pro toto</italic>.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>
         </p>
         <p>However, ritual performances also may recast iconic analogues to fit different semantic fields or new metaphorical domains. Tambiah builds on Michelle Rosaldo’s suggestion that magical spells, for instance, acquire their effectiveness by invoking images from “a number of diverse areas of experience and that these images, in turn, are regrouped and organized in terms of a small set of culturally significant and contextually desirable themes.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>On the basis of Tambiah and Rosaldo, we shall envision ritualization as a reinvigoration of primordial events within newer metaphoric domains. Both the ritual participant and the witnessing audience recognize the primordial event in its newer constellation and respond to the ritual in terms of “pattern recognition and configurational awareness,” essentially as one might respond to an abstract work of art.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>This recognition and response within newer, shifted metaphorical domains will have obvious relevance to 9/11 instructions’ references to ancient battles and the perceived reinvigoration of a seventh‐century war on Meccan polytheists.</p>
         <p>Not surprisingly, then, performers of rituals may undergo various metaphorical shifts in identity, which rely on a play of images associated with underlying paradigms. As James Fernandez sees it, ritual performances accomplish movement in the way a performer sees herself or himself, similar to the way that a metaphor accomplishes a reenvisioning of one thing in terms of another.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>The semantic movement tends to be from the obscure and inchoate in the subject (or “tenor”) to the concrete and ostensive in the metaphoric predicate (the “vehicle”). While this metaphorical switch may appear to narrow the identity of the performer, at the same time the ritual may invoke an entire network of associations that thickens the experience and also highlights different domains of experience for the performer, connecting him to a fecund dimension of cultural imagination. Paul Ricoeur has shown how such dimensions may be bound to the comprehension of a metaphor.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Finally, some ritual performances demonstrate communicational features that up the ante, as it were, stressing a heightened performance register. Roy Rappaport’s “liturgical orders” is the germane concept here.</p>
         <p>Liturgical orders are a subset of ritual performances that are characterized, first, by their punctilious and sacrosanct qualities and, second, by the way their performances instantiate the conventions that they represent.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>Their punctilious and sacrosanct qualities are signaled by a high degree of formality in performance. The degree of formality may be gauged by the detailed sequence of microadjusting ritual steps undertaken by the ritual actor. Recitation, purification, and continuous prayer are a few examples in the 9/11 instructions. Each microadjusting act becomes increasingly persuasive for the participant, helping ultimately to cultivate a particular ritual persona. According to Rappaport, the high formality and fastidious detail of such microadjustments are proportional to the degree of constraint required for the individual entering into the convention established by the ritual. That is, the more likely people are to violate the convention established by the ritual, the more fixed, detailed, even exaggerated will be the ritual form. The fastidiousness and exaggeration help to transpose the ritual action to a different symbolic plane wherein one might perform acts deemed unsuitable outside of it.</p>
         <p>An illustration—its relevance will become clear—is oath making. Oaths are often instantiated by extraordinary ritual acts, beginning with a fastidious sequence of ritualized microadjustments and culminating with sensational commissive gestures, such as, in ancient times, cutting the throats of sacrificial victims and then calling upon cosmic forces to visit the same painful death upon oath breakers.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>Oaths are meant precisely to thwart an inherent instability in human commitments and so tend to be instantiated at the highest end of the formal spectrum and with the most fixed of ritual behaviors. The fixity is an apparent fence against deceit. The formality and fixity of performance conspire to make the oath, and the consequences for breaking it, extramundane.</p>
         <p>Oaths are a perfect example also of the second feature of Rappaport’s liturgical orders, which is that they instantiate conventions by their very performance. That is, as a ritual act the oath does more than just communicate; it actually brings a convention into existence by its performance, and compels recognition of the authority of the convention it instantiates. Rappaport uses the example of dancing the Kaiko among the Maring: dancing the Kaiko brings into effect a commitment to fight beside one’s host in the next war. The dance is more commissive than just saying one will fight, because, unlike words, which are retractable, ephemeral, and potentially ambiguous, dancing the oath is substantial and visceral—a public act that permits little ambiguity, because the Maring know precisely the convention it establishes. The oath is not reversible: its commitment holds regardless of any personal ambivalence or internal infelicity on the part of the dancer. Because it establishes a commitment by its very performance, the oath‐making ritual is considered a metaperformative act. It instantiates the oath at the same time that it commits its performer to upholding it.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>Stanley J. Tambiah, “A Performative Approach to Ritual,”<italic>Proceedings of the British Academy</italic>, vol. 65 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1979), 37. See also the discussion in Roy Rappaport,<italic>Religion and Ritual in the Making of Humanity</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999), 462 n. 1.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Michelle Zimbalist Rosaldo, “It’s All Uphill: The Creative Metaphors of Ilongot Magical Spells,” in<italic>Sociocultural Dimensions of Language Use</italic>, ed. Mary Sanches and B. G. Blount (New York: Academic Press, 1975), 178, quoted in Tambiah, “Performative Approach,” 138.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Tambiah, “Performative Approach,” 34.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Ritual performance effects a “strategic predication upon an inchoate pronoun (an I, a you, a we, a they) which makes a movement and leads to performance”; see James Fernandez, “The Performance of Ritual Metaphors,” in<italic>The Social Use of Metaphor</italic>, ed. J. David Sapir and J. Christopher Crocker (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1977), 2.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Paul Ricoeur, “The Metaphorical Process as Cognition, Imagination, and Feeling,” in<italic>Philosophical Perspectives on Metaphor</italic>, ed. Mark Johnson (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1981), 228–47.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Rappaport,<italic>Religion and Ritual</italic>, 24, 428.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Margo Kitts,<italic>Sanctified Violence in Homeric Society</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005), 115–56.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>J. L. Austin's<italic>How to Do Things with Words</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1975) is the classical source for a discussion of commissive ritual acts. For a summary, see Kitts,<italic>Sanctified Violence</italic>, 27–28.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>The Final Instructions for the Last Night</title>
         <sec id="sc2.1">
            <title>The Text</title>
            <p>Keeping in mind this terse summary of ritual communication and liturgical orders, let us turn to a translation of the final instructions. These are the handwritten instructions found in three copies: the first was in Mohamed el‐Amir Atta’s luggage, which was retained by security agents at the airport in Portland, Maine (FBI document K 70 0109 17003 HC); the second was found in the car left by Nawah al‐Hazmi at Dulles Airport outside Washington, DC (FBI document 0109 18019 K 655); and remnants of the third were found at the crash site of United Airlines flight 93 in Stony Creek Township, Pennsylvania.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>It is presumed that copies were disseminated to the other participants as well.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>The opening sections of the final instructions are disputed.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>The version translated by David Cook, relying on the<italic>New York Times</italic>, is taken as authoritative here.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>Some differences of English wording are offered also from the translation by Kippenberg and Seidensticker.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>
            </p>
            <p>The text is extraordinarily repetitive, for reasons that will become clear. Hence what follows is not an analysis of the entire text but rather of selected instructions from the last night. These are examined in differing depths.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn11">
                  <label>10</label>
                  <p>Hans G. Kippenberg, “Background to the Spiritual Manual,” in Kippenberg and Seidensticker,<italic>9/11 Handbook</italic>, 1–3.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn12">
                  <label>11</label>
                  <p>Kanan Makiya and Hassan Mneimneh, “Manual for a ‘Raid,’”<italic>New York Review of Books</italic>49, no. 1 (January 17, 2002): 18–22, at 18; Hans Kippenberg, “`Consider That It Is a Raid on the Path of God': The Spiritual Manual of the Attackers of 9/11,”<italic>Numen</italic>52, no. 1 (2005): 29–58, at 37–38. The authorial source has been disputed. Abdul Aziz al‐Omari, Mohamed Atta, and Ayman al Zawahiri all have been suggested as individual authors. Terry McDermott (<italic>Perfect Soldiers</italic>[New York: HarperCollins, 2005], 232) identifies al‐Omari in convincing treatment, which supports some original information gathered by Yosri Fouda and Nick Fielding (<italic>Masterminds of Terror: The Truth behind the Most Devastating Terrorist Attack the World Has Ever Seen</italic>[Edinburgh: Main Stream Press, 2003]). See Kippenberg (“Consider That It Is a Raid,” 30–35) on the problem of authorship and specifically the likelihood that the author was not an educated Islamic cleric.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn13">
                  <label>12</label>
                  <p>The dispute regards a fifth page of Mohamed Atta’s version of the document, which contains two sections conceivable as either a preface or an addendum to the standard document:<list>
                        <list-item>
                           <label>1.</label>
                           <p>In the name of God the most merciful, the most compassionate. … In the name of God, of myself, and of my family. … I pray to you God to forgive me from all my sins, to allow me to glorify you in every possible way.</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                           <label>2.</label>
                           <p>Remember the battle of the Prophet … against the infidels, as he went on building the Islamic state.</p>
                        </list-item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Kippenberg and Seidensticker (<italic>9/11 Handbook</italic>, 8–9) point out that the document published by the FBI as K 70 0109 17003 HC lacks these sections, and they doubt the authenticity of the first section. Makiyah and Mneimneh (“Manual for a ‘Raid,’” 18) see the first verse of the fifth page as invoking Islamic heritage and thus not surprising. The<italic>New York Times</italic>version reproduced in Lincoln’s<italic>Holy Terrors</italic>(93–98) included it as a preface, as did the<italic>Washington Post</italic>(September 28, 2001, A18). David Cook (<italic>Understanding Jihad</italic>[Berkeley: University of California Press, 2005], 233 n. 23) points out that a document with such a high religious tenor would be expected to begin with an invocation of God. Mohamed Atta’s fifth page approximates such an invocation, but Cook’s translation does not include those two sections.</p>
                  <p>Kippenberg and Seidensticker may be correct in seeing the first verse, which places the head of family on a par with the god, as shocking from an orthodox Islamic perspective. It is nonetheless a logical extension of the caretaking ethos of Islam generally and the very ethos that bin Laden attempted to promote for himself in his videotaped address of October 7, 2001, wherein he represented the 9/11 bombing as defensive and retaliative for Palestinians and Iraqi children who were indirect victims of U.S. foreign policy (app. C in Lincoln,<italic>Holy Terrors</italic>, 102–3):<list>
                        <list-item>
                           <label>3.</label>
                           <p>God has blessed a group of vanguard Muslims, the forefront of Islam, to destroy America. May God bless them and allot them a supreme place in heaven, for he is the only one capable and entitled to do so. When those have stood in defense of their weak children, their brothers and sisters in Palestine and other Muslim nations, the whole world went into an uproar, the infidels followed by the hypocrites.</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                           <label>4.</label>
                           <p>A million innocent children are dying at this time as we speak, killed in Iraq without any guilt. We hear no denunciation, we hear no edict from the hereditary rulers. In these days, Israeli tanks rampage across Palestine, in Ramallah, Rafah and Beit Jala and many other parts of the land of Islam [dar al Islam], and we do not hear anyone raising his voice or reacting.</p>
                        </list-item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn14">
                  <label>13</label>
                  <p>The original text (September 28–29, 2001) may be found at<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.nytimes.com/library/national/092801letter.htm"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.nytimes.com/library/national/092801letter.htm</ext-link>. See n. 88 in David Cook, “Suicide Attacks or `Martyrdom Operations' in Contemporary<italic>Jihad</italic>Literature,” n.d.,<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.ozlanka.com/commentary/jihad.htm"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.ozlanka.com/commentary/jihad.htm</ext-link>; passages cited from the final instructions are from this version unless otherwise noted.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn15">
                  <label>14</label>
                  <p>Tilman Seidensticker, Albreecht Fuess, Moez Khalfaoui, and Hans G. Kippenberg, “Translation of the Spiritual Manual,” in Kippenberg and Seidensticker,<italic>9/11 Handbook</italic>, 11–18.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.2">
            <title>Introduction: Setting the Tone</title>
            <p content-type="epigraph">
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>The Last Night. He said: one of the Companions said: the Messenger of God ordered us to recite it previous to a raid, and we recited it, took booty and were safe.</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>According to David Cook, this is unlikely to be the beginning of the document, which, being of high religious tenor, would be expected to begin with the<italic>basmallah</italic>(in the name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>The document’s religious tenor is unmistakable because of its repeated references to holy conventions and ancient models and by the fact that it lacks a political rationale for the bombing, aside from an oblique reference to the West and those enamored with it as having drunk of Hell.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>Despite the missing<italic>basmallah</italic>, the introductory section is effective in establishing religious tone. Three references help to accomplish this: the raid, the recitation, and the rather complex model of the Prophet’s life.</p>
            <p>
               <italic>The raid.—</italic>First, given the exalted role of the Prophet in establishing the early Islamic theocracy—a veritable golden age of justice and piety, as seen by most Muslims—invoking him and the companions helps to cast a contemporary ritual performance into a primordial paradigm. The striking context is the raid (<italic>ghazwa</italic>in Arabic).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>The prophet and his companions spent a decade in continuous raiding during the state‐building period of the early Islamic polity (from 622, when he fled the city of Mecca, to 632, when he died, having achieved control over it). A custom among early nomads, raiding was redefined by the early Islamic community, who practiced raiding initially against the polytheistic purveyors of goods to Mecca, with the intention of disrupting corrupt trading caravans and of benefiting the dedicated religious community. Economically speaking, these missions effectively enabled the establishment of the first Muslim state. Invoking the raid here replicates the mission as occurring at an acme of mythical history, which sanctifies the mission as imitative of that glorious age.</p>
            <p>In the scheme of traditional ritual analysis described above, invoking this golden age is typical of ritual performances; they reflect ur‐conventions transhistorically but through the prism of the immediate situation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">18</xref>Reference to the<italic>ghazwa</italic>thickens the significance of the 9/11 event, binding it to a fertile reservoir of cultural imagination. It also refashions the ritual actors as contemporary replicas of companions to the Prophet. The references to booty and safety support this, as booty and safety could not possibly have had tangible significance to ritual actors dedicated to death by suicide.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">19</xref>
            </p>
            <p>
               <italic>The recitation.—</italic>A second reference is the command to recite. This is three times reified, by a “he,” by a companion, and by the Prophet: “He said: one of the Companions said: the Messenger of God ordered us to recite it previous to a raid, and we recited it.” Presuming that the participants themselves recited it too, another recitation is enjoined. Beyond the issue of mythical prototypes,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">20</xref>there is the issue of ritual and aural form.</p>
            <p>It is difficult to imagine that any recitation would occur at the level of everyday language. Rather, it probably was uttered at the level of ritual oratory, that is, in a stressed register akin to a chant or prayer. High register and marked rhythm have long been recognized as components of ritual persuasion. Tambiah describes the “hyper‐regular surface structure of ritual language,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">21</xref>and the way that modulations of speed, loudness, and rhythm can foreground certain messages, “telescoping or fusing them into an amalgam that is given motion and direction by compelling illocutionary words of command and persuasion or declaration.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">22</xref>Bloch too observes the intangible sense of power communicated through the stressed register created by fixed speech and gesture,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">23</xref>and others have studied the rhythmic drivers within ritual performance and their effects on neurophysiology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">24</xref>Such studies support this recitation as powerful in the way of rhythmic or musical performances, which exert pressure on bodies and persons and render the underlying messages difficult to resist.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">25</xref>
            </p>
            <p>The recitation might be compared to the musical performances that commonly launch battle rituals. Von Rad cites musical performance as a first step in mustering troops for biblical holy war, a step that sanctioned the battle as God’s.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">26</xref>Consider Joshua and companions sounding trumpets as they circled Jericho for days before the attack (Joshua 6) or Gideon’s blasting of the trumpet before battle with the Midianites (Judg. 7:16).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">27</xref>Christian crusaders on the way to the holy lands ostensibly were roused by battle hymns,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">28</xref>contemporary equivalents of which (e.g., “Onward, Christian Soldiers,” “Joshua Fought the Battle”) are familiar. We know that jihad songs were popular entertainment at the al Quds mosque of Hamburg, where three of the four 9/11 pilots congregated.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">29</xref>Three battle songs performed at a wedding of one of its members are caught on tape.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">30</xref>In fact, the second stage of the last instructions includes an apparent poetic refrain, conceivably from such a song:<disp-quote>
                  <p>Smiling towards the face of the perished one (dead): O youthYou are coming to the Gardens of Eternity.</p>
               </disp-quote>Against all this, it is not difficult to imagine the rousing effects generated when the 9/11 ritual actors recited in a stressed register verses understood to be transmitted from the Prophet and companions since ancient times. Whether those verses were sung, chanted in rhythm, or simply recited in prayer, their perception must have been enhanced also by ongoing traditions of Quranic recitation in the Islamic world, wherein the aural beauty of scripture is a common delight.</p>
            <p>
               <italic>The model of the Prophet.—</italic>Third, it should be noted that invoking the early wars and the Prophet’s life as a sunna (exemplar) is not simple in Islam, not least because the Prophet is said to have received successively more militant revelations that, some theologians claim, abrogated earlier, more pacifist revelations on fighting. The net result, however, is ambiguous. The stage‐four warring injunction, as is well known, is to fight the unbeliever wherever he is found (Quran 2:191, 9:5). Yet conjoining verses specify that if he desists, then Allah is forgiving and merciful (2:192; see also 9:5, 8:61), and one should not show hostility except to oppressors (2:193). We know that in historical practice the Prophet entered into alliances with unbelieving neighbors and was commanded to honor pacts with them as long as the honor was reciprocal (9:4, 9:7–9). Other Quranic verses permit discernment of differences among unbelievers and impose limits on fighting. For instance, there are the famous injunction not to forcibly proselytize (2:256) and the mandates to offer protection to idolaters who request it (9:6), not to transgress limits while fighting (2:190), to accept offers of peace (8:61 and 4:90), and to fight the idolaters with proportionality (9:36 during the sacred months, 16:126–27 at any time: “If you have to retaliate, do so to the extent you have been injured, but if you forbear, that is best for those who bear with fortitude. Endure with patience”).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">31</xref>Then there are the different responses of the Prophet, as sunna, to polytheists as opposed to hypocrites. Although both are to be treated sternly by God (48:6), the Prophet himself is said to have carried out jihad (struggle) against polytheists by fighting and jihad against hypocrites by preaching and argument.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">32</xref>Nonetheless, the Quran leaves it to God to judge (30:42–46). Even in the eyes of Sayyid Qutb, grandfather of twentieth‐century Islamic revivalism, Muslims have an obligation to eliminate all authorities besides the Quran, in order to allow people to come freely to God.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">33</xref>Considering all this, it is obvious that the last instructions invoke sunna quite freely, as if the Prophet's actions were situated plainly in military force.</p>
            <p>Ritually speaking, since the Prophet spent a decade in armed struggle, invoking his warring years as the model true Muslims are to emulate is a clear example of making primordial paradigms inform the actions of twenty‐first‐century warriors, who see themselves as reinvigorating a sacred call within contemporary metaphorical domains. Yet the apparent contradiction between Mohammad’s sunna as a warrior and the above‐referenced Quranic calls for mercy to suppliants and acceptance of terms of peace supports the truism that what happens on the ritual stage, in this case the domain of war, can be made to assume a more compelling register than what happens off stage, in the domain of peace. As we shall see, numerous microadjusting ritual features instantiate this ritual stage, and highly selective legends from Islamic history become figurative props for it.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn16">
                  <label>15</label>
                  <p>Cook,<italic>Understanding Jihad</italic>, 233, esp. n. 23.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn17">
                  <label>16</label>
                  <p>Those “who are impressed by the civilization of the West, those who have drunk of hell; it has given them to drink together with cold water (?), and they have feared its weak and perishing abilities … but do not fear them and fear Me; if you are true believers!” [3:175] (Cook, “Suicide Attacks”). As Seidensticker (Kippenberg and Seidensticker,<italic>9/11 Handbook</italic>, 22) points out, “There is no allusion to a collective humiliation of Muslims, which is often considered the principal source of Islamist rage; nor is any attempt made to console the perpetrators for the killing of thousands of civilians. The explanation seems to be that both the reason and the justification were self‐evident to the addressees of the Spiritual Manual.” Notably, bin Laden’s letters provide that rationale, reproduced in part in note 12. Makiya and Mneimneh (“Manual for a ‘Raid,'” 18) suggest that the lack of situational detail may be an attempt to eliminate clues about the intended target, should the document fall into the wrong hands.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn18">
                  <label>17</label>
                  <p>On this custom, see Kippenberg, “Consider That It Is a Raid”; and Makiya and Mneimneh, “Manual for a ‘Raid,’” 18.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn19">
                  <label>18</label>
                  <p>For a concise summary of theories of ritual persuasion, including the ritual texture generated by a particular string of spoken words, see Margo Kitts, “<italic>Poinē</italic>as a Ritual Leitmotif in the<italic>Iliad</italic>,” in<italic>Ritual Dynamics and the Science of Ritual</italic>, vol. 3, ed. Axel Michaels (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2010), 11–34.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn20">
                  <label>19</label>
                  <p>I see no way that all of them could not have known they were about to die. Bin Laden’s tape‐recorded conversation (released by the Department of Defense on December 13, 2001) supports this: “The brothers, who conducted the operation, all they knew was that they have a martyrdom operation” (quoted in Makiya and Mneimneh, “Manual for a ‘Raid,’” 18). For a summary of revivalist thinking in Islamic activism, see John Esposito,<italic>Unholy War</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 2003); and Cook,<italic>Understanding Jihad</italic>, esp. chap. 6, 128–62.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn21">
                  <label>20</label>
                  <p>According to Cook (“Suicide Attacks,” n. 90), “This tradition is a paraphrase of Ibn Hanbal,<italic>Musnad</italic>, vol. 5, pp. 248–49, 255, 258, and apparently refers to something cited on the previous page (it is also marked off by a line from the material below it). It is not clear, however, what `it' is (most probably a<italic>sura</italic>or a verse, since according to the gender it cannot be the Quran). In this tradition, a person came to the Prophet asking that he pray to God for martyrdom, but the Prophet only prayed that he be granted booty and safety.”</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn22">
                  <label>21</label>
                  <p>Tambiah,<italic>Performative Approach</italic>, 164.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn23">
                  <label>22</label>
                  <p>Ibid., 137–38. On musicality and rhythm in ritual persuasion, Radcliffe Brown (quoted in Tambiah,<italic>Performative Approach</italic>, 113) wrote: “Any marked rhythm exercises on those submitted to its influence a constraint, impelling them to yield to it and to permit it to direct and regulate the movements of body and even those of the mind.”</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn24">
                  <label>23</label>
                  <p>Maurice Bloch,<italic>Political Language and Oratory in Traditional Society</italic>(London: Academy Press, 1975), 1–28, esp. 6–13.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn25">
                  <label>24</label>
                  <p>Candice S. Alcorta and Richard Sosis, “Ritual, Emotion, and Sacred Symbols,”<italic>Hu</italic>
                     <italic>man Nature</italic>16, no. 4 (2005): 323–59, esp. 336,<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.anth.uconn.edu/faculty/sosis/publications/Alcorta_Sosis,_Signals_and_rituals_of_humans_and_animals.pdf"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.anth.uconn.edu/faculty/sosis/publications/Alcorta_Sosis,_Signals_and_rituals_of_humans_and_animals.pdf</ext-link>.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn26">
                  <label>25</label>
                  <p>Consider recent thinking on ritual, music, and persuasion: “The formality, sequence, pattern, and repetition of such musical structures themselves elicit emotional response through their instantiation of ritual. Music thereby creates an emotive ‘proto‐symbolic’ system capable of abstracting both the signals and structure of ritual” (Alcorta and Sosis, “Ritual, Emotion, and Sacred Symbols,” 336–37). “Human use of ritual to conditionally associate emotion and abstractions creates the sacred; it also lies at the heart of symbolic thought” (348–49).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn27">
                  <label>26</label>
                  <p>Gerhard von Rad,<italic>Holy War in Ancient Israel</italic>, trans. Marva J. Dawn (1958; repr., Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 1991), 39–51.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn28">
                  <label>27</label>
                  <p>All biblical citations are to the New International Version, unless noted otherwise.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn29">
                  <label>28</label>
                  <p>Michael Routledge, “Songs,” in<italic>The Oxford Illustrated History of the Crusades</italic>, ed. Jonathan Riley‐Smith (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1997), 91–111.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn30">
                  <label>29</label>
                  <p>McDermott,<italic>Perfect Soldiers</italic>, 54.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn31">
                  <label>30</label>
                  <p>Tilman Seidensticker, “Jihad Hymns (<italic>Nashīds</italic>) as a Means of Self‐Motivation in the Hamburg Group,” in Kippenberg and Seidensticker,<italic>9/11 Handbook</italic>, 71–78.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn32">
                  <label>31</label>
                  <p>Ahmed Ali,<italic>Al‐Quran, A Contemporary Translation</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1993). All Quranic passages are from this translation, unless otherwise noted.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn33">
                  <label>32</label>
                  <p>Sayyid Qutb,<italic>Milestones</italic>(Indianapolis: American Trust Publications, 1990), 44.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn34">
                  <label>33</label>
                  <p>“The reasons for jihad … are these: to establish Allah’s authority on earth; to arrange human affairs according to the true guidance provided by Allah; to abolish all the Satanic forces and Satanic systems of life; to end the lordship of some men over others, since all men are creatures of Allah and no one has the authority to make others his slaves or to make arbitrary laws for them. These reasons are sufficient for proclaiming jihad. One should always keep in mind, however, that there is no compulsion in religion; that is, once the people are free from the lordship of men, the law governing civil affairs will be purely that of Allah, while no one will be forced to change his beliefs and accept Islam” (ibid., 57).</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.3">
            <title>Purification and the Oath</title>
            <p>Perhaps the most striking sanctification of violence is the first section, which inaugurates the instructions for the last night:<disp-quote>
                  <p>1. Mutual swearing of the oath to the death<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">34</xref>and renewal of [one’s] intention. Shave excess hair from the body and apply cologne. Shower.</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <italic>Purification.—</italic>Let us begin with shaving hair, applying cologne, and showering, clearly steps in a purification process. Purification is not an unusual feature of preliminary war rituals from ancient times through the Christian crusades. Consecration of warriors is indeed one of the twelve steps for biblical warfare according to von Rad: Josh. 3:5 mandates that warriors “hallow themselves” before taking Jericho; in 1 Sam. 21:3–7 a priest waits to give templar bread to David’s troops until David reassures him that “Women have been denied us hitherto, when I have been on campaign, even an ordinary campaign, and the young men’s bodies have remained holy.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">35</xref>Possibly within the same ritual scheme, Uriah the Hittite refrains from going in to his wife while Israel and Judah are under attack (2 Sam. 11:10–11). Leaping ahead to Christian emperor Charlemagne, ritual purification is suggested when Frankish priests under Leo III blessed warriors and their weapons during a solemn mass. The church also authorized forms of prayer asking for divine blessing on the army that was to fight pagan peoples.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">36</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Likewise, in the traditional war verses of the Quran, we read of divine purification: “A blanketing sleep came over you as a measure of security from Him, and He sent down rain from the skies to cleanse you, and to remove the plague of Satan, and to strengthen your hearts and steady your steps” (8:11). Scholars of Islamic warfare point out that ancient warriors about to fight unbelievers typically performed ascetic practices, which prepared them for holy war.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">37</xref>In section 1 of the final instructions, as in the Bible, church history, and the Quran, purifying rites inaugurate holy warriors.</p>
            <p>One can imagine the transforming effects of purification before a holy mission: possible doubt is overcome as the purified actor understands himself to be catapulted onto a cosmic stage whereon killing takes on special sanctity. Purification arguably heightens the register of the whole event. Considering the aforementioned features of liturgical orders, here shaving, showering, and applying cologne might be seen as finite, microadjusting steps in a liturgical order that ultimately initiates the sanctified warrior.</p>
            <p>In a perfect circle, the instructions for the last night will close with a statement of the consequences of purification at the moment of death:<disp-quote>
                  <p>15. Pray the morning [prayer] in a group, and meditate on its merit. Repeat the devotionals after it [the prayer], and do not leave your apartment without performing the ritual ablutions.Continue to pray. … Read His Word: “Did you, then, think that We created you in vain and that unto Us you will not be returned?” [23:115].</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>It is well known that ritual ablutions prepare the body for prayer but also for burial, as attested plainly in Mohamed el‐Amir Atta’s last will.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">38</xref>Conversely, martyrs who die with the proper intent are said to be purified just by dying in battle, and go directly to paradise.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">39</xref>If there is an implied inconsistency in this instruction—are the 9/11 bombers martyrs or not?—one may presume that the instruction is not concerned with facts but rather is exhortative, aiming at spiritual transformation.</p>
            <p>Sections 7 and 8 reinforce this theme:<disp-quote>
                  <p>7. Purify your heart and cleanse it from all uncleanliness. Forget and become oblivious to that thing called “this world.”</p>
                  <p>8. Let your breast be open, tranquil to the bounty of God because it is only a few minutes before the happy, satisfying life and the eternal Paradise begins in the company of the prophets, the upright people, the martyrs and the righteous, may God have mercy on all of them.</p>
               </disp-quote>Paradise is won by purity of heart and, by implication from section 15 above, of body.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">40</xref>Upon death, the purified ritual actor will be delivered to the select company of the prophets, the upright and righteous (presumably the companions of old), and the martyrs. As pointed out in the discussion of Fernandez, the semantic movement in ritual transformation tends to narrow from the obscure and inchoate in the subject (or “tenor”)—who were these young men, anyway?—to the concrete and ostensive in the metaphoric predicate (the “vehicle”); now they rank with the prophets, martyrs, and the righteous. Through purification, among other things, the ritual actor has shifted his identity to the holy sphere, which clearly enlists an entire network of fecund associations. Inferring from Sura 9:111, he has been initiated to a holy mission:<disp-quote>
                  <p>God has verily bought the souls and possessions of the faithful in exchange for a promise of Paradise. They fight in the cause of God, and kill and are killed. This is a promise incumbent on Him, as in the Torah, so the Gospel and the Quran. And who is more true to his promises than God?</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <italic>The oath.—</italic>Then there is the oath: “Mutual swearing of the oath unto death and renewal of [one’s] intention” (Cook’s translation), or, alternatively, “Mutual pledge to die, and renewal of one’s intention” (translation of Kippenberg and Seidensticker). Given the deadly events that indeed occurred, this oath unto death would appear to be in fact a pledge to die.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">41</xref>In any case, a<italic>bay’a</italic>(oath) is absolutely binding, in this case unto death.</p>
            <p>Bruce Lincoln has pointed out the inestimable significance of binding oaths in launching religions of rebellion,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">42</xref>which is supported by Rappaport’s observation that violating oaths is the one apparently universal proscription across cultures, whereas proscriptions against murder, rape, and mayhem may vary considerably.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">43</xref>Swearing by one’s life and the lives of one’s family—presuming one cares about these lives—is common enough in ancient Near Eastern oaths, but the source by which one swears might also be the deity or its symbol. Oaths before a deity in many ancient documents (the<italic>Iliad</italic>, the Bible, Hittite treaties, Assyrian royal annals, even testimonials from the crusades) tend to be cosmically binding, enduring as long as the source by which one swears.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">44</xref>An obvious historical comparison is “taking the cross” for Christian crusaders. It has been argued that taking the cross amounted to a vow before one’s god and that failure in the crusade would invite chastisement by people at home, who saw themselves as defenders of oaths to that god.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">45</xref>The oath holds as long as the god holds. Practically speaking, swearing an oath unto death is equally final.</p>
            <p>Within the Quran, oath‐making conventions are clearly binding. It is said in Sura 9 that God has no contract/no oath with unbelievers (9:3), yet immunity from battle is granted to unbelievers with whom the early community had a treaty (9:1, 9:4). At the same time, believers are urged to strive against breakers of oaths to the Prophet Mohammad (9:13–14) until they desist from disdaining their oaths (9:12), “for God does not show transgressors the way” (9:24). In Sura 48, God’s armies are called the armies of heaven and earth, and the oath‐making language is explicit: The fighters are sent out as witnesses (48:8), and God protects those who swear allegiance to his followers, who are in fact swearing allegiance to God (48:10). But whereas in, say, the<italic>Iliad</italic>or the crusades, human witnesses have a role in avenging the oath before the gods should it be broken, in the Quran, whosoever breaks that oath breaks it at the cost of his own relationship with God (48:10). That relationship thereafter is lost. Clearly, the early Islamic community saw oath making as a sacred institution and compelling for Muslims.</p>
            <p>The compulsion is supported in this case by the oath’s mutuality. The need for solidarity is evident in the legendary battles of Islam. The war suras begin with an exhortation not to fight over the spoils of war and to promote accord, obeying God and his messenger (8:14). Sura 3:152–54 warns of the retraction of divine blessing at the battle at Uhud, a pivotal battle that the army was on the verge of winning before it became lax and failed to heed the prophet’s directions. Because some people desired goods of the world and others desired the hereafter, God ostensibly withdrew his support. The band fled, with Mohammad calling from the rear. The failure exemplifies fighting without solidarity.</p>
            <p>But to whom is this mutual oath sworn? It is conceivable that this oath unto death is sworn to bin Laden or some other emir,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">46</xref>but in the third stage of the final instructions we learn that it is to God. We are told that one must not become distracted by one’s own passion, appetite, or vendetta, because the mission is entirely for God. The revered example is the prophet’s son‐in‐law:<disp-quote>
                  <p>Do not take vengeance for yourself, but strike every blow for God Most High. This is in accordance with ‘Ali b. Abi Talib who fought one of the unbelievers in [a spirit of] vengeance against the unbeliever and the latter pressed upon ‘Ali, and he brandished his sword, and then struck him and then struck [again]. When the battle finished, the Companions [of the Prophet] asked him about this action—why was it that he had not struck [back at] this unbeliever, who had struck him and struck him again. ‘Ali said: “This was because I was afraid that I would strike him in vengeance for myself, so I lifted my sword [only in defense],” or whatever he said. Then when he had summoned [correct] intention, he went and struck him [the unbeliever], killing him. “All of this was my religion in the hands of God, seeking to do well to myself before God, so that this action would be for the sake of God alone.”</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>One is reminded of Augustine, who points out that in war Moses too acted in obedience to God.</p>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>In wars carried out by divine command, Moses showed no ferocity, but obedience; and God, in giving the command, acted not in cruelty, but in righteous retribution, giving to all what they deserved, and warning those who needed warning.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">47</xref>
                  </p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>As does Ali, Augustine endorses dispassion in battle:<disp-quote>
                  <p>The real evils in war are love of violence, revengeful cruelty, fierce and implacable enmity, wild resistance, the lust of power, and such like; and it is generally to punish these things, when force is required to inflict the punishment, that, in obedience to God or some lawful authority, good men undertake wars. Thus John allowed soldiers to take up arms by law, but did not authorize them to avenge themselves personally: “Do violence to no man, accuse no man falsely, and be content with your wages” (Luke 3:14). … To the Centurion Christ gave due praise. He did not tell him to leave the service (Matt. 8:9–10).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">48</xref>
                  </p>
               </disp-quote>Differences of context notwithstanding, these examples specify that fighting is a duty, not a personal quest.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">49</xref>
            </p>
            <p>But the astonishing aspect of this oath is, of course, its binding unto death, joined to an apparent intention to die, when suicide is forbidden in the Quran (e.g., at 4:29). While suicide pledges are legendary in the history of warfare (e.g., the Zealots at Masada, the kamikaze of World War II) and understandably equated with a love greater than love of oneself, noble suicides have never been conventional in Islamic societies and planned deaths were not sanctioned during the society’s golden age.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">50</xref>Suicide operations are in fact a relatively new phenomenon in Islam,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">51</xref>with questionable etiologies.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">52</xref>Traditionally, death in battle was graded against a strenuous code that measured purity of fighting intention and determined the slain’s status as a potential martyr.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">53</xref>An implicit code such as this may explain why the bulk of the instructions, and indeed this very one, emphasize purifying oneself, even of the desire for vengeance against those who “fear death and follow Satan.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">54</xref>Conceivably, only the purest ritual actor, transported onto a ritual stage, may transcend Islamic proscriptions on suicide and give his life as an offering to God. While the ritual actors do not outrightly endorse an oath to die—proscribed in Islamic theology—they certainly knew they would die.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">55</xref>Purification helps to sanctify a mission that, on its face, should be forbidden.</p>
            <p>In sum, implicit in this oath to the death are all the features described above under “Ritual Performances and Liturgical Orders.” The oath relies for compulsion on oath‐making paradigms from the times of the nascent Islamic community and imposes a hallowed duty to respect oaths onto the ritual actors. The composer of these instructions would have known that oath making is strongly conventionalized in the Islamic tradition and would have relied on the convention’s persuasive sanctity to coax the ritual actor to see himself as bound to the oath. Within the scheme of liturgical orders, the oath’s purifying rites (shaving, showering, etc.) might be seen as ritualized microadjustments that help to seal a sacred commitment. Such microadjustments also propel ritual communication to a very high register, which is one measure of its irrevocability. As noted above, just swearing an oath is a metaperformative ritual that compels recognition of the convention it enacts, exactly while it instantiates it. It thus is final, regardless of any internal infelicities on the part of the oath swearer. The feared infelicities that this oath needed to overcome were, doubtlessly, a victory of self‐love over the intention to die and, more important, moral uncertainty in the face of well‐known Islamic prohibitions on suicide.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn35">
                  <label>34</label>
                  <p>“The term is `bay’a li‐l‐mawt,' an oath unto death, not that necessarily one *has* to die because of the oath, but that the oath is in force until the time of death, and leads inexorably towards death. … A ba’ya is an oath that one makes that is absolutely binding, and signifies one’s allegiance usually towards a caliph or an imam, but occasionally towards a cause as well” (e‐mail to author from David Cook, November 24, 2009).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn36">
                  <label>35</label>
                  <p>Von Rad,<italic>Holy War</italic>, 41–42.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn37">
                  <label>36</label>
                  <p>Peter Partner,<italic>God of Battles</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1997), 64.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn38">
                  <label>37</label>
                  <p>Albrecht Noth,<italic>Heiliger Krieg und Heiliger Kampf im Islam und Christentum: Beiträge zur Vorgeschichte und Geschichte der Kreuzzüge</italic>(Bonn: Röhrscheid, 1966), 52–61, cited in Kippenberg, “Consider That It Is a Raid,” 36, nn. 18–20. See also the equation of jihad with a veritable sacrament by the jihadi Abdallah Azzam, as described in Cook,<italic>Understanding Jihad</italic>, 129–30.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn39">
                  <label>38</label>
                  <p>From the last will of Mohamed Atta,<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/network/personal/attawill.html"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/network/personal/attawill.html</ext-link>:<list>
                        <list-item>
                           <label>8.</label>
                           <p>The people who will clean my body should be good Muslims and I do not want a lot of people to wash my body unless it is necessary.</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                           <label>9.</label>
                           <p>The person who will wash my body near my genitals must wear gloves on his hands so he won’t touch my genitals.</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                           <label>10.</label>
                           <p>I want the clothes I wear to consist of three white pieces of cloth, not to be made of silk or expensive material.</p>
                        </list-item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn40">
                  <label>39</label>
                  <p>See Tilman Seidensticker, “Suicide Attacks in the Name of Islam,” in Kippenberg and Seidensticker,<italic>9/11 Handbook</italic>, 31, for the varying opinions as to what exactly goes directly to heaven: the body, the soul, or the “green bird” that allegorizes it.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn41">
                  <label>40</label>
                  <p>Ibid. Likewise with penitent Christian Crusaders of the twelfth century; see Jonathan Riley‐Smith, “The State of Mind of Crusaders to the East, 1095–1300,” in Riley‐Smith,<italic>History of the Crusades</italic>, 66–90; 83.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn42">
                  <label>41</label>
                  <p>Bin Laden claims they all knew that they were on a martyrdom operation. See Makiya and Mneimneh, “Manual for a `Raid,'” 18; Cook, “Suicide Attacks,” sec. 1; and Seidensticker et al., “Translation of the Spiritual Manual,” 11.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn43">
                  <label>42</label>
                  <p>Lincoln,<italic>Holy Terrors</italic>, 85.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn44">
                  <label>43</label>
                  <p>Rappaport,<italic>Religion and Ritual</italic>, 137.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn45">
                  <label>44</label>
                  <p>Kitts,<italic>Sanctified Violence</italic>, 94–98.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn46">
                  <label>45</label>
                  <p>Riley‐Smith, “State of Mind,” 66–90, esp. 68–71.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn47">
                  <label>46</label>
                  <p>Lincoln,<italic>Holy Terrors</italic>, 85.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn48">
                  <label>47</label>
                  <p>Augustine, “Reply to Faustus the Manichean,” in<italic>Just War: A Wadsworth Casebook in Argument</italic>, ed. Sharon K. Walsh and Evelyn D. Asch (Boston: Wadsworth, 2004), 66–67.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn49">
                  <label>48</label>
                  <p>Ibid.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn50">
                  <label>49</label>
                  <p>In a convoluted way, a section in the second phase also suggests that the mission is for God, or at least all fear should be only for God (Seidensticker et al., “Translation of the Spiritual Manual,” 14):<disp-quote>
                        <p>The believers don’t fear that [death]. Only the followers of Satan will fear it, who in reality fear Satan have become his followers—God forbid! Fear is a great act of worship which is permitted to be offered only to God, and he is most worthy of it. … The Most High has said, commenting on these verses, “That is Satan frightening his friends” [3.175]. Those who are enchanted by Western civilization are people who have drunk their love and reverence with cold water. They feared their (own) weak, fragile devices. “Therefore do not fear them; but fear you Me, if you are believers” [3.175]. Fear is a great act of worship. The followers of God and the believers offer it only to the one and only God in whose hands are all things.</p>
                     </disp-quote>
                  </p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn51">
                  <label>50</label>
                  <p>See Seidensticker, “The Religious and Historical Background of Suicide Attacks in the Name of Islam,” in<italic>The 9/11 Handbook</italic>, 29–36. On the relatively recent glamorization of death and killing in suicide operations, see also Cook,<italic>Understanding Jihad</italic>, 128–62.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn52">
                  <label>51</label>
                  <p>David Cook (“Suicide Attacks”) points out that “time and again prominent prisoners are taken to torture chambers in Arab or Muslim countries under various pretexts; there is virtually no evidence that any of them take their own lives to spare themselves the torture, as Westerners often have done in analogous situations.”</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn53">
                  <label>52</label>
                  <p>Abdullah Azzam, a mentor to bin Laden, wrote in his “Martyrs: The Building Blocks of Nations” (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.religioscope.com/info/doc/jihad/azzam_martyrs.htm"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.religioscope.com/info/doc/jihad/azzam_martyrs.htm</ext-link>): “History does not write its lines except with blood. Glory does not build its loft[y] edifice except with skulls. Honor and respect cannot be established except on a foundation of cripples and corpses. Empires, distinguished peoples, states and societies cannot be established with examples. Indeed those who think that they can change reality or change societies without blood, sacrifices and invalids, without pure, innocent souls, do not understand the essence of this Deen [Islam] and they do not know the method of the best of Messengers [Muhammad].” David Cook (“Suicide Attacks”) points out how forced it is to construe this sentiment as truly Islamic. Nonetheless, he also points out that in the face of adversity Muslims frequently characterize their community as one that is indifferent to death, in opposition to polytheists who love life.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn54">
                  <label>53</label>
                  <p>“The slain [in<italic>jihad</italic>] are three [types of] men: a believer, who struggles (<italic>jahad</italic>) with himself and his possessions in the path of God, such that when he meets the enemy [in battle] he fights them until he is killed. This<italic>shahid</italic>is tested [and is] in the camp of God under His throne; the prophets do not exceed him [in merit] except by the level of prophecy. [Then] a believer, committing offenses and sins against himself, who struggles with himself and his possessions in the path of God, such that when he meets the enemy [in battle] he fights until he is killed. This cleansing wipes away his offenses and his sins—behold the sword wipes [away] sins!—and he will be let into heaven from whatever gate he wishes… [Then] a hypocrite, who struggles with himself and his possessions in the path of God, such that when he meets the enemy [in battle] he fights until he is killed. This [man] is in hell since the sword does not wipe away hypocrisy.” From an early<italic>jihad</italic>collection of ‘Abdallah b. al‐Mubarak (d. 797; cited in Cook, “Suicide Attacks”).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn55">
                  <label>54</label>
                  <p>“The believers will not fear it [death]; only the followers of Satan will fear it—those who at the core are fearful of Satan, and have become his followers” (second phase of the last instructions).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn56">
                  <label>55</label>
                  <p>Hence bin Laden's statement “The brothers, who conducted the operation, all they knew was that they have a martyrdom operation” (quote in Makiya and Mneimneh, “Manual for a `Raid,'” 18).</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.4">
            <title>Primordial Warring Paradigms</title>
            <p>Of course the suicide is not purposeless; it aims to kill. A comparison of the 9/11 event to primordial battles is implied by the injunction to read Suras 8 and 9:<disp-quote>
                  <p>3. Reading/recitation of<italic>suras</italic>al‐Tawba [9] and al‐Anfal [8], and considering their meanings together with Paradise that God has promised to the believers, especially to the martyrs.</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>Sura 8 famously enjoins divinely directed war. Some of its verses might come right out of the Bible, the<italic>Iliad</italic>, Assyrian royal annals, or documents from the first crusade. Take this example: “When you sought aid from your Lord, so He answered you: I will assist you with a thousand of the angels following one another” (8:9).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">56</xref>It is veritably formulaic in ancient Near Eastern battle literature that gods march in front, behind, and beside their favorites in battle,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">57</xref>and crusaders’ letters include accounts of heavenly visitations reflecting divine approval for the holy war into Syria.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn59">58</xref>A primordial event that the 9/11 hijackers surely emulated was the battle at Badr, described elliptically at Sura 8:18–19 and more fully in the Sira of Mohammed. There, the battle at Badr marks the inauguration of Islam’s success as a viable religious‐military community. It was at the battle of Badr that Mohammad threw at the enemy a handful of pebbles that induced angels to descend from heaven to fight by his side. It was there that a wooden cudgel handed by Mohammad to a fellow warrior turned miraculously into a gleaming sword. It was also there that for the first time martyrdom was promised to fighters for God. Hence, warriors such as ‘Awf b. Harith gave up their armor to fight without protection, in the manner of a berserk warrior. He sought and found a martyr’s death.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn60">59</xref>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps the most striking point in Sura 8 is its assurance that one kills on behalf of the deity. In fact, victory is established by God, not by men (8:17):<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn61">60</xref>
            </p>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>So you did not slay them, but it was Allah Who slew them, and you did not smite when you smote (the enemy), but it was Allah Who smote, and that He might confer upon the believers a good gift from Himself; surely Allah is Hearing, Knowing.</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>For comparison, we have numerous biblical references to the deity going out ahead and establishing victory, defeating, say, the Philistine army for David: “Do not attack now but wheel round and take them in the rear opposite the aspens. As soon as you hear a rustling sound in the tree‐tops, then act at once; for the Lord will have gone out before you to defeat the Philistine army” (2 Sam. 5:22–25). No less biblical is this Quranic instruction to the angels (8:12–13): “I am with you, go and strengthen the faithful. I shall fill the hearts of the unbelievers with terror. So smite them on their necks and every joint (and incapacitate them). For they have opposed God and his Apostle. … God is severe in his retribution.” One easily might compare this to the divinely inspired terror of which Moses sings in Exod. 15:14–15:<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn62">61</xref>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>The nations will hear and tremble;anguish will grip the people of Philistia.The chiefs of Edom will be terrified,the leaders of Moab will be seized with trembling.</p>
               </disp-quote>What von Rad points out about biblical war traditions may be said just as well about Islamic: “[The god’s] intervention in the form of a confusing divine terror was an indispensable element of the tradition.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn63">62</xref>
            </p>
            <p>As for Sura 9, it is saturated with strictures and parables about fighting. We have examined already the complex instructions about oaths in Sura 9, but other verses explain why one should fight, whom one should fight, and the punishments for the reluctant and for those who disbelieve. For instance, promises of everlasting rewards are made to those who fight (9:19–22, 38–39, 111–12), while the reluctant are promised punishment (9:81–89). People of the book who do not accept God and the Last Day are promised punishment in hell (9:21–35), but Muslims are to spare them if they pay the protective tax in submission (9:29). Fighters who disbelieve are to suffer defeat by invisible forces sent from above, remembered from the battle at Hunain (9:25–26). Hypocrites who are frivolous may be pardoned, but hypocrites who deliberately sin are to be punished in hell, as covenant breakers with God (9:73–80). At the same time, women (9:87), the old, the ill, and those without means (9:91) are not required to fight, and the deterrent effect of fighting alongside the reluctant is also recognized (9:45–46; cf. Deut. 20:8).</p>
            <p>On the whole, invoking Suras 8 and 9 reminds ritual actors of the investment of the early Islamic community in war. Sadly ignored is the more complex model of the warring prophet as described in our earlier discussion.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn57">
                  <label>56</label>
                  <p>Translation by Muhammed Habib Shakir, University of Southern California Center for Muslim‐Jewish Engagement,<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/quran/"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/quran/</ext-link>.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn58">
                  <label>57</label>
                  <p>See, e.g., Deut. 1:30–31; Judg. 4:14–15;<italic>Iliad</italic>5.590–95, 14.384–87, 15.306–11; [Hittite]<italic>Annals of Hattusili III</italic>, composite, at III:37–38: “At that time also the Goddess Ishtar ran in front of me,” and at IV:7–16: “And so while the Goddess Ishtar, my lady, formerly promised kingship to me continuously, at this time Goddess Ishtar, my lady, appeared in a dream to my wife: `I will run in front of your husband. All Hatti will turn to the side of your husband. Since I myself raised him, and I did not abandon him in any way to an evil judgment or an evil god, now I will take him up. I will set him into priesthood for the Sungoddess of Arinna. Make me, Goddess Ishtar, your special divinity.’ Goddess Ishtar stepped behind me. As she told me, so it became” (author’s translation); Assyrian royal annals: to Esarhaddon: “The great Lady am I. I am Goddess Ishtar of Arbela, who has destroyed thy foes before thee. What words of mine which I spoke to thee could thou not rely upon? I am Ishtar of Arbela, thy foes I will flay and give to thee. I, Ishtar of Arbela, before thee, behind thee, I will go; fear not”; to Assurbanipial: “The troops saw the Idide, a raging torrent, and were afraid to cross. Goddess Ishtar, who dwells in Arbela, in the night time revealed a dream to my armies, thus she addressed them: ‘I will go before Assurbanipal, the king whom my hands have formed.’ My armies put their trust in that dream, and crossed the Idide in safety”; Assyrian passages translated by David Luckenbill (<italic>Ancient Records of Assyria and Babylonia</italic>, vol. 2 [New York: Greenwood Press, 1968], 618, 807).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn59">
                  <label>58</label>
                  <p>Riley‐Smith, “State of Mind,” 78–81.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn60">
                  <label>59</label>
                  <p>Reuven Firestone,<italic>Jihad</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1999), 114.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn61">
                  <label>60</label>
                  <p>Translation by Shakir,<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/quran/"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.usc.edu/schools/college/crcc/engagement/resources/texts/muslim/quran/</ext-link>.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn62">
                  <label>61</label>
                  <p>Or consider the divine feats of which Isaiah (34:5–8) reports:<disp-quote>
                        <p>My sword has drunk its fill in the heavens;see, it descends in judgment on Edom,the people I have totally destroyed.The sword of the LORD is bathed in blood,it is covered with fat—the blood of lambs and goats,fat from the kidneys of rams.For the LORD has a sacrifice in Bozrahand a great slaughter in Edom.And the wild oxen will fall with them,the bull calves and the great bulls.Their land will be drenched with blood,and the dust will be soaked with fat.For the LORD has a day of vengeance,a year of retribution, to uphold Zion’s cause.</p>
                     </disp-quote>
                  </p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn63">
                  <label>62</label>
                  <p>Von Rad,<italic>Holy War</italic>, 49. Lest we presume such verbiage represents a bygone age, we should consider the writings of Michael Bray or Meir Kahane. As Michael Bray puts it, “This Jesus—the same yesterday, today, and forever (Heb. 13:8)—is the `Man of War' of the Scriptures. He is the God of Israel who wrought calamity upon Israel as well as her enemies. He is not squeamish about destruction and war. The One who uses force and consecrates others to do the same does not have a problem with it” (“A Time for Revolution?” in<italic>A Time to Kill</italic>[Portland, OR: Advocates for Life Publications, 1994], chap. 9). As he indicated in an interview with Mark Juergensmeyer, Bray advocates not just vengeance for the unborn, but decisive acts of extravagant terrorism to awaken sensibility to a world gone awry (Mark Juergensmeyer,<italic>Terror in the Mind of God</italic>[Berkeley: University of California Press, 2000], 20–30). In the same vein is the rhetoric of the late Meir Kahane, founder of the Jewish Defense League and the Kach Party of Israel and notorious for his sentiments about annexing lands adjacent to Israel (<italic>The Jewish Idea</italic>, 3rd ed. [Jerusalem: Institute for the Publications of Rabbi Meir Kahane, 1996], 318):<disp-quote>
                        <p>We see that G‐d has declared war on the wicked and described Himself as Master of war, and that we must emulate Him in war the way we emulate His mercy and kindness, etc. Let death take those pompous individuals who rebel against G‐d and against His attributes and principles, who err and mislead others as if they were more righteous than their Creator, pious fools who hypocritically reject the war against evil and evildoers, bleating about peace when we need war, falsifying and distorting G‐d’s Torah and the laws of compulsory war against the wicked. Of them it says (<italic>Isaiah</italic>48:22), “The L‐rd says to the wicked, ‘There is no peace.'”</p>
                     </disp-quote>
                  </p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.5">
            <title>Overdetermining the Message</title>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>4. Reminding the soul of hearing and obedience that night [the “Last Night”] for you will be faced with what will cause it to be less than 100% in its hearing and obedience, so spiritually exercise its purification [the soul], understand it, subordinate it and incite it [to good works] at that time. The Most High said: “And obey God and His Apostle and do not quarrel among yourselves lest you lose heart and your strength dissipates. And stand fast, for God is on the side of those who stand fast” [8:46].</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>We have touched upon Rappaport’s point that the more likely people are to violate a convention, the more fixed, more constraining, even more reifying, will be the ritual form that instantiates it. This exhortation seems to reify the oath of the final instructions' section 1. Notable is the sequence of second person imperatives—subordinate one’s soul, incite it, purify it, understand it—which speaks to Tambiah’s analysis of a ritual’s “compelling illocutionary words of command and persuasion or declaration” whose ultimate purpose is to produce “a sense of heightened and intensified and fused communication.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn64">63</xref>The use of successive imperatives from a family of ideas might be seen as repeating on different frequencies the same core message. As Tambiah has pointed out, the same message may be communicated in a plethora of different ways or by a plethora of symbolic acts that overdetermine the ritual’s message, making it difficult to resist. The imperatives are aimed at inducing a high communicational register and overcoming individual resistance to the sanctified mission.</p>
            <p>As for “do not quarrel among yourselves lest you lose heart and your strength dissipates,” the need for solidarity between companions on the battlefield needs little explanation.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn64">
                  <label>63</label>
                  <p>See Tambiah,<italic>Performative Approach</italic>, 131–42, and “The Magical Power of Words,”<italic>Man</italic>3, no. 2 (1968): 175–208, esp. 189–90.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.6">
            <title>Reading the Book</title>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>6. Much remembrance [of God], and know that the best way of remembrance is to read/recite the Noble Quran—according to the consensus of the knowledgeable people so far as I know. It is sufficient that it is the Word of the Creator of heaven and earth—to whom you are going.</p>
               </disp-quote>Here the Quran functions in the same way as do liturgical orders, as Rappaport sees them. Rappaport points out that by encoding canonical messages, liturgical orders preserve these messages against the vagaries of historical change. They preserve canonical truths, what he calls metatruths, understood to be established at the foundation of the present order. One does not need an anthropologist to understand that a fixity of cultural forms might be based on a book and the golden ideal inscribed therein.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn65">64</xref>
            </p>
            <p>In any case, the Quran prescribes thinking of the deity a great deal and standing firm when one meets an army: “Only they are true believers whose hearts fill up with awe when the name of God is mentioned; and their faith is further strengthened when His Messages are read out to them; and those who put their trust in their Lord, who are firm in devotion” (8:2–3).</p>
            <p>As for the promise of meeting the creator on judgment day, a repeating theme in Quranic war injunctions is the contrast between heaven and earthly life. Although this earth and human life are created good—indeed, Islam denies the doctrine of original sin—the prospects of judgment day and the reward of paradise frequently are held up as the end goal, creating an imbalance of sanctity.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn66">65</xref>This life has less of it, at least in the battle books where, for instance, believing in God and the last day and striving in the cause of God is held up over going on pilgrimage to the sacred mosque (9:19). “Those who accepted the faith and left their homes and fought in the way of God, wealth and soul, have a greater reward with God, and will be successful” (9:20).</p>
            <p>This rhetorical theme is consonant with other Western traditions in times of war. It is well known that Popes Urban, Innocent, and others promised heavenly rewards to crusaders.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn67">66</xref>Pope Leo III blessed the swords of Charlemagne’s army and backed the campaign motto of “baptism or death” in 800, and Pope Leo IX (1049–54) promised forgiveness of sins in heaven and the title of martyr to those who would fight against fearless sinners and die.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn68">67</xref>As did the crusading church, the Quran promises forgiveness of sins to warriors who fight for the cause: “God has preferred those who strive hard over those who remain passive with a mighty reward: degrees of honor, forgiveness of sins and His grace” (4:95–99).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn69">68</xref>
            </p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn65">
                  <label>64</label>
                  <p>See also Catherine Bell,<italic>Ritual Theory, Ritual Practice</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1992), 118–42.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn66">
                  <label>65</label>
                  <p>On sacred scarcity, see Hector Avalos,<italic>Fighting Words: The Origins of Religious Violence</italic>(Amherst, NY: Prometheus, 2005).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn67">
                  <label>66</label>
                  <p>See, e.g., Partner,<italic>God of Battles</italic>; and Riley‐Smith, “State of Mind.”</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn68">
                  <label>67</label>
                  <p>Partner,<italic>God of Battles</italic>, 59–76.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn69">
                  <label>68</label>
                  <p>See Roland Bainton,<italic>Christian Attitudes toward War and Peace</italic>(New York: Abingdon, 1960), for the classical discussion of the early church on homicide.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.7">
            <title>Be Reassured That the Mission Is Holy</title>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>9. You should consider how—if you fall into temptation—you will be able to resist, remain steadfast and recover. You know that whatever happens to you would never detract from [your spiritual level] and whatever would detract from you would never happen to you. This is nothing but God’s test in order to raise the level [of your martyrdom] and to expiate your sins. You can be certain there are only minutes left until the merit will be clear—with God’s permission—of that great reward from God. The Most High said: “Or did you suppose that you will enter Paradise, before God has known who were those of you who have struggled, and those who were steadfast” [3:142].</p>
               </disp-quote>The exhortation to trust must be meant to sooth the ritual actors in case of fleeting doubt as to the mission’s purpose or success. Any obstacle is a test that raises the level of martyrdom.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn70">69</xref>The test of faith and consolation for failure are supported by events during the aforementioned Battle of Uhud, where failure presented an opportunity for expiation:<disp-quote>
                  <p>Then He put you to flight before them in order to try you. But now He has forgiven you, for surely God is kind to the faithful. Remember as you were rushing up (the hill) without turning back to look, though the Prophet was calling you from the rear, He requited you with anguish for an anguish that you do not fret for missed opportunity and what befell you, for God is aware of all that you do. (3:152–53)</p>
               </disp-quote>In other words, occasional loss is a spiritual aid and an opportunity to get closer to God.</p>
            <p>Failure in battle as an opportunity for expiation is notably different than the way it was seen by Christian crusaders, who, according to Jonathan Riley‐Smith, regarded it as a violation of one’s oath to the deity. The losing crusader could expect chastisement by the Christian body, as God’s instrument on earth.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn71">70</xref>
            </p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn70">
                  <label>69</label>
                  <p>On the three levels of martyrdom, see the discussion by David Cook (“Suicide Attacks”).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn71">
                  <label>70</label>
                  <p>Riley‐Smith, “State of Mind,” 71.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.8">
            <title>Mystical States and Trust in Miracles</title>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>10. Remember the Word of God Most High: “You were yearning for death before you actually met it. Now you have seen it and you are beholding it” [3:143]. And also remember: “How many a small band has defeated a large one by God’s leave. [God is with the steadfast]” [2:249]. And His Word Most High: “If God supports you, no one will overcome you; but if He forsakes you, then who will be able to support you after Him? And in God let the believers put their trust!” [3:160]</p>
               </disp-quote>This section is a restating of several Quranic verses. The first is Sura 3:143: “You had wished to know death before you faced it (in battle), so now you have seen it with your own eyes,” a verse often associated with mystical transports resulting in union with the divine.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn72">71</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Second, reference to uneven numbers commemorates miraculous victories on the battlefield in nascent Islam. In Sura 8 we hear that the numbers to defeat may be tenfold: “If there are twenty among you with determination, they will vanquish two hundred; and if there are a hundred, then they will vanquish one thousand” (8:65). The third phase of the last instructions invokes the same kind of legend:<disp-quote>
                  <p>When you see the masses of the unbelievers, remember the Confederates (<italic>al‐ahzab</italic>), whose numbers were approximately 10,000 thousand fighters, and how God gave victory to His servants the believers [Muslims].</p>
               </disp-quote>Miraculous assistance is revealed also in Sura 3:124–26:<disp-quote>
                  <p>Remember when you said to the faithful, “Is it not sufficient that your Lord should send for your help three thousand angels from the heavens? Indeed if you are patient and take heed for yourselves, and the (enemy) come rushing at you suddenly, your Lord will send even five thousand angels on chargers sweeping down.” And God did not do so but as good tidings and to reassure your hearts—for victory comes from God alone.”</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>Celestial support is virtually generic in early war literature. Assyrian king Esarhaddon trusted his goddess to go in front of him and slay his foes,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn73">72</xref>as did Hittite king Hattusili.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn74">73</xref>Deborah trusted her god to do the same (Judg. 4:14 ), as did David (2 Sam. 5:23–24). With hailstones and confusion, the biblical god killed more Gibeonites than did Joshua (Josh. 10:10–11). Clearly, confidence in a warring deity is primordial in the West.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn72">
                  <label>71</label>
                  <p>What may seem to be an astonishing invocation of Sufi mysticism is in fact not unusual in texts aiming to spiritualize jihad, at least among the Muslim Brotherhood; see Seidensticker, “Instructions Given,” 22–23.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn73">
                  <label>72</label>
                  <p>Luckenbill,<italic>Ancient Records</italic>, sec. 618.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn74">
                  <label>73</label>
                  <p>“Never in troubled times did you in any way step away from me. In no way did you abandon me to my enemies. Nor did you abandon me to my court‐opponents, nor to those who envied me. If it was the plot of the enemy, if it was the plot of the prosecutor, if it was the plot of the king’s household, in any way, You, my lady, defended me at every opportunity” (<italic>Apology of Hattusili III</italic>[CTH 81], translation by author).</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.9">
            <title>Blessing, Contagion, and Saturation</title>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>12. The expectoration (from the soul, into a siphon; and the clothes, the knife, your personal belongings, your ID, your passport and all of your papers).</p>
               </disp-quote>Attributed to the earliest days of Islam, the apparent tradition here is to recite verses of the Quran, and then to spit or blow onto whatever is to be blessed by those verses.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn75">74</xref>The practice of blowing inspiration from the Quranic verses into clothing, knife, passport, and papers would seem to saturate the possessions of the ritual actor with sanctity, as if to shower the actor himself with a sacred vapor and drive divine grace into his person. In old school anthropology, this might have been called “contagious magic,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn76">75</xref>but within the schemes of Tambiah, Fernandez, and Ricoeur, it is probably better understood as a thickening of the metaphorical domain the ritual actor enters by contact with the verses. The thickening of the metaphorical domain helps to transform him into a pious persona on a holy mission. Spitting Quranic verses onto tokens might also be seen as another form of supplicating/praying.</p>
            <p>A somewhat comparable tradition in early Western war lore is the wearing of the cross in the time of Pope Urban. Contact with the cross was said to induce a blessing, based on Matt. 16:24 and Luke 14:27: “If any man will come after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross and follow me.” The derived blessing was also from Matthew: “Every one that has left house or brothers or sisters or father or mother or wife or children or lands, for my name’s sake, shall receive a hundredfold and shall possess life everlasting” (19:29). Riley‐Smith cites reports of crusaders hysterically branding crosses on their bodies, although more usually they just committed to wearing crosses sewn into their clothing until their vows were fulfilled.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn77">76</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Physical engagement with the symbols of power in these instances (the cross, Quranic verses) would seem intended to persuade. The persuasion promotes ritual transformation.</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn75">
                  <label>74</label>
                  <p>Seidensticker et al., “Translation of the Spiritual Manual,” in Kippenberg and Seidensticker,<italic>9/11 Handbook</italic>, 91 n. 39.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn76">
                  <label>75</label>
                  <p>An ancient and easily verifiable tradition in Western oath making, as attested in Assyrian and Hittite oaths and curses involving the rubbing of oils into the skin; see Anne Marie Kitz, “An Oath, Its Curse and Anointing Ritual,”<italic>Journal of the American Oriental Society</italic>124, no. 2 (2004): 315–21.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn77">
                  <label>76</label>
                  <p>Riley‐Smith, “State of Mind,” 68.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.10">
            <title>How to Strike Your Enemy</title>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>13. Check your weapon before you leave and again before you leave. “Sharpen your knives so as not to cause pain to your sacrifice.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn78">77</xref>
                  </p>
               </disp-quote>According to Bruce Lincoln, this instruction about sacrifice may imply the preliminary throat cutting of the flight attendants.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn79">78</xref>One could choose from any number of ancient prebattle animal slaughters for comparison, and any number of theorists, such as P. Stengel, Walter Burkert, and René Girard, to explain them. Explanations range from sanctifying the war to breaking the taboo on killing to a kind of prebattle catharsis.</p>
            <p>More important to reconcile with this injunction, however, are the ethical restrictions on fighting as given in hadiths. Qutb cites these: First, Mohammad once ordered that no women or children be killed during combat. Second, he forbade the looting and mutilation of dead bodies. He is quoted as saying: “Proceed to fight in God’s name and for His cause. Fight those who deny God. Take the initiative but do not commit any acts of treachery, do not mutilate your victims, and do not kill any children.” Third, he once said that striking the face of an opponent should be avoided. Fourth, he forbade intentional, slow killing.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn80">79</xref>This is all to be understood in the context of seventh‐century Arabia, of course.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn81">80</xref>The net point is that killing is not supposed to give satisfaction. It is something one does for the deity.</p>
            <p>Care not to inflict undue pain on the victim is difficult to reconcile with an instruction in the third phase:<disp-quote>
                  <p>Then follow the law regarding prisoners and pay very close attention to them, fighting them as the Most High said: “It is not up to any prophet to take captives except after too much blood is shed in the land. You desire the fleeting goods of this world, but God desires the Hereafter, and God is Mighty, Wise” [8:67].</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>Cook reads this as a revision of Sura 8:67, which prohibits the bartering of prisoners for ransom: “No apostle should take captives until he has battled and subdued the country.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn82">81</xref>
            </p>
            <p>Yet it should be noted that accepting ransom for captives is older than Islam and is approved in Sura 47:4: “So, when you clash with the unbelievers, smite their necks until you overpower them, then hold them in bondage. Then either free them graciously or after taking a ransom, until war shall have come to end. If God had pleased, he could have punished them himself.” In practice, of course, Mohammad often took prisoners instead of killing everyone, as recorded in several hadiths. He took seventy prisoners of war at the famous Battle of Badr, for instance (<italic>al Bukhari</italic>, vol. 5, bk. 59, no. 322), and one of the female prisoners he freed from slavery and married (<italic>al Sahih Muslim</italic>, vol. 8, bk. 33, no. 25). We have stories that show the prophet’s compassion toward prisoners, as when Mohammad found a shirt for a naked prisoner of war (taking the shirt of the prophet’s friend, then giving his own shirt to the friend [<italic>al Bukhari</italic>, vol. 4, bk. 52, no. 252]), or when he freed prisoners of war to a group of newly converted Muslims (<italic>al Bukhari</italic>, vol. 4, bk. 53, no. 360).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn83">82</xref>
            </p>
            <p>On the other hand, the Quran says that slaughter is an evil thing, but<italic>fitna</italic>—persecution or a betrayal of a basic social bond—is worse (2:191). Military jihad (struggle) could become a sacred duty when it was to defend the community against<italic>fitna</italic>. Twentieth‐century revivalists such as Qutb have seen<italic>fitna</italic>as occurring wherever God is not recognized as sovereign.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn84">83</xref>
            </p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn78">
                  <label>77</label>
                  <p>In “Suicide Attacks,” Cook reports this as a hadith deriving from Muslim,<italic>Sahih</italic>, 6:72; Ibn Hanbal,<italic>Musnad</italic>, 4:123; cited in al‐Nawawi,<italic>Forty Hadith</italic>, trans. Ezzedin Ibrahim and Denys Johnson‐Davies (Cairo: Dar al‐Manar, 1976), 64–65 (hadith 17).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn79">
                  <label>78</label>
                  <p>Lincoln,<italic>Holy Terrors</italic>, 10.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn80">
                  <label>79</label>
                  <p>Qutb,<italic>Milestones</italic>, 74.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn81">
                  <label>80</label>
                  <p>See<italic>al Bukhari</italic>, vol. 1, bk. 2, no. 17, on illegal sexual intercourse during battle, and the prohibition on killing children,<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.usc.edu/dept/MSA/reference/searchhadith.html"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.usc.edu/dept/MSA/reference/searchhadith.html</ext-link>.</p>
                  <p>Note the utter contradiction between the humanitarian emphasis in these early instructions and the lack of one in the post‐9/11 “Communiqué from Qa’Idat al‐Jihad concerning the Testaments of the Heroes and the Legality of the Washington and New York Operations” (April 24, 2002). Invoking Sura 2:194, the author (presumably bin Laden and Zawahiri) claims that “Muslims are permitted to kill infidel innocents reciprocally; if the infidels are targeting the women, the young children, and the elderly Muslims, then it is permissible for Muslims to act reciprocally, and kill just as they were killed” (Cook,<italic>Understanding Jihad</italic>, 178).</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn82">
                  <label>81</label>
                  <p>A slightly different interpretation is given in this translation: “It behooves not a Prophet to take captives, except in the course of regular fighting” (The Quran, trans. Muhammad Zafrulla Khan [New York: Olive Branch Press, 1991]). According to Cook (“Suicide Attacks,” n. 125), the purpose of invoking this sura is to attempt to justify the killing of innocents in cold blood.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn83">
                  <label>82</label>
                  <p>See<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.usc.edu/dept/MSA/reference/searchhadith.html"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.usc.edu/dept/MSA/reference/searchhadith.html</ext-link>for these hadiths.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn84">
                  <label>83</label>
                  <p>Qutb,<italic>Milestones</italic>, 44. Peter Partner (<italic>God of Battles</italic>, 45–47) points out that this duty might have ended by the second century of Islam, when Islamic rule extended over three continents.</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
         <sec id="sc2.11">
            <title>Modesty and Prayer</title>
            <p>
               <disp-quote>
                  <p>14. Tighten your clothing tightly around you. This is the way of the pious forefathers. They would tighten their clothing around them previous to a battle. Tighten your shoes well. Wear socks so that your feet will fit in the shoes and not come out. All of these things are circumstances of this present [world]. God suffices for us, and what a Guardian!</p>
                  <p>15. Pray the morning [prayer] in a group, and meditate on its merit. Repeat the devotionals after it [the prayer], and do not leave your apartment without performing the ritual ablutions.</p>
               </disp-quote>
            </p>
            <p>As already argued, the battle to come is seen as a kind of devotion, for which one must be prepared. Preparations include dressing in the way of the prophet and companions, with a sense of modesty and so as to permit ease of movement.</p>
            <p>They also include mutual prayer. Prayer has been an essential element in Islamic battle preparations from ancient times through recent terrorist activities. Turkish‐Arabic prayer books from the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries illustrate the role of prayer recitation as calming, initiating a sublime state of mind in warriors before battle.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn85">84</xref>Some commentators envision the last instructions as 90 percent prayer, wherein prayer is defined as “lifting up heart and mind to God.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn86">85</xref>Prayer is enjoined at least four times in the first stage (instructions 3, 6, 11, 15), four times in the second stage and five times in the third stage. Presumably its purpose here is the same as it was in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries: to induce a sublime state of mind before battle.</p>
            <p>In sum, the reiteration of the same themes seems to flood the mission with sanctity, and probably calms and reassures the ritual actors right into the last phase when they are told that, “After that—if God wills—there will be a meeting [with God] and the opening into the mercy of God.”</p>
            <fn-group>
               <fn id="fn85">
                  <label>84</label>
                  <p>Seidensticker, “Instructions Given,” 26–27.</p>
               </fn>
               <fn id="fn86">
                  <label>85</label>
                  <p>Clark McCauley, “Understanding the 9/11 Perpetrators: Crazy, Lost in Hate, or Martyred?” in<italic>History behind the Headlines: The Origins of Ethnic Conflicts Worldwide</italic>, ed. N. Matuszak (New York: Gale, 2002), 5:274–86, available at<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                               xlink:href="http://www.ideologiesofwar.com/docs/cm_understanding.htm"
                               xlink:type="simple">http://www.ideologiesofwar.com/docs/cm_understanding.htm</ext-link>under the heading “Prayer.”</p>
               </fn>
            </fn-group>
         </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Conclusion: On Ritualized Violence</title>
         <p>One apparent goal of the last night’s instructions was to saturate the mission with selected images from the foundations of Islamic cultural experience, inducing the ritual actors to perform, and a certain audience to recognize, an iconic analogue of a primordial act. If the instructions are to be taken as sincere, the ritual injunctions encourage the ritual actor to envision his identity as undergoing a structural metaphorical switch, from a contemporary man to a seventh‐century hero. This is because the instructions repeatedly enlist domains of experience from sanctified history and persuade him to imagine his mission in terms of heroic models.</p>
         <p>At a more intricate level, the metaphorical switch of the ritual actor might be deemed textural, not just structural. Structural metaphorical switches tend to translate between contemporary and ancient models based on some isomorphism of structure or similarity of relationship of parts (structural similarities), whereas textural transformations, according to Fernandez, tend to assimilate ritual actors to new personas based on similarity in feeling tone, contiguities in previous experience, or syntagmatic habit.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn87">86</xref>In this case a simulation of heroic mentality may have been produced by ritual acts such as reciting, praying, blowing Quranic verses into one’s possessions, purifying the body, and so on, which together induced a transformation irreducible to the sum of its parts. As Ricouer might see it, the metaphor was thickened and enriched by a spectrum of images, practices, and stories that attached themselves to the imaginative process when the ritual actor encountered the enacted metaphor, thus enhancing the paradoxical figuration of the 9/11 ritual actor as a seventh‐century holy warrior.</p>
         <p>Understanding the play of metaphor is therefore critical to understanding the last instructions. As Ricoeur might see it, the ritual actor has suspended his literal reference (the 9/11 hijackers are not really seventh‐century jihadists fighting Meccan polytheists) in order to allow a metaphorical reference (their motives are the same!) to emerge when he reads and follows the last instructions. At the same time, he had to preserve the ordinary vision (twenty‐first‐century hijacker) in tension with the figurative one (seventh‐century holy warrior) in order to grasp the ancient relevance of the contemporary situation. Based upon the repeated invocations of primordial battles and detailed ritual preparations (i.e., praying, purifying, blowing Quranic verses), it would appear to be the figurative vision that gave the ritual actors their motivating punch.</p>
         <p>In ritual performances in general, the line between suspended literal reference and embraced figurative reference is delicate. Johan Huizinga, Adolf Jensen, and Pierre Smith, among others, have hinted that one must cultivate a ludic appreciation of the events on the ritual stage, whereby one suspends one’s ordinary perspective on the ritual action in order to allow the ritual drama to emerge and to flourish.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn88">87</xref>The reiteration of sanctifying models and exhortations in the last instructions suggests that the 9/11 actors successfully embraced the ludic dimension of the ritual (revival of an ancient war on infidels) quite alongside the ritual’s apparent purpose (to kill passengers and harm the United States).</p>
         <p>From this we may venture a truism about those forms of religious terrorism which are based on ancient models. Ritual actors who draw inspiration from foundational struggles must maintain a contemporary, actual target for their activities at the same time as they emulate primordial legends and heroic personalities from the tradition’s roots. The radical vision iconically reconfigures the contemporary one and helps to deliver the action onto a primordial stage. The ritual actors and presumably their audiences too are expected to grasp this constellation of visions and to appreciate the ritual performance as one might appreciate an ancient and compelling work of art. Hence, however abhorrent to most people and particularly to the majority of Muslims, the last instructions bid the actors of September 11, 2001, to see their actions as iconically reconfiguring for a select audience a seventh century drama of primordial religious beauty.</p>
         <p>Aiding in this iconical reconfiguration were the microadjusting features of ritual performance. Procedures such as shaving, showering, praying, and blowing Quranic verses helped to heighten the register of the ritual event, and ultimately to instantiate an irreversible commitment to the end goal. Indeed, the entire ritual process might be seen as secondary to, or at least supportive of, the oath unto death in section 1. No differently than oaths in ancient war literature, the oath of the last instructions was a highly sanctified liturgical order that aimed to instantiate a commitment and to communicate binding intent.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn87">
               <label>86</label>
               <p>James Fernandez distinguished between textural and structural metaphorical transformations in “Persuasions and Performances: Of the Beast in Every Body … and the Metaphors of Everyman,”<italic>Daedalus</italic>101, no. 1 (1972): 39–60, esp. 47.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn88">
               <label>87</label>
               <p>Johann Huizinga,<italic>Homo Ludens: A Study of the Play‐Element in Culture</italic>(Boston: Beacon, 1950); Adolf E. Jensen,<italic>Myth and Cult among Primitive Peoples</italic>, trans. Marianna Tax Choldin and Wolfgang Weissleder (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1963); Pierre Smith, “Aspects of the Organization of Rites,” in<italic>Between Belief and Transgression: Structuralist Essays in Religion, History and Myth</italic>, ed. Michael Izard and Pierre Smith and trans. John Leavitt (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1979), 103–28.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
