<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4625829</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/513233</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR87225</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Glenn</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Whitehouse</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Florida Gulf Coast University.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2007</year>
            <string-date>April 2007</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>87</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>509553</issue-id>
         <fpage>299</fpage>
         <lpage>300</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Wall, </surname>
               <given-names>John</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>Moral Creativity: Paul Ricoeur and the Poetics of Possibility</source>. Reflection and Theory in the Study of Religion Series. New York: Oxford University Press, 2005. viii+234 pp. $55.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/513233"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In<italic>Moral Creativity</italic>, John Wall gives us a work that is at once a constructive metaethical reflection, an interpretation of Paul Ricoeur, and a conversation with various strands of postmodern philosophical and theological ethics.</p>
      <p>Wall claims that “moral life is inherently creative” and that this fact “demands a fundamental rethinking of the nature and meaning of moral life itself” (vii). For Wall, creativity is a possibility that is primordial to human being, ultimately expressing humans’ imitation of the creative power of God. The importance of creativity has been covered over by a tendency in the West to separate poetics from ethics. Wall aims to remedy this lack by explicating moral creativity as the capacity to invent an ever more inclusive vision of life. This moral creativity is developed in stages, from the being of the moral self as a creative tension of freedom and finitude (chap. 1), to the capacity of humans to bring narrative unity to their moral lives (chap. 2), through the poetic response demanded by otherness (chap. 3), to the creation of ideologies and utopias in social life (chap. 4). As an original contribution to moral reflection, this book has much to recommend it. While it is certainly not unusual today to see a call for ethics to become poetic, in postmodernism this usually means abandoning ethical reflection in favor of poetic invention of self or community. Wall manages instead to link poetic creativity to philosophical reflection, making creativity the symbolic ground of discourses of philosophical anthropology, teleological and deontological ethics, and social critical/liberationist thought. Wall’s use of specific narratives is likewise fruitful: tragedy is used for reflection on the status of moral evil and limitation, while the biblical creation story is interpreted to symbolize the potentialities of creativity. In sum, the book delivers on its promise to heal the divide between poetics and ethics, rather than simply replacing ethics with poetics.</p>
      <p>
         <italic>Moral Creativity</italic>is also a book about Paul Ricoeur. Throughout, Wall turns to Ricoeur’s philosophical and religious thought for theoretical support, using a wide range of primary and secondary literature. Wall works from a Ricoeurian idea that the self is a synthesis of activity and passivity, freedom and finitude. He finds in this ontology of selfhood a basis for conceiving of creativity as the activity of inventing free action amid the limitations of finitude. This anthropology is then tied to Ricoeur’s work on narrative identity, love, ideology, and other topics. Wall’s exegesis of Ricoeur is accurate and astute, succinctly connecting the thinker’s early and late writings on selfhood. The book faults Ricoeur for having an insufficient sense for the entrenchment of social/cultural injustice and for the radical otherness of other people. The discussion of Ricoeur and Emmanuel Levinas on otherness is one of the most interesting parts of the book but also an argument that might need expansion. Wall laments Ricoeur’s decision to separate philosophy from religious discourse, claiming this was a purely pragmatic decision whereby “Ricoeur ultimately does himself a disservice” (181). This may be so, but regardless of intent, wouldn’t we have to say that such a separation is part of the thought world projected by Ricoeur’s writings? Patching over this separation may bring Ricoeur closer to writers of the current “theological turn” of postmodernism but possibly at the price of losing one of Ricoeur’s great virtues—his usefulness in mediating between postmodernism and the modernity that insists on dividing religion and reason.</p>
      <p>Finally, in<italic>Moral Creativity</italic>Wall carries out a dialogue with a wide variety of contemporary philosophical and theological voices, including narrative theology, recent Aristotelianisms, feminism, liberation theology, communicative ethics, and others. Often, the intent is to show how the voice captures only one side of the tension between freedom and finitude. Ricoeur, with his passive/active model of selfhood, is presented as the corrective to such one‐sided accounts. In fact, one of the great virtues of the book is the fact that it makes Ricoeur’s voluminous writings available to the debates of contemporary ethics in an accessible way. Wall’s original reflections on contemporary ethical thought are clear‐eyed as well, particularly some of his comments on the status of evil in narrative theology.</p>
      <p>Wall has skillfully woven the exegetical, dialogical, and constructive parts of his project into a thought‐provoking and readable work.<italic>Moral Creativity</italic>could be profitably read by anyone familiar with contemporary debates in religious and philosophical ethics. It will both broaden the appeal of Ricoeur’s writings and advance the conversation about the relation of ethics to poetics.</p>
   </body>
</article>
