<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">interevieducinte</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100192</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>International Review of Education / Internationale Zeitschrift für Erziehungswissenschaft / Revue Internationale de l'Education</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00208566</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15730638</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">41480683</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Dancing on the deck of the Titanic? Adult education, the nation-state and new social movements</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Carlos Alberto</given-names>
                  <surname>Torres</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>57</volume>
         <issue>1/2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40072145</issue-id>
         <fpage>39</fpage>
         <lpage>55</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2011 Springer and UNESCO Institute for Lifelong Learning</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/41480683"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article begins with a discussion of the implications of CONFINTEA VI having been organised in Brazil - the author uses the term "Brazilian effect" - and the role of social movements challenging neoliberalism. Next, drawing from the experience of Latin America, this paper analyses the counterhegemonic practice of the new social movements. The concluding section highlights the dilemmas faced by UNESCO in trying to create a democratic and efficient process of policy-making and institutional service in adult education in the nationstates. Furthermore, the proposal of popular education portrayed by the new social movements is described as a tool for empowerment. CONFINTEA VI's recommendation of moving from rhetoric to action in adult education programmes, practices and policies demands that we take the agendas of the new social movements in the post-neoliberalism era seriously. Cet article commence par une discussion sur les implications de CONFINTEA VI organisée au Brésil - l'auteur utilise le terme « effet Brésil » - ainsi que sur le rôle des mouvements sociaux qui contestent le néolibéralisme. À partir de l'expérience de l'Amérique latine, l'auteur analyse ensuite la pratique des nouveaux mouvements sociaux qui s'oppose à toutes les formes d'hégémonie. Dans la dernière partie sont abordés les dilemmes auxquels est confrontée l'UNESCO dans ses efforts de créer au coeur des Étatsnations un mécanisme démocratique et efficace d'élaboration de politiques et de prestations institutionnelles en matière d'éducation des adultes. En outre, l'éducation populaire telle qu'elle est proposée par les nouveaux mouvements sociaux y est décrite comme un instrument d'autonomisation. La recommandation de CONFINTEA VI de passer de la parole aux actes dans les programmes, les pratiques et les politiques d'éducation des adultes exige que nous prenions au sérieux les concepts des nouveaux mouvements sociaux en cette ère postnéolibérale. Dieser Artikel beginnt mit einer Diskussion darüber, was es bedeutet, dass die CONFINTEA VI in Brasilien organisiert wurde - der Autor benutzt den Begriff „Brasilien-Effekt“ - und der Rolle der sozialen Bewegungen, die sich gegen den Neoliberalismus richten. Sodann wird, aufbauend auf den Erfahrungen Lateinamerikas, die gegenhegemoniale Praxis der neuen sozialen Bewegungen analysiert. Im Schlussteil wird darauf eingegangen, in welchen Dilemmata die UNESCO steckt, wenn sie versucht, einen demokratischen und effizienten Prozess für Politikgestaltung und institutionelle Dienstleistungen der Erwachsenenbildung in den Nationalstaaten zu initiieren. Zudem wird der von den neuen sozialen Bewegungen ausgearbeitete Vorschlag der Volksbildung als Ermachtigungsinstrument beschrieben. Die Empfehlung der CONFINTEA VI, bei den Programmen, der praktischen Umsetzung und den politischen Strategien im Bereich der Erwachsenenbildung den Worten nunmehr Taten folgen zu lassen, erfordert eine ernsthafte Beschäftigung mit den Vorstellungen der neuen sozialen Bewegungen in der postneoliberalen Ära. Este artículo comienza con un comentario sobre las implicaciones - que el autor denomina "efecto brasileño" - de que la CONFINTEA VI haya sido organizada en Brasil y el papel que desempeñan los movimientos sociales en su desafío al neoliberalismo. Luego, partiendo de la experiencia de América Latina, analiza la práctica contra-hegemónica de los nuevos movimientos sociales. En la parte final se realzan los dilemas encarados por la UNESCO en el intento de crear un proceso democrático y eficiente de delineación de políticas y servicio institucional en la educación para personas adultas dentro de los estados nacionales. Además, la propuesta de educación popular que presentan los nuevos movimientos sociales está descrita como herramienta de empoderamiento. La recomendación de la CONFINTEA VI, de pasar de la retórica a la acción en programas, prácticas y políticas de educación de personas adultas, exige que tomemos en serio las agendas de los nuevos movimientos sociales en la era del postneoliberalismo. Данная статья начинается с дискуссии о результатах КОНФИНТЕА VI, которая проводилась в Бразилии. Автор использует термин «бразильский эффект» и обсуждает роль социальных движе-ний относительно неолиберализма. Далее, основываясь на опыте Латинской Америки, в данной статье анализируется антиглобальная практика новых социальных движений. В заключительной части подчеркиваются проблемы, стоящие перед ЮНЕСКО, пытающейся создать демократический и эффек-тивный процесс политических и институциональных услуг в образовании взрослых в государствах-нациях. К то же время предложение народного образования, представленного новыми социальными движениями, рассматривается как инструмеит расширения полномочий. Рекомендация КОНФИНТЕА VI о переходе от заявлений к действиям в программах, практикe и политике образования взрослых настаивает на том, чтобы программы новых социальных движений в эпоху пост-неолиберализма рассматривались серьезно.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d3282e116a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d3282e123" publication-type="other">
(Teodoro and Torres 2007, p. 1).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d3282e139a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e143" publication-type="other">
Antikainen, A. (2005). Empowerment and control: A state intervention into participation in adult
education in Finland. European Education, 37(2), 21-31.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e153a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e157" publication-type="other">
Antikainen, A. (2006). In search of the Nordic Model in education. Scandinavian Journal of Educational
Research, 50(3), 229-243.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e167a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e171" publication-type="other">
Antikainen, A., Harinen, P., &amp; Torres, C. A. (Eds.). (2006). In from the margins: Adult education, work
and civil society. The Hague: Sense.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e181a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e185" publication-type="other">
Apple, M. W. (2004). Ideology and curriculum (3rd ed.). New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e193a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e197" publication-type="other">
Amove, R. (1986). Education and revolution in Nicaragua. New York: Praeger Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e204a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e208" publication-type="other">
Amove, R. F., &amp; Torres, C. A. (1995). Adult education and state policy in Latin America: The contrasting
cases of Mexico and Nicaragua. Comparative Education, 31(3), 311-325.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e218a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e222" publication-type="other">
Carnoy, M., &amp; Levin, H. (Eds.). (1985). Schooling and work in the democratic state. Stanford, CA:
Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e232a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e236" publication-type="other">
Carnoy, M., &amp; Samoff, J. (1990). With M. A. Burris, A. Johnston &amp; C. A. Torres (Eds.), Education and
Social Transition in the Third World. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e246a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e250" publication-type="other">
Dale, R. (2000). Globalization and education: Demonstrating a "common world education culture" or
locating a "globally structured educational agenda"? Educational Theory, 50(4), 427-448.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e260a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e264" publication-type="other">
Daly, K., Schugurensky, D., &amp; Lops, K. (Eds.). (2009). Learning democracy by doing: Alternative
practices in citizenship learning and participatory democracy. Toronto: Transformative Learning
Centre, OISE/UT.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e278a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e282" publication-type="other">
Desjardins, R., Rubenson, K., &amp; Milana, M. (2006). Unequal chances to participate in adult learning:
International perspectives. Paris: UNESCO, HEP.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e292a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e296" publication-type="other">
Dialogue. (2010). Interview with Carlos Pineiro Iñiguez, Monday 12 July 2010, p. 12. Accessed
December 15, 2010, from http://www.paginal2.com.ar/diario/dialogos/21-149326-2010-07-12.html.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e306a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e310" publication-type="other">
Faure, E., et al. (1972). Learning to be. Paris: UNESCO.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e317a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e321" publication-type="other">
Freire, P. (1968). Pedagogy of the oppressed. New York: Continuum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e328a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e332" publication-type="other">
Freire, P. (1997). El grito manso, Paulo Freire en la Universidad de San Luis. San Luis, Argentina:
Universidad de San Luis, Siglo XXI.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e342a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e346" publication-type="other">
Freire, P. (1998). Politics and Education. Los Angeles UCLA Latin American Center Publications.
Translated by Pia Lindquist Wong, with an introduction entitled "The Political Pedagogy of Paulo
Freire" by Carlos Alberto Torres.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e360a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e364" publication-type="other">
Gadotti, M. (2010). Foro social mundial. Em Processo. São Paulo, Brazil: IPF.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e371a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e375" publication-type="other">
Gadotti, M., &amp; Torres, C. A. (Eds.). (1993). Educación popular: Crisis y perspectivas. Buenos Aires,
Argentina: Miño y Dávila Editores.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e385a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e389" publication-type="other">
Gadotti, M., &amp; Torres, С. А. (2009). Paulo Freire: Education for development. Development and change,
40(6), 1255-1267.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e399a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e403" publication-type="other">
Galbraith, J. K. (1954). The Great Crash, 1929 (p. xx). Cambridge: Houghton Mifflin Co.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e410a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e414" publication-type="other">
Hake, В. J. (2006). Late modernity and learning society: problematic articulations between social arenas,
organisations and individuals. In R. V. Castro, A. V. Sancho, &amp; P. Guimarães (Eds.), Adult
education. New routes in a new landscape (pp. 31-56). Braga, Portugal: Unit for Adult Education of
the University of Minho.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e430a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e434" publication-type="other">
Hinzen, H. (2007). CONFINTEA VI—The UNESCO International Conference on Adult Education in the
context of MGDS, EFA, UNLD, LIFE and DESD. Convergence, 40(3/4), 265-283.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e445a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e449" publication-type="other">
International Civil Society Forum (FISC). (2009). What is the FISC? Accessed December 15, 2010, from
http://www.fisc2009.org/eng/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=17&amp;Itemid=2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e459a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e463" publication-type="other">
Jones, L., &amp; Torres, C. A. (2010). The struggle for memory and social justice education: Popular
education and social movements reclaiming Latin American Civil Society. In P. Rose (Ed.),
Achieving education for all through public-private partnerships?: Non-state provision of education
in developing countries. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e479a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e483" publication-type="other">
Kettunen, P. (2004). The Nordic model and consensual competitiveness in Finland. In A. M. Castén, et al.
(Eds.), Between sociology and history. Essays on microhistory, collective action and nation-
building. Helsinki: SKS.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e496a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e500" publication-type="other">
Knoll, J. H. (2007). The history of the UNESCO International Conferences on Adult Education.
Convergence, 40(3/4), 21-41.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e510a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e514" publication-type="other">
Lima, L. C. (2010a). On the right hand of lifelong education. Unpublished paper presented to a meeting
of ICAE, Germany.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e524a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e528" publication-type="other">
Lima, L. C. (2010b). Do FISC para a CONFINTEA VI, em Belém do Pará. Associação O Direito de
Aprender Accessed December 15, 2010, from http://www.direitodeaprender.com.pt.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e539a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e543" publication-type="other">
Matynia, E. (2009). Performative democracy. Boulder, CO: Paradigm.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e550a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e554" publication-type="other">
Meyer, J., Kamens, D., &amp; Benavot, A. (1992). School knowledge for the masses: World models and
national primary curricular categories in the twentieth century. Philadelphia: Falmer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e564a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e568" publication-type="other">
Milani, С. R. S. &amp; Laniado, R. N. (2006). Transnational social movements and the globalization agenda:
A methodological approach based on the analysis of the World Social Forum. Working Paper 5,
December 2006. The Edelstein Center for Social Research. Accessed December 15, 2010, from
http://www.edelsteincenter.org.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e584a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e588" publication-type="other">
Morrow, R., &amp; Torres, C. A. (1995). Social theory and education: A critique of theories of social and
cultural reproduction. Albany, NY: State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e598a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e602" publication-type="other">
O'Cadiz, P., Torres, C. A., &amp; Wong, P, (1998). Education and democracy: Paulo Freire, social
movements, and educational reform in Sao Paulo. Boulder, CO: Westview Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e612a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e616" publication-type="other">
Olmos, L., Van Heertum, R., &amp; Torres, C. A. (Eds.). (2010). In the shadows of neoliberal globalization:
Educational reform in the last 25 years in comparative perspective. Oak Park, IL: Bentham Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e627a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e631" publication-type="other">
Rizvi, F. (2006). Imagination and the globalization of educational policy research. Globalization,
Societies and Education, 4(2), 193-206.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e641a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e645" publication-type="other">
Robertson, S. L. (2003). WTO/GATS and the global education services industry. Globalization, Societies
and Education, 1(3), 259-266.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e655a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e659" publication-type="other">
Schugurensky, D., &amp; Torres, C. A. (1994). Adult education and political education: Lessons from
comparative, cross-national research in Cuba, México, Nicaragua, and Tanzania. In B. Claussen
(Ed.), Aspects of globalization and internationalization of political education. Hamburg: Krämer.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e672a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e676" publication-type="other">
Teodoro, A. (2003). Educational policies and new ways of governance in a transnationalization period. In
C. A. Torres &amp; A. Antikainen (Eds.), The international handbook on the sociology of education.
Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e689a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e693" publication-type="other">
Teodoro, A., &amp; Torres, C. A. (2007). Introduction. Critique and utopia in the sociology of education.
In C. A. Torres &amp; A. Teodoro (Eds.), Critique and utopia: New developments in the sociology of
education (pp. 1-8). Lanham: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e706a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e710" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A. (1989). Political culture and state bureaucracy in Mexico: The case of adult education.
International Journal of Educational Development, 9(1), 53-68.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e721a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e725" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A. (1991). The state, nonformal education, and socialism in Cuba, Nicaragua. Comparative
Education Review, 39(1), 1-27.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e735a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e739" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A. (1995a). State and education revisited: Why educational researchers should think politically
about education. Review of Research in Education, 21, 255-331.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e749a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e753" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A. (1995b). Estado, políticas públicas e educação de adultos. In M. Gadotti &amp; J. E. Romão
(Eds.), Educação de Jovens e Adultos. Teoria, pratica e proposta. São Paulo, Brazil: Cortez Editora
and Paulo Freire Institute.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e766a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e770" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A. (1996). Adult education and instrumental rationality: A critique. International Journal of
Educational Development, 16(2), 195-206.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e780a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e784" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A. (2009a). Globalizations and education : Collected essays on class, race, gender, and the
state. New York: Teachers College Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e794a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e798" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A. (2009b). Education and globalization. New York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e806a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e810" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A., &amp; Puiggrós, A. (1995). The state and public education in Latin America. Boulder, CO:
Westview Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e820a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e824" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A., &amp; Schugurensky, D. (1994). The politics of adult education in comparative perspective:
Models, rationalities and adult education policy implementation in Canada, Mexico and Tanzania.
Comparative Education, 30(2), 131-152.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e837a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e841" publication-type="other">
Torres, C. A., &amp; Schugurensky, D. (1995). A therapeutic model of adult education in Canada: Skills and
academic upgrading programs in the province of Alberta. International Journal of Lifelong
Education, 14(2), 144-161.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e854a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e858" publication-type="other">
UIL (UNESCO Institute for Lifelong Learning) (2009). Global Report on Adult Learning and Education.
Hamburg: UNESCO Institute for Lifelong Learning.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e868a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e872" publication-type="other">
UIL (UNESCO Institute for Lifelong Learning) (2010). The Belem Framework for Action. Harnessing the
power and potential of adult learning and education for a viable future. Hamburg: UNESCO
Institute for Lifelong Learning.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e885a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e889" publication-type="other">
Zibechi, R. (2003). Los Movimientos sociales latinoamericanos: tendencias y desafíos. In OSAL,
Observatorio de America Latina, 9(January 2003), 185-188.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3282e900a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3282e904" publication-type="other">
Zibechi, R. (2007). La educación en los Movimientos Sociales. FLAPE. Foro Latinoamericano de
Políticas Educativas. Available from www.foro-latino.org/flape/. . ./MovSociales/educacion_en_
los_mov_sociales.pdf.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
