<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philrefo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018096</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philosophia Reformata</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318035</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23528230</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24707974</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>REFORMATIONAL PHILOSOPHY ON THE BOUNDARY BETWEEN THE PAST AND THE FUTURE</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Jacob</given-names>
                  <surname>Klapwijk</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Herbert Donald</given-names>
                  <surname>Morton</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1987</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>52</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24707971</issue-id>
         <fpage>101</fpage>
         <lpage>134</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24707974"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d926e113a1310">
            <label>*</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e120" publication-type="other">
This paper was prepared for the Third International Symposium of the Association for Calvin-
ist Philosophy, On Being Human', and presented on August 15,1987 at Zeist, The Netherlands,
in celebration of the Fiftieth Anniversary of the Association.
To facilitate international discussion I have referred to English-language publications as much
as possible, in both the text and the notes. As a regrettable but unavoidable result, a number of
publications important to the Association have been left out of consideration.
I wish to thank especially, among those to whom I am indebted, dr. J. D. Dengerink and dr.
M. D. Stafleu, for their extensive and documented commentaries on an earlier version of the
text.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e152a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e159" publication-type="other">
See J. Klapwijk, 'Rationality in the Dutch Neo-Calvinist Tradition', pp. 94-99.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e166a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e173" publication-type="other">
For a profound analysis of Kuyper's view, see S.U. Zuidema, 'Common Grace and Chris-
tian Action in Abraham Kuyper', trans. Harry van Dyke, in Communication and Confron-
tation, pp. 52-106. With respect to Calvin, Kuyper, Dooyeweerd and Vollenhoven see further
Klapwijk, 'Calvin and Neo-Calvinism on Non-Christian Philosophy' and 'Dooyeweerd's
Christian Philosophy'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e192a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e199" publication-type="other">
J. H. Bavinck, An Introduction to the Science of Missions, pp. 178-79. Cf. C. H. Kraft,
Christianity in Culture, pp. 318-23, 345-59.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e210a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e217" publication-type="other">
Cf. G. W. F. Hegel, Einleitung in die Geschichte der Philosophie, p. 192.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e224a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e231" publication-type="other">
See for a further elaboration Klapwijk, 'Antithesis, Synthesis, and the Idea of Transfor-
mational Philosophy', and 'The Idea of Transformational Philosophy'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e241a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e248" publication-type="other">
See D. H. Th. Vollenhoven, Isagoogi Philosophiae, §171, p. 119.
Characteristic of Vollenhoven's position is a statement such as the following: 'If you be-
lieve God's Word and trust that Word, you obtain a philosophy the basis of which is formed
by that non-philosophical, non-scientific belief in Holy Scripture and in God' ('Schriftge-
bruik en wijsbegeerte', MVCW, September 1953, p. 8).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e267a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e274" publication-type="other">
See, e.g., H. Dooyeweerd, A New Critique of Theoretical Thought, vol. 1, pp. 173-74; vol. 2,
p. 52.
Characteristic of Dooyeweerd's position is a statement such as the following: 'The philoso-
phy of the cosmonomic idea rejects indeed every notion of a scriptural philosophy that seeks
support in particular Bible texts for statements of intrinsically philosophical and, in general,
scientific problems and theories' ('De strijd om het schriftuurlijk karakter van de Wijsbegeerte
der Wetsidee', MVCW, July 1950, p. 3).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e300a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e307" publication-type="other">
For the review in question, see Klapwijk, 'Over mogelijkheden van christelijk filosoferen'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e314a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e321" publication-type="other">
This new development began with Dooyeweerd's 'De transcendentale critiek van het
wijsgeerig denken' (1939) and 'De transcendentale critiek van het wijsgeerig denken en de
grondslagen van de wijsgeerige denkgemeenschap van het Avondland' (1941). Cf. J. N.
Kraay, 'Successive Conceptions in the Development of the Christian Philosophy of Herman
Dooyeweerd', Philosophia Reformata 45, 1/2 (1980): 26, 29, 39.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e341a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e348" publication-type="other">
See, e.g., H. Evan Runner, 'The Relation of the Bible to Learning' and H. van Riessen,
Wijsbegeerte. In his personal presentation of Dooyeweerd's philosophy, H. J. van Eikema
Hommes, in contrast, arrives at a complete rejection of 'such external points of contact
between biblical revelation and scientific problems', which are called 'scholastic' in character
and hence reveal the need for 'an inner point of connection resident in the nature of scientific
thought itself (Inleiding tot de Wijsbegeerte van Herman Dooyeweerd, pp. 9, 11).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e371a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e380" publication-type="other">
Philosophy and worldview both have a religious starting point, so Dooyeweerd and Vollen-
hoven maintain. The question however is whether philosophical thought is conditioned in
its own turn by worldview. Although in Vollenhoven and even more so in Dooyeweerd
there is a tendency to deny the latter, their standpoint on the issue is not entirely consistent.
Vollenhoven writes: 'What the view of life is to non-scientific knowledge, philosophy is to
scientific knowledge' ('Schriftgebruik en wijsbegeerte', p. 8). Yet as it turns out, philosophy
on the one hand and life and world view on the other are not completely separated in his
conception, for he continues: 'scientific knowledge never loses all traces of what is non-
scientific'. Dooyeweerd observes: 'Philosophy cannot take the place of a life- and world-view,
nor the reverse, for the task of each of the two is different' (A New Critique, vol. 1, p. 128);
and elsewhere: Ά life- and world-view may not be "elaborated" philosophically. It must
elaborate itself (Ibid., p. 158). Nonetheless, he goes on to say also: Ά life - and world-view
should come to theoretical clarity in philosophic thought' (Ibid., p. 165). I call such state-
ments happy inconsistencies!</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e428a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e435" publication-type="other">
To accomplish that was the main reason I recently wrote Oriëntalie in de Nieuwe Filosofie.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e442a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e449" publication-type="other">
The mediating role of the worldview between religion and philosophy has been presented
clearly in our circles by A. M. Wolters, who writes in his Creation Regained: 'Philosophical
categories... are themselves decisively shaped by a deeper-lying worldview' (p. 97). It remains
unclear in this work however whether worldviews play a mediating role between religion
and philosophy just in historical or also in systematical perspective. This question applies
especially to the reformational worldview. Taking a systematic point of view, Wolters more or
less identifies the reformational or calvinistic worldview with the biblical religion or 'biblical
worldview' in the normative sense. In contrast, he approaches other Christian worldviews
from a historical point of view and considers them one-sided in their mediating role (p. 10).
Cf. his 'Dutch Neo-Calvinism: Worldview, Philosophy, and Rationality'. See further J. H.
Olthuis, 'On Worldviews'; and S. Griffioen, P. Marshall, and R. Mouw, eds., Worldview and
Social Theory.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e491a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e498" publication-type="other">
Cf. A. Kuyper, Lectures on Calvinism, chs. 1 and 6.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e505a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e514" publication-type="other">
In the conception of Dooyeweerd the 'cosmonomic idea' (Dutch: wetsidee) is a limiting
concept within philosophy regarding the coherence, unity and origin of all reality. It refers
by way of philosophical approximation to three boundary problems: the mysteries of the
world, of man, and of God (A New Critique, vol. 1, p. 101). In my view it is not so much
religion (as ultimate commitment) as it is the worldview that can shed light on these mys-
teries, since in the worldview a view of man and a view of God are always inevitably in-
cluded. See A. Kuyper, Lectures and Calvinism, p. 19.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e541a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e548" publication-type="other">
Calvin emphasizes both when he writes: Ί call "service" not only what lies in obedience
to God's Word but what turns the mind of man, empty of its own carnal sense, wholly to the
bidding of God's Spirit' (Institutes, III, vii, 1).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e561a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e568" publication-type="other">
Cf. Klapwijk, On Worldview and Philosophy'. For the 'expressivist' vision of life, see C.
Taylor, Hegel and the Modern Society, pp. 2-3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e578a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e585" publication-type="other">
The idea of creation ordinances may be found in, e.g., the Confessio Augustana, art. 16;
in Melanchthon's Apologia, art. 16; and in Calvin's Institutes, I, v, 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e595a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e602" publication-type="other">
See, e.g. Kuyper, De gemeene grade, 3d ed., vol. 3, passim; Kuyper, Pro Rege, vol. 1, pp.
447-57; and Geesink, Van 's Heeren Ordinantiën.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e612a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e619" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Vernieuwing en bezinning, p. 241. This passage has not been included in
Roots of Western Culture.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e629a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e636" publication-type="other">
Calvin even speaks of a 'principle' when discussing the inner coherence of the creation
and its renewal, and so says regarding man as the image of God: 'For although I confess that
these forms of speaking are synechdoches, yet this principle cannot be overthrown, that what
was primary in the renewing of God's image also held the highest place in the creation itself
(Institutes, I, xv, 4).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e656a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e663" publication-type="other">
Attractive in Nicholas Wolterstorffs position is that he sees both: the creation perspective
and the perspective of shalom, 'Amsterdam' and 'Lima'. The weak side of his position to my
mind is that the two perspectives have not been actually integrated: 'The cultural mandate
is insufficient as a grounding for the practice of scholarship. One meets as well the mandate
to work for shalom' (Until Justice and Peace Embrace, p. 172).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e682a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e689" publication-type="other">
I just borrow the expression from Paul Ricœur. I take distance from its dialectical back-
ground, which is described by Ricaeur himself as a 'dialectic with postponed synthesis'
(Histoire et Vérité, p. 16). For the rest, I would recall that the symbolism of the apocalypse,
particularly in Revelation 22, itself refers to the symbolism of the creation account.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e705a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e712" publication-type="other">
J. P. A. Mekkes, Tijd der bezinning (1973), p. 60; Radix, tijd en kennen (1970), p. 183.
Already in Scheppingsopenbaring en wijsbegeerte (1961) we find the words: 'The way of cre-
ation [is] the way of the Kingdom' (p. 90). See also H. G. Geertsema, who in his paper
'Higher Education as Service to the King' starts (!) with 'the Christian expectation' and
subsequently relates it to 'the order of God's creation' (pp. 54-72).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e731a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e738" publication-type="other">
See E. Levinas, Totalité et infini, p. 261 and T. W. Adorno, Minima moralia, § 153.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e745a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e752" publication-type="other">
Cf. T. de Boer, 'De filosofie van Dooyeweerd', pp. 250-51.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e759a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e766" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, Isagoogè Philosophiae, §§ 13-18, pp. 12-16.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e774a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e781" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, A New Critique, vol. 1, p. 4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e788a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e795" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd recognizes the problem, to be sure, when he asks, 'Is sinful reality still mean-
ing?' And then he acknowledges: 'Here we indeed touch the deepest problem of Christian
philosophy'. But the answer follows, without restriction and without hesitation, on the same
page: 'Sinful reality remains apostate meaning under the law and under the curse of God's
wrath' (A New Critique, vol. 2, p. 33). The 'Why?' of the Crucified One and so many cross
bearers finds no echo here.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e818a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e825" publication-type="other">
J. van der Hoeven, 'The Problem of Evil - Crucible for the Authenticity and Modesty of
Philosophizing: In Discussion with Paul Ricoeur', South African Journal of Philosophy 5, 2
(1986): 44-52.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e838a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e845" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, A New Critique, vol. 1, pp. 83-85; vol. 2, pp. 429-35.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e852a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e859" publication-type="other">
C. Van Til: 'There is no naive experience as a primary datum any more than that there
is anything like theoretical thought as such'. (Jerusalem and Athens, p. 109).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e869a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e876" publication-type="other">
J. D. Kim, 'Wissen und Glauben', pp. 55, 86, 139, etc.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e884a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e891" publication-type="other">
See M. Heidegger, Sein und Zeit, §§ 7, 31-33 and R. Bultmann, History and Eschatology,
ch. 8.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e901a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e908" publication-type="other">
I refer here to an untitled lecture of 1980 by M. C. Smit, which has recently appeared as
ch. 9 under the title 'Bedenkingen tegen de objectief-wetenschappelijke en historisch-
hermeneutische denkwijzen van deze tijd' in De eerste en tweede geschiedenis: Nagelaten ge-
schriften van Meijer C. Smit.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e924a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e931" publication-type="other">
H.-G. Gadamer, Truth and Method, pp. 271-74,340-41. Cf. also L. D. Derksen, On Univer-
sal Hermeneutics, pp. 107-79.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e941a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e948" publication-type="other">
See J. Klapwijk, 'The Universal in Hans-Georg Gadamer's Hermeneutic Philosophy'; and
H. Vander Goot, Interpreting the Bible, pp. 15-17.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e958a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e965" publication-type="other">
For this supratemporal but to Dooyeweerd's mind not static character of the human heart
see Dooyeweerd, A New Critique, vol. 1, pp. 30-33; and In the Twilight of Western Thought,
p. 19.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e978a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e985" publication-type="other">
See A. Kuyper, Lectures on Calvinism, pp. 20, 45-46.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e993a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1000" publication-type="other">
See Vollenhoven, Isagoogè Philosophiae §§ 113-34, pp. 74-98; and also especially 'Proble-
men van de tijd in onze kring'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1010a1310">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1017" publication-type="other">
Cf. Heidegger, Sein und Zeit, pp. 38, 313-14, 426.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1024a1310">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1031" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, Isagoogè Philosophiae, p. 96.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1038a1310">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1045" publication-type="other">
Calvin, Institutes, I, i, 12.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1052a1310">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1059" publication-type="other">
M. Buber speaks of 'das Apriori der Beziehung; dos eingeborene Du' (Dos Dialogische Prin-
zip, p. 31). E. Levinas refers to 'la conjonction extraordinaire de l'homme fini et mortal et
d'un Dieu infini et "absolument autre" ' ('Religion et idée de l'infini').</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1072a1310">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1079" publication-type="other">
This historical approach is maintained by Calvin throughout the first three books of his
Institutes. See also the title of II, iv and, for the messianic perspective, III, ix and III, xxv.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1090a1310">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1097" publication-type="other">
According to John Kraay this is really what the later Dooyeweerd also had in mind: 'The
heart of man is nothing other than the ek-sistent self-transcendence toward God, fellow-man,
and cosmos' ('Successive Conceptions in the Development of the Christian Philosophy of
Herman Dooyeweerd', p. 35). Yes, according to Kim, in Dooyeweerd man's heart is his ek-
sistentiality, 'wie sie geschichtlich, geselschaftlich vermittelt ist' ('Wissen und Glauben', p.
131). Although perhaps too free as interpretations, in some ways these are, it seems to me,
necessary corrections.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1123a1310">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1130" publication-type="other">
See J. P. A. Mekkes, Tijd der bezinning; M. F. J. Marlet, Grundlinien, H. van Riessen,
Wijsbegeerte; D. F. M. Strauss, 'An Analysis of the Structure of Analysis'; and H. G. Geertse-
ma, 'Transcendentale openheid'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1143a1310">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1150" publication-type="other">
See Zuidema, 'Transcendentale problemen', pp. 3-4, Geertsema, 'Transcendentale
openheid', pp. 48-49; Mekkes, 'Bijdrage'; Th. De Boer, 'De filosofie van Dooyeweerd', pp.
252-53. Cf. in this regard Dooyeweerd, A New Critique, vol. 1, pp. 56-59.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1163a1310">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1170" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, A New Critique, vol. 1, p. 38.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1177a1310">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1184" publication-type="other">
For this reason I also share De Boer's view that the Christian-religious ground motive, as
it is presented by Dooyeweerd, must be regarded as a 'hermeneutical guideline' ('De filosofie
van Dooyeweerd', pp. 248, 251, 258, 260).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1197a1310">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1204" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, A New Critique, vol. 1, p. 38.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1212a1310">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1219" publication-type="other">
Mekkcs, Tijd der bezinning, pp. 14, 31, 81-82.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1226a1310">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1233" publication-type="other">
Van Ricssen, Wijsbegeerte, p. 26.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1240a1310">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1247" publication-type="other">
I take distance here from the language used by K.-O. Apel. Apel speaks of a 'transcenden-
tal-hermeneutical synthesis' which would be proper to the pre-theoretical constitution of
the Lebenstaeli (Heidegger, Wittgenstein) and which would found the kantian synthesis of
apperception. See Apel, Transformation der Philosophie, vol. 1, pp. 246, 308.1 reject however
the notion of pre-theoretical 'synthesis' and prefer the notion of 'systasis', i.e., the oneness
(één-zijri) of man and world, subject and object, in pre-scientific experience. Transcendental
hermeneutical reflection can for the rest not be called pre-scientific, because and insofar as
it is explicitly engaged in tracing man's transcendental openness.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1276a1310">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1283" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, Tijd der bezinning, pp. 19-25, 57. That transcendental hermeneutical reflection
occurs elsewhere as well needs no argument. Naturally, perspectives change. One may think
of Heidegger and his idea of the 'abyss', of Levinas and his idea of 'the infinite', of M. Polanyi
and his idea of a 'tacit dimension'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1299a1310">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1306" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, Tijd der bezinning, p. 39; cf. pp. 48, 66, 73.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1313a1310">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1320" publication-type="other">
Ibid, pp. 39, 43, 46, 55, 58.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1328a1310">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1335" publication-type="other">
Ibid., pp. 46, 58.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1342a1310">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1349" publication-type="other">
J. Klapwijk, 'Geloof en rede in de théologie van Troeltsch en Pannenberg', pp. 81-82. See
also W. Pannenberg, Grundfragen systematischer Theologie, pp. 142-51.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1359a1310">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1366" publication-type="other">
Karl Popper's well-known notion that the perception of the empirical facts is already
theory-laden must mean, as I would re-formulate it, that the perception of the empirical
facts - even apart from science - is in any case worldview-laden. At the same time, I assume
that an element of theory has been integrated into practically every modern worldview -
think of evolutionism or of historical materialism. In Popper too as it turns out the 'theory'
that is said to be presupposed in observation amounts more generally to a 'point of view'. It
can, so he holds, be a theory but also a general expectation or a myth. See Popper, Conjectures
and Refutations, p. 47.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1395a1310">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1402" publication-type="other">
Cf. J. Klapwijk, 'Science and Social Responsibility', pp. 87-89.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1409a1310">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1416" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Roots, p. 61.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1423a1310">
            <label>63</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1430" publication-type="other">
For Dooyeweerd's conception of history, see in particular A New Critique, vol. 2, part 1,
chs. 3 and 4; see further his Roots of Western Culture, ch. 1, §§ 14-25; and In the Twilight of
Western Thought, chs. 3 and 4.
With regard to Vollenhoven's conception of history, see especially his Isagooge Philoso-
phiae, §§ 113-34, pp. 74-98. In 'Problemen van de tijd in onze kring' Vollenhoven notes that
he 'already in 1929 in a debate wih Dooyeweerd openly differed with him in opinion regard-
ing the modal character of history'. Naturally, it remains a question whether Dooyeweerd's
conception of history, substantively speaking, is not more than modal. In Dutch he preferred
to describe this modal history not as 'cultural development' but more broadly as 'development
of civilization' (beschavingsontwikkeling). Compare, e.g., A New Critique, vol. 1, pp. 267, 362-
65 with De Wijsbegeerte der Wetsidee, vol. 2, pp. 187, 296-300; see also p. 143.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1469a1310">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1476" publication-type="other">
With regard to Mekkes and his 'hermeneutics of history', which is directed towards the
entire 'history of creation', see especially Radix, tijd en kennen, e.g. pp. 226, 230. With regard
to K. J. Popma and his conception of 'creation history', see Evangelie en geschiedenis, e.g. pp.
233-34, 306. See also the more extensive analysis by J. Klapwijk, 'Geloof en geschiedenis'.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1492a1310">
            <label>65</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1499" publication-type="other">
For the idea of a religious 'history', see A New Critique, vol. 2, pp. 268,363 and in particular
294 ('the course of the history of the world is a struggle between the civitas Dei and the
ci vitas terrena'). For the idea of a religious dialectics, see vol. 1, p. 64.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1512a1310">
            <label>66</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1519" publication-type="other">
For the marty objections that can be raised against Dooyeweerd's conception of history,
see J. Klapwijk, 'Een voorlopige standpuntbepaling t.a.v. de geschiedfilosofie van prof. dr.
H. Dooyeweerd'. See also C. T. Mclntire, 'Dooyeweerd's Philosophy of History', in The
Legacy of Herman Dooyeweerd.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1535a1310">
            <label>67</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1542" publication-type="other">
A New Critique, vol. 2, p. 297.
For Kuyper's hegelian view of history, see Kuyper, Lectures on Calvinism. The book is
organismic through and through ('so truly as every plant has a root, so truly does a principle
hide under every manifestation of life', p. 189); is permeated with the belief in progress
('Protestantism succeeded it and hence occupies a spiritually higher standpoint,' p. 186); and
is based on the idea of a universal, Western oriented history ('there is but one world-stream,
broad and fresh... and [it] has steadily continued its course from East to West,' p. 32).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1568a1310">
            <label>68</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1575" publication-type="other">
Β. Goudzwaard, Aid for the Overdeveloped West, chs. 1 and 5; and Capitalism and Progress,
chs. 2-3. See also N. Wolterstorff, Until Justice and Peace Embrace, chs. 2-4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1585a1310">
            <label>69</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1592" publication-type="other">
A New Critique, vol. 2, p. 361; cf. pp. 334-37.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1600a1310">
            <label>70</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1607" publication-type="other">
A New Critique, vol. 2, pp. 263-65, 363-65.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1614a1310">
            <label>71</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1621" publication-type="other">
For Dooyeweerd's Western oriented, sometimes even nationalistically tinted and yet, in
its intention, normative view of culture, see A New Critique, vol. 2, pp. 266-68, etc. In his
Roots in particular, the Occident' is very central (ch. 1, §§ 3,17-25), as the following passage
illustrates: Ά truly scriptural view of history... knows that the great antithesis between the
ground motive of the divine revelation of the Word and the ground motive of the apostate
spirit operates [in history] in the power struggle for the future of western civilization' (p.
108). Yes, Dooyeweerd at one point even calls the Dutch national character, in view of its
calvinistic bent, its humaneness, its sober life-style, and the like, a 'normative type' of histor-
ical disclosure and differentiation (p. 82). See also the striking analysis by C. T. Mclntire in
'Dooyeweerd's Philosophy of History', especially pp. 104-5, together with the nuanced criti-
cism of S. Griffioen in 'De betekenis van Dooyeweerd's ontwikkelingsidee', pp. 105-7.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d926e1659a1310">
            <label>72</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d926e1666" publication-type="other">
Thus J. van der Hoeven in an article with the telling title, Ontwikkeling in het Iicht van
ontmoeting' [Development in the light of encounter], p. 159.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>LIST OF REFERENCES</title>
         <ref id="d926e1685a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1689" publication-type="other">
Adorno, Theodor Wiesengrund. Minima Moralia: Reflexions from Damaged Life. Translated
by E. F. N. Jephcott. London: NLB, 1974.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1699a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1703" publication-type="other">
Apel, Karl-Otto. Transformation der Philosophie. 2 vols. Frankfurt am Main: M. Suhr-
kamp Verlag. 1971; 2d printing, 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1713a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1717" publication-type="other">
Bavink, Johan H. An introduction to the Science of Missions. Translated from the Dutch by
D. H. Freeman. Philadelphia: Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company, 1960.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1727a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1731" publication-type="other">
Boer, Theodorus de. 'De filosofie van Dooyeweerd'. Algemeen Nederlands Tijdschrift voor
Wijsbegeerte 76, 4 (October 1984): 247-61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1742a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1746" publication-type="other">
Buber, Martin. Dos Dialogische Prinzip. 5th ed. Heidelberg: Verlag Lambert Schneider, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1753a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1757" publication-type="other">
Bultmann, Rudolf. History and Eschatology. Gifford Lectures. Edinburg: Edinburgh
University Press, 1957.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1767a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1771" publication-type="other">
Calvin, John. Institutes of the Christian Religion. Edited by John T. McNeill. Translated and
indexed by Ford Lewis Battles. Philadelphia: The Westminster Press, 1960-61.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1781a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1785" publication-type="other">
Derksen, Louise Dorothea. On Universal Hermeneutics: A Study in the Philosophy of Hans-
Georg Gadamer. Amsterdam: Free University Press, 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1795a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1799" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. A New Critique of Theoretical Thought. 4 vols. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij
H. J. Paris, 1953-58; Philadelphia: The Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company,
1953-58.
Vol. 1: The Necessary Presuppositions of Philosophy. Translated by David H. Freeman and
William S. Young. 1953.
Vol. 2: The General Theory of the Modal Spheres. Translated by David H. Freeman and H.
de Jongste. 1955.
Vol. 3: The Structures of Individuality of Temporal Reality. Translated by David H. Free-
man and H. de Jongste. 1957.
Vol. 4: Index of Subjects and Authors. Prepared by H. de Jongste. 1958.
Translation of De wijsbegeerte der wetsidee.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1837a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1841" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. Roots of Western Culture: Pagan, Secular, and Christian Options. Trans-
lated by John Kraay. Edited by Mark Vander Vennen and Bernard Zylstra. Toronto: Wedge
Publishing Foundation, 1979. Translation of the greater part of Vernieuwing en bezinning.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1855a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1859" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. 'De strijd om het schriftuurlijk karakter van de Wijsbegeerte der
Wetsidee'. Mededelingen van de Vereeniging voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte, July 1950, pp.
3-6.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1872a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1876" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. 'De transcendentale critiek van het wijsgeerig denken'. Synthèse 4
(1939): 314-39.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1886a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1890" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. 'De transcendentale critiek van het wijsgeerig denken en de grondsla-
gen van de wijsgeerige denkgemeenschap van het Avondland'. Philosophia Reformata 6
(1941): 1-20.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1903a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1907" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. In the Twilight of Western Thought: Studies in the Pretended Autonomy
of Western Thought. Philadelphia: The Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company,
1960.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1920a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1924" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. Vernieuwing en bezinning: Om het reformatorisch grondmotief Zut-
phen: J. B. van den Brink, 1959.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1934a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1938" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, Herman. De wijsbegeerte der wetsidee. 3 vols. Amsterdam: H. J. Paris, 1935-36.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1946a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1950" publication-type="other">
Eikema Hommes, Hendrik Jan van. Inleiding tot de wijsbegeerte van Herman Dooyeweerd. The
Hague: Martinus Nijhoff, 1982.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1960a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1964" publication-type="other">
Gadamer, Hans-Georg. Truth and Method. Translated by Gjarrett] Burden and J[ohn] Cun-
ning. New York: Seabury Press, 1975.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1974a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1978" publication-type="other">
Geertsema, Hendrik Gerrit. 'Higher Education as Service to the King'. In Critique and
Challenge of Christian Higher Education, pp. 54-78. Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e1988a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e1992" publication-type="other">
Geertsema, Hendrik Gerrit. 'Transcendentale openheid'. Philosophia Reformata 35 (1970):
25-56, 132-55.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2002a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2006" publication-type="other">
Geesink. Willem. Van 's Heeren Ordinantiën. Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1908; 2d printing, 4 vols.,
1925.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2016a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2020" publication-type="other">
Goot, Henry vander. Interpreting the Bible in Theology and the Church. New York and
Toronto: The Edward Mellon Press, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2031a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2035" publication-type="other">
Goudzwaard, Bob. Aid for the Overdeveloped West. Toronto: Wedge Publishing Foun-
dation, 1975.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2045a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2049" publication-type="other">
Goudzwaard. Bob. Capitalism and Progress: A Diagnosis of Western Society. Translated by
Josina van Nuis-Zylstra. Toronto: Wedge Publishing Foundation, 1979; Grand Rapids: Win.
B. Eerdmans, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2062a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2066" publication-type="other">
Griffioen, Sander. 'De betekenis van Dooyeweerd's ontwikkelingsidee'. Philosophia Reforma-
ta 51 (1986): 83-109.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2076a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2080" publication-type="other">
Griffioen, Sander, Paul Marshall, and Richard Mouw, eds. Worldview and Social Theory.
Lanham and London: University Press of America, forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2090a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2094" publication-type="other">
Hart. Hendrik. Understanding Our World: An Integral Ontology. Lanham, New York, and
London: University Press of America, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2104a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2108" publication-type="other">
Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich. Einleitung in die Geschichte der Philosophie. Edited by J.
Hoffmeister. Berlin: Felix Meiner Verlag, 1966.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2119a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2123" publication-type="other">
Heidegger, Martin. Sein und Zeit. Tubingen: Max Niemeyer Verlag, 1927; 1960.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2130a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2134" publication-type="other">
Hoeven, Johannes van der. 'Ontwikkeling in het licht van ontmoeting'. In
Ontwikkeling, rationaliteit en cultuur: Opstellen, aangeboden aan prof. dr. C. A. van Peursen,
pp. 147-63. Edited by F. Schipper, M. C. Doeser, D. Nauta, Jr., and C. Sanders. Kampen: J.
H. Kok, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2150a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2154" publication-type="other">
Hoeven, Johannes van der. 'The Problem of Evil - Crucible for the Authenticity and Modesty
of Philosophizing: In Discussion with Paul Ricoeur'. Translated by John N. Kraay. South
African Journal of Philosophy 5, 2 (1986): 44-52. Translation of Peilingerv Korte exploraties
in wijsgerig stroomgebied (Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn, 1980) ch. 8, pp. 168-203.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2170a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2174" publication-type="other">
Kim, Jong Doo. 'Wissen und Glauben bei I. Kant und H. Dooyeweerd: Der Kantische Dual-
ismus und Dooyeweerds Versuch zu seiner Oberwindung'. Philosophia Reformata 48, 2
(1983): 1-145.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2187a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2191" publication-type="other">
Klafwijk, Jacob. 'Antithesis, Synthesis, and the Idea of Transformational Philosophy'. Trans-
lated by H. D. Morton. Philosophia Reformata 51 (1986): 138-54.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2201a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2205" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'Calvin and neo-Calvinism on Non-Christian Philosophy'. Translated by
Graham E. Morbey. In The Idea of a Christian Philosophy: Essays in Honour of D. H. Th.
Vollenhoven, pp. 43-61. Edited by K. A. Bril, H. Hart, and J. Klapwijk. Toronto: Wedge
Publishing Foundation, 1973.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2222a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2226" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'Dooyeweerd's Christian Philosophy: Antithesis and Critique'. Translated
by John Kok. The Reformed Journal, March 1980, pp. 20-24.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2236a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2240" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'Geloof en geschiedenis'. In Het leven beschouwà Facetten van het werk van
prof. dr. K. J. Popma, pp. 53-80. Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn, 1974; Kam-
pen: J. H. Kok, 1974.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2253a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2257" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'Geloof en rede in de théologie van Troeltsch en Pannenberg'. In Vrede met
de rede: Over het vraagstuk van rede en religie, van autonomie en heil, pp. 63-83. Edited by J.
Klapwijk, S. Griffioen, and G. Groenewoud. Assen and Amsterdam: Van Gorcum, 1976.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2274" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'The Idea of Transformational Philosophy'. Translated by H. D. Morton.
Epilogue to Christian Assessments of Secular Thought: Wavering between Antithesis and Syn-
thesis. Edited by J. Klapwijk, S. Griffioen, and G. Groenewoud. Lanham and London: Uni-
versity Press of America, forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2290a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2294" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. Oriëntatie in de nieuwe filosofie. Assen and Maastricht: Van Gorcum, 1986.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2301a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2305" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. Over mogelijkheden van christelijk filosoferen'. Mededelingen van de
Vereeniging voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte, September 1973, pp. 7-10.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2316a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2320" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'Rationality in the Dutch Neo-Calvinist Tradition'. [Translated by Graham
E. Morbey and H. D. Morton.) In Rationality in the Calvinian Tradition, pp. 93-111. Edited
by H. Hart, J. van der Hoeven, and N. Wolterstorff. Lanham and London: University Press
of America, 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2336a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2342" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'Science and Social Responsibility in Neo-Marxist and Christian Perspec-
tive'. Translated by L. D. Derksen. In Wetenschap, uiijsheid, filosoferen: Opstellen aangeboden
aan Hendrik van Riessen bij zijn afscheid als hoogleraar aan de Vrije Universiteit te Amster-
dam, pp. 75-98. Edited by P. Blokhuis, B. Kee, J. H. Santema, and E. Schuurman. Assen:
Van Gorcum, 1981.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2361a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2365" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'The Universal in Hans-Georg Gadamer's Hermeneutic Philosophy'. Trans-
lated by John N. Kraay. Philosophia Reformata 50, 1/2 (1985): 119-29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2375a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2379" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'Een voorlopige standpuntbepaling t.a.v. de geschiedfilosofie van prof. dr.
H. Dooyeweerd*. Correspondentie-Bladen van de Vereniging voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte
29 (April 1965): 18-21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2392a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2396" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, Jacob. 'On Worldview and Philosophy'. Translated by A. Toi. In Griffioen, S.;
Marshall, P.; and Mouw, R., eds. Worldview and Social Theory. Lanham: University Press of
America, forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2409a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2413" publication-type="other">
Kraay, John N. 'Successive Conceptions in the Development of the Christian Philosophy of
Herman Dooyeweerd*. Philosophia Reformata 44, 2 (1979): 137-49; and 45, 1/2 (1980): 1-46.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2424a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2428" publication-type="other">
Kraft, Charles H. Christianity in Culture: A Study in Dynamic Biblical Theologizing in Cross-
cultural Perspective. New York: Maryknoll, Orbis Books, 1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2438a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2442" publication-type="other">
Kuyper, Abraham. Lectures on Calvinism. Grand Rapids: Wim B. Eerdmans, 1961. The Stone
Lectures of 1898.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2452a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2456" publication-type="other">
Kuyper, Abraham. De gemeene gratie. 3 vols. Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1902-1905; 3d ed. 1931-32.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2463a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2467" publication-type="other">
Kuyper, Abraham. Pro Rege ofhet Koningschap van Christus. 3 vols. Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1911-
12.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2477a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2481" publication-type="other">
Kuyper, Abraham. Souvereiniteit in eigen kring: Rede 1er inwijding van de Vrije Universiteit
den 20sten October 1880 gehouden in het koor der Nieutoe Kerk te Amsterdam. 3d printing.
Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1930.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2494a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2498" publication-type="other">
Levinas, Emmanuel. 'Religion et idée de l'infini'. Le Monde, 5 September 1982.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2506a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2510" publication-type="other">
Levinas, Emmanuel. Totalité et infini: Essay sur l'extériorité. The Hague: Martinus Nijhoff,
1961.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2520a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2524" publication-type="other">
Marlet, Michael F.J. Grundlinien der kalvinistischen 'Philosophie der Gesetzesidee' als
christlicher Transzendentalphilosophie. Munich: Karl Zink Verlag, 1954.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2534a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2538" publication-type="other">
McIntire, Carl Thomas. 'Dooyeweerd's Philosophy of History'. In The Legacy of Herman
Dooyeweerd: Reflections on Critical Philosophy in the Christian Tradition, pp. 81-117. Edited
by C. T. McIntire. Lanham, New York, and London: University Press of America, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2551a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2555" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, Johan Peter Albertus. 'Bijdrage tot een discussie'. Mededelingen van de Vereeniging
voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte, December 1971, pp. 12-15.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2565a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2569" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, Johan Peter Albertus. Radix, tijd en kennen: Proeve ener critiek van de belevingssub-
jectiviteit. Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn, 1970.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2579a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2583" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, Johan Peter Albertus. Scheppingsopenbaring en wijsbegeerte. Kampen: J. H. Kok,
1961.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2594a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2598" publication-type="other">
Mekkes, Johan Peter Albertus. Tijd der bezinning. Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn,
1973.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2608a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2612" publication-type="other">
Olthuis, James H. 'On Worldviews'. Christian Scholar's Review 14 (1985): 153-64. Also in
Worldview and Social Theory. Lanham and London: University Press of America,
forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2625a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2629" publication-type="other">
Pannenberg, Wolfhart. Grundfragen systematischer Théologie: Gesammelte Aufsàtze. Gôttin-
gen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 1967; 2d ed., 1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2639a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2643" publication-type="other">
Popma, Klaas Jan.: Evangelie en geschiedenis. Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schipperheijn, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2650a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2654" publication-type="other">
Popper, Karl R. Conjectures and Refutations: The Growth of Scientific Knowledge. Lon-
don: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1973; 4th ed., 1982.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2664a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2668" publication-type="other">
Ricœur, Paul. Histoire et Vérité. Paris: Editions du Seuil, 1955; 3d éd., n.d.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2676a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2680" publication-type="other">
Riessen, Hendrik van. Wijsbegeerte. Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1970.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2687a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2691" publication-type="other">
Runner, Howard Evan. 'The Relation of the Bible to Learning'. In Christian Perspectives
1960, pp. 85-107. Pella: Pella Publishing, Inc., 1960.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2701a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2705" publication-type="other">
Smit, Meijer Cornelis. De eerste en tweede geschiedenis: Nagelaten geschriften van Meijer C.
Smit. Edited by J. Klapwijk, with a retrospect by S. Griffioen. Amsterdam: Buijten &amp; Schip-
perheijn, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2718a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2722" publication-type="other">
Strauss, Daniel François Malherbe. 'An Analysis of the Structure of Analysis'. Philosophia
Reformata 49 1/2 (1984): 35-56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2732a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2736" publication-type="other">
Taylor, Charles. Hegel and the Modern Society. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
1979.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2746a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2750" publication-type="other">
Van Til, Cornelius. Jerusalem and Athens: Critical Discussion on the Philosophy and Apolo-
getics of Cornelius Van Til. Edited by E. R. Geehan. Nutley, New Jersey: Presbyterian and
Reformed Publishing Company, 1971.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2764a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2770" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, Dirk Hendrik Theodoor Isagoogè Philosophiae. Amsterdam: Filosofisch Insti-
tuut der Vrije Universiteit, 1967. Mimeographed syllabus.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2780a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2784" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, Dirk Hendrik Theodoor. 'Problemen van de tijd in onze kring'. Amsterdam:
Free University, n.d. An unpublished, typed manuscript of a lecture delivered in 1968.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2794a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2798" publication-type="other">
Vollenhoven, Dirk Hendrik Theodoor. 'Schriftgebruik en wijsbegeerte'. Mededelingen van
de Vereeniging vocr Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte, September 1953, pp. 6-9.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2808a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2812" publication-type="other">
Wolters, Albert M. Creation Regained- Biblical Basics for a Reformational Worldview. Grand
Rapids: Wm. B. Eerdmans, 1985.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2822a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2826" publication-type="other">
Wolters, Albert M. 'Dutch Neo-Calvinism: Worldview, Philosophy, and Rationality'. In
Rationality in the Calvinian Tradition, pp. 113-31. Edited by H. Hart, J. van der Hoeven,
and N. Wolterstorff. Lanham and London: University Press of America, 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2839a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2843" publication-type="other">
Wolterstorff, Nicholas P. Until Justice and Peace Embrace: The Kuyper Lectures for 1981
delivered at the Free University of Amsterdam. Grand Rapids: Wm. B. Eerdmans, 1983 and
Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2857a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2861" publication-type="other">
Zuidema, Sytse Ulbe. Communication and Confrontation: A Philosophical Appraisal and Cri-
tique of Modern Society and Contemporary Thought. Edited by Hendrik van Riessen, Jacob
Klapwijk, et. al. Assen: Van Gorcum, 1972; Kampen: J. H. Kok, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d926e2874a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d926e2878" publication-type="other">
Zuidema, Sytse Ulbe 'Transcendentale problemen van het wijsgeerig denken'. Mededelingen
van de Vereeniging voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte, June, 1949, pp. 3-4.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
