<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">curranth</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Current Anthropology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00113204</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375382</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3596847</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/381011</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">CA041802</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Books</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Freud Meets Lévi‐Strauss in Melanesia<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1"/>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Vincent</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Crapanzano</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Programs in Comparative Literature and Anthropology, Graduate Center of the City University of New York, New York, NY<italic>
                  <sc>10016</sc>
               </italic>, U.S.A. (<email xlink:href="mailto:vcrapanzano@earthlink.net" xlink:type="simple">vcrapanzano@earthlink.net</email>). 28<sc>vii</sc>03</aff>
            <x xml:space="preserve"/>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2004</year>
            <string-date>February 2004</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>45</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>ca.2004.45.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>127</fpage>
         <lpage>128</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <italic>Penser limaginaire: Essais danthropologie psychanalytique</italic>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Bernard</given-names>
               <surname>Juillerat</surname>
            </string-name>. Lausanne: Editions Payot, 2001. 309 pp.</product>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/381011"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <p>Permission to reprint items in this section may be obtained only from their authors.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>The reader of<italic>Penser limaginaire</italic>unfamiliar with the work of Bernard Juillerat, one of Frances leading psychoanalytic anthropologists, will no doubt be surprised by the absence of epistemological conundra and fanciful wordwork so characteristic of contemporary French psychoanalysis. Juillerats approach falls within a more conservative Freudian tradition. His primary concern is not with the individual but with myth, ritual, and other modes of cultural expression. It is rooted in years of meticulous fieldwork among the Yafar people of the western Sepik region of Papua New Guinea.</p>
      <p>Several of the essays arein the theological senseapologetic. The first is a selfsituating, at times trenchant criticism of cognitive anthropology. The second is a historical account of psychoanalytic anthropology that is so parochial, so superficial that it hardly merits reading. Juillerat considers neither the critiques of psychoanalytic anthropology nor the research of ethnopsychoanalysts such as Paul Parin in Zurich, Waud Kracke in the United States, or the anthropologically oriented psychoanalysts in India, Japan, and South America. It would be a pity, however, if readers dismissed the book at this point, for the remaining essays are theoretically interesting, ethnographically rich, and at times conceptually disquieting. They include such topics as the nature of the symbol; the relationship between Freuds originary fantasies and LviStrausss basic kinship units (<italic>atomes de parent</italic>); the interaction between individual and collective representations; the conjunction of endopsychic projections of cosmologies and social reality; splitting and metamorphosis in the Yafar conception of death; parallels between the evolutionism in Yafar mythology and in Bachofens<italic>Mutterrecht</italic>; the stress on the paternal principle in Freud and the maternal in Jung; a rethinking of Maussian exchange theory that recognizes gifts that impose no obligation; an interpretation of a recent cargo cult that relates the land of plenty to the terror and longing for intrauterine return that is expressed in Yafar myth; and a reinterpretation of Naven as a psychodrama in which the uterine nephewthe eternal herois caught between agnatic law and incestuous ties with the mother. The last chapter consists of theoretical excerpts from Juillerats<italic>Lavnement du pre</italic>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf1">1995</xref>), which, though meant to enrich the reading of Yafar ritual and myth, are difficult to evaluate out of context.</p>
      <p>As one might expect, the Oedipus complex provides the hermeneutic dnouement to nearly all the essays in this book. Juillerat does not, however, reduce, in the manner of a Gza Rheim, all cultural phenomena to expressions of that complex. He is primarily concerned with the relationship between psychically constituted projective systems and social and cultural structures and institutions. He does accept the universality of the Oedipus complexits originary role in psychic development and the evolution of social and cultural institutions, at least their affective charge and symbolic effectiveness. He does not accept Freuds theory of an everafter determinative patricide. Though he is careful not to confuse the two dimensions of originarythe temporal (read historical) and the atemporal (read structural)he is not altogether immune to blending them when he speaks of individual and social development. The structural moment occurs within history.</p>
      <p>Juillerat has an extended view of the Oedipus complex, one that includes the tales/complexes of Laius and Jocasta. His understanding of the complex incorporates at least two not altogether compatible approaches. On the one hand, following Paul Ricoeur, the complex is a<italic>seuil</italic>or threshold, a structured moment that opens up a set of possibilities. Methodologically one decomposes the range of possibilities that are given expression in the cultural products of the unconscious (p. 72)myths, rituals, and dreamsin order to discover the minimal structure from which they can be derived. That which is universal is not such and such a particular form of the Oedipus [complex], but rather that which is common in all the possible figures of the Oedipus combinatory, the varied cultural expressions of which must be able to be reduced to a model that contains them all (p. 69). Like all quest arguments, Juillerats is circular: that for which he searches is predetermined by the object of his questthe Oedipus complexand by the range and definition of material that quest presupposes. What is more interesting, as Juillerat acknowledges at times, is the transformational capacity of the minimal structurethe thresholdas it is given varied cultural expression.</p>
      <p>On the other hand, the Oedipus complex is likened to a basic unit of kinship subject to a set of transformative possibilities that lead, ideally, through the resolution of (incestuous) intrafamilial conflict, to wider extrafamilial relations through marriage and the social institutions and cultural expression that derive therefrom. The move, as Ricoeur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf3">1969</xref>:121) would have it, is from destiny to history. Juillerat is more cautious, recognizing, as he does, the structural constraints of marital exchange.</p>
      <p>Juillerats argument is worthy of more detailed consideration. For LviStrauss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf2">1958</xref>), the minimal kinship unit from which all kinship systems can be derivedone that has often been challengedconsists of a brother, a sister, her husband, and their son. This atom includes both relations of filiation and (extrafamilial) matrimonial alliance. A man gives his sister to another man (who, in turn, gives his sister away). For LviStrauss, the move facilitates not only the avoidance of sororal incest but social reproduction. It gives importance to the maternal uncle and uterine nephew, but, as Juillerat notes, it underplays the role of sexuality in exchange, the ambivalence of relations, and the role of women as agents and subjects.</p>
      <p>To this atom of kinship Juillerat juxtaposes a secondthe Oedipus complexwhose dynamic concerns the nuclear family. The excessive attachment of the son to the mother is disturbed by the father, leading to impossible patricidal fantasies. The resolution of this hyperconflictual situation, freeing the son from both his maternal attachment and his patricidal fantasies, promotes his desire for women outside the nuclear family. For Juillerat Oedipal resolution is preliminary to, if not a prerequisite for, the exchange of women, the structure of which is generated from the basic unit of kinship.<italic>Voil</italic>the two systems are complementary. The atom of kinship is constituted as much from the interior as from the exteriorfrom the interior through the investment of affect, the repression of drives, Oedipal conflicts and their resolution, from the exterior, through the need for social and psychic exchange and communication (p. 124). Though Juillerat insists on taking the perspective of the different actors in these two dramas, it is ultimately the sons perspective that prevails.</p>
      <p>Doctrine and method, theory and interpretation are not necessarily coordinate. Were such coordination possible, a metacritical stance would be required. By accepting uncritically the presuppositions that lie behind psychoanalytic metapsychology, Juillerat abrogates, in my view, ethnological responsibility, that is, the responsibility to measure in a receptive manner the presuppositions of ones hermeneutic against those of the culture one is studying. Though his attention to ethnographic detail leads Juillerat to refine psychoanalytic doctrine, it confirms the epistemological and hermeneutic assumptions of that doctrine (e.g., notions of the unconscious, id, ego, and superego, drives, repression, and, indeed, psychic space). Yafar myth and ritual as he presents them become allegories of that doctrineallegories, I would argue, of allegories. There would appear to be no escape, were it not for the Yafar voices that sound through Juillerats psychoanalytically predetermined presentations. (He offers us almost no contextualized verbatim texts in these essays, though he does in his monographs.) They remind us that, as LviStrauss demonstrated, myths are readily translated one into another, particularly when they are decontextualized. What is of ethnographic, indeed, psychoanalytic import is howand perhaps whytranslation is arrested and a particular myth (e.g., the Oedipal tale) becomes so authoritative that it has the power of promiscuous reduction. Though fascinated by the range of Yafar cultural expression, Juillerat fails to consider the implications of Yafars refusal to reduce their corpus of mythology and ritual to a single mytha singular ritual.</p>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed">
         <title>References Cited</title>
         <ref id="rf1">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Juillerat, Bernard. 1995.<italic>Lavnement du pre: Rite, reprsentation, fantasme dans un culte mlansin</italic>. Paris: Editions de la Maison des Sciences de lHomme.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf2">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">LviStrauss, Claude. 1958 (1945). Lanalyse structurale en linguistique et en anthropologie, in<italic>Anthropologie structurale</italic>, pp. 3762. Paris: Plon.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf3">
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Ricoeur, Paul. 1969. Le conscient et linconscient, in<italic>Le conflit des interpretations: Essais dhermneutique</italic>, pp. 10121. Paris: Editions du Seuil.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
