<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">style</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Style</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00394238</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23746629</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">style.34.2.188</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">style.34.2.188</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>ARTICLES</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>
               <italic>Maurice</italic>in Time</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Matz</surname>
                  <given-names>Jesse</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <aff>Harvard University</aff>
            </contrib>
            <bio>
               <p>
                  <bold>Jesse Matz</bold>(<italic>
                     <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            xlink:href="jmatz@fas.harvard.edu">jmatz@fas.harvard.edu</email>
                  </italic>) is assistant professor of English at Harvard University. He has recently completed a book on literary impressionism, and is currently doing work on the cultural uses of narrative temporality.</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>6</month>
            <year>2000</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2000</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">34</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">style.34.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>188</fpage>
         <lpage>211</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2000 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2000</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/style.34.2.188"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>
               <italic>Maurice</italic>is a novel that waits for the future (for completion, publication, and audience) but also looks nostagically to the past. This strange temporal location reflects a temporality basic to Forster's narrative structures and sexual identity: like philosophers who presently ascribe to the “tenseless theory of time,” Forster dispels identity among a tenseless order of moments, in a narrative structure that seeks likewise to trade “becoming” for a better order. In<italic>Maurice</italic>, such tactics as iterative seriality, overdetermined prolepsis, nonephiphany, and other modes of “detensing” give form to a version of homosexuality that would escape “identity,” with unusual implications for moderist temporality and narratological criticism. Forster's modernist time is eccentric for its interest in logical order; and the narratological criticism which would attend to his “tenseless” homosexual form must remember that it is often the combination of subversion and order that encourages the best narratological advances.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Isherwood</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Christopher and His Kind</italic>
               </source>:<article-title>“Almost every time they met, after this, they discussed the problem: how should<italic>Maurice</italic>end? […] He loved this continuous discussion, simply as a game”</article-title>(<fpage>127</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">After meeting Mohammed, his Alexandrian lover,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Forster</string-name>
               </person-group>wrote,<article-title>“Wish I was writing the latter half of<italic>Maurice</italic>. I now know so much more”</article-title>(<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Furbank</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <volume>II</volume>
               <fpage>40</fpage>); and he described himself sitting on a hillside in Alexandria in 1918<article-title>“as Maurice and Clive sat at Cambridge”</article-title>(<fpage>49</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Here I refer of course to Foucault and his claim that the nineteenth-century “persecution of the peripheral sexualities entailed an<italic>incorporation of perversions</italic>and a new<italic>specification of individuals</italic>” in which homosexuality went from being “a category of forbidden acts” to marking “a personage, a past, a case history” (<fpage>43</fpage>). Foucault's observation that the homosexual now had a “past,” and that his sexuality was now “everywhere present” in him, contributes to my sense that identity has a narrative temporality.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See for example<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Gérard Genette</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Narrative Discourse</italic>
               </source>
               <fpage>33</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">That homosexuals in particular would end up in lunatic asylums at<italic>Maurice's</italic>moment in history seems unlikely, but<italic>Maurice</italic>itself says so: when a distraught Maurice seeks advice from Dr. Jowitt, Maurice asks, “I say, in your rounds here, do you come across unspeakables of the Oscar Wilde sort?,” and Jowitt answers, “No, that's in the asylum work, thank God” (<fpage>156</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">That this fundamental, disciplinary distinction is at the heart of the dispute between the detensers and their opponents has been only implicitly recognized (see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Oaklander</string-name>
               </person-group>,<article-title>“Experience”</article-title>
               <fpage>344</fpage>-<lpage>45</lpage>). Detensers and their opponents, it seems, are really different kinds of philosophers, despite their various efforts to reconcile the philosophical claims of reason and experience.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bergson also opposes the “myth of passage,” but I nevertheless associate<italic>duration</italic>with<italic>becoming</italic>, because Bergsonism seeks the truth of time in<italic>change</italic>(see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Bergson</string-name>
               </person-group>'s distinction between homogeneous time and pure duration, in<source>
                  <italic>Time and FreeWill</italic>
               </source>
               <fpage>90</fpage>-<lpage>91</lpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Other relevant theories of tense exist: Ricoeur discusses Harold Weinrich's theory of the significance gap between grammatical tense and the time of lived experience, a gap that suggests that fiction's tenses always challenge those of nonfictional discourse (<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ricoeur II</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <fpage>66</fpage>-<lpage>76</lpage>).<italic>Tenselessness</italic>better captures the spirit of the gap Forster creates between his fiction and life's plots because of the way it suggests that the challenge is not necessarily “fictional.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">On Forster's pragmatism, see May, whose definition of the pragmatic as that “which looks forward and backwards at the same time, no less alert to utopian possibility than opportunistic with the past” is particularly relevant here (<fpage>ix</fpage>); “moralist of the possible” is John Cronin's phrase for Forster (<article-title>“Publishable—But Worth It?,”</article-title>in<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Gardner</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <fpage>458</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">See<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Forster</string-name>
               </person-group>'s<article-title>“Art for Art's Sake,”</article-title>which also calls for a certain kind of “order” in form, for another version of the unique combination of attitudes at work here (<source>
                  <italic>Two Cheers for Democracy</italic>
               </source>
               <fpage>90</fpage>,<fpage>94</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herman defines polychrony as “a mode of narration that purposely resists linearity by multiplying ways in which narrated events can be ordered” (<fpage>76</fpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The term is<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>D. A. Miller</string-name>
               </person-group>'s, in<source>
                  <italic>Bringing Out Roland Barthes</italic>
               </source>(<fpage>48</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">The following observations about<italic>Maurice's</italic>ironic linearity attempt the rigor of similar points made by Susan Stanford Friedman in her work on the “lyric subversion” of plot in women's writing and Margaret Homans in her work on feminist theories of narrative. Both of these critics successfully question the equation of linearity with patriarchy, and explain exactly what is subversive about such things as “lyric strategies,” and the following observations aim at a similar rigor through their ultimate claim that the opposite of the linear, in Forster's case, is greater narrative order, rather than some freedom that only superficially conflates the political and the textual.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">This refutation is not quite what Scott Nelson describes in his study of “narrative inversion” in Forster. Nelson holds that the homosexual text “inverts its very commercial narrative structure,” reorienting the structure of narrative seduction in order to “expose society's dominant narratives as homophobic and oppressive” (<fpage>315</fpage>). “Inversion” suggests a tendency too agonistic to match Forster's irony.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <italic>Maurice</italic>therefore expresses Forster's well-known antipathy towards a decadent aestheticism, that for him went too far in “introduc[ing] the fallacy that only art matters” and in “overstress[ing] idiosyncracy and waywardness—the peacock-feather aspect—rather than order” (<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Forster</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Two Cheers</italic>
               </source>
               <fpage>92</fpage>). Here again Forster suggests that it is<italic>order</italic>that matters, rather than the style of liberation presumably indulged in the sexual identity he associates with “peacock-feathers.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">I borrow this term from<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Paul Fry</string-name>
               </person-group>'s<article-title>“Non-Epiphany in Wordsworth”</article-title>(<source>
                  <italic>A Defense of Poetry</italic>
               </source>
               <fpage>91</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">A brief reference to biography might help to explain how the denial of presence works in a moment like this one. Forster himself became aware of the homosexual possibility—or at least one homosexual possibility—in a very different way. As a boy in his second term at Kent house, Forster “figured in a sexual drama”: an older man molested him, giving Forster a shilling in exchange for fondling. What is interesting is how Forster recorded this event in his diary. As P. N. Furbank puts it, “Morgan made an entry in his diary &lt;&lt;Nothing&gt;&gt;, to remind himself that there had been something” (<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Furbank</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <volume>I</volume>
               <fpage>38</fpage>). Here, at an early moment, is that effacement of the present that allows the past to communicate with the future; making “nothing” the<italic>reminder</italic>of something, Forster already exhibits that detachment that will not give Maurice affirmative sexual awakening.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">These observations about the relation between closure and the narrative line owe a debt to<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>D. A. Miller</string-name>
               </person-group>'s theory (in<source>
                  <italic>Narrative and Its Discontents</italic>
               </source>) of the conflict between “closure” and the “narratable” and to Joseph Boone's sense of the way that untraditional endings bleed backwards.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Works Cited</title>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Bakshi, Parminder Kaur</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Distant Desire: Homoerotic Codes and the Subversion of the English Novel in E. M. Forster's Fiction</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Peter Lang</publisher-name>,<year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Bergson, Henri</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Free Will</italic>
               </source>.<year>1889</year>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>F. L. Pogson</string-name>
               </person-group>.<year>1910</year>.:<publisher-name>Kessinger Publishing Company</publisher-name>,<year>1996</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Bersani, Leo</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Homos</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Harvard UP</publisher-name>,<year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Boone, Joseph</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Tradition Counter Tradition: Love and the Form of Fiction</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>U of Chicago P</publisher-name>,<year>1987</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Bredbeck, Gregory W.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“‘Queer Superstitions’: Forster, Carpenter, and the Illusion of (Sexual) Identity.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Queer Forster</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Robert K. Martin</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>George Piggford</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>U of Chicago P</publisher-name>,<year>1997</year>.<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Colmer, John</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Comradeship and Ecstacy.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Australian</italic>
               </source>(<day>16</day>
               <month>October</month>
               <year>1971</year>):<fpage>18</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fletcher, John</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Forster's Self-Erasure:<italic>Maurice</italic>and the Scene of Masculine Love.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Sexual Sameness: Textual Differences in Lesbian and Gay Writing</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Joseph Bristow</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,<year>1992</year>.<fpage>64</fpage>-<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Forster, E. M.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Aspects of the Novel</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Harcourt, Brace &amp; World</publisher-name>,<year>1927</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Forster, E. M.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Howards End</italic>
               </source>.<year>1910</year>.:<publisher-name>Knopf</publisher-name>,<year>1921</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Forster, E. M.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Maurice</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Harcourt Brace Jovanovich</publisher-name>,<year>1971</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Forster, E. M.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Two Cheers for Democracy</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Harcourt, Brace and Company</publisher-name>,<year>1951</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Foucault, Michel</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>The History of Sexuality: An Introduction</italic>
               </source>. Vol.<volume>1</volume>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Robert Hurley</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>,<year>1990</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Friedman, Susan Stanford</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Lyric Subversion of Narrative in Women's Writing: Virginia Woolf and the Tyranny of Plot.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Reading Narrative: Form, Ethics, Ideology</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>James Phelan</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>Ohio State UP</publisher-name>,<year>1989</year>.<fpage>162</fpage>-<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fry, Paul</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>A Defense of Poetry: Reflections on the Occasion of Writing</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Stanford UP</publisher-name>,<year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Furbank, P. N.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>E. M. Forster: A Life</italic>
               </source>.<volume>2</volume>vols.:<publisher-name>Harcourt Brace Jovanovich</publisher-name>,<year>1977</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Gardner, Philip</string-name>
               </person-group>, ed.<source>
                  <italic>E. M. Forster: The Critical Heritage</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Routledge and Kegan Paul</publisher-name>,<year>1973</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Genette, Gérard</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Narrative Discourse: An Essay in Method</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Cornell UP</publisher-name>,<year>1980</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Herman, David</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Limits of Order: Toward a Theory of Polychronic Narration.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Narrative</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>6</volume>.<issue>1</issue>(<month>January</month>
               <year>1998</year>):<fpage>72</fpage>-<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Homans, Margaret</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Feminist Fictions and Feminist Theories of Narrative.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Narrative</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>2</volume>.<issue>1</issue>(<month>January</month>
               <year>1994</year>):<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Isherwood, Christopher</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Christopher and His Kind</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Farrar, Strauss, Giroux</publisher-name>,<year>1976</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Lanser, Susan S.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“Sexing the Narrative: Propriety, Desire, and the Engendering of Narrative.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Narrative</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>3</volume>.<issue>1</issue>(<month>January</month>
               <year>1995</year>):<fpage>85</fpage>-<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Martin, Robert K.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“Edward Carpenter and the Double Structure of<italic>Maurice</italic>.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>E. M. Forster</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Jenny Tambling</string-name>
               </person-group>.:<publisher-name>St. Martin's</publisher-name>,<year>1995</year>.<fpage>100</fpage>-<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>McTaggart, J. E.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“The Unreality of Time.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Mind</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>18</volume>(<year>1908</year>):<fpage>457</fpage>-<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Mellor, D. H.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“Thank Goodness That's Over.’”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>The New Theory of Time</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Oaklander</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Smith</string-name>
               </person-group>.<fpage>293</fpage>-<lpage>304</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Miller, D. A.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Bringing Out Roland Barthes</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>U of California P</publisher-name>,<year>1992</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Miller, D. A.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <source>
                  <italic>Narrative and Its Discontents: Problems of Closure in the Traditional Novel</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Princeton UP</publisher-name>,<year>1981</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Nelson, Scott</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Narrative Inversion: The Textual Construction of Homosexuality in E. M. Forster's Novels.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Style</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>26</volume>.<issue>2</issue>(<season>Summer</season>
               <year>1992</year>):<fpage>310</fpage>-<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Oaklander, L. Nathan</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“On the Experience of Tenseless Time.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>The New Theory of Time</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Oaklander</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Smith</string-name>
               </person-group>.<fpage>344</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref47">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Oaklander, L. Nathan</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Introduction: The Problem of Our Experience of Time.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>The New Theory of Time</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Oaklander</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Smith</string-name>
               </person-group>.<fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref48">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Oaklander, L. Nathan</string-name>
               </person-group>, and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Quentin Smith</string-name>
               </person-group>, eds.<source>
                  <italic>The New Theory of Time</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Yale UP</publisher-name>,<year>1993</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref49">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Prince, Gerald</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“On Narratology: Criteria, Corpus, Context.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Narrative</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>3</volume>.<issue>1</issue>(<month>January</month>
               <year>195</year>):<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref50">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Narrative</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Kathleen McLaughlin</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>
               </person-group>.<volume>3</volume>Vols.:<publisher-name>U of Chicago P</publisher-name>,<year>1984</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref51">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Sedgwick, Eve</string-name>
               </person-group>.<source>
                  <italic>Epistemology of the Closet</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>U of California P</publisher-name>,<year>1990</year>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref52">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Smart, J. J. C.</string-name>
               </person-group>
               <article-title>“Time and Becoming.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Time and Cause</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>P. Van Inwagen</string-name>
               </person-group>.,<year>1981</year>.<fpage>3</fpage>-<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref53">
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Stallybrass, Oliver</string-name>
               </person-group>.<article-title>“Introduction.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>The Life to Come and Other Stories, by E. M. Forster</italic>
               </source>:<publisher-name>Norton</publisher-name>,<year>1972</year>.<fpage>vii</fpage>-<lpage>xxi</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
