<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jpalestud</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Palestine Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of California Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0377919X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15338614</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jps.2014.43.3.26</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/jps.2014.43.3.26</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>French Intellectuals and the Palestine Question</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Mardam-Bey</surname>
                  <given-names>Farouk</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <bio>
               <p>Farouk Mardam-Bey is the author of numerous books and essays on cultural history, politics, Arabic poetry, and food. Mardam-Bey was the editor of<italic>JPS</italic>'s French-language sister publication,<italic>Revue des Études Palestiniennes</italic>, for 27 years and is currently the head of Sindbad, an imprint of the prestigious French publisher, Actes-Sud. This article was originally published in French in Confluences Méditerranée (No. 72, 2010).</p>
            </bio>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>5</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>Spring 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">43</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jps.2014.43.issue-3</issue-id>
         <fpage>26</fpage>
         <lpage>39</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2014 by the Institute for Palestine Studies. All rights reserved. Please direct all requests for permission to photocopy or reproduce article content through the University of California Press's Rights and Permissions website, at<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.ucpressjournals.com/reprintInfo.asp">http://www.ucpressjournals.com/reprintInfo.asp</uri>.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/jps.2014.43.3.26"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article focuses on intellectuals—writers, philosophers, academics, scientists, and artists—who, by virtue of their accomplishments and talents, or simply because of their renown, wielded such moral authority that they became at times veritable “leaders of conscience,” influencing public opinion and, indeed, government policy in France. Responding to major events, whether colonial wars, international crises, or significant domestic political battles, French intellectuals weighed in time and again, from the Dreyfus affair to the bogus Sarkozy debate on “national identity.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
                  <sup>1</sup>
               </xref>This article reviews the stance of French intellectuals on the question of Palestine and the wider Arab-Israeli conflict, and examines how the ideological and political assumptions underlying their positions were not always amenable to rational explanation or easily ascribed to traditional attitudes of the Left and Right.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <title>ENDNOTES</title>
         <fn id="fn1">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>See, for example, Jean-François Sirinelli,<italic>Intellectuels et passions françaises</italic>(Paris: Gallimard, 1996); or Michel Winock,<italic>Le Siècle des intellectuels</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 2006).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn2">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>For more on the notion of the “mission to civilize” in the French context, see Dino Costantini,<italic>Mission civilisatrice: le rôle de l'histoire coloniale dans la construction de l'identité nationale française</italic>, trans. Juliette Ferdinand (Paris: La Découverte, 2008).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn3">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>Joseph Kessel,<italic>Terre d'amour et de feu</italic>(Paris: Rombaldi, 1967), p. 40.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn4">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>C. Lehrmann,<italic>L'Elément juif dans la littérature française, v. 2: De la Révolution à nos jours</italic>(Paris: Albin-Michel, 1961), p. 103.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn5">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>Originally “Nul plus bel hommage offert à la philosophie nationaliste que celui des Juifs sionistes.” Cited by Joseph Alghazi in<italic>La Tentation néo-fasciste en France de 1944 à 1965</italic>(Paris: Fayard, 1984), p. 39.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn6">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>For more on the positioning of political forces in France after World War II, see Samir Kassir and Farouk Mardam-Bey<italic>, Itinéraires de Paris à Jérusalem, la France et le conflit israélo-arabe, v. 1: 1917</italic>–<italic>1958</italic>(Washington, DC: Institut des études palestiniennes, 1992), pp. 71–113.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn7">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>Kassir and Mardam Bey<italic>, Itinéraires de Paris à Jérusalem</italic>,<italic>v. 1</italic>, pp. 76–79.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn8">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>André Blumel,<italic>Léon Blum, juif et sioniste</italic>(Paris: Editions de la Terre retrouvée, 1953). Moreover, the socialist leader played a decisive role in the French vote for the partition plan in November 1947.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn9">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>For more on the coverage of these events by<italic>L'Humanité</italic>, the daily of the Parti communiste français (French Communist Party), see Kassir and Mardam-Bey,<italic>Itinéraires de Paris à Jérusalem, v. 1,</italic>p. 98.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn10">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>It should be noted that for decades—and in particular since the creation of the Arab League in 1945—Arab nationalism has been the<italic>bête noire</italic>of practically all the French political forces, which saw in it a ploy by London and a threat to French possessions in North Africa.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn11">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>In particular see David Lazar,<italic>L'Opinion française et la naissance de l'Etat d'Israël, 1945</italic>–<italic>1949</italic>(Paris: Calmann-Lévy, 1972), p. 128.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn12">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>Originally “Je considère que le devoir des non-juifs est d'aider les Juifs, et la cause palestinienne.” In Michel Contat et Michel Rybalka<italic>, Les Ecrits de Sartre</italic>(Paris: Gallimard, 1970), p. 205.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn13">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>Originally “[U]n Etat palestinien, un Etat indépendant, libre et pacifique, c'est une garantie de paix, à condition qu'il soit assez fort pour se faire respecter. Jean-Paul Sartre, “C'est pour nous tous que sonne le glas,”<italic>Caliban</italic>, no. 16 (May 1948), pp. 13-16.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn14">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>Originally “La formation de l'Etat palestinien doit être considérée comme un des événements les plus importants de notre époque, un des seuls qui permettent aujourd'hui de conserver l'espoir.” Jean-Paul Sartre, “Naissance d'Israël,”<italic>Hillel</italic>, 2nd ser., no. 7 (June 1949), p. 6.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn15">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>See, for example, Lazar,<italic>L'Opinion française,</italic>p. 213, on the resolutions of the 3<sup>rd</sup>Congress of the International Council of Christians and Jews, held in Fribourg, Switzerland in July 1948.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn16">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>Among other examples, see Jacques Madaule,<italic>Le retour d'Israël</italic>(Paris: Desclée de Brouwer, 1951).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn17">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>Massignon's texts on the Palestinian question can be found in<italic>Opera Minora</italic>(Paris: Presses universitaires de France, 1969), pp. 461–528.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn18">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>«C'est une loi de ce temps qu'un groupe humain persécuté, à peine est-il délivré de ses oppresseurs, opprime à son tour. L'esprit totalitaire enfante les mêmes monstres chez les victimes d'hier que chez leurs bourreaux. Les juifs du groupe Stern, par la terreur qu'ils ont répandue, ont arraché de leurs foyers près de 600.000 êtres humains, dont 100.000 chrétiens.… Il importe que le plus tôt possible, ces foules retrouvent le chemin de leurs maisons.» Francois Mauriac,<italic>Le Figaro</italic>, 16 November 1948.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn19">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>Lazar,<italic>L'Opinion française</italic>, pp. 209–210.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn20">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>Sylvia K. Crosbie,<italic>A Tacit Alliance: France and Israel from Suez to the Six-Day War</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1974).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn21">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>Originally “La milice révolutionnaire d'une révolution inconnue.” Lehrmann,<italic>L'Elément juif dans la littérature française, v. 2</italic>, p. 209.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn22">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>Albert Camus, “Les vues de Nasser et de quelques esclavagistes romantiques,” in<italic>Essais,</italic>Roger Quilliot and Louis Faucon, eds. (Paris: Gallimard, Bibliothèque de la Pléiade, 1965), p. 1859.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn23">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>Albert Camus,<italic>Essais,</italic>p. 1859.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn24">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>Albert Camus,<italic>Essais,</italic>p. 1013.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn25">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>Contat and Rybalka,<italic>Les Ecrits de Sartre</italic>. A review of the authors' quasi-exhaustive annotated bibliography will show that while Sartre denounced the Suez aggression, he remained silent about the Franco-Israeli collusion.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn26">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>Raymond Aron, “L'Explosion,”<italic>Le Figaro,</italic>30 October 1956.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn27">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>Originally “[N]e ment pas s'il entre dans les mensonges des autres.” François Mauriac,<italic>Bloc-notes</italic>(Paris: Flammarion, 1958), p. 277.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn28">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>Jean Lacouture,<italic>Pierre Mendès France</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 1981), p. 426.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn29">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>André Neher, “Réflexions sur Israël,”<italic>Esprit</italic>, February 1958.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn30">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>A reproduction of Ricœur's article, “Perplexités sur Israël,” can be found in Paul Ricœur,<italic>Lectures 1</italic>:<italic>Autour du politique</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 1991), pp. 358–367.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn31">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>Raymond Aron, “Les Juifs et l'Etat d'Israël,”<italic>Le Figaro littéraire</italic>, 24 February 1962.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn32">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>Georges Friedmann<italic>, Fin du peuple juif?</italic>(Paris: Gallimard, 1965).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn33">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>Roger Ikor,<italic>Peut-on être juif aujourd'hui?</italic>(Paris: Grasset, 1968).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn34">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>Albert Memmi,<italic>Portrait d'un juif</italic>(Paris: Gallimard, 1962) and Albert Memmi,<italic>La Libération du Juif</italic>(Paris: Gallimard, 1966), pp. 244–246.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn35">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <italic>Les Temps modernes</italic>, no. 253 (June 1967).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn36">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>Originally “Nous ne pousserons pas la discrétion jusqu'à entériner une guerre d'extermination.” Jean-Paul Sartre, “Le conflit israélo-arabe,”<italic>Les Temps modernes</italic>, no. 253 (June 1967).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn37">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>Originally “Il n'est pas supportable d'imaginer qu'une collectivité juive, où qu'elle soit, quelle qu'elle soit, puisse endurer de nouveau ce calvaire et fournir des martyrs à un nouveau massacre.” Sartre, “Le conflit israélo-arabe.”</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn38">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>Originally “Peuvent-ils empêcher que ces Israéliens pour nous ne soient aussi des juifs<italic>?</italic>” Sartre, “Le conflit israélo-arabe.”</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn39">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>See Annie Cohen-Solal,<italic>Sartre, 1905</italic>–<italic>1980</italic>(Paris: Gallimard, 1985), pp. 682–691.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn40">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>Originally “Un Juif d'Israël a le droit de rester dans sa patrie. En vertu du même principe, un Palestinien a le droit d'y rentrer.” Jean-Paul Sartre, interview with Claudine Chonez,<italic>Le Fait public</italic>, February 1969, pp. 12–17.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn41">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>Jean-Paul Sartre, “Israël, la gauche et les Arabes,” interview by Arturo Schwartz,<italic>L'Arche</italic>, no. 152 (October–November 1969), pp. 32–40, 73, 75.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn42">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>Originally “[L]'armée de défense d'Israël est devenue une armée d'occupation.” Jean-Paul Sartre, “Le général Peled estime que les objecteurs de conscience devraient être exemptés du service militaire,”<italic>Le Monde,</italic>19 June 1972.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn43">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>Jean-Paul Sartre, “A propos de Munich,”<italic>La Cause du peuple—J'accuse</italic>, no. 29, 15 October 1972.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn44">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>Jean-Paul Sartre, interview with Ely Ben Gal,<italic>Al-Hamishmar</italic>, 26 October 1973, reproduced in<italic>Le Monde</italic>, 27 October 1973; and Jean-Paul Sartre, “Contre la guerre du Kippour,”<italic>Libération</italic>, 29 October 1973.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn45">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>In 1974, UNESCO stripped Israel of its membership on the grounds of alleged damage being done by Israel's archaeological excavations on the Temple Mount in Jerusalem. UNESCO defended this decision with two statements in 1974 and 1975, but renewed Israel's membership in 1977, after the United States threatened to withhold $40 million of funding from the organization. See<italic>Le Monde</italic>, 17 November 1974.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn46">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>Published in<italic>Le Nouvel Observateur</italic>, 17 November 1975.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn47">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>Cf. Cohen-Solal,<italic>Sartre, 1905</italic>–<italic>1980</italic>, pp. 842–845.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn48">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>Edward Said, “Ma rencontre avec Jean-Paul Sartre,”<italic>Le Monde diplomatique</italic>, September 2000,<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://www.monde-diplomatique.fr">http://www.monde-diplomatique.fr</uri>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn49">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>Originally “L'etat d'Israël fait preuve d'une évidente volonté de paix et de sang-froid.” This petition, published in<italic>Le Monde</italic>on 1 June 1967, led a number of Arab intellectuals on the Left to sever their close ties with Sartre.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn50">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>In this respect, see press excerpts collected by Lotfallah Soliman in the books<italic>Escalade</italic>(Paris: Cujas, 1968) and<italic>Intoxication</italic>, (Paris: Cujas, 1968). See also Samir Kassir and Farouk Mardam-Bey<italic>, Itinéraires de Paris à Jérusalem, la France et le conflit israélo-arabe, v. 2: 1958</italic>–<italic>1991</italic>, pp. 131–140.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn51">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>Kassir and Mardam-Bey,<italic>Itinéraires de Paris à Jérusalem, v. 2</italic>, pp. 141–157. In particular see Samy Cohen,<italic>De Gaulle</italic>,<italic>les gaullistes et Israël</italic>(Paris: Alain Moreau, 1974), which elaborates extensively on the opposition of many prominent Gaullists to de Gaulle's and Pompidou's Middle Eastern policies.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn52">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>Raymond Aron collected the articles he wrote in 1967 in Raymond Aron,<italic>De Gaulle, Israël et les juifs</italic>(Paris: Plon, 1968).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn53">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>Originally<italic>“</italic>Bouffée de judéïté.” Raymond Aron,<italic>Mémoires, cinquante ans de réflexion politique</italic>(Paris : Julliard, 1983), p. 500.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn54">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>Originally “[L]es juifs français qui … hurlent de douleur pendant que leurs amis hurlent à la mort.” Raymond Aron, “Face à la tragédie,”<italic>Le Figaro littéraire,</italic>June 12, 1967.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn55">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>At this press conference, de Gaulle had wondered whether, “les Juifs, jusqu'alors dispersés, mais qui étaient restés ce qu'ils avaient été de tout temps, c'est-à-dire un peuple d'élite, sûr de lui-même et dominateur, n'en viennent, une fois rassemblés dans le site de leur ancienne grandeur, à changer en ambition ardente et conquérante les souhaits très émouvants qu'ils formaient depuis dix-neuf siècles.” Charles de Gaulle, “Conférence de presse du 27 novembre 1967,” 27 November 1967, video, 27:50, Charles de Gaulle paroles publiques,<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="http://fresques.ina.fr">http://fresques.ina.fr</uri>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn56">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>Originally “[S]ciemment, volontairement, ouvert une nouvelle période de l'histoire juive, et peut-être de l'antisémitisme. “Le temps du soupçon,” December 28, 1967, in<italic>De Gaulle, Israël et les Juifs</italic>(Paris : Plon, 1968), pp. 18–20.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn57">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>Originally “[M]oins éloigné d'un Français antisémite que d'un Juif du sud marocain.<italic>” “</italic>Le temps du soupçon,” 28 December 1967, in Raymond Aron,<italic>De Gaulle, Israël et les juifs</italic>, pp. 35, 38, 43.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn58">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>Originally “Je ne peux évidemment pas ressentir comme une blessure à mon flanc la destruction des Peaux-Rouges et réagir à l'inverse quand des Arabes palestiniens sont en cause.<italic>”</italic>Aron,<italic>Mémoires,</italic>pp. 520–521.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn59">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>Vladimir Rabi,<italic>Un peuple de trop sur la terre?</italic>(Paris: Les Presses d'aujourd'hui, 1979), p. 13, which cites this declaration by Neher: “Si Israël détient une bombe thermonucléaire, j'approuverai qu'il la fasse exploser.” (“If Israel possesses a thermonuclear bomb, then I'm for Israel making it explode.”)</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn60">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>According to Mandel, the destruction of Arab homes was a “revolutionary act.” Wladimir,<italic>Un peuple de trop sur la terre?</italic>, p. 18.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn61">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>Rodinson's main texts are collected in Maxime Rodinson,<italic>Peuple juif ou problème juif</italic>? (Paris: Maspero, 1981) and published in a new edition with a new introduction in 1997 by La Découverte.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn62">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>In this regard, see his preface to Richard Marienstras,<italic>Etre un peuple en Diaspora</italic>(Paris: Maspero, 1975).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn63">
            <label>63</label>
            <p>See the petition signed by leading intellectuals, such as Simone de Beauvoir, Nathalie Sarraute, and Vladimir Jankélévitch, in<italic>Le Monde</italic>on 19 October 1973.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn64">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>Alain Finkielkraut,<italic>Le Juif imaginaire</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 1980), pp. 13–14.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn65">
            <label>65</label>
            <p>Annie Kriegel, “Une communauté à double foyer,”<italic>L'Histoire</italic>, no. 3, November 1979, p. 69.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn66">
            <label>66</label>
            <p>The movement Le Renouveau juif was launched on 27 April 1980 by militants of the Comité juif d'action, which had organized the first “Douze heures pour Israël” in 1976. It is noteworthy that François Mitterrand, who was soon to challenge Giscard d'Estaing for the French presidency, was present at this gathering.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn67">
            <label>67</label>
            <p>See, for example, Alain Finkielkraut,<italic>La Réprobation d'Israël</italic>(Paris: Denoël-Gonthier, 1983).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn68">
            <label>68</label>
            <p>Kassir and Mardam-Bey,<italic>Itinéraires de Paris à Jérusalem, v. 2: 1958</italic>–<italic>1991</italic>, pp. 421–425.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn69">
            <label>69</label>
            <p>Originally “[L]es actes de violence, mais aussi les illogismes, les faux raisonnements, les fausses garanties qui prétendent les compenser ou les justifier. … Les conquérants étaient de ceux qui avaient subi le plus grand génocide de l'histoire. De ce génocide, les sionistes avaient fait un<italic>mal absolu</italic>. Mais transformer le plus grand génocide de l'histoire en mal absolu, c'est une vision religieuse et mystique, ce n'est pas une vision historique. Elle n'arrête pas le mal; au contraire, elle le propage, elle le fait tomber sur d'autres innocents, elle exige une réparation qui fait subir à ces autres une partie de ce que les juifs ont subi (l'expulsion, la mise en ghetto, la disparition comme peuple). Avec des moyens plus froids que le génocide, on veut aboutir au même résultat.<italic>"</italic>(italics added). Gilles Deleuze, “Grandeur d'Arafat,”<italic>Revue d'études palestiniennes,</italic>no. 10 (Winter 1984), pp. 41<italic>–</italic>43.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn70">
            <label>70</label>
            <p>François Châtelet, “Réflexions sur une hypothèse: la Grande Palestine,”<italic>Revue d'études palestiniennes</italic>, no. 10 (Winter 1984), pp. 35–40.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn71">
            <label>71</label>
            <p>It should be made clear here that, since the 1950s, the extreme Right in France has in its great majority been and continues to be pro-Israeli, its Arabophobia and Islamophobia being far greater than its anti-Semitism.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn72">
            <label>72</label>
            <p>Thanks to the support of the Socialist Party and the Paris media world, SOS Racisme (founded in 1984) was able to rapidly marginalize the young people of North African immigrant origin who, on 15 October 1983, had launched the “March for Equality and against Racism” from Marseille to Paris.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn73">
            <label>73</label>
            <p>It is remarkable that the Front National (FN) has avoided taking a stand on the Palestinian question, although Marine Le Pen is trying to draw closer to Israel in order to circumvent the hostility of French Jews toward her party. The interventions of the FN concerning Near Eastern affairs are rare, but they are significant: for example, support for Saddam Hussein in the past and for Bashar al-Assad at present.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn74">
            <label>74</label>
            <p>This publication was produced under Bensoussan's direction and published under the pseudonym Emmanuel Brenner,<italic>Les Territoires perdus de la République</italic>(Paris: Mille et Une Nuits, 2002). An English version of the book was produced by the American Jewish Committee in 2006 under the title<italic>The Lost Territories of the Republic</italic>. For further details, see<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ajc.org">http://www.ajc.org</uri>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn75">
            <label>75</label>
            <p>For a good description of this general atmosphere, see Denis Sieffert, “La ‘Sarkozye’ médiatique et intellectuelle,” in<italic>Sarkozy au Proche-Orient</italic>, ed. Farouk Mardam-Bey (Paris: Sindbad/Actes Sud, 2010).</p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
