<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">isis</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Isis</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00211753</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15456994</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">ISIS101304</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/655792</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Focus: History of Science and Literature and Science: Convergences and Divergences</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Making Knowledge: History, Literature, and the Poetics of Science</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>James J.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Bono</surname>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">*</xref>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="a1">*Departments of History and Medicine, University at Buffalo, State University of New York, Buffalo, New York 14260‐4130.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>9</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>September 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>101</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>652685</issue-id>
         <fpage>555</fpage>
         <lpage>559</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2010 by The History of Science Society. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The History of Science Society</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/655792"/>
         <abstract>
            <label>ABSTRACT</label>
            <p>As a field of study, literature and science has gradually expanded to encompass both the impact of science on literary culture and the literary‐linguistic practices intrinsic to the production of scientific knowledge. Such transformations both reinforce and fundamentally recalibrate the detailed attention focused on scientific practice by historians of science since the 1980s. As a result, this essay and the Focus section it introduces suggest that history of science and literature and science are, in fact, interdependent fields. Attention to their convergences will yield better understanding of the performative dimensions of scientific practices and thence of science itself as a form of making of knowledge of things and events in the world of nature. Science as a form of making involves the convergence of things, material practices, and a panoply of meaningful artifacts—instruments of thought and action—that refuse any simple dichotomy between “text” and “action.”</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fnu1">
               <p>This Focus section was organized by James J. Bono.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title/>
         <p>IN 1978, the esteemed scholar G. S. Rousseau surveyed the state of the field of literature and science in the pages of<italic>Isis</italic>. As he noted, the work of Marjorie Hope Nicholson inspired a generation of scholars during the 1950s to establish a new Literature and Science division within the Modern Language Association of America (MLA). The story Rousseau tells is largely one of the impact of science—and of history of science—on the study of literature by literary and intellectual historians. While carefully taking account of the diverse approaches informing the practice of literature and science through the late 1970s, Rousseau observed with concern just how vulnerable to methodological critiques were studies of the “influence” of science on literature that then dominated the field. Ultimately, his essay strikes a pessimistic note. Specifically, Rousseau voiced concern that “structuralism” would undermine any question of the “validity of literature and science as a field”; “as proof,” he cited the “sharp plunge” in the number of “members of the [MLA] division” of Literature and Science.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>The future did not look bright for this field.</p>
         <p>Rousseau's story seemed to chart the rapid rise and impending fall of literature and science as a field ancillary to and asymmetrically dependent on history of science. Yet lurking within the shadows of this narrative one finds the apparition of a quite different vision: an alternative universe where relations between science and literature are dominantly symmetrical and where a focus on the divergence of history of science and literature and science gives way to plotting their multiple and unpredictable convergences and interdependencies. For Rousseau in 1978, such a world of scholarship remained a longed‐for terra incognita: “Literary scholars are understandably far more concerned about literature than about science, and most applied scientists as well as historians of science have not seriously considered the possibility that literature has shaped or can shape scientific developments. The latter is an unexplored territory, probably the one in greatest need of cultivation right now and also the one requiring learning so vast that it is hard to imagine it in a single scholar.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">2</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Fast‐forward some thirty years, and, as the authors contributing to this Focus section attest, literature and science finds itself a permanent resident of just such a new landscape, whose topography it has for some time been busily mapping. Literature and science today is a robust field, one whose practitioners regularly work at and across the permeable boundaries it shares with history of science. Indeed, while the field continues to be populated by a growing number of literary scholars, its practitioners now include science studies scholars from a broad range of disciplines, including history of science. Why this turnaround from the somber vision offered by Rousseau of an earlier generation of scholars who, in the late 1970s, “abandoned the ship before it could sink” to a landscape densely inhabited and fundamentally transformed by a multidisciplinary cohort of literature and science scholars whose work beckons historians of science to join with them in exploring this shared terrain?<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">3</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Surely one major pertinent transformation has involved a recalibration of the analytic practices of, on the one hand, literary scholars interested in science and, on the other, select cohorts of science studies experts. In each case, such recalibration involved new and intensive attention to the practices of “scientists” themselves.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">4</xref>From the early 1980s on, a new generation of scholars increasingly turned their attention to performative dimensions of the different kinds of work avidly pursued by scientific practitioners in the making of knowledge about nature. The common thread that bound together emerging work in the reconfigured field of literature and science was analytic attention to the performative effects and affordances of literary and linguistic dimensions of scientific practice and communication.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">5</xref>For science studies more generally, including the history of science, attention turned in parallel fashion to the material practices associated with different sciences and thus to the performative effects and affordances of laboratory and experimental protocols; collecting, observing, recording, and categorizing devices and procedures; the material regimes constituting such analytic practices, from mathematical and statistical analysis to myriad techniques for “reading” particular kinds of data critical to specific scientific subspecialties; and, finally, the networks of exchange that foster the circulation of the objects, material practices, and epistemic things that contribute to the making of scientific knowledge.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">6</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Not all of these recalibrations occurred at the same time, or at the same pace, in fields associated with science studies, including literature and science and history of science. Nor were they adopted in every instance by any given field. Instead, we can note a series of transformations leading to convergences and divergences among fields such as history of science and literature and science. Picking up the story where Rousseau left off in 1978: the 1980s proved formative for literature and science precisely because traditional studies of the influence of science on literature were supplemented by new genres of studies that stressed more forcefully the reciprocal and symmetric impact of literature, the literary and linguistic, and performative elements often associated with literary practice and creativity on science itself. In 1985 we witnessed the founding of the Society for Literature and Science (SLS)—later renamed the Society for Literature, Science, and the Arts (SLSA). It is now in its twenty‐fifth year, and its annual meeting and (since 1993) its scholarly journal,<italic>Configurations</italic>, have provided a rich interdisciplinary forum for exploring and debating just such reciprocal, symmetric, and performative dimensions of science.</p>
         <p>If, as I have suggested, literature and science shares with the history of science a concern to understand the making of science—that is, the making of the different forms of knowledge of things and events in nature—through attentive focus on scientific practice(s) as performative, then we should ask how the distinctive ways in which each field contributes to an understanding of the making of science might lead to fruitful convergences and interdependencies. The essays that follow contribute to this goal. Crucial here, I would argue, is a fundamental question: How does the analysis of literary and linguistic dimensions of scientific practice and communication map onto the preoccupations of historians of science with the material practices of scientists? What this question in turn reveals is an abiding, if false, dichotomy: that between discourse and (material) practice or, to put it differently, between text and action.</p>
         <p>The work of scientists continually demands the intimate interweaving of text and action in the making of science. As Laura Otis notes in her essay in this Focus section, language, narrative, and metaphor play important roles in the making of scientific knowledge and hence in the history of science. She cites the example of Santiago Ramón y Cajal to suggest how the superiority of metaphors drawing on “trees and plants” to the metaphor of “telegraphic networks” rests in no small part in the ability of the former to fix the attention of the neurobiologist on precisely those material phenomena—and techniques of active observation appropriate to them—that might reveal how “nervous systems grew and changed throughout organisms' lives in response to ongoing activity.” Laura Dassow Walls explicitly evokes the root meaning of “text” (“<italic>textum</italic>,” in Latin) as the action of weaving together in order to insist that we “extend Lorraine Daston's gallery of ‘things that talk’ by proposing that literary texts are ‘things’ too—they too are talkative, they too ‘knit together matter and meaning.’”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">7</xref>In fact, for Walls a key commonality science shares with literature is that both actively seek through the generation of fictive “gestalts”—or forms—to<italic>gather together</italic>things in their respective universes in such a way that they “knit together matter and meaning.” In effect, Walls calls for literary scholars to attend to “things” as agents capable of being made to talk, just as scientists who “make things talk” as a matter of course through their own material practices need to attend to the ways that “literature”—and, I would add, the literary in their own work—“weave[s] the talking things of the sciences into new and surprising alliances.”</p>
         <p>Henry Turner's essay returns us to the very notion of “form” to underscore once again this key commonality that ties together literature and science, the literary scholar, the historian of science, and the scientist. In so doing, he works to dispel the text/action dichotomy, in part by noting that the “category of form” itself embraces “meaningful artifacts” of the sort that constitute the very material tools of the trade of the practices through which scientists make scientific knowledge: for example, “physical specimens, instrument readings, photographs, models.” Citing a range of examples that include Francis Bacon and Galileo, Turner importantly insists that form, while critical to making knowledge, is “never simply a tool of knowledge” but, rather, is always about the constitution of things, about “ontology.” Thus the forms utilized by scientists, whatever their particularity as “meaningful artifacts” may be in a given instance, also serve to gather together, to relate and draw into relation with one another, features of an experienced world that form associations as objects and as “enduring network[s]” of things. The final essay, by Colin Milburn, also highlights the dynamic nature of texts, particularly by drawing attention to their ability to constitute themselves as, and hence actively create, “assemblages.” His discussion of the relation of science to science fiction through processes collectively termed “modding” (processes of “reworking and transforming”) points to just this generative and dynamic property of texts that once again underscores the creative and pragmatic conjoining of text and action. By analyzing the specific forms that “mods” take in translating science fiction among “scientists as cultural consumers” into the work of the laboratory, Milburn provides testimony for one possible site where we may witness the continuing role that the fictive might play in science.</p>
         <p>Let me end by offering my own provocation to thinking about the relationship of history of science with literature and science, one that aims to invite historians of science to explore science as a form of making that involves the convergence of things, material practices, and “meaningful artifacts,” embracing a panoply of possibilities from metaphoric to narrative to visual to instrumental resources.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">8</xref>Elsewhere, I have written:<disp-quote>
               <p>The world as we know it and operate upon it is one in which we continually conjoin discourse and practice, text and action: where we simultaneously learn<italic>and</italic>act by embodying intentions and projecting our metaphorically constructed models onto matter which we shape and use to our ends as<italic>instruments</italic>of thought and action. The world as we know it and study it is filled with material‐textual, or material‐discursive, hybrids—instruments; machines; illustrations; diagrams; maps; charts; physical models; computer simulations—that are simultaneously part of the material world and<italic>instruments</italic>for our knowing and manipulating it. They are all, in their own way, what I like to call<italic>material metaphors</italic>: embodied metaphors‐in‐action!<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">9</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>At stake in the convergence of history of science and literature and science, I would submit, is the very possibility of a poetics of science: of understanding science as itself a form of<italic>poiesis</italic>, of making.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">10</xref>
         </p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>G. S. Rousseau, “Literature and Science: The State of the Field,”<italic>Isis</italic>, 1978,<italic>69</italic>:583–591, on pp. 583 (new MLA division), 589.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Ibid.</italic>, pp. 587–588.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>
                  <italic>Ibid.</italic>, p. 589.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>On the turn toward practice see Timothy Lenoir, “Practice, Reason, Context: The Dialogue between Theory and Experiment,”<italic>Science in Context</italic>, 1988,<italic>2</italic>:3–22; Jan Golinski, “The Theory of Practice and the Practice of Theory: Sociological Approaches in the History of Science,”<italic>Isis</italic>, 1990,<italic>81</italic>:492–505; Golinski,<italic>Making Natural Knowledge: Constructivism and the History of Science</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge Univ. Press, 1998); Joseph Rouse,<italic>Engaging Science: How to Understand Its Practices Philosophically</italic>(Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell Univ. Press, 1996); Rouse, “Kuhn and Scientific Practices,”<italic>Configurations</italic>, 1998,<italic>6</italic>:33–50; and Rouse,<italic>How Scientific Practices Matter: Reclaiming Philosophical Naturalism</italic>(Chicago: Univ. Chicago Press, 2002).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>See, e.g., Stuart Peterfreund, ed.,<italic>Literature and Science: Theory and Practice</italic>(Boston: Northeastern Univ. Press, 1990); N. Katherine Hayles, ed.,<italic>Chaos and Order: Complex Dynamics in Literature and Science</italic>(Chicago: Univ. Chicago Press, 1991); Hayles,<italic>How We Became Posthuman: Virtual Bodies in Cybernetics, Literature, and Informatics</italic>(Chicago: Univ. Chicago Press, 1999); and Mary Baine Campbell,<italic>Wonder and Science: Imagining Worlds in Early Modern Europe</italic>(Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell Univ. Press, 1999).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Among the many works that one could cite, see the foundational studies by Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar,<italic>Laboratory Life: The Social Construction of Scientific Facts</italic>(Beverly Hills, Calif.: Sage, 1979); Latour,<italic>Science in Action: How to Follow Scientists and Engineers through Society</italic>(Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard Univ. Press, 1987); and Steven Shapin and Simon Schaffer,<italic>Leviathan and the Air‐Pump: Hobbes, Boyle, and the Experimental Life</italic>(Princeton, N.J.: Princeton Univ. Press, 1985). Later studies contributing to these trends are legion, but among them consider Geoffrey C. Bowker,<italic>Memory Practices in the Sciences</italic>(Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2005); Peter Dear,<italic>Discipline and Experience: The Mathematical Way in the Scientific Revolution</italic>(Chicago: Univ. Chicago Press, 1995); Paula Findlen,<italic>Possessing Nature: Museums, Collecting, and Scientific Culture in Early Modern Italy</italic>(Berkeley: Univ. California Press, 1994); Timothy Lenoir, ed.,<italic>Inscribing Science: Scientific Texts and the Materiality of Communication</italic>(Stanford, Calif.: Stanford Univ. Press, 1998); Andrew Pickering,<italic>The Mangle of Practice: Time, Agency, and Science</italic>(Chicago: Univ. Chicago Press, 1995); Pickering, ed.,<italic>Science as Practice and Culture</italic>(Chicago: Univ. Chicago Press, 1992); Hans‐Jörg Rheinberger,<italic>Toward a History of Epistemic Things: Synthesizing Proteins in the Test Tube</italic>(Stanford, Calif.: Stanford Univ. Press, 1997); and M. Norton Wise, ed.,<italic>The Values of Precision</italic>(Princeton, N.J.: Princeton Univ. Press, 1995).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Walls is drawing on Lorraine Daston, ed.,<italic>Things That Talk: Object Lessons from Art and Science</italic>(New York: Zone, 2004).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>Within the history of science, Donna Haraway has from the inception of her career attended to scientists' uses of metaphoric and narrative resources and the convergence of things, material practices, and the making of science. In this way, her work both pre‐ and postdates Rousseau's observations about the glaring need for historians of science to chart the impact of literature (and the literary) on science. See Donna J. Haraway,<italic>Crystals, Fabrics, and Fields: Metaphors of Organicism in Twentieth‐Century Developmental Biology</italic>(New Haven, Conn.: Yale Univ. Press, 1976); and Haraway,<italic>Primate Visions: Gender, Race, and Nature in the World of Modern Science</italic>(New York: Routledge, 1989). Of course, many of her essays and other books contribute importantly to just such convergences between history of science and literature and science.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>James J. Bono, “Why Metaphor? Toward a Metaphorics of Scientific Practice,” in<italic>Science Studies: Probing the Dynamics of Scientific Knowledge</italic>, ed. Sabine Maasen and Matthias Winterhager (Bielefeld: Transcript, 2001), pp. 215–234, on p. 228. See also Paul Ricoeur,<italic>From Text to Action: Essays in Hermeneutics</italic>, trans. Kathleen Blamey and John B. Thompson (Evanston, Ill.: Northwestern Univ. Press, 1991); and Elizabeth Grosz,<italic>Space, Time, and Perversion: Essays on the Politics of Bodie</italic>s (New York/London: Routledge, 1995), pp. 125–126.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>For an approach to the issues raised by this Focus section see James J. Bono, “Perception, Living Matter, Cognitive Systems, Immune Networks: A Whiteheadian Future for Science Studies,”<italic>Configurations</italic>, 2005,<italic>13</italic>:135–181.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
