<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3591497</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/431812</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR850404</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Identity of the Literal Sense: Midrash in the Work of Hans Frei<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">*</xref>
            </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>William W.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Young III</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">King's College, Pennsylvania</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>October 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>85</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2005.85.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>609</fpage>
         <lpage>633</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2005 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/431812"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>*</label>
               <p>My thanks to Phil Muntzel, Mark Ryan, Chad Pecknold, Ben Fulford, and two anonymous reviewers for their comments on earlier drafts of this essay, and to Gene Rogers for discussion and suggestions at an early stage of the process. Also, thanks to Jonathan DeCarlo and Christopher Boos, with whom I first tried out many of these ideas in discussion. Errors remain my own.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>One finds in the work of Hans Frei one of the most provocative and insightful challenges to the project of theological hermeneutics. From tracing the trajectory of hermeneutics through modernity, with its bifurcation of the narrative coherence of scripture into “meaning” or historical reference, to arguing that hermeneutics effectively dissolves the uniqueness of the identity of Jesus Christ, by determining general categories of understanding within which Christ’s salvific activity is to be understood, Frei’s work displaces hermeneutics from its central place in the modern theological canon. This displacement has opened the possibility of a turn to narrative, figural, or typological interpretations of scripture.</p>
      <p>Frei’s constructive proposal does more than simply advocate a return to earlier “precritical” Christian practices of reading. He frequently argues that the recovery of the literal sense opens the possibility of constructive engagement by Christian theology with the Jewish practice of Midrash. As John David Dawson has recently noted, for Frei, attention on the part of Christians to the distinctive, unsubstitutable practices of reading constitutive of Jewish life should follow from attunement to the narrative uniqueness of the Gospel’s portrayal of Jesus Christ.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">1</xref>At first glance, it would appear that these references to Midrash can be attributed simply to its typological pattern of interpretation, which understands the coherence of Jewish scriptures via internal repetitions and patterns of representation, rather than appeal to external categories of understanding. Midrash thus parallels the figural patterns of connection that marked precritical Christian readings of scripture, a pattern of reading that only appeared arbitrary or without any sure criteria of guidance in the eyes of modern readers.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">2</xref>In light of the retrieval of figural reading, Christians would come to appreciate the distinctive form of Midrashic reading.</p>
      <p>However, Frei’s discussion of Midrash goes beyond an aesthetic appreciation. Frei often brings Midrash into his discussion of the literal sense of scripture when he seeks to transform Christian understandings of the literal sense. Moreover, the points that Frei highlights in Midrash frequently signify the aspects of interpretation that he thinks must be reshaped within Christianity, in order for the narrative sense to guide and form Christian community. These may include elements that have been lost or eclipsed by both historical criticism and hermeneutics, as well as elements not emphasized within traditional figural readings. What is more, it is frequently in conjunction with his comments on Midrash, and its community‐forming role in Judaism, that Frei alludes to the cultural and political significance of a Christian theology and community rooted in the literal sense of scripture. Thus, his discussion of Midrash actually serves as a central component of his articulation of what the Christian literal sense should be.</p>
      <p>This essay will argue that Frei’s discussion of Midrash can help us to see that his focus on the literal sense is, at its heart, an argument for the<italic>indirect</italic>transformation of the Christian life via the literal sense, which is of course the direct and primary focus of his work. This serves, I think, to qualify Dawson’s conclusion regarding Frei; as he writes, Frei “minimizes the subjective and personal experience of transformation” by focusing on the unique identity of Jesus Christ,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">3</xref>in a way that potentially strips the reader of her embodiment and uniqueness. Rather, Frei’s discussions of Midrash illuminate his understanding of the transformative dimensions of scriptural reading; this enables us to build on Dawson’s rapprochement between Frei and Origen and can shed new light on Frei’s extended debate with Paul Ricoeur. There is an irony here: for all that he focuses on Christ as the one who gives us our unique identities, it is in the light of Midrash, Origen’s allegory (as explicated by Dawson), and Ricoeur’s hermeneutics that we can see more clearly the distinctive uniqueness of Frei’s understanding of the literal sense.</p>
      <p>The central reference point for Frei’s reflection on Midrash is an essay by Raphael Loewe, which Frei cites on multiple occasions. The essay, “The ‘Plain’ Meaning of Scripture in Early Jewish Exegesis,” argues against the view that the “plain” sense of scripture in rabbinic interpretation was simply what the text itself says (i.e., biblical literalism); for Loewe, this view obfuscates the argumentative and subjective elements underlying the presentation of an interpretation as “literal.” Rather,<italic>peshat</italic>, the plain or “flat” sense of scripture, functions as the extension of authoritative communal readings that should guide the ongoing practice of interpretation. “The evidence here set forth … suggests that the essential notion conveyed by the root at this semantic stage is<italic>authority</italic>… the extension of an opinion, received by a teacher or elaborated by himself, over a wider body which (by acknowledgement therefore) broadens the currency of the authority of the source whence it emanates.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">4</xref>As authoritative teaching,<italic>peshat</italic>represents the reading (or body of readings) passed on by the authority of the teacher. Such authority, however, is not heteronomous with respect to the community; rather, it grows from the communal tradition’s reading and depends on the reception and recognition (“acknowledgement”) of the authority by the community. “<italic>Peshat</italic>, therefore, means authoritative teaching in two possible senses. Either teaching propounded by an authoritative teacher, or<italic>teaching recognized by the public as obviously authoritative, since familiar and traditional</italic>. … It is the italicized alternative that is the more important where the noun<italic>peshat</italic>occurs.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">5</xref>
      </p>
      <p>The crucial question that emerges for Loewe is how such received, authoritative reading relates to the dynamic, innovative reading associated with the “applied” sense, or<italic>derash</italic>. Loewe’s conclusion is startling: while<italic>peshat</italic>functions as a static reading, where “the scales are weighed in favour of conservatism” by extending the received teaching, it remains open to<italic>derash</italic>,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">6</xref>when required by changes in conditions. This is as true, on Loewe’s view, for halacha as for Haggadah: “The fact that exegesis at least theoretically dynamic predominates even in halakhic contexts after the effective freezing of halakhic development, seems to me to reflect the essential vitality of halacha as a humane discipline—a vitality which conditions might circumscribe, but could not crush.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">7</xref>Thus, one should recognize both the shifts in meaning of<italic>peshat</italic>over time and its implicit dynamism and openness in early Jewish exegesis to transformation when so required by the life of the community.</p>
      <p>While what follows will discuss the importance of Loewe’s understanding of Midrash with regards to both Frei’s early and later work, it should be noted that the references to Midrash occur in Frei’s later work, where he shifts from a more formalist vocabulary that describes the “literal sense” in terms of the text itself to a focus on how it is read in the community.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">8</xref>As Kathryn Tanner describes the “plain sense” in Christian theology, capturing Frei’s later articulation of the<italic>sensus li</italic>
         <italic>te</italic>
         <italic>ralis</italic>, it is “what a participant in the community automatically or naturally takes a text to be saying on its face insofar as he or she has been socialized in a community’s conventions for reading that text as scripture.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">9</xref>The parallels between Tanner’s description of the literal sense (in which communal reading is authoritative though open to change) and Loewe’s description of<italic>peshat</italic>are striking, and the chronological parallel between Frei’s explicit interest in Midrash and his rearticulation of the literal sense suggests that the parallels between Midrash and the literal sense may be, in Frei’s own words, “instructive.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">10</xref>To explore this, let us turn to Frei.</p>
      <sec>
         <title/>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn2">
               <label>1</label>
               <p>John David Dawson,<italic>Christian Figural Reading and the Fashioning of Identity</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 2001), 12. Of course, as Dawson notes, the questions of whether Christian figural reading, as practiced by Frei and Karl Barth,<italic>does</italic>give others their unique identities remains an open question. Like Dawson, and assuming his discussion of Frei and Origen as a starting point, this essay attempts to articulate such a reading.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3">
               <label>2</label>
               <p>See, e.g., Frei,<italic>The Eclipse of the Biblical Narrative</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1975), 30–31.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4">
               <label>3</label>
               <p>Dawson,<italic>Christian Figural Reading</italic>, 215.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5">
               <label>4</label>
               <p>Raphael Loewe, “The ‘Plain’ Meaning of Scripture in Early Jewish Exegesis,”<italic>Papers of the Institute of Jewish Studies London</italic>1 (1964): 158; my emphasis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6">
               <label>5</label>
               <p>Loewe, “The ‘Plain’ Meaning of Scripture,” 181; his emphasis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7">
               <label>6</label>
               <p>Ibid.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8">
               <label>7</label>
               <p>Ibid. 184.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9">
               <label>8</label>
               <p>See, e.g., Gerard Loughlin,<italic>Telling God’s Story: Bible, Church, and Narrative Theology</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996), 78–79.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10">
               <label>9</label>
               <p>Kathryn E. Tanner, “Theology and the Plain Sense,” in<italic>Scriptural Authority and Narrative Imagination</italic>, ed. Garrett Green (Philadelphia: Fortress, 1987), 63.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11">
               <label>10</label>
               <p>Frei’s work relies largely upon Loewe’s understanding of<italic>peshat</italic>. This essay will focus on Frei’s understanding of Midrash, with the caveat (as noted by a reviewer) that there are competing understandings. An important question is to consider responses to Loewe’s work and how such challenges might transform the literal sense. For example, David Weiss Halivni has contested Loewe’s emphasis on the authoritative character of<italic>peshat</italic>and sees the term as more properly understood in terms of the verbal context of a word or phrase. See<italic>Peshat and Derash: Plain and Applied Meaning in Rabbinic Exegesis</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1991), 53–63. Furthermore, while Frei turns to Midrash in the context of arguing for how the text is read in community, Daniel Boyarin has argued that Midrash takes its character from the ambiguity of the biblical text. See “Inner Biblical Ambiguity, Intertextuality, and the Dialectic of Midrash: The Waters of Marah,”<italic>Prooftexts</italic>10 (1990): 29–48.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>I</title>
         <p content-type="epigraph">
            <disp-quote>
               <p>Then there are those in our own day who suggest that both ways of looking at the principles of interpretation are utterly wrong‐headed. These people say we ought not even raise the question of “use,” and that to use the very term meaning is already to be engaged in a kind of unintelligible global speculation. In saying this, they suggest a very curious thing: namely, that the way to understand a text is not by principles of interpretation but by a kind of thick tradition of reading, very much like that of Midrash; that it is not that the text fits into a contextual, nontextual world in which it “means” or does not “mean,” or that it is a text that can be used within such a world, but rather that the world, any “world,” should be understood on the model of “text,” and that reading therefore constitutes a more profound and genuine use of language than speaking in dialogue or communicating in a common world. The best‐known proponent of this view is Jacques Derrida.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">11</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>In<italic>Types of Christian Theology</italic>, as in much of his later work, Frei’s primary conversation partners are Frank Kermode and Paul Ricoeur. Ricoeur, as the foremost advocate of a hermeneutics of understanding, and Kermode, as a literary critic who refuses esoteric or figural interpretation, both render problematic the literal sense as Frei understands it. As Frei says on numerous occasions, the literal sense of scripture is best understood as taking the text to mean what it says, with the caveat that the text means what the community agrees that it says. As we shall see, in both its pluralism and its interpretive potency, this is a far more complex claim than is frequently assumed, and it can be best understood via contrast with Ricoeur’s approach.</p>
         <p>As developed in<italic>Interpretation Theory</italic>and elsewhere, Ricoeur’s position is best known for his reworking of the “reference” of the text. Where many philosophers and theologians have tended to treat reference as ostensive, designating a state of affairs or event “outside” or prior to the text, Ricoeur calls us to think of reference as a world of possibility that opens through the text. The text—especially biblical scripture—opens a distinctive, unique world in which a range of possibilities for reflection and practice emerge; as he writes, the goal of interpretation “is achieved insofar as the interpretation actualizes the meaning of the text for the present reader.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">12</xref>Ricoeur and Frei therefore agree that biblical reference need not be conceived ostensively. However, from Frei’s standpoint, Ricoeur’s emphasis on the text opening a world of understanding for the reader moves too quickly toward the subjective appropriation of reference, occluding the possibility of the biblical narrative’s self‐referentiality.</p>
         <p>Ricoeur and Frei separate from one another in according priority to either the parables or the narratives of Jesus’s life as the guiding texts for Christian interpretation. For Ricoeur, the parables condense and subvert the standard, ostensive meaning of narrative—opening it to interpretive reference for the reader. Serving as symbolic “limit‐expressions” that give rise to thought, they take priority in interpretation, though not to the exclusion of other genres or biblical texts.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">13</xref>By breaking with ostensive reference, biblical narrative becomes kerygmatic. Ricoeur’s emphasis on this kerygmatic dimension is apparent in multiple commentaries, such as his discussion of the “opacity” of the Markan Gospel: “Perhaps the distinctive feature of the Gospel of Mark is that Mark narratively produces more opacity than clarification. This feature, better than the inverse one of amplification, can be set in relation with the type of Christology that constitutes the kerygmatic intention of his narrative.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">14</xref>Likewise, the conjunction between God’s names in Exodus 3:14—“I will be who I will be” and “the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob,” points the reader toward a narrative dimension that “cannot be told,” summoning the subject before the unsayable.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">15</xref>The underlying conjunction between narrative ineffability, naming God, and subjective appropriation is best expressed by Jim Fodor: “The Gospel’s inexhaustibility formally mirrors the ineffability of God’s name by virtue of the continuous circulation, the incessant interanimating movement, between and within the multiple forms of biblical discourse … while the text closing in on itself may foreshadow its final canonical shape, at the same time it also indicates the centrifugal ontological impulse of the text to refer beyond itself, to point beyond the written page to the life lived.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">16</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Frei, by contrast, gives priority to the narrative of Jesus’s life and identity, such that the parables have “meaning” when they are ascribed to Jesus himself. Their meaning, in other words, comes from their narrative connection with Jesus’s life and story. Indeed, his ascription of the parables to Jesus exemplifies the figural reading that gives coherence to the literal sense, bringing together otherwise disparate texts by reading them in light of the narrative of Christ’s life. The “meaning” of parables, for Frei, resides in their speaking<italic>of Jesus</italic>, rather than signifying a generalizable feature of human experience. Similarly, Frei’s reading of Exodus 3 illustrates the difference between his approach and Ricoeur's: he reads the narrative primarily as ascribing the Abrahamic history and covenant<italic>to</italic>the God who liberates the Israelites from Egypt, rather than introducing an opacity and ineffability.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">17</xref>While Frei clearly intends such claims to highlight the intertextual reading that constitutes the literal sense, Ricoeur and others will argue that this strongly resembles what Mark Wallace has termed a “free‐floating intertextualism,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">18</xref>as shall be discussed further in Section II.</p>
         <p>It is in the context of this debate that Frei brings up Midrash, in the passage quoted above, and correlates it with deconstruction’s refusal of a hermeneutics of understanding as a form of metaphysical pretension that closes off the practice of reading. Specifically, he is responding to Kermode’s<italic>The Genesis of Secrecy</italic>, which sees parables as making everyone an “outsider”to the text: “A parable does not open up; a parable closes. A parable is a puzzle; it is precisely that which prevents literal reading.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">19</xref>Where Ricoeur sees parables as opening the possibility of understanding in the phenomenological sense, Kermode sees them as precluding understanding—in effect, ruining the meaning of the text. And, for Kermode, parables ruin the meaning of a text by refusing the sort of figural, narrative interpretation that constitutes the literal sense.</p>
         <p>There are, I think, two ways to read this exchange. First, the invocation of Midrash may be intended primarily to problematize Ricoeur’s position: it shows that there is a practice of reading that does not depend on the hermeneutics of understanding and in fact rejects them. This move, then, is one that makes room for the literal sense, as a reading that treats the scriptures as texts—“not sources,” as Frei quotes Barth. Or one can read the passage as introducing Kermode’s position, which highlights the narrative manipulation of the Gospel texts, which generate the appearance of historicity and meaning, while foreclosing interpretation.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">20</xref>This then becomes the opponent that literal reading must contest. Both readings, in this brief introduction to<italic>Types</italic>, are possible. However, as shall become clear below, Frei does not reject deconstruction or Kermode’s position outright, only its global methodological claims; it shall be highly useful in contesting the subject‐centered hermeneutics of modern theology and thus may play an important role in figural reading’s fidelity to the text. There is, here, a strategic agreement with poststructuralism, without Frei thereby turning it into a general theory of reading.</p>
         <p>By contrast with both Ricoeur and Kermode, Frei emphasizes narrative in order to foreground a way of reading that centers on the person of Jesus as the one who unifies the disparate genres and texts of scripture. This involves shifting the focus from the<italic>what</italic>of Jesus’s life to the<italic>who</italic>—or better, only understanding what Jesus does in light of who he is. As is clear in many of Frei’s writings, but particularly in<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, the danger in focusing on the “what”—the meaning of the text, or the quality that we attribute to Jesus’s presence—is that our appropriation of this quality (e.g., the wandering stranger, or the human being fully open to God‐consciousness) effaces the textual ascription of this quality to Jesus himself. It is by ascribing the qualities to Jesus, in the act of figural reading, that one turns away from the interpreting subject. As the qualities become markers of Christ’s identity, they no longer serve as general concepts representative of human nature. It is less, I think, that the subject is dispossessed (though this may happen), than that the subject becomes possessed by Jesus.</p>
         <p>In “Theology and the Interpretation of Narrative,” in the context of a debate with Ricoeur, Frei further highlights the significance of the narrative focus of Christian reading. As he writes, the narrative of Jesus is understood “both as … the enactment of who he is, and in its emblematic function for the life of the community.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">21</xref>Frei highlights that such Christian reading, in its focus on the story, involves an “amazing abandonment of halacha in favor of haggadah,” which he partly attributes to antinomian tendencies in Gentile communities. He also distinguishes this “Christian equivalent of haggadah” from Midrash’s emphasis on “sets of individual, cryptic, metaphoric tales.” However, while seeing the narrative as primarily haggadic, Frei’s discussion of the narrative focus of Christian reading indicates that he does think its “emblematic function” serves a role analogous to law, in terms of shaping the community. Highlighting a point already discussed, Frei says that the “parables of the kingdom of God, whatever their original intent, were used … as figurations of Jesus,” and ascribed to him.</p>
         <p>The difference from Ricoeur, who focuses more directly on the parables, is thus once more apparent. While Frei’s reading thus subordinates the parables to Jesus’s identity, this recognition of Jesus’s uniqueness does signal a “limit experience” that opens a world for the reader: “the identity of the messenger became the clue to the character of the message.” Here, one does well to remember that in<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, Frei argues that the grasp of Christ’s uniqueness effects a sense of his presence in both worship and responsibility for the world. As shall be discussed further below, the<italic>sensus literalis</italic>is thus transformative (<italic>a</italic>) in its reshaping of how Christians read and perceive the world and (<italic>b</italic>) in thereby shaping a Christian sense of responsibility (what Frei calls “moral”). This transformation is, at its core, a call to discipleship, in its privileging of the uniqueness of Christ, which nonetheless opens a world for the reader in the pattern of Christ’s story. As Frei writes, “The church … is called upon to be a collective disciple, to follow at a distance … serving rather than being served, and accepting (as the disciple, as differentiated from his Lord) the enrichment given to him by his neighbor.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">22</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The dislocation of the turn to the subject, through the privileging of narrative, renders the subject’s “world of possibilities” secondary; however, it does not deny it. Frei is clear that such hermeneutical interpretation may occasionally be suitable<italic>within</italic>the literal sense. It is, however, the literal sense, and its practice of reading, that creates room for hermeneutics, rather than a second naïveté that makes room for narrative. This becomes clearest when one notes that for all of his criticism of the hermeneutical focus on parables, Frei turns to parables in the culminating section of<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>and suggests that through recognizing Jesus’s identity, one may learn to read history<italic>as</italic>a parable. A properly narrative literal sense, whose ascriptive reading is never complete or final, ultimately may recognize its own parabolic nature: “This brings us to our second parable: Jesus Christ, precisely because he is not only an individual but an individual in a narrated story,<italic>serves as a parable</italic>.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">23</xref>As narrated, Christ’s identity grows from the interaction between his character and the circumstances of his life; the reader cannot grasp it conceptually, in a clear and distinct Cartesian sense. This parabolic aspect of identity—the irreducible singularity of the conjunction between character and circumstances—prevents Christ from simply being a manifestation of a “savior‐myth,” a static, conceptual figure who is ultimately divorced from history.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">24</xref>His identity, within the narrative, is an event—unique and singular in its occurrence, contingent, and therefore not readily mapped onto other events.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">25</xref>Rather, it is only in undergoing the narrative by making ascriptive connections that the reader comes to understanding history in its contingency.</p>
         <p>The parabolic dimension of Christ’s narrative not only guards the singularity of Christ’s identity; Frei sees the application of the “Christlike pattern” to history as requiring that we see events as parables, obscurely and only partially interpretable. In the parabolic, dark light of Christ’s identity we thereby come to glimpse the uniqueness of other events and identities as well: “His specific identity is such that others cannot merge into a common indistinguishable identity with him; instead they find that their own specific and unsubstitutable identity becomes sharply accentuated by relation to Jesus’ own identity.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">26</xref>While we cannot read the story of Jesus onto history in any clear and distinct way, we can see patterns of Christlike death and resurrection in various places in our world and history—the civil rights movement being foremost among others when Frei wrote this text (as if it isn’t today!): “Surely the pattern of this agony and hope may be discerned in such instances as a nation of brothers fighting a civil war to purge itself of the curse of slavery and so achieve concretely a union previously little more than a contractual arrangement. One may dimly discern the same pattern in the equally agonized and uncertain fight of the same nation to complete the unfinished task of reconciliation of those who have lived in estrangement from each other because of racial discrimination.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">27</xref>It is clear, then, that Frei does not see the literal narrative as separating Christ’s narrative from history, so much as providing a way to<italic>read</italic>history that can do justice to the contingent, aleatory character of events and identities, both within scripture and beyond.</p>
         <p>If we return to Ricoeur for a moment, Frei’s emphasis on how the “Christlike pattern” of the literal sense attends to contingency and eventuality may answer some of Ricoeur’s concerns regarding the privilege of narrative in Christian interpretation. For, as Ricoeur describes, the “Christian pattern” of narrative tends to highlight continuity and function as a form of consolation that freezes the polyphony of discourse: “The question, then, is whether the so‐called biblical narrative is not a culturally motivated reduction of the rich interplay of temporal qualities that are displayed by the different literary genres encompassed in the canonical scriptures.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">28</xref>In light of the above comments, and given the further discussions of Midrash that follow below, then one can see that Frei envisages the literal sense of narrative as providing an alternative to the “Christian pattern” that troubles Ricoeur. At its best—perhaps, when practiced with real obedience—the literal sense envisages a scriptural world that is attentive to the temporality and historicity of singularity.</p>
         <p>To summarize, then, the emphasis on narrative requires turning away from modern hermeneutics, dislocates parables from the center of Christian self‐understanding, and initially distinguishes the textuality of scripture from history. However, the narrative approach, as Frei envisages it and practices it, makes room for parables within the narrative field and enables a new way of interpreting and relating to the history in which we live. From seeing how the parables grow into the narrative of Christ’s life, crucifixion, and resurrection, we may glimpse, if darkly, how our own lives can grow into this narrative as well; it is within this scriptural worldview that Frei’s “carefully circumscribed progressive politics” emerges.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">29</xref>It is by according priority to the literal sense, and in light of the identity of Jesus Christ that tentatively emerges from our readings, that our own self‐understanding and our place in the world can be grasped and articulated, if always in a partial, opaque, and humble manner.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn12">
               <label>11</label>
               <p>Hans Frei,<italic>Types of Christian Theology</italic>(New Haven, CT: Yale University Press, 1992), 17.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13">
               <label>12</label>
               <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Interpretation Theory: Discourse and the Surplus of Meaning</italic>(Fort Worth: Texas Christian University Press, 1976), 92.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14">
               <label>13</label>
               <p>Frei is frequently understood to claim that Ricoeur focuses solely on the parables in his interpretation; this view would be clearly mistaken, but I take his point to be that parables, as texts that dispossess the subject, take a central place in Ricoeur’s hermeneutics. For understanding Ricoeur, I follow here Mark Wallace’s<italic>The Second Naïveté: Barth, Ricoeur, and the New Yale Theology</italic>(Macon, GA: Mercer University Press, 1990), 99 and passim.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15">
               <label>14</label>
               <p>Ricoeur, “Interpretive Narrative,” in<italic>Figuring the Sacred: Religion, Narrative, and Imagination</italic>, ed. M. Wallace, (Minneapolis: Fortress, 1995), 187. See also Ricoeur's “Naming God,” in the same volume, and his work with André LaCocque,<italic>Thinking Biblically: Exegetical and Hermeneutical Studies</italic>, trans. David Pellauer (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1998).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16">
               <label>15</label>
               <p>Ricoeur, “Toward a Narrative Theology: Its Necessities, Its Resources, and Its Difficulties,” in Wallace,<italic>Figuring the Sacred</italic>, 243.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17">
               <label>16</label>
               <p>Jim Fodor,<italic>Christian Hermeneutics: Paul Ricoeur and the Refiguring of Theology</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1995), 336.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18">
               <label>17</label>
               <p>See Frei,<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>(Philadelphia: Fortress, 1975), 148–49.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19">
               <label>18</label>
               <p>Wallace,<italic>The Second Naïveté</italic>, 112.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20">
               <label>19</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>Types of Christian Theology</italic>, 18.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21">
               <label>20</label>
               <p>See Frank Kermode,<italic>The Genesis of Secrecy</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1979), 81–85, 95–99.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22">
               <label>21</label>
               <p>All quotes in this paragraph from Frei, “Theology and the Interpretation of Narrative: Some Hermeneutical Considerations,” in<italic>Theology and Narrative: Selected Essays</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1993), 111.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23">
               <label>22</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, 160.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24">
               <label>23</label>
               <p>Ibid., 162; my emphasis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25">
               <label>24</label>
               <p>Ibid., 58–62. Here, one hears echoes of Karl Barth’s distinction between “saga” and myth, with myth being an ahistorical category, whereas saga is a narrative that connects with history. See<italic>Church Dogmatics</italic>(Edinburgh: T&amp;T Clark, 1958), vol. 3, pt. 1, 78–93. What is intriguing in Frei, that is at most implicit in Barth, is that the distinction between narrative and myth is less a difference within a text, than a distinction in two ways of reading. Furthermore, Frei suggests that myth is a way of founding a conceptual understanding of history that cannot recognize the contingency of events.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26">
               <label>25</label>
               <p>It is also important to note that Frei’s reading privileges the public facet of identity—as Mike Higton writes, “<italic>assuming the priority of a kind of identity that can be gained and achieved over time in public</italic>,” and this is true, I take it, both for Jesus and his followers. See Mike Higton,<italic>Christ, Providence, and History: Hans Frei’s Public Theology</italic>(London: T&amp;T Clark, 2004), 71; his emphasis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27">
               <label>26</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, 133.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28">
               <label>27</label>
               <p>Ibid., 162.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29">
               <label>28</label>
               <p>Ricoeur, “Toward a Narrative Theology,” 238.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30">
               <label>29</label>
               <p>See M. A. Higton, “A Carefully Circumscribed Progressive Politics: Hans Frei’s Political Theology”<italic>Modern Theology</italic>15 (1999): 55–83.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>II</title>
         <p content-type="epigraph">
            <disp-quote>
               <p>If I may recall an impression of my own: Because of early Jewish‐Christian theological arguments, like that of Justin Martyr’s<italic>Dialogue</italic>…</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>Jewish writers were more apt to develop theological concerns when they were in strong contact, friendly or hostile, with other cultures and religions—for example, in the twelfth and nineteenth centuries—than at times when Judaism was more inwardly focused. One would have to ask if the sort of reflective energy, largely but not exclusively borne by an intellectual elite, that went into theology in most Christian groups, went into an equivalent but different activity in Judaism. Is Midrash the theology‐equivalent of Judaism? Or, vice versa, is theology the Midrash‐equivalent of Christianity? Suppose that were the case—both the parallel and the difference between the two might be instructive.</p>
            </disp-quote>
            <disp-quote>
               <p>One often hears arguments as to whether one can make significant generalizations about the internal logic of Midrash, or whether it is more nearly an exegetical art with typical formal moves like those to which Robert Alter recently drew attention. A puzzle or a kind of gap in a biblical verse is stated; next, reference is made to verbal or semantic parallels in parts of the Bible distant from the original verse. With their help, one returns to the original verse, often with something like an element of surprise connection—hence the temptation of poststructuralists to see Midrash as an instance if not a paradigm of intertextuality—and so covers the hiatus between verse and problem. There seems to be general agreement among the Rabbis that the literal sense takes priority over any other in this operation (at least until Kabbala), but this seems to be more an insistence on sticking to the recognized range of use of specific biblical words than a self‐conscious appeal to a logical or other, wider frame for interpretation. What the rabbis agree on is not generally as ambitious as, for example, the rule that interpretation covers in three aspects,<italic>explicatio</italic>,<italic>meditatio</italic>,<italic>applicatio</italic>, or the distinction between varieties of nonliteral senses. Midrash is unlike Christian theology but may well fill a similar function: showing the community how to use its sacred text, and doing so through the instrument of a kind of instruction that has continuity of form. In each case, the ultimate recipient of instruction is the community, and it is equally true that in each case the instructional activity is itself communally sanctioned. The method of instruction is in each case one of defining the elements of that religion as a semiotic system, and we might say after Max Weber that rabbis and theologians are ideal types. The mode of instruction employed in each case is in the service of the tradition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">30</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>This passage is Frei’s most extensive descriptions of the practice of Midrash. It elucidates the aspects of Midrash that he sees as particularly significant. The primary sense of the discussion is to differentiate Christian narrative reading from Midrash, but when we read this passage in its context, some commonalities between the two also begin to emerge. In particular, three central tropes emerge: Midrash as a typological, figural practice of interpretation; Midrash as a community‐focused, nonapologetic theology; and the emphasis in Midrash on the grammatical sense of scripture.</p>
         <p>In Frei’s typology of modern theology, types 4 and 5 focus primarily on the self‐description of the Christian community and its intelligibility on its own terms rather than in apologetic terms that would submit Christian discourse to general norms of understanding. While Frei’s opposition to the apologetic approach to theology is well documented, as is his appreciation for Barth’s modeling of type 4, his opposition to the fifth type, as represented by D. Z. Phillips, has received less attention—even though, as David Ford has written, in these lectures his opposition to Phillips’s position is the most vehement.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">31</xref>The above description of Midrash as an “exegetical art” helps to clarify and elaborate how Frei’s understanding of the literal sense differs from the strictly internal, practice‐based understanding of the meaning of religious language set forth by Phillips.</p>
         <p>Frei highlights several crucial features of Phillips’s views: first, the meaning of religious language is grounded in the way of life and practice of the believer—the language therefore takes on a meaning incommensurable with the ways that a philosopher (or a believer in a different faith tradition) would understand it. Second, because of this incommensurability, the work of philosophy can only be to clarify the distinction between different uses of language; it is only from within the terms and practices of a community that one can judge one use of language to be “better” than another, and this judgment is made solely through practice. In Frei’s view, Phillips effectively effaces the possibility of Christian self‐description that would explain why one formulation of doctrine is better than another, by “absolutizing and rigidifying the warranted, indeed essential, distinction between religious statements and statements about religion.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">32</xref>This effaces the possibility of self‐description because the best way to understand—perhaps, really, the only way to understand—is through deeper practice. It is, in a sense, as if upon expressing incomprehension regarding the incarnation, one were told to simply pray harder. The hard and fast distinction between religious utterances and statements about religion leads, on Frei’s view, to the collapse of the distinction between second‐order and first‐order religious statements. There is no logic that could explain the statements—not even to the community itself. Theology is reduced to “parroting” traditional statements: “I wanted to raise the question whether this procedure and this conviction didn’t mean that the theologian could do no more than repeat without conceptually redescribing the words of doctrines or scriptural statements that had doctrinal overtones and aftereffects.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">33</xref>Frei’s fear is not that explanations come to an end, but rather that Phillips’s radically Wittgensteinian position means that explanations never really get started.</p>
         <p>This specter of self‐description that collapses into “parroting” or mechanical repetition of statements without internalization helps to clarify Frei’s own position. In his rejection of Phillips’s position, we see his appreciation for Barth’s recognition that various logics and forms of description may be necessary in various circumstances and thus can be imported into theological discourse. However, over against those such as David Tracy and (perhaps) Ricoeur, it is on the basis of the needs of the Christian community that judgments are made as to whether and when such discourses may be imported. The distinction between conceptual schemes and religious statements is not hard and fast—indeed, it<italic>cannot</italic>be if second‐order religious discourse is really possible. Thus, Frei’s appreciation of Barth’s method, and even of a certain reading of Schleiermacher, becomes clearer in light of the contrast with Phillips.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">34</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Closer to home, those familiar with Frei will recognize that his opposition to Phillips’s position clarifies his own ad hoc apologetic practice. In describing the literary character of the literal sense of scripture, Frei makes frequent use of form criticism as a model for theological discourse—a discourse that grows from understanding the coherence between the various parts of the text, without being determined by historical or other forms of investigation. As T. S. Eliot, one of the most influential New Critics says, an artistic or literary creation is “autotelic,” and if a poem communicates, “that which is to be communicated is the poem itself.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">35</xref>Likewise, the biblical narrative primarily seeks to communicate itself—neither the historical world of the author nor that of the reader (nor, one could say, a world of possibility, à la Ricoeur). Ultimately, however, Frei fears that like Phillips, the New Critics reduce the biblical narrative to being a member of a class of “realistic narratives,” with the effect that it is only on the terms of the text, and within the terms of the text, that “understanding” can happen. He therefore distances himself from New Criticism as a theory of reading, thereby opening space for other forms of reflection within the literal sense.</p>
         <p>The parallels between Frei’s description of Phillips and his encapsulation of New Criticism are striking:<disp-quote>
               <p>Despite their anti‐ or non‐philosophical bearing, in fact many of them [New Critics] espouse a theory of a purely aesthetic kind of truth in literature. … It is similarly artificial to claim a purely external relation of text and reading, which in effect sets aside the mutual implication of interpretation and textual meaning (as hermeneutical theorists would have it) or of reading and the textuality of the text (in terms of the Deconstructionists). If a narrative or a poem should “not mean but be,”<italic>avoiding paraphrase as the proper means to the realization of this ideal comes close to enthroning verbal repetition as the highest form of understanding</italic>.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">36</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>New Criticism subsumes criticism under creativity; “avoiding paraphrase,” as the ideal of New Criticism, effectively denies second‐order discourse, and thus real critical reflection. Given the striking convergence between “enthroning verbal repetition” and “parroting,” as two forms in which repetition of established texts becomes the exclusive path to understanding, the contrast between Frei and Phillips become particularly important. Unlike the New Critics, Frei sees the literal sense as governed by the text, but not to the exclusion of second‐order discourse. Such intertextuality involves a practice of reading that makes space for reflection, including the ad hoc use of philosophical and other logics so as to meditate on and apply the text.</p>
         <p>Frei’s discussion of Midrash contrasts with his criticism of Phillips’s position. He describes Midrash as a practice of reading that is primarily responsible to the community, but in such a way that it enables second‐order discourse to emerge. Indeed, the description above is very close to the type 4 of Barth’s theology. Midrash avoids “parroting” because of its recognition that there are gaps, or problems, within the biblical text—issues that arise within the practice of reading by the community.<italic>Derash</italic>arises from within<italic>peshat,</italic>which, as Loewe describes, always already has a latent dynamism. The priority of the literal sense emerges in how the problems raised by such gaps are resolved—namely, through intratextual reading that relates the words and phrasings of the texts to other scriptural passages. The juxtaposition and interplay of diverse, often “surprising” passages opens the world of understanding for Midrash, without appeal to a general logical framework that would be imported and imposed onto the text. This practice of reading then becomes authoritative for the community—in Frei’s words, “a kind of instruction that has continuity of form.” It is, then, an interpretive practice that is primarily directed toward the community’s self‐understanding—but that can, to some degree, be understood by outsiders, and may make use of alternative logics to help clarify a particular case.</p>
         <p>Another striking feature about Frei’s discussion is his historical classification of various types of Jewish thought. As he describes it, Jewish “theology” develops largely through engagement with its surrounding cultures, while Midrash occurs when the community cultivates a more distinctive identity. If Midrash operates analogously to type 4 theology, then perhaps “Jewish theology” would be closer to type 3. That much of Christian discourse falls under the category of “theology,” indicates that Frei sees Christianity as devoting much of its “Reflective energy” to the apologetic task, rather than to cultivating its own self‐understanding and practice by giving priority to its figural reading. The Kabbala, likewise, represents the rise of allegory as a practice that distorted, and perhaps “eclipsed,” the literal sense of Midrash. The specter of allegory in Frei’s work, as a loss of the literal sense within Christianity, has been well described by Dawson. These comments, then, are perhaps best taken as markers for how Frei would like to locate the<italic>Christian</italic>literal sense: neither allegorical nor apologetic, nor entirely self‐contained, it is the community’s self‐understanding through typological engagement with the text, rooted in a practice that can engender a plurality of readings within the literal sense.</p>
         <p>Finally, Frei’s description of Midrash emphasizes its focus on verbal and semantic features of the text. It is a form of typological interpretation that engages the grammatical sense of scripture in depth. As will become clear below, this is clearly a different understanding of the literal sense than the narrative focus of Christian readings. Nonetheless, the grammatical sense has been a central issue for Christian communities in the modern era, particularly in light of the rise of historical criticism. The intratextual grammatical sense exemplified in Midrash, then, may help Christian communities to articulate the distinctive grammatical typology of scripture.</p>
         <p>As Frei discusses in<italic>The Eclipse of Biblical Narrative</italic>, the study of philology and the grammar of scripture has been a central component of redaction and historical criticism. By and large, grammatical study has examined the language of scripture in light of the uses of language in the historical settings in which texts were written. Grammatical analysis took the form of historical analysis of the verbal forms used in the composition of the texts; as Frei writes of Johann Philipp Gabler, it “meant working out from a text’s words, as used at the time they were written, and the single, and never more than single, meaning of the text and its author, quite regardless of one’s estimate of the soundness of his position.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">37</xref>This single, ostensive meaning of words, in association with the world of the author, subsequently permeated historical‐critical studies, dogmatic theology, and hermeneutics. This historical determination of grammatical meaning comes to fruition in the work of Schleiermacher, whose hermeneutics oscillated dialectically between the poles of psychological, “technical” interpretation and grammatical interpretation. Grammatical understanding involves understanding “the discourse as a focus within a language as a whole, characterized by its relation to the total linguistic stock” of the author, for whose completion, quoting Schleiermacher, “there would have to be a complete knowledge of the language.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">38</xref>While grammatical interpretation is necessary, and always remains incomplete, the “divinatory” element of psychological interpretation governs and guides the interpretation, leading the reader to the text’s meaning, in knowing the author better than she knows herself.</p>
         <p>Ultimately, Frei’s analysis leads to the conclusion that understanding the grammar of the text in terms of its historical linguistic context—in other words, with reference to the culture outside the text itself—divorces the meaning or subject matter of the text from the narrative cohesion of scripture, such that a practice that finds “meaning” in the ascriptive, figural resonances between passages fades from view. “Where hermeneutics and interpretation are governed by the conviction that the interpreter’s unique stance and process of understanding are face to face with that same motion within the discourse to be interpreted, and that this affinity alone (apart from the `linguistic stock’) is the ground for understanding what is being said, such ‘surface’ reading, finding character and society firmly related—a reading, moreover, which discovers the continuity of the narrative in its very contingency—must be viewed as superficial or worse.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">39</xref>In the conclusion to<italic>Eclipse</italic>, Frei suggests that if one divorces grammatical interpretation from its psychological cohort, it may serve as a more appropriate interpretive approach for recovering a narrative sense: “If they are not [united], it still does not necessarily follow that grammatical interpretation can do justice to the obviously narrative features of such realistic texts as the biblical stories. But it does follow that of these two it alone is a candidate, since it alone is concerned with verbal connections.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">40</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Of course, Midrash provides such an example of grammatical interpretation that is not harnessed by psychological interpretation, or the unity of the subject—nor, indeed, that defines the grammatical sense in strictly historical terms, but rather in terms of “verbal connections” between uses of words within scripture. In my opinion, it is therefore not accidental that Frei turns with increased frequency to Midrash in his later work. While perhaps not sufficient for Christian reading, it thus may model a necessary practice of reading that, in the wake of modern hermeneutics, can help in the retrieval of the narrative sense of scripture, in part by opening the possibility of a grammatical sense<italic>within</italic>the world of scripture. The consequences of such Midrash for Christian community, as well as differences in their practices of reading, remain to be considered.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn31">
               <label>30</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>Types of Christian Theology</italic>, 124. This is from an appendix to the lectures, “Theology in the University.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32">
               <label>31</label>
               <p>See David Ford, “On Being Theologically Hospitable to Jesus Christ: Hans Frei’s Theological Achievement,”<italic>Journal of Theological Studies</italic>46 (1995): 532–46. See also Dawson,<italic>Christian Figural Reading</italic>, 167–71.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33">
               <label>32</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>Types</italic>, 55.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn34">
               <label>33</label>
               <p>Ibid., 93.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn35">
               <label>34</label>
               <p>See Frei's essay, “Barth and Schleiermacher,” in<italic>Theology and Narrative,</italic>177–99.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn36">
               <label>35</label>
               <p>T. S. Eliot, “The Use of Poetry and the Use of Criticism,” in<italic>Selected Prose of T. S. Eliot</italic>, ed. Frank Kermode (New York: Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, 1975), 80.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn37">
               <label>36</label>
               <p>Frei, “The ‘Literal Reading’ of Biblical Narrative in the Christian Tradition: Does It Stretch or Will It Break?” in<italic>Theology and Narrative</italic>, 141; my emphasis.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn38">
               <label>37</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>Eclipse</italic>, 166.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn39">
               <label>38</label>
               <p>Ibid., 292. Quote from Schleiermacher,<italic>Hermeneutik</italic>, 82.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn40">
               <label>39</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>Eclipse</italic>, 312</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn41">
               <label>40</label>
               <p>Ibid., 319.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>III</title>
         <p content-type="epigraph">
            <disp-quote>
               <p>Indeed, it seems to me … that a case might well be made that the literal reading of Scripture in the Christian tradition is virtually organized around this story, that the reading of Scripture becomes in a loose and not fully aesthetic sense a literary literal exercise, unlike (for instance) Midrash in Jewish tradition, for which a similar primacy of the literal reading is much more nearly a syntactical and lexicographical rather than literary exercise, in which possible options of biblical verbal uses are carefully explored and compared.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">41</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>As discussed in the previous section, the verbal focus of Midrash embodies a distinctive mode of reading that neither hermeneutics nor historical criticism can fully grasp and thus models a way toward a literal sense beyond the purview of modern theology. However, Frei also makes it clear that in his view, the Christian reading of scripture will differ significantly from how Midrash has been practiced in the Jewish tradition. As this passage suggests, the difference between the two rests largely on the importance of narrative interpretation for the Christian community. Highlighting the central features of “literary” reading will therefore elucidate the contrast and clarify the relationship between figural reading and Midrash for Frei’s work.</p>
         <p>As stated in<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, the narrative set forth in the Gospels sets forth a Christian way of reading in which Jesus’s identity is understood as the conjunction of his enacted intention, the enacted intentions of God and others, and the circumstances in which he finds himself, including Israel’s history with God. The narrative of Christ’s life serves as a “summation” of Israel’s history, as scripturally narrated.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">42</xref>Jesus’s identity is thus the continuation, and intensification, of this history, and the narrative is of his making this history his own. Continually, however, such appropriation is shaped by Jesus’s obedience to God; his “identity” is thus found in his responsive actions, rather than his own intentionality. His obedience to God, as the unifying element of his character, integrates varied states of character and existence: “There is no power for salvation in such pre‐established, paradoxical qualities as helplessness and power, guilt and purity, either in themselves or apart from him. They become efficacious because they are<italic>his</italic>and because he holds them together in the enactment of his obedience to God.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">43</xref>
         </p>
         <p>Obedience to God unifies Christ’s identity by incorporating his powerless submission to the circumstances in which he finds himself and his love of neighbor. As Frei notes, at several central points in the passion narrative, where Jesus is powerless, he nonetheless turns others’ power to his own ends—either by appropriating their words or reshaping the significance of their action. Moreover, Jesus’s agency is far stronger in the Gospel of John than in the Synoptic Gospels.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">44</xref>John’s portrayal of Jesus’s agency also progressively emphasizes Jesus’s unity with the Father, such that what is presented at the beginning as the Father’s intention becomes Jesus’s own through the course of the story.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">45</xref>Frei presents this conjunction as demonstrating that one cannot simply highlight Jesus’s powerlessness in the Synoptic Gospels; rather, to be faithful to the narrative one must grasp both his power and his powerlessness, in these disparate depictions. This exemplifies what one might call a “narrative typology,” which, like Midrash, conjoins apparently disparate or conflicting texts so as to deepen the literal sense.</p>
         <p>Jesus’s love of neighbor is likewise rooted in obedience to God. Obedience is the “referent,” while love is the “content,” but Frei’s point is precisely to emphasize the referent—the “who”—over the “what” of the text. To treat love of one’s fellow humanity as salvific in itself is, for Frei, to reduce or efface the singularity of Jesus’s enacted intention: he is loving toward his neighbors, “enacting the good of men on their behalf,”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">46</xref>out of his obedience to God. By highlighting that it is God’s intention that Jesus act on others’ behalf, Jesus’s uniqueness comes to the fore; this is not simply a love for others that can become the “pattern of exchange” so prevalent in literary representations of Christ. Thus, again, the narrative conjunctions between Jesus’s identity, obedience, love, and circumstance, together form the unique unity of the narrative and thereby envisage a singular, full humanity irreducible to other forms or representations. The narrative is itself typological, while also enabling further typological connections between scriptural passages. It thus resembles Midrash while still remaining distinct, in the “connected narrative sequences” that Christian readers are called to discern.</p>
         <p>The particularly distinctive element of Christian typology is its ascription of titles, actions, and qualities to Jesus.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">47</xref>This pattern of reading, while at work throughout the Gospels, is particularly intense in Christ’s resurrection. Frei reads Luke 24:13–35, where Jesus meets the disciples on the road to Emmaus, as central to Christian reading.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">48</xref>In Jesus’s interpretation of the scriptures with respect to himself—ascriptively—the narrative pattern of interpretation emerges from within the Gospel narrative itself. “He, the unsubstitutable Jesus, now makes the stylized titles his own. He claims them for himself in his very identity of Jesus of Nazareth.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">49</xref>To recognize that Jesus’s self‐identification as the Son of God is actualized in the resurrection, emerging contingently within the story, makes the Christian naming of Jesus as the Son of God dependent upon engagement with the narrative sense. To engage in narrative interpretation, then, is to<italic>follow</italic>Jesus’s act of self‐ascription—or, really, to obey his obedience. One ascribes this name to Jesus, because God, through Jesus’s action, ascribes it to him in the resurrection. Ascription, then, is, first, Jesus’s own practice, second, the practice of the Gospel writers, and, third, the practice of reading constitutive of the Christian community.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">50</xref>Ascription thus constitutes a particular form of “double‐dialogue,” as the text brings together the divine act of reading by Jesus and the community’s act of reading in response.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn52">51</xref>
         </p>
         <p>The contrast with Midrash thus clarifies the distinctive shape of the Christian literal reading, which, in its ascription, is a<italic>form of discipleship</italic>. The Christian pattern of reading is distinctive because it follows, at a distance, the practice of reading ascribed to Jesus in the Gospel narrative itself. While we cannot describe this pattern exhaustively, several central features can be stated. First, and obviously, it is a practice that typologically reads scripture in ascriptive relation to Jesus Christ, as presented within the Gospel narrative. Second, such ascription requires that the reader lay down her own general, conceptual understanding of salvation, redemption, or the “meaning” of human life, as all such conceptual understandings founder before Jesus’s unsubstitutable, narrative identity. Third, one receives new interpretive life in and through narrative ascription. The literal sense, one could say, is the crucifixion and resurrection of hermeneutics, in light of Christ’s unique identity.</p>
         <p>It should be said, moreover, that seeing narrative reading as a form of discipleship may help us to understand the somewhat puzzling shift in Frei’s work. Early in his work, as mentioned above, he draws heavily on New Criticism, treating figural reading as a formal aspect of the text itself. Later, as mentioned above (see n. 8), Frei shifts to speaking of the literal sense as how the community reads the text. This may have been because Frei became suspicious that narrative was being co‐opted as a new hermeneutical category; as Stanley Hauerwas writes, “He rightly fears that the theological construal of scripture as a narrative of God’s work in behalf of his creation might be qualified by claims of the narrative quality of existence or the self.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn53">52</xref>Such a theory of narrative would occlude the ascriptive narrative reading of Christianity, patterned after Christ’s reading. The shift to speaking of the literal sense as “how the community understands the text” thus serves as a corrective to such generalizations. However, it is possible that these stages of his work reflect two dimensions of the literal sense that remain in constant tension: Christian communal reading always follows at a distance, and only in a veiled and partial way, the reading of the one in whom we live and move and have our being.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn42">
               <label>41</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>Types of Christian Theology</italic>, 141.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn43">
               <label>42</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, 128–32.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn44">
               <label>43</label>
               <p>Ibid., 108. See Dawson,<italic>Christian Figural Reading</italic>, 174–78.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn45">
               <label>44</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, 113.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn46">
               <label>45</label>
               <p>Ibid., 118–19.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn47">
               <label>46</label>
               <p>Ibid., 111.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn48">
               <label>47</label>
               <p>See also Frei, “The Accounts of Jesus’ Death and Resurrection,” in<italic>Theology and Narrative</italic>, 70–74, 81–82.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn49">
               <label>48</label>
               <p>Frei,<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>, 149.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn50">
               <label>49</label>
               <p>Frei, 136.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn51">
               <label>50</label>
               <p>Intriguingly, does this not correlate with Karl Barth’s discussion of the threefold form of the Word of God?</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn52">
               <label>51</label>
               <p>I borrow the term “double‐dialogue” from Steven Fraade,<italic>From Tradition to Commentary: Torah and Its Interpretation in the Midrash Sifre to Deuteronomy</italic>(Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 1991), for his discussion of how Midrash creates a “socially situated discursive universe” in which “the commentary progressively constructs by inter‐responsively drawing together and engaging the polyphonic world of Scripture with that of its students—divine will and presence with human society” (14). My thanks to a reviewer for suggesting the source.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn53">
               <label>52</label>
               <p>Hauerwas, “The Church as God’s New Language,” in Green,<italic>Scriptural Authority and Narrative Imagination</italic>, 189.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>IV</title>
         <p content-type="epigraph">
            <disp-quote>
               <p>A far more urgent issue for Christian interpretation is the unpredictable consequences of learning the “language” of the Jewish tradition, including the nearest Jewish equivalent to Christian literal reading. To discover Midrash in all its subtlety and breadth of options and to understand<italic>peshat</italic>(the traditional sense) may well be to begin to repair a series of contacts established and broken time and again, whenever linguistic and textual Old Testament issues become pressing in intra‐Christian debate. Perhaps the future may be better than the past as a result of the intervening period of liberal scholarship and the persuasion that the two religions, even though closely intertwined, are quite distinct, each with its own integrity. The convergence of distinctness and commensurability between them has yet to be discovered, and attention to Midrash and to the literal sense may play a significant part in the discovery.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn54">53</xref>
               </p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>In this passage, the strongest sense of the implications of Midrash for Christian community and practice emerges within Frei’s work. Here, the distinctive political implications of the literal sense for Christian community begin to emerge. This passage, at the end of one of his most influential essays, is particularly striking because the Midrash‐centered life of Judaism, in its particularity, models what Frei wants the Christian community to become.</p>
         <p>What is particularly intriguing here is Frei’s connection between the “particularistic” practices of reading represented by Midrash and the “cultural future” of civilization. Adherence to the literal sense, through typological practices of reading, thus cultivates a practice and informs a worldview that can resist and challenge the universal, hegemonic tendencies of modernity. As he continues, “The Protestant theologian Friedrich Schleiermacher called Judaism a fossil religion, in part at least out of the animus which many Rationalist, Romantic, and Idealistic thinkers bore toward Jewish particularism. And yet it is now conceivable that that `fossil' may bear more of the future of the culture of the West in its hands than Christianity, and its traditional, particularistic forms may not be adventitious to the fact.” The “fossilization” of Judaism from the perspective of the Enlightenment is well known; moreover, the rejection of Jewish particularism by Rationalism, Romanticism, and Idealism bears a strong resemblance to the simultaneous occlusion of the practice of figural reading so powerfully described in<italic>Eclipse</italic>: “Beyond that, however, the example of Judaism in the modern Western world might be a beacon to a reconstituted Christian community. One never knows what this community might then contribute once again to that culture or its residues, including its political life, its quest for justice and freedom—and even its literature. If the priorities are rightly ordered, the literal sense may be counted on to play a significant part in such a less pretentious enterprise. It will stretch and not break.” As Frei notes, such cultural benefits must be considered “secondary” or “incidental”—yet, this paragraph speaks volumes as to the potentially transformative impact that he envisages through adherence to the literal sense of scripture and attention to its relation to Midrash. Such potential is highly significant, given Frei’s frequent disparagement of allegorical readings of scripture that focus on transforming the reader.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn55">54</xref>As throughout, Frei’s work is one of indirection: it is by the detour through the literal sense that a faithful selfhood can be cultivated.</p>
         <p>Frei’s closing comment articulates what is at stake in his emphasis on the literal sense: hermeneutics, as a field of study that has sought a generalizable meaning within the scriptural texts, has effectively redefined Christianity within the terms of general culture—and interpreted Christian doctrines and/or scriptures in ways that provide support for the ideology of that culture. The distinctiveness and particularity of Christian practice and narrative are lost, devaluing the particular integrity of other individuals, communities, and traditions as well. By contrast, a community centered on the literal sense would give up its pretension to universality, standing with other particular communities, first among them Judaism, in their integrity, against a general cultural assimilation. Perhaps a commensurability between these traditions would emerge through shared cultivation of distinctive practices of reading, but such commensurability could not be defined in advance (though my sense is that Frei<italic>hopes</italic>it would emerge). Moreover, to seek commensurability in a contingent, historically located way, apart from or over against the cultural sameness of rationalism and of the global marketplace, would in itself be a gesture of humility, hospitality, and generosity. Attending to the relationship between Midrash and the literal sense would help the Christian community to realize that its identity is enriched by its neighbors and the world.</p>
         <p>Defenders of Frei’s understanding of the literal sense frequently mention that it involves an openness to a plurality of meanings. From<italic>Eclipse</italic>onward, Frei has argued that the modern focus on a unitary meaning, whether historical or existential, obscures the generative self‐referentiality of scripture from view. Given that the conjunctions between disparate texts and grammatical overlaps are innumerable, figural reading, in its practice, must be open to a range of possible senses within the narrative of scripture. The plurality of senses, however, is not simply a theoretical point for Frei. Frei sees Midrash as involving the cultivation of a literal sense that encompasses a range of views within the community (what Frei refers to here as a “breadth of options”). Dissent is recorded, and even the views that are not adopted by the community remain a part of the tradition and can be drawn upon by later scholars as well—reflecting the dynamism and humanism set forth in Loewe’s essay.</p>
         <p>While much of Frei’s work engages liberalism as its foil, his later work takes the shape of a mediating role between liberal and evangelical theology.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn56">55</xref>In so doing, he puts into effect the claim that the literal sense can include the range of concerns and perspectives across the theological spectrum of Christianity. As one recognizes that these diverse perspectives emerge from the literal sense—in other words, through a shared way of reading—one can recognize a unity within the differences of the church. The literal sense, clearly, is not only hospitable to Jesus Christ; at its best, Frei’s hope is that it enables Christians to be more hospitable to one another and to cultivate an alternative hospitality to its surrounding culture.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn57">56</xref>The plurality of interpretations in Midrash may thus model the hospitality created by the literal sense as a feature of what “reconstitutes” the Christian community in its distinctiveness and its unity.</p>
         <p>While Frei’s work models a way for extant Christian communities to mediate their differences, it also challenges their self‐understanding. The mediation that Frei envisages is inseparable from the engagement in shared reading by these communities. One could say that the contingent, pluralistic unity of the literal sense embodies, and makes room for, a contingent, pluralistic unity within the church.</p>
         <p>As with many of these issues, there is more that could be said. The point can be taken, however, that Frei’s attunement to Midrash emerges within his writings in conjunction with a stronger emphasis on the plurality of views within the literal sense.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn58">57</xref>It also models how Christianity, in the particularity of the literal sense, is called to be a countercommmunity, defined and interpreted within the world of scripture rather than on the general, ideologically‐driven criteria of a culture. Such particularity would enable an alternative way of living in our world—transforming relations between Judaism and Christianity, as well as redefining Christianity in relation to its surrounding culture. It also enables a pluralistic unity within the Christian community, as grounded in the shared pursuit of the literal sense.</p>
         <p>To conclude, the frequent reference to Midrash within Frei’s work shows its importance in its connection with the central tenets of his work: its intertextuality, grammatical sense, focus on self‐description, pluralism, and particularity all illuminate these dimensions of the literal sense and thereby help Frei to articulate how the literal sense, from a Christian perspective, exceeds the grasp of modern hermeneutics. Simultaneously, its focus on verbal typology, as opposed to narrative ascription, clarifies via contrast the distinctive typological practice of reading that Frei envisages as central to Christian community. The similarities and differences, together, demonstrate that the literal sense, on Frei’s view, always remains something that exceeds the grasp of any one community or reading. Ultimately, perhaps, one should say that the identity of the literal sense would be the conjunction, or reconciliation, of the communities rooted in these two intertextual approaches to reading, as well as their parabolic engagement with the broader world.</p>
         <p>One could ask, theoretically, whether Frei’s recovery of the narrative sense in Christian theology could proceed without his discussion and study of Midrash. Yet, it is more important to note that these two aspects of his work do go hand in hand and that the concluding passage on the “particularism” of Christianity suggests that such particularity is best maintained and understood in and through engagement with other traditions and practices of reading. Such engagement reminds us of the limitations of our reading, our tendency to privilege certain ways of reading and certain texts, and thereby continually to eclipse the biblical narrative in our own ways. Perhaps it is through the shared study to which Frei’s work points that the literal sense may more fully illuminate and transform our fragmentary, partial habits of reading.</p>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn54">
               <label>53</label>
               <p>Frei, “The Literal Reading of Biblical Narrative,” 149.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn55">
               <label>54</label>
               <p>See Dawson,<italic>Figural Reading and the Fashioning of Christian Identity</italic>.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn56">
               <label>55</label>
               <p>See George Hunsinger’s “Afterword,” in<italic>Theology and Narrative</italic>, 256–57, and Frei’s essay, “Response to Narrative Theology: An Evangelical Appraisal” in the same volume.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn57">
               <label>56</label>
               <p>My thanks to Phil Muntzel for this suggestion.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn58">
               <label>57</label>
               <p>Frei recognized the need for greater plurality within his own reading as well, particularly with regard to the “Gospel narrative” set forth in<italic>The Identity of Jesus Christ</italic>. See Higton,<italic>Christ, Providence, and History</italic>, 200–201.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back/>
</article>
