<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">latiameranti</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100853</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Latin American Antiquity</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Society for American Archaeology</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">10456635</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23072558</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>PEOPLE WHO LIVED IN STONE HOUSES: LOCAL KNOWLEDGE AND SOCIAL DIFFERENCE IN THE CLASSIC MAYA PUUC REGION OF YUCATAN, MEXICO</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Kelli</given-names>
                  <surname>Carmean</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Patricia A.</given-names>
                  <surname>McAnany</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Jeremy A.</given-names>
                  <surname>Sabloff</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>6</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>22</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23072521</issue-id>
         <fpage>143</fpage>
         <lpage>158</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2011 The Society for American Archaeology</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/23072558"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This study builds on the premise that local knowledge of limestone—and its workable characteristics—was foundational to landscape inhabitation in the Puuc region of Yucatán, México. Classic Maya architecture of the northern Yucatán generally is considered to represent the apogee of Maya construction prowess with extensive use of core-veneer masonry and the creation of tall, wide corbelled vaults. Less commonly discussed is the variable distribution of high-quality limestone across the Yucatán, the social matrix that undergirds the quarrying, transporting, and working of limestone, and the pronounced social differences materialized in stone architecture. This study explores these three topics by bringing to bear Yucatec Mayan linguistic evidence and excavation data from the archaeological site of Sayil, in the hilly Puuc region of Yucatán. That information provides a basis for understanding the development of a sprawling residential complex, the role that variable limestone quality played in its expansion, and serves as an index of intra-compound social difference. Late additions to the dwellings indicate that recognition of the cultural value of carved stone persisted long after masonry skills became attenuated. The durability of stone renders it a particularly effective—if underutilized—medium for interpreting social landscapes of the past. Este estudio amplifica la premisa de que el conocimiento de la piedra caliza—y sus propiedades arteseanales—fue una base fundamental para la ocupación del paisaje de la Región Puuc, Yucatán, México. En general, la arquitectura de los mayas de la época Clásica del norte de Yucatán se considera representativa del apogeo de su proeza arquitectónica con el uso extensivo de núcleos de piedra burda recubiertos de piedra labrada y la creación de habitaciones con bóvedas altas y anchas. Menos mencionados son la distribución geográfica variable de piedra caliza de alta calidad a través de Yucatán, la matriz social que permite la explotación de canteras y el transporte y trabajo de los bloques, y la diferencia social profunda que se nota en la arquitectura en piedra. Este estudio explora estos tres temas usando evidencia de la lengua maya yucateca y datos de excavaciones del sitio arqueológico de Sayil, en la serranía Puuc. Esta información proporciona las bases para entender el desarrollo de un grupo residencial expansivo y el papel que la calidad variable de la piedra caliza tuvo en su expansión, y sirve como índice de diferencias sociales entre los habitantes del mismo grupo. Adiciones tardías a los edificios indican que el reconocimiento del valor cultural de la piedra trabajada persistió mucho tiempo después de la disminución de las técnicas especializadas de albañilería. La durabilidad de la piedra la hace un buen instrumento, aunque poco utilizado, para interpretar los paisajes sociales del pasado.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References Cited</title>
         <ref id="d9287e211a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e215" publication-type="other">
Abrams, Elliot M.
1994 How the Maya Built Their World: Energetics and
Ancient Architecture. University of Texas Press, Austin.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e227" publication-type="other">
1998 Structures as Sites: The Construction Process and
Maya Architecture. In Function and Meaning in Classic
Maya Architecture, edited by Stephen D. Houston, pp.
123-140. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collec-
tion, Washington, D.C.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e246a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e250" publication-type="other">
Attanasio, Donato, Rosario Platania, and Paolo Rocchi
2005 White Marbles in Roman Architecture: Electron Para-
magnetic Resonance Identification and Bootstrap Assess-
ment of the Results. Journal of Archaeological Science
32:311-319.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e269a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e273" publication-type="other">
Barrera Väsquez, Alfredo
1980 Diccionario Maya Cordemex. Ediciones Cordemex,
Merida, Yucatan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e286a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e290" publication-type="other">
Blanton, Richard E.
1994 Houses and Households: A Comparative Study.
Plenum Press, New York and London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e304a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e308" publication-type="other">
Carmean, Kelli
1990 The Ancient Households of Sayil: An Archaeologi-
cal Study of Wealth in Terminal Classic Maya Society.
Unpublished Ph.D. Dissertation, University of Pittsburgh,
Pennsylvania.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e326" publication-type="other">
1991 Architectural Labor Investment and Social Stratifica-
tion at Sayil, Yucatan, Mexico. Latin American Antiquity
2:151-165.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e338" publication-type="other">
1998 Leadership at Sayil: A Study of Political and Religious
Decentralization. Ancient Mesoamerica 9:259-270.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e348a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e352" publication-type="other">
Carmean, Kelli, Nicholas Dunning, and Karl Jeff Kowalski
2004 High Times in the Hill Country: A Perspective from
the Terminal Classic Puuc Region. In The Terminal Clas-
sic in the Maya Lowlands: Collapse, Transition, and Trans-
formation, edited by Arthur A. Demarest, Don S. Rice, and
Prudence M. Rice, pp. 424-449. University Press of Col-
orado, Boulder.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e378a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e382" publication-type="other">
Dunning, Nicholas
1992 Lords of the Hills: Ancient Maya Settlement in the
Puuc Region, Yucatdn, Mexico. Monographs in World
Archaeology No. 15. Prehistory Press, Madison, Wiscon-
sin.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e400" publication-type="other">
1994 Soil Erosion, Slope Management, and Ancient Ter-
racing in the Maya Lowlands. Latin American Antiquity
5:51-69.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e413a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e417" publication-type="other">
Feeley-Harnik, Gillian
1985 Issues in Divine Kingship. Annual Review of Anthro-
pology 14:273-313.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e430a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e434" publication-type="other">
Freidel, David, and Jeremy A. Sabloff
1984 Cozumel: Late Maya Settlement Patterns. Academic
Press, New York.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e447a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e451" publication-type="other">
Hansen, Richard
1998 Continuity and Disjunction: The Pre-Classic
Antecedents of Classic Maya Architecture. In Function
and Meaning in Classic Maya Architecture, edited by
Stephen D. Houston, pp. 49-122. Dumbarton Oaks
Research Library and Collection, Washington, D.C.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e475a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e479" publication-type="other">
Hirth, Kenneth G.
2000 Ancient Urbanism at Xochicalco. University of Utah
Press, Salt Lake City.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e492a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e496" publication-type="other">
Houston, Stephen. D.
1998 Classic Maya Depictions of the Built Environment.
In Function and Meaning in Classic Maya Architecture,
edited by Stephen. D. Houston, pp. 333-372. Dumbarton
Oaks Research Library and Collection, Washington, D.C.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e515a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e519" publication-type="other">
Killion, Thomas W, Jeremy A. Sabloff, Gair Tourtellot, and
Nicholas P. Dunning
1989 Surface Assemblages at Terminal Classic (A.D.
800-1000) Sayil, Puuc Region, Yucatan, Mexico. Journal
of Field Archaeology 16:273-294.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e538a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e542" publication-type="other">
Lucero, Lisa J.
2006 Water and Ritual: The Rise and Fall of Classic Maya
Rulers. University of Texas Press, Austin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e555a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e561" publication-type="other">
McAnany, Patricia A.
1987 Sayil 1987: Excavation and Site Structure at Miguel
T. Manuscript on file, Santa Fe Institute.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e573" publication-type="other">
1995 Living with the Ancestors: Kinship and Kingship in
Ancient Maya Society. University of Texas Press, Austin.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e582" publication-type="other">
1998 Stone Tool Production and Exchange in the Eastern
Maya Lowlands: The Consumer Perspective from Pull-
trouser Swamp, Belize. American Antiquity 45:332-346.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e595" publication-type="other">
2004 Appropriative Economies: Labor Obligations and
Luxury Goods in Ancient Maya Society. In Archaeologi-
cal Perspectives on Political Economies, edited by Gary
M. Feinman and Linda M. Nicholas, pp. 145-165. Uni-
versity of Texas Press, Salt Lake City.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e613" publication-type="other">
2008 Shaping Social Difference: Political and Ritual Econ-
omy of Classic Maya Royal Courts. In Dimensions of Rit-
ual Economy, edited by E. Christian Wells and Patricia A.
McAnany, pp. 219-247. REA Vol. 27, JAI Press, Emerald
Group Publishing Ltd., Bingley. UK.</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e631" publication-type="other">
2010 Ancestral Maya Economies in Archaeological Per-
spective. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e641a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e645" publication-type="other">
McAnany, Patricia A., and Ian Hodder
2009 Thinking about Stratigraphic Sequence in Social
Terms. Archaeological Dialogues 16( 1): 1—22.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e659a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e663" publication-type="other">
Patrois, lulie
2008 Etude Iconographique Des Sculptures Du Nord de La
Peninsule Du Yucatan A L'Epoque Classique. BAR Inter-
national Series 1779. British Archaeological Reports,
Oxford.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e682a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e686" publication-type="other">
Plank, Shannon E.
2004 Maya Dwellings in Hieroglyphs and Archaeology: an
Integrative Approach to Ancient Architecture and Spatial
Cognition. BAR International Series 1324. British Archae-
ological Reports, Oxford.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e705a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e709" publication-type="other">
Pollock, Harry E. D.. Ralph L. Roys, Tatiana Proskouriakoff,
and A. Ledyard Smith
1962 Mayapan, Yucatdn, Mexico. Publication No. 619.
Carnegie Institute of Washington, Washington D.C.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e725a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e729" publication-type="other">
Rathje, William L., and David A. Phillips, Jr.
1975 The Ruins of Buena Vista. In A Study of Changing
Precolombian Commercial Systems. The 1972-1973 Sea-
sons at Cozumel, Mexico, edited by Jeremy A. Sabloff and
William L. Rathje, pp. 77-87. Monographs of the Peabody
Museum No. 3. Harvard University, Cambridge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e752a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e756" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul
1985 Time and Narrative, Volume 2. Translated by Kath-
leen McLaughlin and David Pellauer. University of
Chicago Press, Chicago.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e772a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e776" publication-type="other">
Sabloff, Jeremy A.
2007 It Depends on How We Look at Things: New Per-
spectives on the Postclassic Period in the Northern Maya
Lowlands. Proceedings of the American Philosophical
Society 151(1):11—26. Philadelphia.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e796a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e800" publication-type="other">
Sabloff, Jeremy A., and Gair Tourtellot
1991 The Ancient Maya City of Sayil: The Mapping of a
Puuc Region Center. Middle American Research Institute
Publication 60. Tulane University, New Orleans.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e816a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e820" publication-type="other">
Sahlins, Marshall
1981 Historical Metaphors and Mythical Realities: Struc-
ture in the Early History of the Sandwich Islands King-
dom. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e836a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e840" publication-type="other">
Schreiner, Thomas P.
2002 Traditional Maya Lime Production: Environmental
and Cultural Implications of a Native American Technol-
ogy. Ph.D. Dissertation (Architecture), University of Cal-
ifornia, Berkeley. University Microfilms, Ann Arbor.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e859a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e863" publication-type="other">
Smyth, Michael P., and Christopher D. Dore
1992 Large-site Archaeological Methods at Sayil, Yucatan,
Mexico: Investigating Community Organization at a Pre-
hispanic Maya Center. Latin American Antiquity 3:3-21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e879a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e883" publication-type="other">
Smyth, Michael P., Christopher D. Dore, and Nicholas P. Dunning
1995 Interpreting Prehistoric Settlement Patterns: Lessons
from the Maya Center of Sayil, Yucatan. Journal of Field
Archaeology 22:321-347.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e899a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e903" publication-type="other">
Stuart, David
1998 "The Fire Enters His House": Architecture and Rit-
ual in Classic Maya Texts. In Function and Meaning in
Classic Maya Architecture, edited by Stephen D. Hous-
ton, pp. 373-425. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and
Collection. Washington D.C.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e927a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e931" publication-type="other">
Touraine, Alain
1977 The Self-Production of Society. University of Chicago
Press, Chicago and London.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e944a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e948" publication-type="other">
Tourtellot, Gair, Jeremy A. Sabloff, Patricia A. McAnany,
Thomas W. Killion, Kelli Carmean, Rafael Cobos Palma,
Christopher D. Dore, Bernd Famel Bayer, Sandra Lopez
Varela, Carlos Perez Alvarez, and Susan J. Wurtzburg</mixed-citation>
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e963" publication-type="other">
1989 Archaeological Investigations at Sayil, Yucatan, Mex-
ico: Phase II, The 1987 Season. University of Pittsburgh
Publications in Anthropology No. 1. Pittsburgh.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e976a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e982" publication-type="other">
Ward, William C.
1985 Quaternary Geology of Northeastern Yucatan Penin-
sula, Part 2. In Geology and Hydrogeology of the Yucatan
and Quaternary Geology of Northeastern Yucatan Penin-
sula, edited by William C. Ward, Alfred E. Weidie and
William Back, pp. 23-53. New Orleans Geological Soci-
ety, University of New Orleans, New Orleans.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d9287e1008a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d9287e1012" publication-type="other">
Wurtzburg, Susan J.
1991 Sayil: Investigations of Urbanism and Economic
Organization at an Ancient Maya City. Unpublished Ph.D.
Dissertation, Department of Anthropology, State Univer-
sity of New York at Albany.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
