<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">scanstud</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Scandinavian Studies</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00365637</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">21638195</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">scanstud.86.2.0169</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5406/scanstud.86.2.0169</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Remixing Religion in Hanne Ørstavik’s Presten and Lars Amund Vaage’s Tangentane</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="Author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Shackelford</surname>
                  <given-names>Frankie</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">86</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">scanstud.86.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>169</fpage>
         <lpage>207</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2014 by the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/scanstud.86.2.0169"/>
         <abstract>
            <p/>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a collection of essays that illustrates how Nietzsche’s pronouncement of the death of God invites a continuing search for and dialogue about the divine, see Wrathall (2003). See also Hawkins (2003) for an analysis of the poetic and ethical force Jewish authors have drawn from the post-Nietzschean loss of the God of the covenant.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Explaining his writing process, Solstad claims: “Det er ikke min metafysiske lengsel, men det uoppløselig episke element som har bestemt den drift som fikk meg til å avslutte romanen akkurat som jeg gjorde” (2013, 16) [It is not my metaphysical longing, but the indissolvably epic element that determined the urge that made me conclude the novel as I did].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Vaage resists the old methods of realism, which were skewed in favor of scientific explanation: “Å laga kunst er å strekkja seg mot noko ein ikkje kan forklara. Det er ikkje alltid overflata i teksten, handlinga eller argumentasjonen som er det vesentlege, men heller det desse handlingane og argumenta viser, demonstrasjonen av romma bak og under teksten” (2001, 67) [To make art is to reach out toward something one cannot explain. What is essential is not always the surface of the text, the plot or argumentation, but rather what these actions and arguments show, the demonstration of the spaces behind and beneath the text].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kallestad analyzed four novels looking for the presence of the divine: Dag Solstad’s Professor Andersens natt, Jon Fosse’s<italic>Morgon og kveld, Hanne Ørstavik’s</italic>
               <italic>Like sant som jeg er virkelig, and Erlend Loe’s</italic>Naiv. Super. In summary, she finds that “Gud kom tilbake i norsk litteratur på 90-tallet … men Han representerer ingen religion” (2004, 212) [God came back in Norwegian literature in the 1990s … but He does not represent any religion].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kallestad concluded from her study of religious expressions in literature: “de [religiøse uttrykkene] fungerer religiøst ved at de komuniserer en religiøs lengsel eller en lengsel mot overordnet mening i livet” (2004, 212) [they function in a religious way by communicating a religious longing or a longing for an overarching meaning in life]. But in a later article, Kallestad (2008) compares the use of language in the Book of Job with that in<italic>Presten</italic>and finds that in contrast to Job and his friends, for whom language is still potent in dealing with his suffering, Liv is verbally bankrupt and has no rational, mythic, or symbolic language to explain, transcend, or offer solace.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Vaage encourages the subjective reception of novels, recalling the process of oral storytelling he grew up with: “Forteljinga skulle jo mottakast og tolkast, reformulerast, inne ein sjølv” (2001, 69) [The story was meant to be received and interpreted, reformulated, inside oneself].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ørstavik (2010) points to the function of the blank spaces and temporal gaps in Presten as intervals where unarticulated meaning inheres. These openings invite readers to experience Liv’s quandary as their own.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See, among others, Hauge and Ørjasæter (2008) and Bramness and Thon (2012).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>A prelude to this intertextual link can be found early in Rubato: “Det byrja ein vårdag … eller var det slutten? Kven kan vita det? Kven kan fortelja? Kven kan spenna ut eit svar mellom ytterpunkta, slutten av noko og byrjinga på noko anna?” (Vaage 1995, 17) [It started one spring day … or was that the end? Who can know that? Who can tell the story? Who can stretch out an answer between those outer points, the end of something and the beginning of something else?].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Jakobsen (2008) argues that the tired trope of the hypocritical pastor is being replaced by more sympathetic treatments in Nordic film and literature today due to the reduced dominance of the church in society, a decline in social status of the clergy, its growing exotic appeal, and a more nuanced perception of the profession related to an increasing number of women pastors.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>All translations are my own.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>On the role of shame in the novel, see Jakobsen (2008, 127–9).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For a historical overview of the concept of vocatio with examples from the writings of Christian martyrs, monastics, and modern clergy, see Placher (2005). A brief introduction to contemporary interpretations of vocatioand a working definition follow the discussion of narrative identity below.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur conceived of narrative identity as configured both retrospectively and prospectively in the emplotment of stories. In the dialectical relationship between character and plot, readers can perceive a “discordant concordance” that gives provisional unity to each life story (1992, 140–68).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The motifs of a bottomless free fall or the fear of falling appear repeatedly in the novel as an existential threat or submission to fate, as in Liv’s recurring dream of driving through a tunnel and seeing girls fall into pools of water. For an interpretation of this dream, see Høy (2008, 68). In an interview for the Bergen Public Library, Ørstavik described her own path to writing in terms similar to Liv’s turn to theology: “I stedet for et sprang, så handlet det vel om å synke ned, synke inn. Og ikke ha noen annen vei ut” (quoted in Bergsvåg 2013) [Instead of a leap, it was more about sinking down, sinking in. And not having any other way out].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The first three Gospels describe the temptation of Christ during his sojourn in the desert (Matthew 4:1–11; Mark 1:12–3; Luke 4:1–13) and place it at a pivotal time between his baptism and the beginning of his public ministry. Christ’s three temptations include performing the miracle of turning stone into bread to satisfy his hunger, casting himself down from the roof of the temple to prove that his fall will be intercepted by angels, and worshipping Satan in order to receive the kingdoms visible from the mountain top. Scholarship diverges on the figure of Kristiane. Rösing (2008, 108) notes the ambiguity of Kristiane’s name and points to her temptress qualities. Paulson (2008, 73) sees Kristiane as a Christ-figure who animates both her puppets and Liv by sacrificing her own life.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Høy’s reading of the pools of water in Liv’s dream as representations of female sexuality would support an analysis of this moment as a turning point in her gender performance, moving from the male role she assumed with the study of theology to a submissive, female role. Høy does not entertain the idea of bisexuality as a solution or synthesis, although the text could warrant that interpretation.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>In a conversation with Olaug Nilssen, Ørstavik expressed her aim to provide readers a direct experience both intellectually and existentially: “Det å vere i denne situasjonen, i denne erfaringa—berre stå i den og nærast la den slite gjennom deg” (quoted in Nilssen 2003, 48) [To be in this situation, in this experience—just be there and sort of let it wear through you].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ragnar Arntzen (2012, 73) criticizes Erik Bjerck Hagen for not seeing the parody in the novel and dismissing it summarily as another hackneyed account of a pastor’s tribulations. But Arntzen himself does not recognize Hans’s freely assumed clown’s mask as foundational in Vaage’s overall narrative project to point beyond itself, as articulated in his earlier essay: “All god forteljing et opp seg sjølv, vil eg påstå, motverkar seg sjølv” (Vaage 2001, 69) [All good storytelling eats itself up, I would contend, works against itself]. In reducing Hans to a fool, Arntzen is unable to reconcile his immature behavior with his intelligent and sensitive descriptions of classical music, and he unfairly discounts Hans’s self-awareness.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“The self, stripped bare in this way, has been evoked by thinkers as different as Jean Nabert, Gabriel Marcel, and Emmanuel Lévinas—a fact that should make it clear to us that the issue here is the ethical primacy of the other than the self over the self. Even recognizing this, it is still necessary that the irruption of the other, breaking through the enclosure of the same, meet with the complicity of this movement of effacement by which the self makes itself available to others. For the effect of the ‘crisis’ of selfhood must not be the substitution of self-hatred for self-esteem” (Ricoeur 1992, 168).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See, among others, Hahnenberg (2010) and Schuurman (2004). In Scandinavia, Gustav Wingren’s controversial reinterpretation of Luther continues to spawn work on vocation and ethical praxis; see Uggla (2010).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Vatican II resulted in a “universal call to holiness” officially stated as “all Christians in whatever state or walk in life are called to the fullness of Christian life and to the perfection of charity, and this holiness is conducive to a more human way of living even in society here on earth” (Hahnenberg 2010, xi).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>At the center of a contemporary theology of vocation, Hahnenberg places the human subject (“God calls me”). Finding the path forward demands that the individual establish a “sense of oneself before God that, to serve as a reliable guide to discernment, requires brutal honesty and ongoing conversion” (2010, 152). Hahnenberg argues that the kind of conversion needed today comes through “an openness to the interruption of ‘the other’” (2010, 191). The language of interruption in theology, however, originates with the German Catholic political theologian Johann Baptist Metz’s formulation of the “interruptive memories of suffering” (Hahnenberg 2010, 197).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The connection between Latin “pupa” (doll or little girl), appropriated in entymology as the intermediate state between the larval and imaginal stages of metamorphosis, and its German derivative “<italic>Puppe</italic>” (doll or puppet) is significant in that Kristiane’s dark blue puppet, which she had awakened to life on stage and had with her when she shot herself, accompanies Liv to Norway and hangs dormant like a chrysalis on the wall. It is a reminder of Kristiane’s absence and Liv’s own need for rebirth. Readers of Norwegian may hear a resemblance to “<italic>pupper</italic>” (breasts), lending support to an interpretation of Kristiane’s magical<italic>Puppe</italic>and sensuous lifestyle as a form of homoerotic temptation that Liv rejects. For an analysis of the puppet theater as a mediating space between art and life in Ørstavik’s fiction, see Paulson (2008).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Skjerdingstad (2007) analyzes how Liv’s objectifying gaze atomizes everything and everyone around her and renders her own body an empty shell. He also observes that Liv is a kind of “inverted Narcissus” who sees her own reflection in everyone else (292). I would argue, rather, that her very inability to see others as like her has prevented her from the critical recognition of herself as another in Ricoeur’s understanding. Skjerdingstad focuses only on Liv’s intellectual self and ignores her transformation by reading her fate as one of disappearance into the novel’s “dark Orphic gaze.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Rahner sees the non-conceptual experience of grace, God’s “self-communication,” as universally available, yet constitutive of each individual’s concrete existence (1978, 126–7). In this formulation, he expands on Heidegger’s “existentials” by adding “a supernatural existential: the offer of grace in the depths of the human person” (Hahnenberg 2010, 137; emphasis in original).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Matthew 17:4–5 recounts Peter’s offer being interrupted by the voice of God: And Peter said to Jesus, “Lord, it is good that we are here. If you wish, I will make three tents here, one for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah.” He was still speaking when, behold, a bright cloud overshadowed them, and a voice from the cloud said: “This is my beloved Son, with whom I am well pleased; listen to him” (English Standard Version, 2001).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Arntzen (2012) argues that the “big story” is a comedy about a minor pianist or “the pastor who wanted to become a fool,” while the “little story” (the italicized intratext) is a tragedy about a concert pianist. Arntzen’s tongue-in-cheek argument for reading Tangentane as Vaage’s “divine comedy” allows him to put a Nietzschean slant on the work as liberating the reader from undue seriousness. But he ignores the wisdom behind the fool’s mask and with it the integrity of the narrative.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Marstein (2005), for instance, saw the italicized text as opaque and poorly integrated.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <label>30.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Here I see a parallel in Vaage’s own assertion that one writes for personal transformation: “Å fortelja er å bli borte. Å fortelja er å bli ein annan. Å fortelja er å trassa avgjerdene om kven ein er. Å fortelja er å gå under for så kanskje å bli fødd på ny” (Vaage 2001, 69) [To write is to disappear. To write is to become someone else. To write is to defy the determinations of who one is. To write is to submerge onself in order perhaps to be born again].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <label>31.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Barth underscores God’s initiative in revelation: “All our efforts to apprehend Him by ourselves shipwreck. … He is always the One who will first and foremost apprehend and possess us” (Barth 1957, 188). For more on Barth’s view of God’s self-revelation and its importance for vocatio, see Hahnenberg (2010, 111–22).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <label>32.</label>
            <mixed-citation>At the Kvinnherad Kulturfestival in February 2006, which honored Vaage’s literary career, he expressed gratitude for the privilege that allows him to focus on his self-development, to get inside the head of his characters and perhaps become a different person. But he also spoke about writing as a means to survive, to seek hope, to laugh at things, and to “være på livet si side” [join forces with life]. Tangentane, published only a few months before Vaage’s festival remarks, unites all these impulses.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <label>33.</label>
            <mixed-citation>On Luther’s notion of paradox and his insistence on human finitide as the basis for a Lutheran model of intellectual inquiry, see Hughes (2005, 60–8).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <label>34.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The verb here “forskjøvet seg” (displaced itself) and the related noun “<italic>forskyvning</italic>” (shift, displacement) are marked terms, occurring repeatedly in this novel and in Ørstavik’s work more generally. When applied to this “something,” the shift implies a fundamental necessity of one truth displacing another over time.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <label>35.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For the roots of today’s vision of the open church, see Rahner (1974, 93–101).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
