<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">dialanth</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50002488</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Dialectical Anthropology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">03044092</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15730786</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">43895120</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>'Dreaming the dream of a dead man' memory, media, and youth in postwar El Salvador</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Rafael Alarcón</given-names>
                  <surname>Medina</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>38</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40160154</issue-id>
         <fpage>481</fpage>
         <lpage>497</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Springer Science+Business Media 2014</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/43895120"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Using postwar El Salvador as a case study, I argue against the dominant paradigm that situates the repressive role of the state as both the central object of memorialization and the main subject of history. Instead, I focus on the ways in which the memory of insurgent collective action is constructed among young members of the popular classes in postwar El Salvador. Drawing on extensive ethnographic research in the communities of northern Morazán, I understand memory as the suspended time of praxis. Media—such as Internet, Facebook, and TV play a key role in this process, impinging on the ways youth relate with the revolutionary past of their relatives making sense of their present living conditions. I argue that memory must be understood as a particular form of praxis, one that is embedded in historic concrete forms of class constitution in which the role of media has become a constitutive element in the labors of memory, particularly among young people.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d2373e141a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2373e148" publication-type="other">
Ibisate 2001</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d2373e155a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d2373e162" publication-type="other">
https://www.youtube.com/watch7vs-CGYPCvnlZg.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d2373e178a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e182" publication-type="other">
Alarcon Medina, Rafael, (forthcoming). Peasant warriors in an electronic social-formation. From rural
communities to transnational circuits of dependence in Postwar El Salvador, Convergence, SAGE.
México: Anthropos.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e195a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e199" publication-type="other">
Arango, Julián. 2009. Somos tiempo. Crítica a la simplificación del tiempo en occidente. México:
Anthropos.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e209a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e213" publication-type="other">
Arditi, Benjamin (ed.). 2000. El reverso de la diferencia. Identidad y política. Venezuela: Nueva
Sociedad.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e223a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e227" publication-type="other">
Arriarán, Samuel. 2010. Filosofia de la memoria y el olvido. México: Universidad Pedagógica Nacional -
Itaca.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e238a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e242" publication-type="other">
Auyero, Javier. 2003. Contentious lives: Two Argentine women, two protests and the quest for
recognition. Durham and London: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e252a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e256" publication-type="other">
Benavides, Hugo. 2008. Drugs, thugs and divas. Austin: University of Texas Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e263a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e267" publication-type="other">
Benjamin, Walter. 2008. Tesis sobre la historia y otros fragmentos, Edición y traducción de Bolívar
Echeverría. México: Universidad Autónoma de la Ciudad de México-Ithaca.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e277a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e281" publication-type="other">
Bergson, Henri. 2001. Time and free will. An essay on the immediate data of consciousness. New York:
Dover.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e291a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e295" publication-type="other">
Bergson, Henri. 2006. Materia y memoria. Ensayo sobre la relación del cuerpo con el espíritu. Argentina:
Cactus.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e305a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e309" publication-type="other">
Bilbija, Ksenija, and Leigh Payne. 2011. Accounting for violence. Marketing memory in Latin America.
Durham and London: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e320a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e324" publication-type="other">
Binford, Leigh. 2010. A perfect storm of neglect and failure: Postwar capitalist restoration in Northern
Morazán, El Salvador. The Journal of Peasant Studies 37(3): 531-557.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e334a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e338" publication-type="other">
Brockmeier, Jens. 2010. After the archive: Remapping memory. Culture &amp; Psychology 16(1): 5-35.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e345a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e349" publication-type="other">
Cagan, Beth, and Steve Cagan. 1991. This promised land, El Salvador. USA: Rutgers University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e356a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e360" publication-type="other">
de Giovanni Biagio. 1984. La teoría política de las clases en 'El Capital'. Mexico: Siglo XXI.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e367a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e371" publication-type="other">
Ernst, Wolfgang. 2013. Digital memory and the archive. Minneapolis-London: University of Minnesota
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e381a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e385" publication-type="other">
Feierstein, Daniel (ed.). 2011. State violence and genocide in Latin America: The Cold War years. New
York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e396a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e400" publication-type="other">
Garde-Hansen, Joanne, Andrew Hoskins, and Anna Reading. 2009. Save as... digital memories. New
York: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e410a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e414" publication-type="other">
Gómez-Barris, Macarena. 2008. Where memory dwells: Culture and state violence in Chile. California:
University of California Press, USA.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e424a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e428" publication-type="other">
Gorkin, Michael, Marta Pineda, and Gloria Leal. 2013. De abuela a nieta. Historias de mujeres
salvadoreñas. El Salvador: Universidad Centroamericana.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e438a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e442" publication-type="other">
Gould, Roger V. 1995. Insurgent identities: Class, community and protest in Paris from 1848 to the
commune. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e452a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e456" publication-type="other">
Grandin, Greg, and Joseph Gilbert (eds.). 2010. A Century of Revolution: Insurgent and Counterinsurgent
Violence during Latin America's Long Cold War. USA: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e466a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e470" publication-type="other">
Hardt, Michael, and Toni Negri. 2004. Multitud: Guerra y democracia en la era del Imperio. España:
Debate.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e481a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e485" publication-type="other">
Hardt, Michael, and Toni Negri. 2009. Commonwealth. USA: Belknap-Harvard.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e492a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e496" publication-type="other">
Hoskins, Andrew. 2011. Anachronisms of media, anachronisms of memory: From collective memory to a
new memory ecology. In On media memory: Collective memory in a new media age, ed. Motti
Neiger, Oren Meyers, and Eyal Zandberg, 278. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e509a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e513" publication-type="other">
Ibisate, Francisco. 2001. La turbo-dolarización. Realidad 79: 9-29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e520a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e524" publication-type="other">
Jelin, Elizabeth. 2003. State repression and the labors of memory. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e534a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e538" publication-type="other">
Lebow, Richard. 2008. The future of memory. Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social
Science 617: 25-41.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e548a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e552" publication-type="other">
Marx, Karl. 1973. Grundrisse. UK: Penguin Classics.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e560a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e564" publication-type="other">
Morris-Suzuki, Tessa. 2005. The past within us: Media, memory, history. London: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e571a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e575" publication-type="other">
Neiger, Motti, Oren Meyers, and Eyal Zandberg (eds.). 2011. On media memory: Collective memory in a
new media age. New York: Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e585a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e589" publication-type="other">
Pentzold, Christian. 2010. Fixing the floating gap: The online encyclopaedia Wikipedia as a global
memory place. Memory Studies 2(2): 255-272.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e599a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e603" publication-type="other">
Ramos, Carlos. 2011. Identidades, prácticas y expectativas juveniles al inicio del siglo XXI. El Salvador:
FLACSO.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e613a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e617" publication-type="other">
Ricouer, Paul. 2003. La memoria, la historia, el olvido. Madrid: Trotta.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e624a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e628" publication-type="other">
Rieser, Vittorio. 1987. "La 'apariencia' del capitalismo en el análisis de Marx", en Dobb, Maurice et al,
Estudios sobre el capital. México: Siglo XXI.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e639a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e643" publication-type="other">
Rigney, Ann. 2012. Reconciliation and remembering: (how) Does it work? Memory Studies 5(3):
251-258.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e653a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e657" publication-type="other">
Rivas, Cecilia. 2014. Salvadoran imaginaries: Mediated identities and cultures of consumption. New
Brunswick: Rutgers University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e667a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e671" publication-type="other">
Robinson, William. 2003. Transnational conflicts: Central America, social change and globalization.
United Kingdom: Verso.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e681a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e685" publication-type="other">
Robinson, William. 2008. Latin America and global capitalism. A critical globalization perspective.
Baltimore: Johns Hopkins.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e695a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e699" publication-type="other">
Rubin, Isaak. 1974. Ensayos sobre la teoría marxista del valor. Argentina: Cuadernos de Pasado y
Presente.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e709a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e713" publication-type="other">
Silber, Irina. 2010. Everyday revolutionaries: Gender, violence, and disillusionment in postwar El
Salvador. USA: Rutgers University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e724a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e728" publication-type="other">
Sohn-Rethel, Alfred. 1978. Intellectual and manual labour: A critique of epistemology. London:
Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e738a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e742" publication-type="other">
Sohn-Rethel, Alfred. 2010. La pensé marchandise. France: Editions du croquant.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e749a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e753" publication-type="other">
Steiner, Uwe. 2010. Walter Benjamin: An introduction to his work and thought. Chicago and London:
The University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e763a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e767" publication-type="other">
Todd, Molly. 2010. Beyond displacement: Campesinos, refugees, and collective action in the Salvadoran
Civil War. Madison: The University of Wisconsin Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e777a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e781" publication-type="other">
Van Dijk, Jose. 2007. Mediated memories in the digital age. California: Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e788a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e792" publication-type="other">
Van House, Nancy, and Elizabeth Churchill. 2008. Technologies of memory: Key issues and critical
perspectives. Memory Studies 1(3): 295-310.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e803a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e807" publication-type="other">
Wood, Elizabeth. 2003. Insurgent collective action and civil war in El Salvador. New York: Cambridge
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d2373e817a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e821" publication-type="other">
Zelizer, Barbie. 2011. Cannibalizing memory in the global flow of news. In On media memory: Collective
memory in a new media age, ed. Motti Neiger, Oren Meyers, and Eyal Zandberg, 27-36. New York:
Palgrave Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Films</title>
         <ref id="d2373e843a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d2373e847" publication-type="other">
Consalvi, Carlos, and Geoffrey Gould. 2011. La palabra en el bosque (The word in the woods). El
Salvador: Museo de la Palabra y la Imagen.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
