<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="ucp-id">jr</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/679208</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JR351614</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="af1" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Glenn</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Whitehouse</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af1">Florida Gulf Coast University.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>October 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>94</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>677726</issue-id>
         <fpage>553</fpage>
         <lpage>554</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>
               <surname>Peperzak</surname>,<given-names>Adriaan T.</given-names>
            </string-name>
            <source>Thinking about Thinking: What Kind of Conversation Is Philosophy?</source>New York: Fordham University Press, 2012. x+211 pp. $75.00 (cloth); $26.00 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>For permission to reuse, please contact<email xlink:type="simple">journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu</email>.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/679208"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In this book, Adriaan Peperzak, the Arthur J. Schmitt Professor of Philosophy at Loyola University Chicago, reflects broadly on the nature of philosophy, its relation to concrete life, and its rootedness in our encounters with other humans and God. The book covers similar themes as Peperzak’s earlier<italic>Thinking: From Solitude to Dialogue and Contemplation</italic>(New York: Fordham University Press, 2006) and largely collects material previously published or presented. Far from being redundant, however, Peperzak’s metaphilosophy benefits from the essayistic style in which it is presented in<italic>Thinking about Thinking</italic>, and the occasional nature of some of the pieces illustrates Peperzak’s point that philosophy arises out of the commitments and engagements of an individual life.</p>
      <p>Peperzak critiques the self-image of philosophy as “strictly autonomous thought, in the strong, wholly independent, and autarkic sense of this word” (129). Philosophy in this, typically modern, mold starts with a laudable commitment to freedom but ends up “obsessed by the sovereign position of an ego on top of a panoramic universe” (156) and coldly abstracted from the particularities of individual thinkers, its discourse closed off from relation to others.</p>
      <p>In response, Peperzak offers what would most accurately be described as a phenomenology of the practice of philosophy. Peperzak applies Emmanuel Levinas’s phenomenology of the Other to the critique of this philosophical autarky. Philosophy cannot be conceived simply as a system of propositions. Any Said implies someone saying it to someone, and Saying limits the totality of thematic thought through the encounter with the infinitude of the Other to whom I address my saying (8–19). Peperzak invites philosophers to reconsider their discipline by attending to the lived intersubjective context of philosophical conversation, rather than to systematically thematized rational propositions alone.</p>
      <p>Peperzak’s account of philosophy as conversation emphasizes a few key themes. First, he defends the view that the history of philosophy is an integral part of the practice of philosophy. A tradition in his account is a living conversation in which philosophical sources are not simply transmitted but transformed in the process. Speaking to his fellow Catholic philosophers, Peperzak at once defends the legitimacy of appeal to the historical traditions of communities for citizens of the “Republic of philosophy” (176) and insists that tradition cannot simply canonize past thinkers but must become part of the ongoing conversation of the present. Second, Peperzak emphasizes more than most philosophers the significance of philosophical style. For him, style is the particularization of philosophical tradition and thematics in lived conversations. It marks my individual way of offering my voice to a philosophical companion—a unique event, even if what is Said may repeat inherited propositions (90–91).</p>
      <p>Peperzak is concerned with the relation between philosophy and faith, more than any other topic, however. Following his phenomenology of philosophical conversation, he claims, “The encounter with God is somewhat comparable to a face-to-face relationship that stretches me when I look up to a human person who loves me. Since God is infinite, however, faith and love toward God encompass the universe of all that exists. … Faith thus mobilizes and orients the entirety of one’s existence from top to bottom” (120–21). Peperzak regards faith as a fundamental Desire that orients us in an encounter with the absolute. As such, there is no clean separation of faith and philosophy. All thinking emerges from some sort of faith, and while philosophy has a universality that can engender conversation across differences of faith orientation, its autonomy is a relative and limited one. Moreover, Peperzak associates the infinity of God encountered as Other with the Platonic Good that illuminates all thinking and being, while itself escaping thematization: “the<italic>phila</italic>(love) of<italic>philosophia</italic>reaches out toward a wisdom (<italic>sophia</italic>) that implies … a sense of the difference between this cosmos and the ultimately desired but ungiven Good. … By longing, Eros reaches further than any theory” (159).</p>
      <p>This book about the conversation of philosophy itself connects with a number of conversations current in philosophy and religious studies. For one, Peperzak provides a compelling defense of the claim that philosophy is fundamentally a way of life and not only a scholastic practice of system building. In this, he joins a growing interest among neohumanists and continental thinkers in reviving premodern senses of philosophy as a spiritual practice, drawing off the earlier work of Pierre Hadot and others.</p>
      <p>Peperzak in this book also offers continental thinkers an appealing alternative to the theological turn of phenomenology as practiced by Jean-Luc Marion and others. While Peperzak takes seriously the idea that “God cannot be investigated or explained … because God is not given as a describable phenomenon,” this realization does not turn his phenomenology away from the investigation of rational thinking because for Peperzak reason itself has to be rethought in terms of the intersubjective encounters between nonthematizable—human and divine—sayers (121). Consequently, much more than some of the thinkers of the theological turn, Peperzak’s work maintains a broadly humanist sensibility and a conviction that theological thinking and philosophy can be integrated quite well, provided the latter does not close itself off in autarky. In his humanism, Peperzak echoes the best elements in the philosophical style both of his teacher Paul Ricoeur and the philosophical tradition of his own Catholic faith, although he implicitly critiques the former for insisting too vehemently on the autonomy of philosophy (128) and calls out the latter for separating “natural reason” from faith (182–86). For his own part, Peperzak hopes to maintain an open space between faith and reason: “I do not see any valid argument against the integration of philosophical insights into a faith-inspired theology … neither would I protest if an integrated reflection of the Christian community about its faith would call itself<italic>philosophia</italic>” (160). For the many who share similar sentiments today,<italic>Thinking about Thinking</italic>will make a valuable guide to the conversation of philosophy.</p>
   </body>
</article>
