<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">quiparle</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full" xml:lang="en">Qui Parle: Critical Humanities and Social Sciences</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Nebraska Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">10418385</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">19388020</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">quiparle.19.1.0205</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5250/quiparle.19.1.0205</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>REVIEW ESSAYS</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>On the Cognitive Turn in Literary Studies</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>MICHELLE TY</string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2010</year>
            <string-date>Fall/Winter 2010</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2010</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>19</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>quiparle.19.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>205</fpage>
         <lpage>219</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>Stanislas Dehaene</string-name>
            <source>Reading in the Brain: (<italic>New York: Viking Press</italic>, 2009)</source>
         </product>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>Irving Massey</string-name>
            <source>The Neural Imagination: Aesthetic and Neuroscientific Approaches to the Arts: (<italic>Austin: University of Texas Press</italic>, 2009)</source>
         </product>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>Blakey Vermule</string-name>
            <source>Why Do We Care about Literary Characters?: (<italic>Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press</italic>, 2010). Cited in the text as RB, NI, and WWC, respectively.</source>
         </product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2010 Qui Parle</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5250/quiparle.19.1.0205"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="parsed-citations">
         <title>Notes</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Max Horkheimer</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Theodor Adorno</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Dialectic of Enlightenment</italic>
               </source>, trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>John Cumming</string-name>
               </person-group>(:<publisher-name>Continuum</publisher-name>,<year>1972</year>),<fpage>26</fpage>.<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Edmund Jephcott</string-name>
               </person-group>' translation (:<publisher-name>Stanford University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2002</year>) substitutes<article-title>“knowledge”</article-title>for<article-title>“science.”</article-title>In both versions of the sentence, the meaning remains apposite to the present discussion.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">My examples are not given in the spirit of scientific rigor but are admittedly quite suggestive. As compensation for taking some liberties in making these scientific findings digestible, I have provided citations for less-digestible sources when applicable.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">While the case presented here involves only visual stimuli, research has shown that mirror neurons are multimodal, meaning that they respond to multiple senses. Hearing, not just seeing, another monkey rip a piece of paper produces neural effects similar to those that occur during the grasping exercise. A similar neural network is being mapped in humans. The evidence for the human mirror system is more indirect, because scientists aren't often permitted to implant electrodes directly onto human brains. Information about single neurons in humans is often restricted to a small body of research on epileptic patients who had already consented to invasive surgery for other reasons. Many scholars have made speculations about the mirror system' role in language acquisition, imitation, empathy, and what scientists have called “embodied simulation.” One of the neuroscientists most involved in mirror systems research, Vittorio Gal-lese, has reported that his own work has been influenced by Maurice Merleau-Ponty. It' little surprise that many of those working with mirror systems have an inclination toward phenomenology. For a useful introduction to mirror neuron research, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Marco Iacoboni</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Mirroring People: The New Science of How We Connect with Others</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Farrar, Straus, and Giroux</publisher-name>,<year>2008</year>); and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Giacomo Riz-zolatti</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Mirrors in the Brain: How Our Minds Share Actions, Emotions, and Experience</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2008</year>). For something more technical, see<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Maksim Stamenov</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Vittorio Gallese</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Mirror Neurons and the Evolution of Brain and Language</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>John Benjamins</publisher-name>,<year>2002</year>); and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Christian Keysers</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Luciano Fadiga</string-name>
               </person-group>, eds.,<source>
                  <italic>The Mirror Neuron System</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>,<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Karim Nader</string-name>
               </person-group>,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Glenn Schafe</string-name>
               </person-group>, and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Joseph LeDoux</string-name>
               </person-group>,<article-title>“Fear Memories Require Protein Synthesis in the Amygdala for Reconsolidation After Retrieval,”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Nature</italic>
               </source>,<month>August</month>
               <day>17</day>,<year>2000</year>,<fpage>722</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>. Nader' is one of the foundational experiments in support of the reconsolidation theory of memory. His experiment involved administering electroshocks to lab rats. Nader found that if rats were injected with a protein synthesis inhibitor just after the trauma, they would fail to generate any corresponding fear memories. Nader then allowed fear conditioning to proceed without the introduction of chemicals. He found that he could effectively “erase” the fear memory in rats if he injected the protein synthesis inhibitor during the brief window of time when the memory was being retrieved. Recently (and perhaps alarmingly), Nader began using these findings to treat patients with post-traumatic stress disorder.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Olaf Hauk</string-name>
               </person-group>,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Ingrid Johnsrude</string-name>
               </person-group>, and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Fridemann Pulvermüller</string-name>
               </person-group>,<article-title>“Somato-topic Representation of Action Words in Human Motor and Premo-tor Cortex,”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Neuron</italic>
               </source>
               <month>January</month>
               <day>22</day>,<year>2004</year>,<fpage>301</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">There are far too many neuroscience crossover books to list here. With regard to neurobiological accounts of morality,<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Laurence Tan-credi</string-name>
               </person-group>'<source>
                  <italic>Hardwired Behavior</italic>
               </source>(<year>2005</year>) and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Richard Joyce</string-name>
               </person-group>'<source>
                  <italic>The Evolution of Morality</italic>
               </source>(<year>2007</year>) are among the most widely read.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Edward O. Wilson</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Consilience: The Unity of Knowledge</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>,<year>1999</year>),<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Jean-Pierre Changeux</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Paul Ricoeur</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>What Makes Us Think? A Neuroscientist and a Philosopher Argue about Ethics, Human Nature, and the Brain</italic>
               </source>, trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>M. B. DeBevoise</string-name>
               </person-group>(:<publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2000</year>),<fpage>11</fpage>. Hereafter cited as<italic>WM</italic>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Semir Zeki</string-name>
               </person-group>,<article-title>“Statement on Neuroesthetics,”</article-title>
               <uri xlink:href="http://neuroesthetics.org/statement-on-neuroesthetics.php">http://neuroesthetics.org/statement-on-neuroesthetics.php</uri>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">Consider this passage from the introduction of Hume'<italic>Treatise of Human Nature</italic>: “‘Tis evident, that all the sciences have a relation, greater or less, to human nature; and that however wide any of them may seem to run from it, they still return back by one passage or another. Even Mathematics, Natural Philosophy, and Natural Religion, are in some measure dependent on the science of Man. … Here then is the only expedient, from which we can hope for success in our philosophical researches, to leave the tedious lingring method, which we have hitherto follow'd, and instead of taking now and then a castle or village on the frontier, to march up directly to the capital or center of these sciences, to human nature itself.” Neuroscience seems to be resurrecting an old tactic of British empiricism. Like Hume, Zeki and other cognitive scientists position themselves at the forefront of an emerging super-discourse on human nature. Only now, the Science of Man is replaced by the paradigm of neurobiology.<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Hume</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Treatise of Human Nature</italic>
               </source>(<publisher-name>New York: Oxford University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2008</year>),<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Patricia Cohen</string-name>
               </person-group>,<article-title>“The Next Big Thing in English: Knowing They Know That You Know,”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>New York Times</italic>
               </source>,<month>March</month>
               <day>31</day>,<year>2010</year>. Hereafter cited as “NBT.”</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Michael Holquist makes a different though not unrelated claim about literature' value. He argues that good literature is edifying in a specific, cognitive way. He plans to test his hypothesis at the Haskins Laboratory in New Haven, where he and a research team will monitor twelve subjects in an MRI machine as they read passages of increasing literary complexity. Holquist describes his project: “We begin by assuming that there is a difference between the kind of reading that people do when they read Marcel Proust or Henry James and a newspaper, that there is a value cognitively when we read complex literary texts” (quoted in “NBT”).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Suzanne Nalbantian</string-name>
               </person-group>,<article-title>“Neuroaesthetics: Neuroscientific Theory and Illustration from the Arts,”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>33</volume>, no.<issue>4</issue>(<year>2008</year>):<fpage>357</fpage>. The two central book-length studies in the field of neuroaesthetics are<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>V. S. Ramachandran</string-name>
               </person-group>'<source>
                  <italic>The Artful Brain</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Fourth Estate</publisher-name>,<year>2005</year>) and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Semir Zeki</string-name>
               </person-group>'<source>
                  <italic>Inner Vision: An Exploration of Art and the Brain</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Paul Ricoeur made a similar point in the debate with Changeaux mentioned above. When the neuroscientist suggested that the most vital question facing contemporary science involves how to reconcile neuronal descriptions and their outward manifestations, Ricoeur responded, “It' not only the anatomical and the behavioral that have to be related to each other, for they both fall under the category of objective knowledge; but observed and scientifically described behavior, on the one hand, and, on the other, personal experience” (<italic>WM</italic>, 18). Ricoeur is not alone in thinking that science falters before subjective experience.<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Alva Noë</string-name>
               </person-group>takes a similar stand when he persists in saying,<article-title>“you are not your brain.”</article-title>See note<fpage>18</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dehaene advances a hypothesis of “neuronal recycling” to circumvent what he calls the “the reading paradox.” This paradox hinges on the fact that literacy is of recent date and as such cannot be considered an adaptive capacity. Given that reading abilities could not have been targeted by evolution, it is noteworthy that humans have specialized cortical mechanisms finely tuned for the recognition of written words. Dehaene theorizes that reading was predicated on our ability to “recycle” existing neural architecture. He insists that literacy and other cultural activities do not just arise out of the sheer force of innovation but instead develop by capitalizing on the “fringe plasticity” in select neural systems. The “neuronal recycling” hypothesis is one of two deep investments he has in the book. The other has to do with education. Dehaene wants neuroscience to change the pedagogy of reading at an institutional level. To teach children to read properly, the Chomskian-influenced whole-language movement must be fully abandoned. Because the determining factor of literacy is a person' competence in grapheme-to-phoneme conversion—turning marks into the appropriate sounds—phonics is what teachers must bring to the classroom.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dehaene mentions other technologies, such as EEG and MEG (electro-and magnetoencephalogram), that monitor the brain in real time. These methods, like the fMRI, remain indirect. The EEG and the MEG assume that neural activity generates low-level electrical and magnetic responses that can be detected at a distance. When many neurons receive electrical inputs simultaneously, they generate a weak current that can then be measured. PET (positron emission tomography) yields three-dimensional images of the brain without the two-to three-second interval required of fMRI. PET has fallen out of favor because the process involves injecting radioactive isotopes into the body.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Alva Noë</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Out of Our Heads: You Are Not Your Brain, and Other Lessons from the Biology of Consciousness</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Hill and Wang</publisher-name>,<year>2009</year>),<fpage>20</fpage>. For Noë, even more problematic than these technological limitations is something he calls the foundation argument. He paraphrases this fallacious but common form of reasoning as such: “The fact that we dream, and that we can produce events in consciousness by directly stimulating the brain, shows that the brain alone is sufficient for consciousness” (172). Noë objects to this argument on three counts. First, arousing certain experiences by manipulating the brain doesn't necessarily mean that<italic>all</italic>events of consciousness can likewise be produced. Second, concerning the successful stimulation of hallucinations by direct action on the brain, “the best we can say is that… the brain plus the actions of the manipulating scientists are sufficient for the occurrence of hallucinatory events in consciousness” (174). Finally, when scientists induce perceptions by direct brain manipulation, they alter existing states of consciousness; they do not generate it afresh. One cannot then conclude that the brain alone is sufficient for consciousness or that consciousness depends only on the activities of the brain.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Catherine Malabou</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>What Should We Do with Our Brain?</italic>
               </source>trans.<person-group person-group-type="translator">
                  <string-name>Sebastian Rand</string-name>
               </person-group>(:<publisher-name>Fordham University Press</publisher-name>,<year>2008</year>),<fpage>8</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">This now routine trope of “two cultures” was inaugurated and popularized by C. P. Snow in a lecture given at Cambridge in 1959. I am hardly insinuating that a problem of translation does not exist between cognitive science and literary studies, or more broadly, the discourse of science and the arts. My grievance against the “two cultures” paradigm is that figuring science and the humanities as “two polar groups” has severe limitations as a point of departure for interdisciplinary endeavors—not to mention that it relegates the general public to a marginal role.<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Snow</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>The Two Cultures</italic>
               </source>, ed.<person-group person-group-type="editor">
                  <string-name>Stefan Collini</string-name>
               </person-group>(:<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>,<year>1998</year>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Even the popular press is privy to this antagonism in literary studies. An article in<italic>The Observer</italic>sums up the sentiment succinctly: “Forget structuralism or even post-structuralist deconstruction. ‘Neuro lit crit’ is where it's at.”<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Paul Harris</string-name>
               </person-group>and<person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Alison Flood</string-name>
               </person-group>,<article-title>“Literary Critics Scan the Brain to Find Out Why We Love to Read”</article-title>(<month>April</month>
               <day>11</day>,<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation publication-type="book">
               <person-group person-group-type="author">
                  <string-name>Joseph Carroll</string-name>
               </person-group>,<source>
                  <italic>Literary Darwinism: Evolution, Human Nature, and Literature</italic>
               </source>(:<publisher-name>Routledge</publisher-name>,<year>2004</year>),<fpage>25</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
