<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">iyyun</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50004970</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Iyyun: The Jerusalem Philosophical Quarterly / עיון: רבעון פילוסופי</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>החברה הפילוסופית בירושלים</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00213306</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23340010</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>BEYOND THE DETERMINISM AND IRRATIONALISM / מעבר לדטרמיניזם ולאירציונליזם (הערות לפילוסופיה של הרצון של פול ריקר)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>פאני</given-names>
                  <surname>אפשטיין</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>F.</given-names>
                  <surname>EPSTEIN</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>1965</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>ט"ז</volume>
         <issue>ד'</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23340007</issue-id>
         <fpage>204</fpage>
         <lpage>212</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/23340010"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The significance of the conception of the "I" as an "integral ego", which is fundamental to Ricoeur's thought, is brought out. The "integral ego" forms the basis of an analysis of the relations between the voluntary and involuntary in human action and enables these relations to be seen and comperehended from a fresh perspective. The "integral ego" is conceived as an organic unity of the "Cartesian cogito" and the existent body. This necessitates a view of the body as a Corps propre in Merleau-Ponty's sense; "a-body-moved-by-the-will", a conscious body, imbued with meaning. The body is on no account to be regarded as a mere physical object related to other physical objects in a mechanical causal chain. There is no place in man for the Cartesian dualism between thinking substance and extended substance. Although Ricoeur's method in analysing these relations is one of pure or "eidetic" description, he, in contradistinction to Husserl, attempts to integrate the body, as a Corps propre, with the cogito. He repeatedly stresses the danger of naturalizing the cogito; of viewing psychic processes as natural facts and the body as an empirical object. The rigorous phenomenological description clarifies the inter-relation and reciprocity between the voluntary and involuntary—whether in human decision, physical action or consent. The voluntary (the project, the moving of the body and consent) is based on and nourished by the involuntary (motives and given values; body, emotions and habits; character, sub-conscious and life). On the other hand, the involuntary has meaning only within the harmonious synthesis of human action. This analysis enables Ricoeur to refute various traditional explanations of human action. Both deterministic and irrationalistic interpretations distort and misinterpret the place and meaning of the components of human action because of an inadequate representation of man's nature. Determinism is wrong in regarding consciousness as a fact of nature and in confusing motives with causes; irrationalism, which advocates a "liberté d'indifférence", basing itself on the same premise as rationalism, and confusing motives with causes, is wrong in seeing the negation of the very existence of motives as the one way of saving human freedom. Both views disregard the fact that human action is impossible and cannot be understood without motives and that this, in turn, does not mean a determination of man in a mechanical way, for motives are not a part of nature but rather an organic element in a specific human situation—voluntary action. Human freedom is the freedom peculiar to a finite being immersed in time. Both those who stress passivity and receptivity and those who stress the dynamic creating ability of the self are wrong; both those who thought that freedom is possible only on the basis of clear and distinct motives and that action is nothing but the end of deliberation (St. Thomas) and those who thought that freedom is possible only by an irrational emergence of the vital ego (Bergson) or by negating the existence of any previous determination of the self (Sartre) are mistaken. A true human decision is composed of two elements; given motives and values on the one hand, and non-intellectualist spontaneous choice on the other. Duality is peculiar to human action. This is made more explicit in dealing with the more fundamental involuntary elements; character, sub-consciousness and life. Man acts freely from a finite and determined point of view; he acts in a clear and transparent way on the basis of confused and amorphous data; he lives his freedom when thrown into life. Necessity is inherent in man; it is one of his modes of being. There is no "inner freedom" on the one hand and "objective" causal necessity on the other. This conception of human action as both activity and passivity is reminiscent of Merleau-Ponty's statement in his "Philosophie du perception": "Le monde est déjá constitué, mais aussi jamais complètement constitué.... Il n'y a donc jamais déterminisme et jamais choix absolu, jamais je ne suis chose et jamais conscience nue". There is no dilemna between determinism and irrationalism, just as there is none between extended substance and thinking substance; there is dialogue.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>heb</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>[הערות שוליים]</title>
         <ref id="d8504e119a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d8504e126" publication-type="other">
Paul Ricoeur—Philosophie de la Volonte (Ie Volontaire et 1'Involontaire), Paris,
Aubier, 1950</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d8504e136a1310">
            <label>־</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d8504e143" publication-type="other">
1945,Maurice Merleau-Ponty, Phenomenologie de la Perception, Paris, Gallimard
תורתו של מרלו־פונטי על מעמדו של הגוף ועל משמעותה של החרות השפיעה ללא ספק
השפעה מכרעת על השקפתו של ריקר. ראה למשל את דבריו על החרות: Le monde est deja
II n'y done jamais constitue mais aussi jamais completement constitue
determinisme et jamais choix absolu, jamais je ne suis chose et jamais conscience
nue". (pp. 517)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
