<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ethics</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Ethics</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00141704</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">1539297X</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">779615</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/324242</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">ET112218</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Book Review</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Georgia</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Warnke</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of California, Riverside</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2002</year>
            <string-date>January 2002</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>112</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>et.2002.112.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>406</fpage>
         <lpage>408</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Ricoeur,</surname>
               <given-names>Paul</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>The Just</source>. Translated by David Pellauer.Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2000. Pp. xxiv+155. $20.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/324242"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>The third of the lectures that compose<italic>The Just</italic>indicates the cultural distance that separates Paul Ricoeur’s reflections on justice from Anglo‐American normative theory. Ricoeur asks, “How do I justify choosing John Rawls’s book for an inquiry into the theory of justice?” (p. 36). A more relevant question for Anglo‐American philosophers would be, How do I justify<italic>not</italic>choosing<italic>A Theory of Justice</italic>for the inquiry? Indeed, Ricoeur’s preface to his lectures begins by regretting what he regards as a neglect of questions of justice, legitimacy, the “juridical arena,” and the constitutional state in favor of a focus on “the drama of war” (p. viii) and “a philosophy of history haunted in turn by the pitiless torment arising from and sustained by the aporia of political evil” (p. ix). While Anglo‐American theorists have been interested in multicultural societies and political conflict, they have usually discussed such issues precisely in the context of the issues Ricoeur thinks are ignored. Yet this distance between French and Anglo‐American approaches gives Ricoeur’s lectures their interest. In essays on Rawls, Michael Walzer, and Ronald Dworkin, among American philosophers, and Hannah Arendt and Luc Boltanski among European theorists, Ricoeur sketches a distinctive position on questions of justice that straddles the liberal/communitarian divide common in the Anglo‐American world.</p>
      <p>The organization of lectures in<italic>The Just</italic>follows Ricoeur’s earlier book,<italic>Oneself as Another</italic>(trans. Kathleen Blamey [Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992]) and reflects the dimensions of what he calls the moral constitution of action. He understands this constitution in terms of a horizontal and vertical axis. The horizontal axis embeds the individual in both face‐to‐face interactions with others and more distanced interactions mediated by institutions. The vertical axis involves different levels of analysis that indicate the place, for Ricoeur, of both teleological and deontological theories of justice as well as of references to practical reason. Moral action has a teleological dimension, he thinks, insofar as it is rooted in the human desire for personal fulfillment and friendship within just institutions. His lectures suggest that it is this dimension that grounds the bonds of political community. But moral action possesses a deontological dimension as well because the impartiality necessary to just institutions requires a procedural account of justice. Finally, moral action involves an element of practical reason in the moment at which the subject must judge and act in one way or another.</p>
      <p>Suppose we begin with the subject who seeks personal fulfillment and meaningful human associations within just institutions. For Ricoeur, this subject is defined by its capacities for language, action, narrative identity, and for ethical and moral evaluation. As a subject I am that who speaks, acts, narrates my life, and evaluates objects and actions as good in ethical evaluation or obligatory in moral evaluation. These capacities all possess a triadic structure: I can designate myself as an “I” or the subject who is speaking only within a structure that includes a “you” to whom I speak and a he/she/it about whom or which we speak. Ricoeur claims that this last relationship represents the institution of language “inasmuch as it encompasses all the speakers of one natural language who know themselves and who are bound together by the recognition of the common rules that distinguish one language from another” (p. 6). Consequently, Ricoeur criticizes social contract liberalism because it presupposes a subject who possesses natural rights prior to the contractual relation. For Ricoeur, the subject of rights emerges only through the political mediation that provides the institutional conditions under which mere capacities can be actualized as accomplishments.</p>
      <p>Emphasis on institutional mediations provides for Ricoeur’s perspective on the issue of moral responsibility. He takes Hegel’s account of<italic>Sittlichkeit</italic>to have sufficiently answered the question that plagues Anglo‐American theorists of whether imputations of responsibility are compatible with universal determinism. What interest him are imputations of responsibility that dispense with agency and fault in part because of the solidarity<italic>Sittlichkeit</italic>involves. There are risks that individuals take for which business enterprises or the political entity to which they belong takes responsibility and attributions of fault that refer to interconnections of consequences for which no one in particular is responsible. How do we balance, then, ideas of individual risk and responsibility against the virtues of solidarity? When are we responsible as individuals and when can we assume the solidarity of others in accepting a collective responsibility?</p>
      <p>While Ricoeur suggests that recourse to solidarity can go too far in answering these questions, an appeal to the conditions of solidarity provides the basis for his criticism of Rawls. As his account of the subject of rights would suggest, and agreeing with many in the Anglo‐American world, Ricoeur denies that a procedural theory of justice can substitute for the bonds of an ethical community or replace a collective conception of the good. At the same time, he sees Rawls’s analysis as a brilliant articulation of the deontological level of the structure of moral action. For Ricoeur, Rawls’s revisions of his theory of justice in his later work mark his own recognition of the connection between the deontological and teleological levels of moral action since he now explicitly grounds the theory of justice in a particular sort of political community.</p>
      <p>Ricoeur turns to Walzer’s work, then, not to move from a Rawlsian liberalism to communitarianism but to look at another question: that of the divisibility of principles of justice within a particular state. Again Ricoeur emphasizes the importance of political community. He thinks Walzer errs in viewing the question of politics solely as a question of the just distribution of political power since, in doing so, he fails to examine the status of the political community within which distributions proceed. Ricoeur acknowledges the attention Walzer pays to questions of membership in a political community. Still, he thinks that what Walzer’s work illuminates is “the uncomfortable situation of an entity called upon to behave at the same time as the whole and as the part, as the container and the contained, as inclusive agency and an included region” (p. 93). Rather than moving to a more communitarian view, then, Ricoeur accepts a modified version of Rawlsian liberalism: Rawls successfully constructs a single set of principles of justice, and we need only recognize that the grounds for this selection lie in our preexisting conception of the good rooted in our aspirations for meaningful lives and friendships within just institutions.</p>
      <p>What about the last dimension of the constitution of moral action, the dimension of practical reason? Ricoeur agrees with Hans‐Georg Gadamer that judgment and interpretation cannot be removed from the application of laws and principles to particular cases. Hence, he also accepts Ronald Dworkin’s argument against legal positivism. Because legal positivism identifies the meaning of a law with its original intent, it is left no recourse in hard cases that seem to be outside the purview of this intent except to appeal to the discretionary power of the judge. In contrast, Ricoeur emphasizes a criterion of validity that looks to the narrative coherence of a legal judgment in view of the history of the legal enterprise. Yet, Ricoeur thinks that Dworkin misses the opportunity to coordinate his “narrativist notion of fit” (p. 114) with a theory of argumentation borrowed from Habermas and the Erlangen School. Just as Rawls’s theory of justice lends formalism to the selection of principles of justice within a community of shared understandings and aspirations, Habermas’s discourse theory lends formalism to Dworkin’s interpretive judgments insofar as interpreters must argue for their interpretations under a set of discourse rules. Indeed, Ricoeur sees the ideal endpoint of a trial as a kind of ideal speech situation in which both winner and loser recognize each other as subjects of rights whose causes should have been heard, who made plausible arguments, and whose arguments were heard (p. 131).</p>
      <p>The necessity of both solidarity and proceduralism thus holds for both distributive and criminal justice. In the end, Ricoeur remains committed to notions that ground the just polity in community and mutual sharing without thinking that these notions require us to dispense with the formalism of procedures of justice. While the latter are not sufficient on their own to create or sustain a just society, while, indeed, formal procedures always presuppose some conception of the good, procedural conceptions allow us to recognize each other as subjects of rights. Although it is not always clear that Ricoeur succeeds in reconciling Rawls and Walzer or Habermas and Gadamer, he does provide a fresh perspective on current debates within his own interesting account of the structure of moral action.</p>
   </body>
</article>
