<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">polisocirevi</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50003148</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Polish Sociological Review</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The Polish Sociological Association</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">12311413</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">41969498</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>On the Potential of Norbert Elias's Approach in the Social Memory Research in Central and Eastern Europe</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>MARTA</given-names>
                  <surname>BUCHOLC</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <issue>183</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40092224</issue-id>
         <fpage>317</fpage>
         <lpage>334</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © The Polish Sociological Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/41969498"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Norbert Elias never presented his views regarding collective memory in a systematic manner. However, his approach may be reconstructed on the basis of such works as The Civilizing Process, Time: An Essay and The Symbol Theory. The most important tenet of Elias is that human memory can only be explained by the symbol theory. Human ability to use socially created symbols in communication is applied in activities in which symbols are used (speaking, thinking, knowing and remembering), which makes memory a part of general process of symbolic communication. Memory research needs to account for the interactive and communicational origins of both individual and collective remembering. One of the crucial issues related to remembering is collective forgetting. According to Elias it operates by three main mechanisms: (1) elimination and creation of fantastic notions (fantasy being a substitute and subsidiary for experience), (2) modification of social canons of reference as a result of power struggle in social figurations, and (3) delegitimization of alternative imageries by means of marginalization or elimination of groups acting as their social vehicles. I discuss these mechanisms and the dynamics of memory they entail in the broader conceptual framework of the theory of civilizing processes referring to Central and Eastern European examples in order to demonstrate the productivity of Elias's interdisciplinary and multidimensional analysis in social memory studies focusing this region.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d11625e114a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d11625e121" publication-type="other">
Jakoubek, Svoboda, Budilova 2009.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d11625e137a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e141" publication-type="other">
Arditi, Jorge; Swidler, Ann. 1994. The New Sociology of Knowledge, Annual Review of Sociology
vol. 20.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e151a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e155" publication-type="other">
Assman, Jan. 2006. Religion and Cultural Memory: Ten Studies, trans. R. Livingstone. Stanford, CA:
Stanford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e165a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e169" publication-type="other">
Assman, Jan. 2008. Pamięć kulturowa. Pismo, zapamiętywanie i tozsamość polityczna w cywilizacjach
starozytnych, trans. A. Kryczyńska-Pham, Warszawa: Wydawnictwa UW.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e179a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e183" publication-type="other">
Bal, Mieke. 2002. Travelling Concepts in the Humanities: a Rough Guide. Toronto: University of Toronto
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e194a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e198" publication-type="other">
Barnes, Barry. 1977. Interests and the Growth of Knowledge. London, Boston: Routledge and Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e205a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e209" publication-type="other">
Beck, Ulrich; Giddens, Anthony; Lash, Scott. 1994. Reflexive Modernization. Politics, Tradition and
Aesthetics in the Modern Social Order. Cambridge: Polity.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e219a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e223" publication-type="other">
Borbely, Carmen Veronica. 2011. Tropes of Oblivion: The Ethics of Forgetting in the Contemporary
British Novel, Studia Universitatis BabesBolyai Philologia 2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e233a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e237" publication-type="other">
Bloor, David. 1991. Knowledge and Social Imagery. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e244a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e248" publication-type="other">
Bloor, David. 1997. Remember the Strong Program? Science, Technology, &amp; Human Values 3 (22) (Sum-
mer).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e258a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e262" publication-type="other">
Connerton, Paul. 2009. How Modernity Forgets? Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e274" publication-type="other">
Van Dülmen, Richard. 1996. Norbert Elias und der Prozess der Zivilisation. Die Zivilisationstheone
im Lichte der historischer Forschung, in: Norbert Elias und die Menschenwissenschaften. Studien zur
Entstehung und Wirkungsgeschichte seines Werkes, ed. Karl-Siegbert Rehber. Frankfurt am Main:
Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e290a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e294" publication-type="other">
Durkheim, Emile. (1895) 1982. The Rules of the Sociological Method, trans. W. D. Halls. New York: Free
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e304a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e308" publication-type="other">
Elias, Norbert. (1939) 1997. Über den Prozeß der Zivilisation. Soziogenetische und psychogenetische Unter-
suchungen. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp, vol. 1.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e318a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e322" publication-type="other">
Elias, Norbert. (1939) 1997a. Über den Prozeβ der Zivilisation. Soziogenetische und psychogenetische Un-
tersuchungen, Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp, vol. 2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e332a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e336" publication-type="other">
Elias Norbert. 1987. Involvement and Detachment. Contributions to the Sociology of Knowledge. Oxford:
Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e346a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e350" publication-type="other">
Elias, Norbert. 1991. The Symbol Theory. London: Sage.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e358a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e362" publication-type="other">
Elias, Norbert. 1991a. Mozart. Zur Soziologie eines Genies, Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e369a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e373" publication-type="other">
Elias, Norbert. 1994. Time: An Essay. Oxford: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e380a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e384" publication-type="other">
Elias, Norbert. 2001. Symboltheorie, trans. Reiner Ansen. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e391a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e395" publication-type="other">
Elias, Norbert, Scotson, John L. 1965. The Established and the Outsiders. A Sociological Enquiry into
Community Problems. London: Frank Cass &amp; Co.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e405a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e409" publication-type="other">
Heinich, Nathalie. 2010. La sociologie du Norbert Elias. Paris: La Decouverte.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e416a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e420" publication-type="other">
Jakoubek, Marek; Svoboda, Michal; Budilova, Lenka. 2009. One Past, Two Histories: Collective
Memory on the Czech Settlement of the Bulgarian Village of Belinci, Balkanistic Forum 123.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e431a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e435" publication-type="other">
Karstedt, Susanne. 2009. The Life Course of Collective Memories: Persistency and Change in West
Germany between 1950 and 1970, Polish Sociological Review 1 (165).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e445a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e449" publication-type="other">
Kiliánová, Gabriela. 2002. Lieux de Memoire and Collective Identities in Central Europe: The Case of
Devín, Human Affairs 2: 153-165.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e459a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e463" publication-type="other">
Kilminster, Richard. 1993. Norbert Elias and Karl Mannheim: Closeness and Distance, Theory, Culture
&amp; Society 10-3.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e473a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e477" publication-type="other">
Kilminster, Richard. 2007. Norbert Elias. Post-Philosophical Sociology. London and New York: Rout-
ledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e487a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e491" publication-type="other">
Korek, Janusz (ed.). 2007. From Sovietology to Postcoloniality. Poland and Ukraine in the Postcolonial
Perspective. Stockholm: Södertörn Academic Studies.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e501a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e505" publication-type="other">
Kowalska, Wioletta Malgorzata. 2008. Is Policy of Memory Possible and How?, LIMES: Cultural Re-
gionalistics 1/2008.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e516a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e520" publication-type="other">
Krieken, Robert van. 1998. Norbert Elias. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e527a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e531" publication-type="other">
Kripke, Saul. 1982. Wittgenstein on Rules and Private Language: an Elementary Expositio. Cambridge,
Mass.: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e541a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e545" publication-type="other">
Krzemiński, Ireneusz; Raciborski, Jacek (eds.). 2007. Oswajanie wielkiej zmiany Instytut Socjologii
UW o polskiej transformacji [Taming of the Great Change]. Warszawa: IFiS PAN.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e555a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e559" publication-type="other">
Magris Claudio. 2001. Danube: A Sentimental Journey from the Source to the Black See, trans. Patrick
Creagh. London: Harvill Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e569a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e573" publication-type="other">
Magris, Claudio. 2009. Itaka i dalej [Ithaca and Beyond], transl, into Polish by Joanna Ugniewska. Sejny:
Pogranicze.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e583a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e587" publication-type="other">
Mannheim, Karl. [1929] 1955. Ideology and Utopia, trans. L. Wirth, E. Shils. New York: Harvest.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e595a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e599" publication-type="other">
Mark, James. 2010. The Unfinished Revolution: Making Sense of the Communist Past in Central-Eastern
Europe. London and New Haven: Yale University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e609a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e613" publication-type="other">
Mennell, Stephen. 1989. Norbert Elias. Civilization and the Human Self-image. Oxford: Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e620a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e624" publication-type="other">
Mink, Georges. 2008. Between Reconciliation and the Reactivation of Past Conflicts in Europe: Rethink-
ing Social Memory Paradigms, Czech Sociological Review 03.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e634a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e638" publication-type="other">
Misztal, Barbara A. 2005. Memory and the Construction of Temporality, Meaning and Attachment,
Polish Sociological Review 1 (149).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e648a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e652" publication-type="other">
Merz-Benz, Peter-Ulrich. 1996. Verstrickt in Geschichte. Norbert Elias in seiner Breslauer Zeit, in:
Karl-Siegbert Rehberg (ed.), Norbert Elias und die Menschenwissenschaften. Studien zur Entstehung
und Wirkungsgeschichte seines Werkes. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e665a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e669" publication-type="other">
Mongardini, Carlo. 1996. Georg Simmel, Norbert Elias Und die Aufgaben einer soziologischen Neuori-
entierung, in: Karl-Siegbert Rehberg (ed.), Norbert Elias und die Menschenwissenschaften. Studien
zur Entstehung und Wirkungsgeschichte seines Werkes. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e683a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e687" publication-type="other">
Olick, Jeffrey K.; Levy, Daniel. 1997. Collective Memory and Cultural Constraint: Holocaust Myth and
Rationality in German Politics, American Sociological Review.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e697a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e701" publication-type="other">
Olick, Jeffrey K.; Robbins, Joyce. 1998. Social Memory Studies: From 'Collective Memory' to the
Historical Sociology of Mnemonic Practices, Annual Review of Sociology.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e711a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e715" publication-type="other">
Olick, Jeffrey K. 1999. Collective Memory: The Two Cultures, Sociological Theory 3(17).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e722a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e726" publication-type="other">
Olick, Jeffrey K. 1999a. Review of The Norbert Elias Reader' by Johan Goudsblom and Stephen Mennell;
Norbert Elias: On Civilization, Power, and Knowledge: Selected Writings by Stephen Mennell;
Johan Goudsblom, Contemporary Sociology 1 (28).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e739a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e743" publication-type="other">
Olic k, Jeffrey K. 2007. The Politics of Regret: On Collective Memory and Historical Responsibility. New
York: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e753a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e757" publication-type="other">
Quilley, Stephen; Loyal, Steven. 2004. Towards a 'Central Theory': the Scope and Relevance of the
Sociology of Norbert Elias, in: Steven Loyal, Stephen Quilley (eds.), The Sociology of Norbert Elias.
Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e771a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e775" publication-type="other">
Rehberg, Karl-Siegbert (ed.). 1996. Norbert Elias und die Menschenwissenschaften. Studien zur Entstehung
und Wirkungsgeschichte seines Werkes. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e785a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e789" publication-type="other">
Riabczuk, Mykola. 2002. Od Malorosji do Ukrainy, transi, into Polish O. Hnatiuk, K. Kotyńska. Kraków.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e796a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e800" publication-type="other">
Riabczuk, Mykola. 2003. Dwie Ukrainy, transl, into Polish M. Dyhas, K. Kotyñska, and Werestiuk,
W. Witwicki. Kraków.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e810a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e814" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, Paul. 2000. La mémoire, l'histoire, l'oubli. Paris: Seuil.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e821a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e825" publication-type="other">
Salumets, Thomas (ed.). 2001. Norbert Elias and Human Interdependencies. Montreal: McGill-Queen's
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e835a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e839" publication-type="other">
Simmel, Georg. 1906. The Sociology of Secrecy and of Secret Societies, American Journal of Sociol-
ogy 11 (4).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e850a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e854" publication-type="other">
Snyder, Timothy. 2010. Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin. New York: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e861a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e865" publication-type="other">
Spiewak, Pawel. 2005. Pamięć po komunizmie [The Memory of Communism]. Warszawa: Slowo/obraz
terytoria.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e875a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e879" publication-type="other">
Szacka, Barbara. 2006. "Solidarity" and the Martial Law in the Collective Memory of Polish History,
Polish Sociological Review 1 (153).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e889a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e895" publication-type="other">
Szacka, Barbara; Kwiatkowski, Piotr T.; Nijakowski, Lech M.; Szpociński, Andrzej. 2010.
Między codziennošcią a wielką historią. Druga wojna światowa w pamięci zbiorowej spoleczeństwa
polskiego [Between Everyday Life and a Great history. The Second World War in the Collective
Memory of the Polish Society]. Warszawa: Scholar.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e911a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e915" publication-type="other">
Szacki, Jerzy. 1991. Dylematy historiografii idei oraz inné szkice i studia. Warszawa: PWN.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e922a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e926" publication-type="other">
Tănăsoiu, Cosmina. 2005. PostCommunist Political Symbolism: New Myths—Same Old Stories? An
Analysis of Romanian Political Mythology, Romanian Journal of Political Sciences 01.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e937a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e941" publication-type="other">
Theben/Dévény Castle, Human Affairs 2.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e948a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e952" publication-type="other">
Tismaneanu, Valdimir. 2009. The Revolutions of 1989: Causes, Meanings, Legacies, Journal of Con-
temporary European History 18:3 (Spring).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d11625e962a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d11625e966" publication-type="other">
Wittgenstein, Ludwig. 1953. Philosophical Investigations. New York: Macmillan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
