<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">revidemusi</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000994</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Revista de Musicología</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>SOCIEDAD ESPAÑOLA DE MUSICOLOGÍA</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">02101459</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/24246266</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>COMUNIDADES REALES, TRADICIONES NO INVENTADAS: LA DETRACCIÓN DEL FOLKLORE (MUSICAL) EN LA ERA DE LA DECONSTRUCCIÓN</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Javier CAMPOS</given-names>
                  <surname>CALVO-SOTELO</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2012</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">35</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24243488</issue-id>
         <fpage>297</fpage>
         <lpage>333</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24246266"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Son ya varias las décodas transcurridas desde que los estudios de folklore en general y la etnomusicología en particular se han visto dominados por la analitica deconstructiva y el pensamiento culturalista, configurando un bloque paradigmático sumamente influyente en el multidisciplinar territorio de las ciencias sociales. Las aportaciones provenientes de estas corrientes han resultado en líneas generates de gran valor e interés para la comunidad científica, ensanchando y dinamizando el hasta entonces relativamente reducido campo de acción e interpretación de disciplinas como la musicología comparada. Sin embargo el proceso de renovación académica –que encabezarían obras como las de Benedict Anderson y Eric Hobsbawm– ha implicado asimismo un desigual desplazamiento del foco de atención desde el objeto de estudio mismo hacia la esfera de su contexto, relevancia social e implicaciones ideológicas. La deconstrucción se ha ejercido particularmente en contra del aserto diferencial, subrayando sus debilidades argumentales, excesos etnocéntricos y –con frecuencia– obvios intereses espurios, una tarea históricamente necesaria pero que a la par ha sustraído del folklore todo valor ontológico en aras de su significado, y del trabajo científico el vital soporte empírico, que ahora se ve arrinconado por una elaboración altamente abstracta al amparo de un lenguaje en el límite de la saturación semántica. Este artículo explora la vía crítica descrita para concluir planteando determinadas alternativas en defensa de una tradición sostenible –a pesar del vigor innegable y sinergético de las fuerzas del progreso, los procesos de hibridación y globalización y las alteraciones provenientes del constructo folklorista–, así como del hecho diferencial implícito y su asunción y gestión no indefectiblemente en el marco de un proyecto político o comercial. Studies of folklore in general and ethnomusicology in particular have been dominated by deconstructive analysis and culturalist theory for several decades, forming a highly influential paradigm in the multidisciplinary area of the social sciences. In general terms, the contributions originating from these currents of thought have turned out to be of great value and interest for the scientific community, widening and dynamizing the until then relatively small field of action and interpretation of disciplines such as comparative musicology. However, the process of academic renewal –which was led by works such as those of Benedict Anderson and Eric Hobsbawm– has also implied an excessive shift in the focus of attention away from the object of study itself towards its context, social importance and ideological implications. Deconstruction has particularly been used against differential assertion, emphasizing its argumentative weaknesses, ethnocentric excesses and (frequently) its obvious spurious interests, a historically necessary task, but which at the same time has stripped folklore of all of its ontological quality for the sake of its significance, and scientific work of its vital empirical base, which is replaced by a highly abstract elaboration with the help of a language on the verge of semantic saturation. This article explores the critical path described above, and concludes by posing certain alternatives defending a sustainable tradition –in spite of the undeniable and synergetic forces of progress, the processes of hybridization and globalization and the alterations stemming from the folkloristic construct–, as well as the implicit differential fact and its assumption and management, not necessarily in the framework of a political or commercial project.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>spa</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d417727e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e114" publication-type="other">
Enescu, George. «Enescu despre Muzica Româneasc». Muzica, 1921, p. 115.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e120" publication-type="other">
Bartók, Béla. Escritos sobre Mùsica Popular. México, Siglo XXI Editores, 1987, p. 146.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e127a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e134" publication-type="other">
Anderson, Benedict. Comunidades Imaginadas. Reflexiones sobre el Origen y la Difusión del
Nacionalismo. México, Fondo de Cultura Econòmica, 1993 [1983].</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e144a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e151" publication-type="other">
La Invention de la Tradition. Eric Hobsbawm, Terence Ranger (eds.). Barcelona, Critica,
2002 [1983],</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e161a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e168" publication-type="other">
ClNNAMOND, Jeffrey. «Replicating Rhoades: Deconstructing a Deconstructionist». The Journal
of Higher Education, 62, 6 (1991), p. 695.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e179a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e186" publication-type="other">
DERRIDA, Jacques. Margins of Philosophy. Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1982, pp.
320-321.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e196a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e203" publication-type="other">
Contemporary Spanish Cultural Studies. Barry Jordan, Rikki Morgan-Tamosunas (eds.). Nueva
York, Arnold, 2000, p. 4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e213a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e220" publication-type="other">
SOKAL, Alan. «Transgressing the Boundaries: Toward a Transformative Hermeneutics of
Quantum Gravity». Social Text, 46/47 (1996), pp. 217-252.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e230a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e239" publication-type="other">
Jean Bricmont, publicarla Impostures intellectuelles (Paris, Odile Jacob, 1997)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e245" publication-type="other">
Sokal y Bricmont 1997</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e252" publication-type="other">
«Sokal et Bricmont ne sont pas sérieux». Le Monde, 20
de noviembre de 1997, p. 17</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e262a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e269" publication-type="other">
FELPERIN, Howard. «The Anxiety of Deconstruction». Yale French Studies, 69 (1985), p. 254.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e275" publication-type="other">
Litvak, Joseph. «Back to the Future: A Review-Article on the New
Historicism, Deconstruction, and Nineteenth-Century Fiction». Texas Studies in Literature and
Language, 30, 1 (1988), pp. 120-149.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e288a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e295" publication-type="other">
FELPERIN, H. «The Anxiety...», p. 256.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e303a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e310" publication-type="other">
Brubaker, Rogers. Ethnicity Without Groups. Cambridge (MA) y Londres, Harvard Uni-
versity Press, 2004, p. 3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e320a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e327" publication-type="other">
Burke, Peter. iQué es la Historia Cultural? Barcelona, Paidós, 2006, p. 140.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e334a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e341" publication-type="other">
Brunet, Roger. «Anâlisis de Paisajes y Semiologia». El Pensamiento Geogràfico. Estudio
Interpretativo y Antologia de Textos (de Humboldt a las Tendencias Radicales). Josefina Gómez Men-
doza, Julio Munoz Jimenez, Nicolas Ortega Cantero (eds.). Madrid, Alianza Universidad, 1982
[1974], p. 486.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e357a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e364" publication-type="other">
LlSÓN TOLOSANA, Carmelo. «Prius Vita quam Doctrina». Europaea, 2, 2 (1996). http://
www.h-net.org/~sae/europea/1996ii2.html. [Consulta: 22 de mayo de 2009],</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e374a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e381" publication-type="other">
Ibid.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e388a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e395" publication-type="other">
popper, Karl. En Busca de un Mundo Mejor. Barcelona, Paidós, 1994 [1984], p. 20.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e403a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e410" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 114</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e417a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e424" publication-type="other">
WlTZLEBEN, J. Lawrence. «Whose Ethnomusicology? Western Ethnomusicology and the
Study of Asian Music». Ethnomusicology, 41, 2: Issues in Ethnomusicology, (1997), pp. 220-242.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e434a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e443" publication-type="other">
Dundes, Alan. «Folkloristics in the Twenty-First Century». Journal of American Folklore, 118,470,
(2005), p. 392</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e452" publication-type="other">
«Whose Ethnomusicology?...», p. 227</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e459" publication-type="other">
Véanse los trabajos de Denora [«The concerto and society». The Cambridge Companion to the
Concerto. Simon P. Keefe (ed.). Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2005], White [«Review
of Matthew Gelbart: The Invention of'Folk Music' and 'Art Music'. Emerging Categories from Ossian
to Wagner». Journal of the Society for Musicology in Ireland, 4 (2008-09), pp. 75-77]</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e474" publication-type="other">
Kivy [Nuevos
Ensayos sobre la Comprensión Musical. Barcelona, Paidós Iberica, 2005, especialmente pp. 223-230]</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e483" publication-type="other">
McClary [«The Blasphemy of Talking Politics during Bach Year». Music and Society: The Politics
of Composition, Performance and Reception. Susan McClary, Richard Leppert (eds.). Cambridge,
Cambridge University Press, 1987]</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e496a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e503" publication-type="other">
FERGUSON, Marjorie, Golding, Peter. «Cultural Studies and Changing Times: An Intro-
duction». Cultural Studies in Question. Marjorie Ferguson, Peter Golding (eds.). Londres, Sage
Publications, 1997, p. XIV.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e516a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e523" publication-type="other">
McClary, Susan. «Same as it Ever Was: Youth Culture and Music». Microphone Fiends: Youth
Music and Youth Culture. Andrew Ross, Tricia Rose (eds.). Nueva York, Routledge, 1994, p. 38.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e533a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e540" publication-type="other">
Middleton, Richard. «Introduction: Music Studies and the Idea of Culture». The Cultural
Study of Music: A Critical Introduction. Martin Clayton, Trevor Herbert, Richard Middleton (eds.).
Nueva York y Londres, Routledge, 2003, p. 2.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e554a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e561" publication-type="other">
Marx, Karl. Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy. Pekin, Foreign Language Press,
1976 [1859], p. 3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e571a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e578" publication-type="other">
Balliger, Robin. «Politics». Key Terms in Papular Music and Culture. Bruce Horner, Thomas
Swiss (eds.). Cresskill, Hampton Press, 1998, p. 60.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e588a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e595" publication-type="other">
LÉVI-STRAUSS, Claude. Mito y Significado. Madrid, Alianza Editorial, 1987
[1978], p. 89</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e605a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e612" publication-type="other">
BERGER, Peter L, LUCKMANN, Thomas. La Construcciôn Social de la Realidad. Buenos Aires,
Amorrortu editores, 1972 [1966].</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e622a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e629" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 13.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e636a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e643" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 69.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e651a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e658" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 216.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e665a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e672" publication-type="other">
Geertz, Clifford. La Interpretation de las Culturas. Barcelona, Gedisa, 2000 [1973], p. 20.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e679a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e686" publication-type="other">
Redfield, Marc. «Imagi-Nation: The Imagined Community and the Aesthetics of Mourn-
ing». Diacritics, 29, 4 (1999), p. 60.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e696a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e703" publication-type="other">
BAHTI, Timothy. «Anacoluthon: On Cultural Studies». MLN, 112, 3 (1997), p. 366.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e710a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e717" publication-type="other">
Gitlin, Todd. «The Anti-political Populism of Cultural Studies». Cultural Studies in Ques-
tion. Marjorie Ferguson, Peter Golding (eds.). Londres, Sage Publications, 1997, p. 25.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e727a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e734" publication-type="other">
DUNDES, A. «Folkloristics in the Twenty-First Century...», p. 385.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e742a1310">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e749" publication-type="other">
WILLIAMS, Raymond. Problems in Materialism and Culture. Selected Essays. Londres, Verso,
1980, p. 48.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e759a1310">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e766" publication-type="other">
Ferguson, M., Golding, P. «Cultural Studies and Changing Times...», pp. XXI-XXIV.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e773a1310">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e780" publication-type="other">
ZUELOW, Eric G. E. «Review of Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of
Nationalism, by Benedict Anderson», http:/ / www.nationalismproject.org/books/a_b htm#Anchor-
Anderson-23526. [Consulta: 22 de octubre de 2006].</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e793a1310">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e800" publication-type="other">
BENDIX, Regina. «National Sentiment in the Enactment and Discourse of Swiss Political
Ritual». American Ethnologist, 19, 4 (1992), p. 768.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e810a1310">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e817" publication-type="other">
CULLER, Jonathan. «Anderson and the Novel». Diacritics, 29, 4 (1999), p. 20.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e824a1310">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e831" publication-type="other">
CHATTERJEE, Partha. «Anderson's Utopia». Diacritics, 29, 4 (1999), p. 128.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e839a1310">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e846" publication-type="other">
Redfield, M. «Imagi-Nation...», p. 60.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e853a1310">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e860" publication-type="other">
Anderson, B. Comunidades Imaginadas..., p. 21.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e867a1310">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e874" publication-type="other">
Nairn, Tom. «Nationalism: The Modem Janus». New Left Review, I, 94 (1975), pp. 3-29.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e881a1310">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e888" publication-type="other">
HOBSBAWM, Eric. «Some Reflections on 'The Break-up of Britain'». New Left Review, 1,105
(1977), pp. 1-14.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e898a1310">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e905" publication-type="other">
ANDERSON, B. Comutiidades Imaginadas..., p. 23.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e912a1310">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e919" publication-type="other">
CONNOR, Walker. Etnonacionalismo. Madrid, Trama, 1998, p. 101.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e927a1310">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e934" publication-type="other">
Abrahams, Roger D. «Phantoms of Romantic Nationalism in Folkloristics». Journal of
American Folklore, 106, 419 (1993), p. 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e944a1310">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e951" publication-type="other">
Dietler, Michael. «"Our Ancestors the Gauls": Archaeology, Ethnic Nationalism, and the
Manipulation of Celtic Identity in Modern Europe». American Anthropologist, 96,3 (1994), p. 584.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e961a1310">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e968" publication-type="other">
Axelrod, Robert. «The Dissemination of Culture: A Model with Local Convergence and
Global Polarization». The Journal of Conflict Resolution, 41, 2 (1997), p. 204.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e978a1310">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e985" publication-type="other">
Feintuch, Burt. «Tradition». The Dictionary of Anthropology. Thomas Barfield (ed.). Oxford,
Blackwell Publishing, 1997, p. 470.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e995a1310">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1002" publication-type="other">
Brubaker, R. Ethnicity Without Groups..., p. 79.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1009a1310">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1016" publication-type="other">
Bendix, R. «National Sentiment...», p. 768.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1024a1310">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1031" publication-type="other">
Parker, Andrew. «Bogeyman: Benedict Anderson's "Derivative" Discourse». Diacritics,
29, 4 (1999), p. 40.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1041a1310">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1048" publication-type="other">
Motyl, Alexander J. «Imagined Communities, Rational Choosers, Invented Ethnies. Review
of The Spectre of Comparisons: Nationalism, Southeast Asia, and the World, by Benedict Anderson;
Identity in Formation: The Russian-Speaking Populations in the Near Abroad, by David D. Laitin and
Nationalism and Modernism: A Critical Survey of Recent Theories of Nations and Nation, by Anthony
D. Smith». Comparative Politics, 34, 2 (2002), p. 234.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1067a1310">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1074" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 235.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1081a1310">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1088" publication-type="other">
Anderson, B. Comunidades Imaginadas..., p. 35.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1095a1310">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1102" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 30.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1109a1310">
            <label>83</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1116" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 267.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1124a1310">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1131" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 29.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1138a1310">
            <label>65</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1145" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 33.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1152a1310">
            <label>66</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1159" publication-type="other">
Hobsbawm, Eric. «Introduction: La Invention de la Tradition». La Invention de la Tradition.
Eric Hobsbawm, Terence Ranger (eds.). Barcelona, Critica, 2002 [1983], p. 19.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1169a1310">
            <label>67</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1176" publication-type="other">
Cohen, Judah. «Musical Institutions and the Transmission of Tradition». Ethnomusicology,
53, 2 (2009), p. 322.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1186a1310">
            <label>68</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1193" publication-type="other">
Handler, Richard; Linnekin, Jocelyn. «Tradition, Genuine and Spurious». Journal of Ameri-
can Folklore, 97, 385 (1984), p. 273.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1203a1310">
            <label>69</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1210" publication-type="other">
RONSTROm, Owe. «Making Use of History; The Revival of the Bagpipe in Sweden in the
1980s». Yearbook for Traditional Music, 21 (1989), p. 95.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1221a1310">
            <label>70</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1228" publication-type="other">
CANTWELL, Robert. When We Were Good; The Folk Revival. Cambridge, Harvard Uni-
versity Press, 1996, p. 38.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1238a1310">
            <label>71</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1245" publication-type="other">
Ibid, p. 54.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1252a1310">
            <label>72</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1259" publication-type="other">
MOORE, Allan. «Authenticity as Authentication». Popular Music, 21, 2 (2002), p. 210.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1266a1310">
            <label>73</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1273" publication-type="other">
MATTAR, Yasser. «Popular Cultural Cringe; Language as a Signifier of Authenticity and
Quality in the Singaporean Popular Music Market». Popular Music, 28, 2 (2008), p. 181.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1283a1310">
            <label>74</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1290" publication-type="other">
Mechling, Jay. «Solo Folklore». Western Folklore, 65, 4 (2006), p. 449.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1297a1310">
            <label>75</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1304" publication-type="other">
Kivy, P. Nuevos Ensayos..., p. 129.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1312a1310">
            <label>76</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1319" publication-type="other">
Ibid, p. 148.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1326a1310">
            <label>77</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1333" publication-type="other">
Burke, P. iQué es la Historia Cultural?..., p. 102.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1340a1310">
            <label>78</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1347" publication-type="other">
Ibid.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1354a1310">
            <label>79</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1361" publication-type="other">
HOBSBAWM, E. «Introduction...», p. 8.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1368a1310">
            <label>80</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1375" publication-type="other">
Abrahams, Roger D. «Personal Power and Social Restraint in the Definition of Folklore».
Towards New Perspectives in Folklore. Américo Paredes, Richard Bauman (eds.). Austin, University
of Texas Press, 1972, p. 16.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1387" publication-type="other">
Ben-Amos, Dan. «The seven stands of tradition. Varieties in its
meaning in american folklore studies». Journal of Folklore Research, 21, 2/3 (1984), p. 97</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1397a1310">
            <label>81</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1404" publication-type="other">
ROSENBERG, Neil. «Revivalism». American Folklore: An Encyclopedia. Jan Harold Brunvand
(éd.). Nueva York y Londres, Garland Publishing, 1996, p. 623.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1415a1310">
            <label>82</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1422" publication-type="other">
Dean-Smith, Margaret. «The Pre-Disposition to Folkery». Folklore, 79 (1968), pp. 161-175.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1429a1310">
            <label>83</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1436" publication-type="other">
DORSON, Richard M. «Fakelore». Zeitschrijt fiir Volkskunde, 65 (1969), pp. 56-64.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1443a1310">
            <label>84</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1450" publication-type="other">
Hirsch, Jerrold. «Folklore in the Making: B. A. Botkin». Journal of American Folklore, 100,
395 (1987), pp. 3-38.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1460a1310">
            <label>85</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1467" publication-type="other">
BENDIX, Regina. «Folklorism: The Challenge of a Concept». International Folklore Review,
6 (1988), pp. 5-14.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1477a1310">
            <label>86</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1484" publication-type="other">
Lau, Frederick. «The Invention of Solo dizi Music in Post-1949 China». British Journal of
Ethnomusicology, 5 (1996), p. 115.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1494a1310">
            <label>87</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1501" publication-type="other">
STOKES, Martin. «Introduction: Ethnicity, Identity and Music». Ethnicity, Identity and Music:
The Musical Construction of Place. Martin Stokes (ed.). Oxford y Nueva York, Berg Publishers,
1997, p. 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1515a1310">
            <label>88</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1522" publication-type="other">
HORNER, Bruce. «Discourse». Key Terms in Popular Music and Culture. Bruce Horner, Thomas
Swiss (eds.). Cresskill, Hampton Press, 1998, p. 18.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1532a1310">
            <label>89</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1539" publication-type="other">
SHEPHERD, John. «Text». Key Terms in Popular Music and Culture. Bruce Horner, Thomas
Swiss (eds.). Cresskill, Hampton Press, 1998, p. 157.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1549a1310">
            <label>90</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1556" publication-type="other">
Small, Christopher. Musicking. Hanover, Wesleyan University Press, 1988, p. 3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1563a1310">
            <label>91</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1570" publication-type="other">
KRAMER, Lawrence. Classical Music and Postmodern Knowledge. Berkeley y Los Angeles,
University of California Press, 1996, p. 17.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1580a1310">
            <label>92</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1587" publication-type="other">
Becker, Judith. «Perspectives on Music and Emotion». Music and Emotion: Theory and
Research. Patrik Juslin, John Sloboda (eds.). Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2001, p. 151.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1597a1310">
            <label>93</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1606" publication-type="other">
BOHLMAN, Philip V. «Becoming Ethnomusicologists: On Cultural Translation». SEM News-
letter, 41, 2 (2007), p. 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1617a1310">
            <label>94</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1624" publication-type="other">
Musique en Jeu, 17,1975, pp. 37-62</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1630" publication-type="other">
Nattiez
en 1987 su Musicologie Générale et Sémiologie (Paris, Christian Bourgois, 1987)</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1640a1310">
            <label>95</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1647" publication-type="other">
Ben-AMOS, Dan. «Toward a Definition of Folklore in Context». Towards New Perspectives in
Folklore. Americo Paredes, Richard Bawman (eds.). Austin, University of Texas Press, 1972,, p. 15.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1657a1310">
            <label>96</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1664" publication-type="other">
Se trata del capltulo 7 («The Invention of Folklore, or the Nostalgia of Origins», pp. 47-
52) de su volumen The Music of the Other: New Challenges for Ethnomusicology in a Global Age.
Aldershot, Ashgate Publishing, 2007.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1677a1310">
            <label>97</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1684" publication-type="other">
Hobsbawm («Introducción...», p. 19).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1690" publication-type="other">
Kirshenblatt-
Gimblett [«Folklore's Crisis». Journal of American Folklore, 111, 441 (1998), p. 283].</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1700a1310">
            <label>98</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1707" publication-type="other">
BOISSEVAIN, Jeremy. «Notas sobre
la renovación. De las celebraciones publicas populares europeas». Arxius de Sociologia, 3 (1999),
pp. 53-67</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1719" publication-type="other">
«Coping with Mass Cultural Tourism: Structure and Strategies». Gazeto Internacia de
Antropologio, 1,1 (2006), pp. 2-13</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1728" publication-type="other">
CRESPI-
VALLBONA, Montserrat, Richards, Greg. «The Meaning of Cultural Festivals. Stakeholder Per-
spectives in Catalunya». International Journal of Cultural Policy, 13, 1 (2007), pp. 103-122</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1741a1310">
            <label>99</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1748" publication-type="other">
Ben-Amos, Dan. «The Seven Strands of Tradition. Varieties in its Meaning in American
Folklore Studies». Journal of Folklore Research, 21, 2-3 (1984), p. 124.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1759a1310">
            <label>100</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1766" publication-type="other">
McDonald, Barry. «The Idea of Tradition Examined in the Light of Two Australian Musi-
cal Studies». Yearbook for Traditional Music, 28 (1996), p. 119.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1776a1310">
            <label>101</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1783" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 121.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1790a1310">
            <label>102</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1797" publication-type="other">
McDonald, Barry. «Tradition as Personal Relationship». Journal of American Folklore, 110,
435 (1997), p. 49.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1807a1310">
            <label>103</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1814" publication-type="other">
SWEERS, Britta. Electric Folk: The Changing Face of English Traditional Music. Nueva York,
Oxford University Press, 2005.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1824a1310">
            <label>104</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1831" publication-type="other">
Neff, Eoghan. «Review of Electric Folk: The Changing Face of English Traditional Music, by
Britta Sweers». Ethnomusicology, 53, 2 (2009), p. 327.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1841a1310">
            <label>105</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1848" publication-type="other">
Calvo-Sotelo, Javier. La Musica Popular Gallega en los Afios de la Transición Polìtica (1975-
1982): Reificaciones Expresivas del Paradigma Identitaria [Tesis doctoral], Madrid, Universidad Com-
plutense de Madrid, 2009. Publicada corno recurso electrónico: http://eprints.ucm.es/8801/</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1860" publication-type="other">
CAMPOS Calvo-
Sotelo, Javier. Fiesta, Identidad y Contracultura. Contribuciones al Estudio Histórico de la Gaita en
Galicia. Pontevedra, Diputación Provincial de Pontevedra, 2007</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1874a1310">
            <label>106</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1881" publication-type="other">
Vozes do Povo: A Folclorizaçào em Portugal. Salwa El-Shawan Castelo-Branco, Jorge Freitas Branco
(eds.). Lisboa, Celta Editora, 2003.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1891a1310">
            <label>m</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1898" publication-type="other">
Pettitt, Tom. «From Journalism to Gypsy Folk Song: The Road to Orality of an English
Ballad». Oral Tradition, 23, 1 (2008), p. 87.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1908a1310">
            <label>108</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1915" publication-type="other">
Oring, Elliott. «Missing Theory». Western Folklore, 65, 4 (2006), p. 459.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1922a1310">
            <label>109</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1929" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 462.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1936a1310">
            <label>110</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1943" publication-type="other">
Carterette, Edward C, Kendall, Roger. «Comparative Music Perception and Cognition».
The Psychology of Music (Cognition and Perception). Diana Deutsch (ed.). San Diego, Academic
Press, 1999.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1956a1310">
            <label>111</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1963" publication-type="other">
Ibid., p. 766.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1971a1310">
            <label>112</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1978" publication-type="other">
Geertz, C. La Interpretación de las Culturas..., p. 20.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1985a1310">
            <label>113</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e1992" publication-type="other">
Carterette, E. C., Kendall, R. «Comparative Music...», p. 782.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e1999a1310">
            <label>114</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e2006" publication-type="other">
Friedrich Meinecke (Weltburgertum und Nationalstaat: Studien zur Genesis
des Deutschen Nationalstaates. Munich y Berlin, R. Oldenbourg, 1919 [1907]).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d417727e2016a1310">
            <label>115</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d417727e2023" publication-type="other">
TITON, Jeff Todd. «Music and Sustainability:
An Ecological Viewpoint». The World of Music, 51, 1 (2009), pp. 119-137</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Referencias</title>
         <ref id="d417727e2042a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2046" publication-type="other">
Abrahams, Roger D. «Personal Power and Social Restraint in the Definition of
Folklore». Towards New Perspectives in Folklore. Américo Paredes y Richard Bauman
(eds). Austin, University of Texas Press, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2059a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2063" publication-type="other">
-«Phantoms of Romantic Nationalism in Folkloristics». Journal of American Folklore,
106, 419 (1993), pp. 3-37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2073a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2079" publication-type="other">
Anderson, Benedict. Comunidades Imaginadas. Reflexiones sobre el Origen y la Difusión
del Nacionalismo. México, Fondo de Cultura Econòmica, 1993 [1983].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2089a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2093" publication-type="other">
Aubert, Laurent. The Music of the Other: New Challenges for Ethnomusicology in a Global
Age. Aldershot, Ashgate Publishing, 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2104a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2108" publication-type="other">
AXELROD, Robert. «The Dissemination of Culture: A Model with Local Convergence
and Global Polarization». The Journal of Conflict Resolution, 41,2 (1997), pp. 203-226.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2118a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2122" publication-type="other">
Bahti, Timothy. «Anacoluthon: On Cultural Studies». MLN, 112,3 (1997), pp. 366-384.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2129a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2133" publication-type="other">
Balliger, Robin. «Politics». Key Terms in Popular Music and Culture. Bruce Horner y
Thomas Swiss (eds). Cresskill, Hampton Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2143a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2147" publication-type="other">
BartÓK, Béla. Escritos sobre Mùsica Popular. México, Siglo XXI Editores, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2154a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2158" publication-type="other">
Becker, Judith. «Perspectives on Music and Emotion». Music and Emotion: Theory and
Research. Patrik Juslin y John Sloboda (eds). Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2168a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2172" publication-type="other">
Ben-Amos, Dan. «Toward a Definition of Folklore in Context». Towards New Perspec-
tives in Folklore. Américo Paredes y Richard Bauman (eds). Austin, University of
Texas Press, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2186a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2190" publication-type="other">
-«The Seven Strands of Tradition. Varieties in its Meaning in American Folklore
Studies». Journal of Folklore Research, 21, 2-3 (1984), pp. 97-131.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2200a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2204" publication-type="other">
Bendix, Regina. «Folklorism: The Challenge of a Concept». International Folklore Re-
view, 6 (1988), pp. 5-14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2214a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2218" publication-type="other">
-«National Sentiment in the Enactment and Discourse of Swiss Political Ritual».
American Ethnologist, 19, 4 (1992), pp. 768-790.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2228a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2232" publication-type="other">
Berger, Peter L, Luckmann, Thomas. La Construction Social de la Realidad. Buenos
Aires, Amorrortu editores, 1972 [1966].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2242a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2246" publication-type="other">
Bohlman, Philip V. «Becoming Ethnomusicologists: On Cultural Translation». SEM
Newsletter, 41, 2 (2007), pp. 4-5.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2256a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2260" publication-type="other">
BOISSEVAIN, Jeremy. «Notas sobre la renovación. De las celebraciones publicas popu-
lates europeas». Arxius de Sociologìa, 3, (1999), pp. 53-67.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2271a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2275" publication-type="other">
-«Coping with Mass Cultural Tourism: Structure and Strategies». Gazeto Internatio
de Antropologio, 1, 1 (2006), pp. 2-13.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2285a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2289" publication-type="other">
Brubaker, Rogers. Ethnicity Without Groups. Cambridge (MA) y Londres, Harvard
University Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2299a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2303" publication-type="other">
Brunet, Roger. «Anâlisis de Paisajes y Semiologia». El Pensamiento Geogràfico. Estudio
Interpretativo y Antologia de Textos (de Humboldt a las Tendencias Radicales). Josefina
Gómez Mendoza, Julio Munoz Jiménez y Nicolas Ortega Cantero (eds). Madrid,
Alianza Universidad, 1982 [1974].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2319a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2323" publication-type="other">
Burke, Peter. iQué es la Historia Cultural? Barcelona, Paidós, 2006.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2330a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2334" publication-type="other">
CAMPOS Calvo-Sotelo, Javier. Fiesta, Identidad y Contracultura. Contribuciones al Estudio
Histórico de la Gaita en Galicia. Pontevedra, Diputación Provincial de Pontevedra, 2007.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2344a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2348" publication-type="other">
-La Mùsica Popular Gallega en los Alios de la Transition Politica (1975-1982): Reificaciones
Expresivas del Paradigma Identitaria [Tesis doctoral]. Madrid, Universidad Complutense
de Madrid, 2009. Publicada corno recurso electrónico: http://eprints.ucm.es/8801/.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2362a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2366" publication-type="other">
CANTWELL, Robert. When We Were Good: The Folk Revival. Cambridge, Harvard Uni-
versity Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2376a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2380" publication-type="other">
Carterette, Edward C., Kendall, Roger. «Comparative Music Perception and Cog-
nition». The Psychology of Music (Cognition and Perception). Diana Deutsch (ed.).
San Diego, Academic Press, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2393a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2397" publication-type="other">
CHATTERJEE, Partha. «Anderson's Utopia». Diacritics, 29, 4 (1999), pp. 128-134.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2404a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2408" publication-type="other">
ClNNAMOND, Jeffrey. «Replicating Rhoades: Deconstructing a Deconstructionist». The
Journal of Higher Education, 62, 6 (1991), pp. 694-706.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2418a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2422" publication-type="other">
COHEN, Judah. «Musical Institutions and the Transmission of Tradition». Ethnomusi-
cology, 53, 2 (2009), pp. 308-325.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2432a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2436" publication-type="other">
CONNOR, Walker. Etnonacionalismo. Madrid, Trama, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2444a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2448" publication-type="other">
Contemporary Spanish Cultural Studies. Barry Jordan y Rikki Morgan-Tamosunas (eds).
Nueva York, Arnold, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2458a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2462" publication-type="other">
Crespi-Vallbona, Montserrat, Richards, Greg. «The Meaning of Cultural Festivals.
Stakeholder Perspectives in Catalunya». International Journal of Cultural Policy, 13,
1 (2007), pp. 103-122.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2475a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2479" publication-type="other">
Culler, Jonathan. «Anderson and the Novel». Diacritics, 29,4 (1999), pp. 19-39.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2486a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2490" publication-type="other">
Dean-Smith, Margaret. «The Pre-Disposition to Folkery». Folklore, 79, (1968), pp. 161-175.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2497a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2501" publication-type="other">
DENORA, Tia. «The concerto and society». The Cambridge Companion to the Concerto.
Simon P. Keefe (ed). Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2511a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2515" publication-type="other">
Derrida, Jacques. Margins of Philosophy. Chicago, University of Chicago Press, 1982.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2523a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2527" publication-type="other">
-«Sokal et Bricmont ne sont pas sérieux». Le Monde, 20 de noviembre de 1997, p. 17.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2534a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2538" publication-type="other">
Dietler, Michael. «'Our Ancestors the Gauls': Archaeology, Ethnic Nationalism, and
the Manipulation of Celtic Identity in Modern Europe». American Anthropologist,
96, 3 (1994), pp. 584-605.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2551a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2555" publication-type="other">
DORSON, Richard M. «Fakelore». Zeitschrijt fiir Volkskunde, 65, (1969), pp. 56-64.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2562a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2566" publication-type="other">
Dundes, Alan. «Folkloristics in the Twenty-First Century». Journal of American Folklore,
118, 470 (2005), pp. 385-408.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2576a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2580" publication-type="other">
Enescu, George. «Enescu despre Muzica Româneasc ». Muzica (1921), p. 115.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2587a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2591" publication-type="other">
Feintuch, Burt. «Tradition». The Dictionary of Anthropology. Thomas Barfield (ed).
Oxford, Blackwell Publishing, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2602a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2606" publication-type="other">
Felperin, Howard. «The Anxiety of Deconstruction». Yale French Studies, 69, (1985),
pp. 254-266.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2616a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2620" publication-type="other">
FERGUSON, Marjorie, Golding, Peter. «Cultural Studies and Changing Times: An In-
troduction». Cultural Studies in Question, Marjorie Ferguson y Peter Golding (eds).
Londres, Sage Publications, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2633a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2637" publication-type="other">
Geertz, Clifford. La Interpretation de las Culturas. Barcelona, Gedisa, 2000 [1973].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2644a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2648" publication-type="other">
Gitlin, Todd. «The Anti-political Populism of Cultural Studies». Cultural Studies in
Question. Marjorie Ferguson y Peter Golding (eds). Londres, Sage Publications, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2658a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2662" publication-type="other">
Handler, Richard; Linnekin, Jocelyn. «Tradition, Genuine and Spurious». Journal of
American Folklore, 97, 385 (1984), pp. 273-290.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2672a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2676" publication-type="other">
Hirsch, Jerrold. «Folklore in the Making: B. A. Botkin». Journal of American Folklore,
100, 395 (1987), pp. 3-38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2687a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2691" publication-type="other">
Hobsbawm, Eric. «Some Reflections on 'The Break-up of Britain'». New Left Review,
1, 105 (1977), pp. 1-14.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2701a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2705" publication-type="other">
-«Introducción: La Invención de la Tradición». La Invention de la Tradition. Eric
Hobsbawm y Terence Ranger (eds). Barcelona, Critica, 2002 [1983].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2715a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2719" publication-type="other">
HORNER, Bruce. «Discourse». Key Terms in Popular Music and Culture. Bruce Horner y
Thomas Swiss (eds). Cresskill, Hampton Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2729a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2733" publication-type="other">
Kirshenblatt-Gimblett, Barbara. «Folklore's Crisis». Journal of American Folklore, 111,
441 (1998), pp. 281-327.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2743a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2747" publication-type="other">
Kivy, Peter. Nuevos Ensayos sobre la Comprensión Musical. Barcelona, Paidós Ibèrica, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2754a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2758" publication-type="other">
KRAMER, Lawrence. Classical Music and Postmodern Knowledge. Berkeley y Los Angeles,
University of California Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2769a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2773" publication-type="other">
La Invención de la Tradición. Eric Hobsbawm y Terence Ranger (eds). Barcelona, Critica,
2002 [1983].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2783a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2787" publication-type="other">
Lau, Frederick. «The Invention of Solo dizi Music in Post-1949 China». British Journal
of Ethnomusicology, 5 (1996), pp. 113-131.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2797a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2801" publication-type="other">
Lévi-Strauss, Claude. Mito y Significado. Madrid, Alianza Editorial, 1987 [1978].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2808a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2812" publication-type="other">
LlSÓN TOLOSANA, Carmelo. «Prius Vita quam Doctrina». Europaea, 2,2 (1996), http://
www.h-net.org/~sae/europea/1996ii2.html. [Consulta: 22 de mayo de 2009].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2822a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2826" publication-type="other">
LlTVAK, Joseph. «Back to the Future: A Review-Artide on the New Historicism, Decons-
truction, and Nineteenth-Century Fiction». Texas Studies in Literature and Language,
30, 1 (1988), pp. 120-149.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2839a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2843" publication-type="other">
Marx, Karl. Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy. Pekin, Foreign Language
Press, 1976 [1859],</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2854a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2858" publication-type="other">
Mattar, Yasser. «Popular Cultural Cringe: Language as a Signifier of Authenticity and
Quality in the Singaporean Popular Music Market». Popular Music, 28, 2 (2008),
pp. 179-195.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2871a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2875" publication-type="other">
McClary, Susan. «The Blasphemy of Talking Politics during Bach Year». Music and
Society: The Politics of Composition, Performance and Reception. Susan McClary y
Richard Leppert (eds). Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2888a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2892" publication-type="other">
-«Same as it Ever Was: Youth Culture and Music». Microphone Fiends: Youth Music
and Youth Culture. Andrew Ross y Tricia Rose (eds). Nueva York, Routledge, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2902a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2906" publication-type="other">
McDonald, Barry. «The Idea of Tradition Examined in the Light of Two Australian
Musical Studies». Yearbook for Traditional Music, 28 (1996), pp. 106-130.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2916a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2920" publication-type="other">
-«Tradition as Personal Relationship». Journal of American Folklore, 110,435 (1997),
pp. 47-67.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2930a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2934" publication-type="other">
Mechling, Jay. «Solo Folklore». Western Folklore, 65, 4 (2006), pp. 435-453.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2942a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2946" publication-type="other">
Meinecke, Friedrich. Weltbiirgertum und Nationalstaat: Studien zur Genesis des Deutschen
Nationalstaates. Munich y Berlin, R. Oldenbourg, 1919 [1907].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2956a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2960" publication-type="other">
Middleton, Richard. «Introduction: Music Studies and the Idea of Culture». The
Cultural Study of Music: A Critical Introduction. Martin Clayton, Trevor Herbert y
Richard Middleton (eds). Nueva York y Londres, Routledge, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2973a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2977" publication-type="other">
Molino, Jean. «Fait Musical et Sémiologie de la Musique». Musique en Jeu, 17 (1975),
pp. 37-62.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2987a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e2991" publication-type="other">
MOORE, Allan. «Authenticity as Authentication». Popular Music, 21,2 (2002), pp. 209-223.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e2998a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3002" publication-type="other">
Motyl, Alexander J. «Imagined Communities, Rational Choosers, Invented Ethnies.
Review of The Spectre of Comparisons: Nationalism, Southeast Asia, and the World, by
Benedict Anderson; Identity in Formation: The Russian-Speaking Populations in the
Near Abroad, by David D. Laitin and Nationalism and Modernism: A Critical Survey
of Recent Theories of Nations and Nation, by Anthony D. Smith». Comparative Politics,
34, 2 (2002), pp. 233-250.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3025a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3029" publication-type="other">
Nairn, Tom. «Nationalism: The Modern Janus». New Left Review, 1,94 (1975), pp. 3-29.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3037a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3041" publication-type="other">
Nattiez, Jean-Jacques. Musicologie Generale et Semiologie. Paris, Christian Bourgois, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3048a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3052" publication-type="other">
Neff, Eoghan. «Review of Electric Folk: The Changing Face of English Traditional Music,
by Britta Sweers». Ethnomusicology, 53, 2 (2009), pp. 326-329.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3062a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3066" publication-type="other">
Oring, Elliott. «Missing Theory». Western Folklore, 65, 4 (2006), pp. 455-465.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3073a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3077" publication-type="other">
Parker, Andrew. «Bogeyman: Benedict Anderson's 'Derivative' Discourse». Diacritics,
29, 4 (1999), pp. 40-57.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3087a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3091" publication-type="other">
PETTUT, Tom. «From Journalism to Gypsy Folk Song: The Road to Orality of an English
Ballad». Oral Tradition, 23,1 (2008), pp. 87-117.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3101a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3105" publication-type="other">
Popper, Karl. En Busca de un Mundo Mejor. Barcelona, Paidós, 1994 [1984],</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3113a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3117" publication-type="other">
Redfield, Marc. «Imagi-Nation: The Imagined Community and the Aesthetics of
Mourning». Diacritics, 29, 4 (1999), pp. 58-83.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3127a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3131" publication-type="other">
RONSTROM, Owe. «Making Use of History: The Revival of the Bagpipe in Sweden in
the 1980s». Yearbook for Traditional Music, 21 (1989), pp. 95-108.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3141a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3145" publication-type="other">
Rosenberg, Neil. «Revivalism». American Folklore: An Encyclopedia. Jan Harold Brun-
vand (ed). Nueva York y Londres, Garland Publishing, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3155a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3159" publication-type="other">
SHEPHERD, John. «Text». Key Terms in Popular Music and Culture. Bruce Horner y Tho-
mas Swiss (eds). Cresskill, Hampton Press, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3169a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3173" publication-type="other">
Small, Christopher. Musicking. Hanover, Wesleyan University Press, 1988.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3180a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3184" publication-type="other">
SOKAL, Alan. «Transgressing the Boundaries: Toward a Transformative Hermeneutics
of Quantum Gravity». Social Text, 46-47 (1996), pp. 217-252.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3195a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3199" publication-type="other">
Sokal, Alan, BRICMONT, Jean. Impostures Intellectuelles. Paris, Odile Jacob, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3206a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3210" publication-type="other">
STOKES, Martin. «Introduction: Ethnicity, Identity and Music». Ethnicity, Identity and
Music: The Musical Construction of Place. Martin Stokes (ed). Oxford y Nueva York,
Berg Publishers, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3223a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3227" publication-type="other">
SWEERS, Britta. Electric Folk: The Changing Face of English Traditional Music. Nueva York,
Oxford University Press, 2005.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3237a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3241" publication-type="other">
TiTON, Jeff Todd. «Music and Sustainability: An Ecological Viewpoint». The World of
Music, 51, 1 (2009), pp. 119-137.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3251a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3255" publication-type="other">
Vozes do Povo: A Folclorizaçào em Portugal. Salwa El-Shawan Castelo-Branco y Jorge
Freitas Branco (eds.). Lisboa, Celta Editora, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3265a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3269" publication-type="other">
WHITE, Harry. «Review of Matthew Gelbart: The Invention of 'Folk Music' and 'Art Mu-
sic'. Emerging Categories from Ossian to Wagner». Journal of the Society for Musicology
in Ireland, 4, (2008-09), pp. 75-77.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3283a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3287" publication-type="other">
Williams, Raymond. Problems in Materialism and Culture. Selected Essays. Londres,
Verso, 1980.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3297a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3301" publication-type="other">
WlTZLEBEN, J. Lawrence. «Whose Ethnomusicology? Western Ethnomusicology and
the Study of Asian Music». Ethnomusicology, 41, 2: Issues in Ethnomusicology
(1997), pp. 220-242.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d417727e3314a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d417727e3318" publication-type="other">
ZUELOW, Eric G. E. «Review of Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and
Spread of Nationalism, by Benedict Anderson». http://www.nationalismproject.
org/books/a_b-htm#Anchor-Anderson-23526. [Consulta: 22 de octubre de 2006].</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
