<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">philrhet</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Philosophy &amp; Rhetoric</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318213</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15272079</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">philrhet.46.2.0182</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/philrhet.46.2.0182</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The “Agential Spiral”:</article-title>
            <subtitle>Reading Public Memory Through Paul Ricoeur</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Sara C. VanderHaagen</string-name>
               <aff>Communication Studies, University of Nevada, Las Vegas</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2013</year>
            <string-date>2013</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">46</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">philrhet.46.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>182</fpage>
         <lpage>206</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2013</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/philrhet.46.2.0182"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article mines the work of philosopher Paul Ricoeur in order to construct a critical framework for the rhetorical analysis of public memory. Through a reading of Ricoeur's concept of “threefold mimesis,” I develop the idea of the “agential spiral.” The “spiral” frames a repetitive yet progressive process in which a series of agents or groups of agents both interpret and act in response to the past. When linked together, these moments of agency form a spiral that metaphorizes the process of creating and deploying public memories across time. I argue that the concept of the agential spiral enables scholars to focus not only on the ways that memories unite human agents synchronically but also on how those memories structure a relationship among agents across time through the performance and representation of agency. I situate this argument within scholarship on rhetorical studies and public memory.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In an essay examining Hannah Arendt's approach to public memory, rhetorical scholar Stephen H. Browne notes that “to remember is thus not simply to turn backward; it is itself a type of action that steadies us in the face of an unknown and unpredictable future” (2004, 60). The act of remembering connects the rememberer to both the past and the future. As scholars such as Benedict Anderson, John Bodnar, and John Gillis have pointed out, remembering also connects human beings to their contemporaries and “imagined communities” by establishing a common narrative and space for identification. In many cases, action itself provides the material from which memories are formed—an individual from the past betrayed his country, ran for office, spoke against injustice, or refused to move to the back of the bus. Human action thus appears in our shared memories in a variety of ways—as an impetus for remembrance, as a means for recollection, and as the product of remembering.</p>
      <p>This article seeks to advance our understanding of how human agency supplies the fodder for public memories, thereby linking individuals and groups across time and perpetuating the memorial process. In order to accomplish this goal, I examine the work of philosopher Paul Ricoeur. I use his idea of “threefold mimesis” to develop a critical framework—the “agential spiral”—for reading examples of public memory. I argue that the concept of the agential spiral enables scholars to focus not only on the ways that memories unite human agents in the same temporal moment but also on how memories structure a relationship among agents across time through the performance and representation of agency. The image of a spiral highlights the cyclical yet potentially innovative process in which different agents (or groups of agents) at different points in time rhetorically reconstruct the past so that it can be productively appropriated by other agents. Unlike a circle, a spiral does not travel in precisely the same path but follows it in parallel motion, as one coil in a spring follows another. This framework foregrounds key agents in the process of creating public memories: those acting in history, those interpreting and fixing historical narratives, and those reading about or otherwise consuming these narratives. The spiral linking these agents would follow a general pattern: historical events occur, are recognized as significant “actions” and are recorded; historians, curators, memorialists, and other interpreters translate these events into explanatory narratives of human action; and readers, listeners, and other members of the public engage these narratives in order to understand the meaning of the past for the present. Then audience members become actors and contribute again to the cycle of interpreting and creatively imitating human action.</p>
      <p>The concept of the agential spiral is both derived from and builds on Paul Ricoeur's concept of “threefold mimesis.” Developed most explicitly in<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>, “threefold mimesis” traces how narrative represents human action by emplotting it in a framework of temporality. Ricoeur views time and narrative as integral elements of the human condition and our own understanding of it: “Time becomes human to the extent that it is articulated through a narrative mode, and narrative attains its full meaning when it becomes a condition of temporal existence” (1984, 1:52). The narrative creates an imagined world that, in turn, leads readers to act in the real world. Although Ricoeur gestures toward the public judgment and action that are the end of persuasion, he turns back to the individual experience of catharsis—the end of poetics—to explain how the reader “appropriates” the world of the read text. The concept of appropriation presented by Ricoeur primarily refers to the phenomenological experience of a change in perspective rather than a rhetorically produced orientation toward public action. I argue that Ricoeur's emphasis on appropriation through catharsis limits the usefulness of threefold mimesis as a means of understanding how texts (in our case, texts or practices of public memory) invite specifically<italic>public</italic>actions. Therefore, my reading of Ricoeur draws attention to two issues that Ricoeur underemphasizes. First, my reading highlights both the various agents who interpret and act on the past and their transhistorical relationships with one another. Specifically, I am interested in understanding how public memories respond to diachronic as well as synchronic collective contexts. Focusing on these performances of agency enables critical scholars to see how the representation of agency itself can link past, present, and future. Second, I use Maurice Charland's familiar concept of constitutive rhetoric to knit Ricoeur's ideas more tightly to rhetorical concerns with public action and thereby to close the gap Ricoeur leaves between mimesis<sub>1</sub>and mimesis<sub>3</sub>. By linking those moments, we can better understand the creation of public memories as a spiraling process that connects human communities across time.</p>
      <sec id="s01">
         <title>READING RICOEUR</title>
         <p>I turn to Ricoeur's work first because of its resonances with rhetorical studies. Scholars such as Michael Leff, Andreea Deciu Ritivoi, and Barbara Warnick have productively engaged some of these common themes, but there has not been a sustained effort to use his insights in rhetorical analysis generally, let alone in the rhetorical analysis of memory (Hauser<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Leff<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>and<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Ritivoi<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Warnick<xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>).<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>This lack of attention may result in part from Ricoeur's own ambivalence toward rhetoric, which he once described as “philosophy's oldest enemy and its oldest ally” (1977, 10). Although Ricoeur maintained a rather narrow view of rhetoric, his preoccupation with its themes suggests that scholars of rhetoric can discover ideas in his work that can be developed into tools for critical analysis. Therefore, this article intends to contribute to a broader—albeit currently only intermittent—effort to assess the resonances between Ricoeur's work and the rhetorical tradition and to fashion useful tools from those mutual concerns.</p>
         <p>Two spaces of interface stand out specifically: an interest in interpretation and a commitment to understanding human action. Generally speaking, Ricoeur's foundations in philosophical hermeneutics resonate with inquiries in rhetoric, and his deft balance of analytic and Continental approaches to philosophy provides a sensible perspective on the processes of textual interpretation. Ricoeur's work attends to concerns that might be described by some rhetorical scholars as “traditional” while also taking seriously the challenges that poststructural critiques pose to such concerns (see Ihde 2007, xvi, and Ricoeur<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">1977</xref>, 257–313). For this reason, Ricoeur's scholarship provides a sensible point of mediation between views on language and human agency that can tend toward the extremes.</p>
         <p>Such virtues make Ricoeur's work congenial to a critical focus on how the acts of interpretation and rhetorical production intertwine in discursive processes. Scholars such as Barbie Zelizer have noted that the return to memory reframes human representation of the past as<italic>process</italic>of interpretation and contestation in which individuals and groups both consume and produce historical narratives (Zelizer<xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>, 218). In such a process, one person (or group) can function as both hermeneut and rhetor. The agential spiral, echoing Ricoeur's threefold mimesis, highlights a moment in the discursive process of memory production when one who reads about the past becomes one who speaks about the past.</p>
         <p>For the purposes of this article, I view rhetoric and hermeneutics as two complementary phases in the circulation of discourse, the former being an art emphasizing production and the latter being one emphasizing understanding. I also find H. P. Rickman's characterization illuminating: “Rhetoric is about the process of communication from the point of view of the speaker, hermeneutics about the problems of the listener” (1981, 110). Whereas Rickman describes these fields from the perspective of the human being, both Hans-Georg Gadamer and Ricoeur describe them according to basic function. Gadamer distinguishes between them according to their central practice—speaking for rhetoric, understanding for hermeneutics (1997, 49). Ricoeur defines each one more narrowly, saying that rhetoric is concerned with “arguing,” whereas hermeneutics is concerned with “redescribing” (1997, 71; Ritivoi<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, 6). Although each philosopher offers a slightly different definition, they agree that rhetoric and hermeneutics are complementary discursive practices. Ricoeur's hermeneutic sensibility can help us understand how those practices can function almost simultaneously, within one pivotal moment.</p>
         <p>Ricoeur's work also concentrates on the connection between texts and human action in the world, a fundamental concern of scholars in rhetoric (see Zarefsky<xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, 79). By deploying Ricoeur's prudent approach to agency, the concept of the agential spiral can advance work in rhetorical studies that seeks to balance the power of individual agents with the impact of social forces (see Anderson<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, Campbell<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>, DeLuca<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, Greene<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, Hansen<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, Leff<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>, Stormer<xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, and Turnbull<xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). This struggle for balance can be seen clearly among rhetorical scholars studying public memory, many of whom have noted its simultaneously collective and individual nature (see Dickinson, Blair, and Ott<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, and Phillips<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Because the return to memory emphasizes the strategic use of language to revise representations of the past, it places agency at the center of historical representation. Yet the precise dynamics of individual and collective agency can be difficult to trace. As historian Wulf Kansteiner has explained, “[Memory] is a collective phenomenon but it only manifests itself in the actions and statements of individuals” (2002, 180). Such discussions can be enriched by theories that forfeit neither collective nor individual agency. Because the agential spiral foregrounds the rhetorical choices of specific agents while also emphasizing their relationship to one another, this framework helps to identify a “more modest role” for the individual subject, without ignoring the fact that memories are created in part by individual and collective rhetorical choices, whether conscious or unconscious (Ricoeur 2007, 37). The individual who both reads and acts thus appears neither as a self-possessed Cartesian subject nor as a mere effect of structural systems.<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>As a critical framework, the agential spiral traces the rhetorical influences of individual agents while simultaneously underscoring the fact that the processes of public memory are inherently social.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <title>HERMENEUTICS OF MEMORY</title>
         <p>The concept of the agential spiral engages an implicit assumption that seems to be shared widely by rhetorical scholars who study public memory: memories as such exist in the eye of the beholder, whether that be a scholarly critic or interested citizen. In other words, one's understanding of how humans represent the past depends on the lens one is using to examine that representation. In recommending the agential spiral as a critical framework, I am also suggesting that we use what might be thought of as a set of nested interpretive lenses, each of which focuses analytical vision on ever more specific aspects of historical representation. The most general lens is that of rhetoric, which I understand as a perspective that focuses attention on the public, situated use of language for persuasive and constitutive purposes. The second lens is that of public memory, which spotlights the<italic>uniquely rhetorical</italic>aspects of human representation and experience of the past. By describing public memory as “rhetorical,” I follow to some degree other scholars who have also observed the partial, contested, strategic, and affective nature of the phenomenon (Blair, Dickinson, and Ott<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, 2, 13, 22; Browne<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>, 238; Phillips<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, 2; Zelizer<xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>, 214). Yet characterizing public memory as “uniquely rhetorical” renders explicit the fact that there are decidedly nonrhetorical ways of understanding these processes (e.g., by evaluating a memory according to its factual accuracy). This characterization also helps scholars to avoid the persistent temptation to view public memory as merely a set of objects that are substantively distinct from history rather than as a concept that critically foregrounds certain aspects of the representation of the past—that is, as a<italic>hermeneutic</italic>concept. As historian Geoffrey Cubitt puts it, memory is “not an object, but a concept—a mental category that we make use of<italic>in making sense of</italic>complex and elusive aspects of human behavior and experience” (2007, 6; emphasis mine).<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>Used this way, the term becomes a conceptual lens for sharpening certain features of public and rhetorical phenomena: the representation of temporality, the construction of relations between agents across time (especially between historical subjects and contemporary individuals), the mutability of historical representation, public engagement with these representations, the affective investment in the past encouraged by certain texts and so on.</p>
         <p>Nested within the perspectives of rhetoric and public memory, the agential spiral constitutes the third, most narrow, lens. This hermeneutic lens focuses specifically on three important aspects of rhetorical practices of public memory: first, the central role that human agency plays in constructing memories; second, the tendency of many memories to revolve around the representation of human agency; and, third, the means by which public memories activate representations of agency and so cultivate relationships between agents across distances of time and thereby perpetuate memories. Scholarly work has gestured toward the first issue, suggesting that individuals and groups “deliberate” about the past (Vivian<xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, 13) and “make choices” about how to represent it (Blair, Dickinson, and Ott<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, 7). Drawing on the work of Edward Casey, Kendall Phillips takes that observation a step further by claiming that “the arena of public memory [is] a realm in which we act together” (2004, 4). Although many rhetorical scholars have addressed the performance of agency in the processes of public memory, fewer have explicitly attended to the representation of agency in memories. Historians, on the other hand, have long focused on what William Sewell has described as the “unfolding of human action through time” (2005, 6; see also Kansteiner<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>, 181, and Shaw<xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). As memory emerged as a key term, some historians recognized its ability to maintain a focus on agency and affect in the face of increasing calls to decenter the agent in historical scholarship (Klein<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>, 129; Ermarth<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Palti<xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). As a critical framework, the agential spiral enables scholars to focus on the representation of agency within instances of public memory while recognizing that memories also represent other things such as events or identities. Even less attention has been paid to the precise way that public memories deploy representations of agency specifically in ways that structure and enable relationships among individuals and groups across time. Of course, following works by scholars such as Benedict Anderson, Eric Hobsbawm and Terence Ranger, and Michael Kammen, to name only a few examples, commentary on the role of memory in nationalistic movements has become common. However, such works tend to focus more on cataloging (or worse, in the case of Hobsbawm and Ranger's collection, merely debunking) practices of memory among myriad groups than on explaining why certain memories “stick” and how those memories use representations of agency to make them “sticky” over time (Dickinson, Blair, and Ott<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>,14–16). I contend this is one of the primary contributions of the agential spiral as a critical framework: it highlights the ways that public memories continually cultivate diachronic relationships as well as synchronic relationships. The agential spiral helps us to see not only the individuals in the present who argue about and revise memories but also those in the past who have created the fodder for memories and those in the future who will use public memories as a resource for action.</p>
         <p>To illustrate the spiral's applicability to particular practices of public memory, I employ the example of biographies for children. Although these texts differ from other, more familiar objects of inquiry such as memorials, they are nonetheless significant because of their function within the vast systems of contemporary historical memory, which thus makes them representative as texts of public memory. These widely circulated texts constitute a major component of public school history education in the United States. Because such texts seem to demand more brevity and accessibility than their adult-oriented counterparts, they require careful selection from and representation of the historical record. These texts provide a helpful case because the key agents are relatively simple to identify (e.g., biographical subjects, creators, and readers) and the texts are typically oriented toward producing imitation and action. Biographies foreground the agent who acts in history—the historical figure or group whose acts are represented and/or judged in the text. A second set of agents interpret the actions of the subject in order to assemble them into narratives—the historian, consultant, textbook writer, illustrator, teacher, and possibly parent or community groups advocating certain versions of the past. The texts then pass to a third group of agents, those that may appropriate history—the young readers and future citizens. Because the rhetorical agents in each of these processes are also hermeneutical agents, they easily shade or “pivot” between functions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s03">
         <title>FROM THREEFOLD MIMESIS TO AGENTIAL SPIRAL</title>
         <p>In his foreword to Ricoeur's<italic>From Text to Action</italic>, Richard Kearney asserts that “Ricoeur's work, from beginning to end, was fueled by an ontology of action” (2007, ix). Ricoeur combines his interest in action with questions of memory in the magisterial<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>(<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), in which he systematically explores the phenomenological experience—and to a lesser extent, the ethical implications—of the three central terms. However, because this work focuses more on phenomenology than the public implications of a text, other works by Ricoeur are better suited to redeployment in critical analysis. This is not to say that Ricoeur ignores important themes in<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>. For instance, he uses the evocative phrase “historian-citizen” in order to denote the public responsibility demanded by certain narratives or representations of the past (2004, 259). Unfortunately, however, Ricoeur moves quickly beyond this promising concept without fully developing it. Thus, the concepts from<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>and, to a lesser extent,<italic>From Text to Action</italic>, provide a more congenial point of departure for the agential spiral.</p>
         <p>Ricoeur's discussion of “threefold mimesis” in<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>clearly demonstrates his commitment to understanding human action. Through threefold mimesis, Ricoeur explains, the reader “takes up through doing something—the act of reading—the unity of the traversal from mimesis<sub>1</sub>to mimesis<sub>3</sub>by way of mimesis<sub>2</sub>” (1984, 1:53). This concept connects the three moments in a line across time. The adaptation I propose places these moments in a more circular relationship by linking mimesis<sub>3</sub>back to mimesis<sub>1</sub>through the potentially memorable actions of a reader.</p>
         <p>Mimesis, as Ricoeur describes it, encapsulates both the representation and imitation of human action (1984, 1:33). The representational moments of mimesis occur at three points, which Ricoeur names mimesis<sub>1</sub>, mimesis<sub>2</sub>, and mimesis<sub>3</sub>. Each of these moments is characterized by a distinct kind of figuration. Prefiguration aligns with mimesis<sub>1</sub>, configuration with mimesis<sub>2</sub>, and refiguration with mimesis<sub>3</sub>. As Ricoeur explains, these three moments are interconnected within a process “by which the textual configuration mediates between the prefiguration of the practical field and its refiguration through the reception of the work” (1984, 1:53). The imitation takes place at two key points in this process: at the initial moment when a writer or historian reconstructs the actions into a narrative and at the moment when the reader of this narrative is urged to “take up” the action by imitating it in the real world. Ricoeur is careful to point out that the mimesis that he has in mind is not slavish copying: “If we continue to translate mimesis by ‘imitation,’ we have to understand something completely contrary to a copy of some preexisting reality and speak instead of a creative imitation” (1984, 1:45; see also 2004, 13).</p>
         <p>This formulation of “threefold mimesis” provides a useful starting point for examining precisely how memories deploy certain visions of agency that establish relationships between agents or groups of agents across temporal distance. The concept I derive from Ricoeur's “threefold mimesis”—the “agential spiral”—foregrounds specific moments in which an agent or a group of agents makes hermeneutic and rhetorical choices that both represent action and transmit those representations of agency to temporally remote audiences. The agential spiral helps us to understand how memories transmit certain visions of agency that perpetuate new actions and thus potentially new memories.</p>
         <p>The formulation of the agential spiral activates three possibilities latent in Ricoeur's work in<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>. First, Ricoeur's identification of the three moments of “figuration” gestures toward but does not elaborate on the ways that each of these instances can be connected to a specific agent taking hermeneutic action and, in many cases, rhetorical action. The “prefiguration” of mimesis<sub>1</sub>features the activity and identity of the agent of history—such as the subject of a biography. During her lifetime, this individual lived in a way that left traces on the historical archive, which through accidents or the actions of other people has come to constitute what Hayden White in<italic>Metahistory</italic>(<xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>) calls the “chronicle” of history.<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>4</sup>
            </xref>The reading of these traces in the present is “prefigured” by the frames of interpretation that exist in the culture of the reading public. These frames may be structured by underlying theories of human action, such as the idea that one “possesses” agency (as in the trope of authorship) or the belief that one “activates” it (as in an articulation or “nodal” model).<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>5</sup>
            </xref>Or, these frames may be provided by contemporary public values, such as the American ideal of independent personal growth. The “configuration” of mimesis<sub>2</sub>features the interpretive choices of the agent writing, rewriting, or otherwise transmitting a historical narrative. This agent can be a professional historian, a writer of historical fiction, creators of a nonfiction biography for children, or members of the public who take it upon themselves to interpret the archive. The “refiguration” of mimesis<sub>3</sub>features the actions of those who view, read, or hear these representations of the past. These audience members experience (or are meant to experience) the text in such a way that they can translate the possibilities of the “world of the work,” as Ricoeur describes it, into their own world through action. This action can then leave traces on the archive for future generations, and the circular process can begin again (Ricoeur 2007, 36).</p>
         <p>Second, Ricoeur's theory appreciates narrative's capacity to evoke new visions of the world but does not recognize the role that rhetoric might also play in producing new action. In some places, Ricoeur describes rhetoric as an art defined and constrained by beliefs already held by the audience. For example, when delineating the distinctions among rhetoric, poetics, and hermeneutics, Ricoeur explains that a speaker “begins with the conventional ideas that he shares with [the audience].” “In this,” he continues, “argumentation has little creative function: it transfers the agreement granted to premises onto conclusions” (1997, 62). Such an approach to rhetoric short-circuits Ricoeur's own theories about how texts produce agency, because it removes an important means for encouraging public action. The circularity of threefold mimesis does not just suggest merely repetition; it also implies that each agent's repetition can imaginatively improve on the previous iteration.<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>6</sup>
            </xref>The concept of the spiral uses rhetorical terminology to highlight how memories can encourage action that is both imitative and innovative, action that emerges from the past and projects into the future. As Bradford Vivian explains, citing Hannah Arendt, “Cultivating natality, or beginning again through collective speech and action, is a vital aim of communal recollection rather than mere repetition of the same” (2010, 55). It is this public “beginning again” that Ricoeur's work forgets.</p>
         <p>Finally, Ricoeur's formulation of threefold mimesis in<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>focuses on agency but does not specifically consider its function in the production and consumption of public memory. Ricoeur's most substantive, explicit discussion of the relationship between public remembering and public acting appears in the epilogue of<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, where he uses Arendt's work to address the problem of forgiveness (2004, 457–506). Although incredibly illuminating, this philosophical investigation does not aim to provide a strategy for reading examples of memory—or, more specifically, the<italic>public</italic>memory that interests rhetorical critics.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>7</sup>
            </xref>Yet Ricoeur's earlier works link agency to temporality and the world in ways that can be productively adapted as a hermeneutic tool for reading practices of public memory. Ricoeur approaches agency as a time-bound, text-mediated capacity to affect the self and envision a new world. My conception of the agential spiral takes Ricoeur's threefold mimesis a step further by considering how a specific set of texts figures agency in ways that are inspired by past actions, shaped by contemporary public cultures, and potentially productive of future agency.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s04">
         <title>MIMESIS<sub>1</sub>: AGENTS IN THE PAST</title>
         <p>In<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>, Ricoeur aligns the first stage of the hermeneutic circle, mimesis<sub>1</sub>, with the function of “prefiguration.” This concept describes the way in which narratives are “emplotted” according to “a preunderstanding of the world of action” (1984, 1:54). Ricoeur explains that preunderstanding has three primary features that affect the composition of a plot: meaningful structures, symbolic resources, and temporal character. The “meaningful structures” to which he refers can also be understood as a “conceptual network” of actions, people, events, stories, and the like. Just as words in a sentence constitute the level of semantic composition, the building blocks of activity in a narrative constitute a “semantics of action.” When writing of mimesis<sub>1</sub>, Ricoeur concentrates on the resources available within the context in which the text was produced rather than on describing how texts exhibit a semantics of action. It is in this cultural context that he locates the latent possibilities for emplotting action in a narrative. The “symbolic resources” are the ingredients of emplotment in a narrative, much as nouns, verbs, and objects are the ingredients of a sentence. Which types of resources are publicly available for representing human action? What are the various formulations for embedding human action in the unfolding of time? That is, what is the “temporal character” of narratives? How are human beings within a given cultural and historical context predisposed to understand the relation of human beings and human activities to time? How is time itself conceived in the society? Each of these elements—structures, symbols, and temporality—contributes to the prefiguration of the field of understanding wherein a narrative is emplotted (1984, 1:54–64).</p>
         <p>When one examines this moment of prefiguration against the background of Ricoeur's other work, it becomes evident that the preunderstanding of action relates closely to his concept of<italic>doxa</italic>. Literary and rhetorical scholar Andreea Deciu Ritivoi explains that this concept traditionally has been defined as “the domain of probable knowledge and contrasted to<italic>episteme</italic>, the realm of certainty.”<italic>Doxa</italic>has also been used to describe the “sets of beliefs widely espoused by particular audiences” (Ritivoi<xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, 50). This second sense pertains most directly to Ricoeur's notion of prefiguration.<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>8</sup>
            </xref>Like many rhetorical scholars, philosopher Ricoeur sees<italic>doxa</italic>as a central concept in the rhetorical tradition. Indeed, he argues that<italic>doxa</italic>, “the sedimented universe of conventional ideas,” constitutes the “premises of rhetorical argumentation” (1997, 66). All rhetors, he explains, build their persuasive discourses on conventional ideas they believe their audiences accept. Ricoeur thus argues that<italic>doxa</italic>serves an integrating, socially conservative function (1997, 60–64).</p>
         <p>To sketch how prefiguration works in public memory, I return briefly to the example of contemporary juvenile biographies. Such texts are shaped by enduring commonplaces of U.S. public culture that “prefigure” the narratives in the texts and thus render them intelligible on a basic level to members of that broader culture. Individual life stories become recognizable historical narratives because they resonate with late twentieth- and early twenty-first-century American perceptions of historical action. The introduction to the popular Americans All series of biographies provides an example. This widely circulated series published in the 1960s and 1970s features dozens of juvenile biographies. These books focus on individuals that have “uniquely contributed to the American way of life,” including figures such as Henry Ford, Martin Luther King Jr., and Sojourner Truth. Elaborating on these generic contributions, a short introduction to each text explains that “often despite great odds, these famous people have attained success in their fields through the good use of ability, determination, and hard work” (Patterson 1970, inside cover). Readers of this series learn not only about individual people; they learn about the public culture in which these lives were lived and in which these stories were constructed. As Ricoeur explains, “To understand a story is to understand both the language of ‘doing something’ and the cultural tradition from which proceeds the typology of plots” (1984, 1:57). The “language of ‘doing something’” that shapes children's biographies often stems from cultural assumptions about what it means to be historically significant. Did the subject have a lasting impact on society? Was she or he associated with other prominent figures? In American public culture, other values affect the way in which individual lives will be narrated: liberal individualism; the myth of progress and its individualized variant, “personal growth”; and the ideal of freedom, among other things.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s05">
         <title>MIMESIS<sub>2</sub>: AGENTS WRITING THE PAST</title>
         <p>Mimesis<sub>2</sub>constitutes what Ricoeur calls the “pivot” of his analysis in<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>. By describing mimesis<sub>2</sub>in this way, Ricoeur emphasizes its mediating function: in order for a narrative prefigured in mimesis<sub>1</sub>to be refigured by a reader in mimesis<sub>3</sub>, it must undergo a kind of alchemy that recuperates the same old stories of public opinion into potentially new stories about the possibilities of future action. In order to generate such possibilities—to enter the “kingdom of the<italic>as if</italic>,” as Ricoeur puts it—a narrative must be configured for optimal translation. This configuration phase features an “interplay of innovation and sedimentation” that ensures that the resulting narrative will not simply be a reproduction of the culture in which it was constructed but rather a singular work that presents resources for future action, whether literary or political (1984, 1:64–69). If the prefiguration of mimesis<sub>1</sub>highlights the similarities among historical narratives shaped by the same cultural context and historical subject, then the configuration of mimesis<sub>2</sub>highlights the remarkable variety within this same body of texts. Or, to focus on the significant agent, mimesis<sub>1</sub>prefigures the field of action in which the historical agent exists, whereas mimesis<sub>2</sub>features the configuring choices, self-conscious and otherwise, of the agent who writes, revises, or otherwise re-presents history.</p>
         <p>The moment of configuration occurs uniquely within each individual text, as guided by the interpretive capacities and “productive imagination” of an individual agent or group of agents: the creators of the text.<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>9</sup>
            </xref>An analysis of this mimetic moment focuses on the variety of ways in which the agent writing history configures the agency, relationships, and temporality of historical subjects within the confines of the text. To draw again on the example of juvenile biographies, some creators may explicitly draw attention to these choices in their texts. Some simply execute their conscious choices in ways that leave subtle marks on the texts. Still others may not be fully aware of their interpretive role, yet their texts nonetheless bear the marks of rhetorical selection and arrangement.<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>10</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>In constructing a biography, creators begin with a series of “facts” about the life of the historical figure. This “chronicle” is made available through “prefigured” understandings of what is worth noting for posterity. These facts anchor the narrative, yet they also allow for an interpretive range that in turn produces many different versions of the same story. In assembling their pieces of evidence, creators of the text employ several strategies of rhetorical arrangement. Many texts exhibit the marks of the organizing principles of selection and combination, which both fall easily under Ricoeur's rubric of “configuration.” Creators act on stories from the past by selecting, interpreting, and combining information about the lives of their subjects into a cohesive narrative. The choices of creators, in turn, configure historical personages as intelligible, compelling agents. Moreover, the unique configuration of agency in each individual text, which is layered upon the field of action as prefigured by<italic>doxa</italic>, shows how these texts function both to reinforce existing public memories and values and to become resources for future agents to draw on in taking new, innovative action.</p>
         <p>Ricoeur identifies three ways in which the mediating function of mimesis<sub>2</sub>operates in the configuration of narratives. First, configuration mediates between the individual event and the story as a whole by assigning an event a place of significance in the unfolding of a plot. Let us take, for instance, a book from the aforementioned Americans All series. Lillie Patterson's 1970<italic>Martin Luther King, Jr.: Man of Peace</italic>, which was awarded the first Coretta Scott King Book Award for African American children's literature, begins with an anecdote from King's childhood. This story narrates King's supposed first encounter with the “wall” of racism. When he enters school, his white friends are no longer allowed to play with him. He persists in seeking their company but is rebuffed: “Finally, their mother tried to tell Martin why. ‘You see, you are colored and they are white’” (Patterson 1970, 10). Unsatisfied, Martin goes to his own mother, who explains the history of slavery and its effects on their lives. She concludes by reminding her son that despite this past, “You are as good as anyone” (Patterson 1970, 10–12). As the opening scene, this vignette both introduces King as a child (creating an identificatory link with readers) and frames the remaining story about a confident man who worked to break down that “wall” of racism. Second, configuration joins and relates disparate aspects of the story, including various agents, actions, motivations, and outcomes. Patterson's text, for example, emphasizes both King's personal ambition and his cooperation with others. Members of his family play a key role, and the appearance of his wife, Coretta Scott, warrants an entire chapter (Patterson 1970, 33–38). Their marriage is represented not as mere love story but as the collaboration between two powerful social agents. The narrator explains that in accepting marriage to King, “Coretta decided to join the young minister and share his dream” (Patterson 1970, 37). Finally, configuration links the temporality of the story to deeper understandings of time as linear, periodic, cyclic, and so forth. This temporal mediation affects the potential interpretations of the narrative, and it has the capacity to change deeper understandings of time as well. In its narration of King's education, Patterson's text firmly situates him within a continuous tradition of African American intellectuals and nonviolent activists. The narrator reports King's entrance to Morehouse College at the age of fifteen, explaining, “Many college presidents, ministers, and famous leaders had been trained at Morehouse. Now Martin King, in 1944, began his training in the traditional ‘Morehouse spirit’” (Patterson 1970, 24–25). The narrator also describes his influences in seminary, where “great thinkers” such as Martin Luther, Henry David Thoreau, and Gandhi “fired [his] imagination” (Patterson 1970, 29). Such storytelling represents history as the continuous unfolding of these progressive philosophies.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s06">
         <title>MIMESIS<sub>3</sub>: AGENTS READING THE PAST AND ACTING INTO THE FUTURE</title>
         <p>Ricoeur specifies “refiguration” as the action of mimesis<sub>3</sub>. This moment, he explains, corresponds with the stage of the interpretive process that Gadamer calls “application” and that Ricoeur has referred to as “appropriation” (Gadamer<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>, 30–31, 307–11; Ricoeur 2007, 37, 118). The reader is the focal agent at this phase of the agential spiral. Because of her role in this phase, the reader is indeed essential to the entire threefold process: “Without the reader who accompanies it, there is no configuring act at work in the text; and without a reader to appropriate it, there is no world unfolded before the text” (1985, 2:164). The reader must “refigure” the work by reading it and translating it back into the world in which he exists. In this sense, “the act of reading is … the operator that joins mimesis<sub>3</sub>to mimesis<sub>2</sub>” (1985, 2:77).<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>11</sup>
            </xref>Adapting Aristotle's work from the<italic>Poetics</italic>and the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>, Ricoeur explains that the phase of mimesis<sub>3</sub>creates a crucial space for the translation of the imagined world of the work into the actual world of the reader—or, as Ricoeur calls it, the world of reference (1984, 1:71). From this vantage point, a narrative text can be understood as having certain, though not specific, effects on the world outside of language. Texts invite readers to envision a possible world that can be actualized in the material world through their action.</p>
         <p>For example, juvenile biographical texts engage young readers in the process of refiguration by inviting them to envision such a world through the lens of the past, in this case the experiences of a historical subject. Young readers are encouraged through their interaction with the reimagined worlds of these individual lives to extend each subject's lifework, follow a common historical trajectory, and become active reinterpreters of the public memory that sustains stories. Indeed, many texts explicitly instruct readers to honor the memory of an individual by acting as he or she did in the narrative. The last chapter of Patterson's biography of King begins by narrating his “last and grandest march,” in which he was “stopped in his crusade by assassination” (1970, 91). After describing the memorial services for King, the narrator reminds readers on the final page that “dreamers die, but dreams pass on.” The narrator then retraces the path of nonviolence from Thoreau to King, closing with a hopeful, subtle invitation to readers to continue the civil rights leader's work: “Somewhere, sometime, perhaps someone else will make Dr. King's dream his own” (Patterson 1970, 96). Like many biographies for children, Patterson's text concludes with an orientation toward refiguration.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s07">
         <title>CREATING THE SPIRAL: FROM MIMESIS<sub>3</sub>TO MIMESIS<sub>1</sub>
         </title>
         <p>Ricoeur, however, does not envision so explicit an invitation (or even exhortation) to action. Rather he insists on understanding how poetic or fictional texts refer to the world outside of language. In a significant move, Ricoeur rejects the false choice between conceiving of a text as either a transparent window into conscious authorial intention or as a closed, self-referential world. His approach instead treats authorship as one textual influence among many. Ricoeur says that his formulation of refiguration “is part of a hermeneutics that aims less at restoring the author's intention behind the text than at making explicit the movement by which the text unfolds, as it were, a world in front of itself” (1984, 1:81). Here Ricoeur directly engages the poststructuralist critique of authorial intention and textual reference. Yet he offers an insightful and sensible alternative to the idea that texts should be understood primarily as effects of language.<xref rid="r012" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>12</sup>
            </xref>Like Ricoeur, I see authorial/creative intention as an important aspect of reading texts of public memory that is nonetheless only part of the broader context of textual production and address. The intentions of creators leave indelible marks on the texts and thus on the public memories they disseminate. But many other factors affect the nature of a text, and Ricoeur's approach emphasizes that reality.</p>
         <p>Notably, Ricoeur's work also insists on the fact that texts have “real world” implications. But how do these implications transpire? What, exactly, happens after the text is read? How does an individual's response to a text produce action that continues the narration of human action across time? How does the seemingly closed circle of repetition and imitation become a progressive spiral of innovative action? Ricoeur rightly argues that “it is what comes after reading” that truly determines the transformative potential of a text (1985, 2:170). Although such statements gesture toward judgment and action, the “appropriation” about which Ricoeur speaks remains primarily a phenomenological experience of the reader rather than a public event: “By ‘appropriation,’ I understand this: that the interpretation of a text culminates in the self-interpretation of a subject who thenceforth understands himself better, understands himself differently, or simply begins to understand himself” (2007, 118). To move Ricoeur's “appropriation” outside the self and into the public world, I draw on the idea of “constitutive rhetoric,” first coined by Maurice Charland. This concept not only shifts appropriation into the public realm; it helps us to see how public memories can transform today's readers into tomorrow's agents. This transformation bridges the gap between mimesis<sub>3</sub>and mimesis<sub>1</sub>.</p>
         <p>Let us return to Ricoeur's understanding of “appropriation.” One of the advantages of Ricoeur's formulation is that it recognizes the significance of readerly agency while not relying on the idea of a self-possessed subject. Ricoeur argues that appropriation should not be understood as a function of a sovereign subject who “would possess the key” to understanding. Rather, the reader of a text “exchange[s] the<italic>me</italic>,<italic>master</italic>of itself, for the<italic>self</italic>,<italic>disciple</italic>of the text” (Ricoeur 2007, 37). Such a reader does not project him- or herself onto the text but receives “an enlarged self from the apprehension of proposed worlds which are the genuine object of interpretation” (Ricoeur<xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>, 182). The ability to perform this function depends on what Ricoeur calls “second-order reference,” which requires the reader to suspend concerns with whether the events “really” happened in order fully to understand the world opening up through her or his imaginative engagement with the text (Ricoeur<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">1977</xref>, 216–56).<xref rid="r013" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>13</sup>
            </xref>This “world of the work” that reveals itself before the text becomes the referent of fictional narrative. When engaged in interpretation, then, the reader should seek to understand this “proposed world” as one “which I could inhabit and in which I could project my ownmost possibilities” (Ricoeur 2007, 36). Fictional narratives, then, ultimately create an imagined world that prepares readers to act their way into it, so to speak. In<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>, Ricoeur explains that historical narrative employs a related but distinct “referential mode”: whereas fiction refers to an imagined world that could potentially be enacted in front of it, so to speak, historical narrative also claims to refer to an actual world that already exists behind it (1984, 1:82). Ricoeur productively blurs these distinctions in<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>, explaining that both types of narrative enable the reader to inhabit the “world of the text” (2004, 262).</p>
         <p>According to Ricoeur, this activity of appropriation occurs in a phenomenological, prepublic realm. To link this realm with the public world, I turn briefly to the vocabulary of constitutive rhetoric. In “Constitutive Rhetoric: The Case of the<italic>Peuple Québécois</italic>,” Maurice Charland explains how certain public texts, in addressing individuals as a group before that group actually exists in the extratextual world, can constitute a collective based on identity and oriented toward action. Charland uses the work of Kenneth Burke in order to shift the focus of rhetorical scholars away from “persuasion” and toward “identification” (1987, 133). Charland argues that public texts constitute subjects that didn't previously exist. In this sense, such texts do not<italic>persuade</italic>already existing individuals; they invite individuals to think of themselves in a manner that<italic>entails</italic>certain actions (1987, 134). This conceptualization extends Ricoeur's insights about appropriation and refiguration into the public world of action. Within this formulation, readers or listeners not only imagine themselves in new ways.<xref rid="r014" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>14</sup>
            </xref>They<italic>act</italic>as the world of the text invites them to do and in so doing close the gap between mimesis<sub>3</sub>and mimesis<sub>1</sub>, between reading and acting. This is the space that needs to be crossed in order to give the straight line between mimesis<sub>1</sub>and mimesis<sub>3</sub>its arc and so enable it to form a spiral. A child reading Patterson's book, for instance, might simply dismiss it as a stuffy story about a famous person long dead. Or, the reader may actively engage the narrator's subtle closing exhortation to “make Dr. King's dream his own” (96). Because of “Dr. King's dream,” the reader may speak up when she hears someone employ racial slurs or stereotypes or intervene when a classmate is unjustly punished or bullied. The reader thus acts her way into Dr. King's proposed world and becomes the kind of agent whose actions may in turn inspire others. Her actions may be so compelling as to become the subject of future memories. Thus, she also brings the spiral back to the point of mimesis<sub>1</sub>.</p>
         <p>Ricoeur, however, does not view the movement from mimesis<sub>3</sub>to mimesis<sub>1</sub>as a<italic>rhetorical</italic>moment. He employs rhetorical terminology as he discusses the techniques that the actual (as opposed to implied) author of a text utilizes in order to conceal “the violence … in the strategy of persuasion” (1988, 3:162). But he abandons this vocabulary when he approaches the reader, opting instead for the language of phenomenology and aesthetics (1988, 3:166–67). In part, he discards the language of the rhetorical tradition because of his limited view of rhetoric's capacity to produce real change in the world. He privileges poetics and philosophy “ontologically” over rhetoric, as Michael Leff has rightly pointed out (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>, 60). Ricoeur valorizes these intellectual traditions according to their ends: poetry results in a cathartic moment that purges old emotions and makes way for new ones, whereas rhetoric results in a persuasive moment that merely crystallizes the preexisting opinions of the audience. According to Ricoeur, these two ends are starkly opposed to one another: “Catharsis must, finally, be opposed to persuasion.” Unlike “all seduction or flattery” (i.e., rhetoric), catharsis stirs the emotions in order to enable “the creative imitation of human action” (1997, 66; see also 1977, 35). However, in the third volume of<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>, Ricoeur also admits that the set of effects attached to catharsis is “complex”: “It designates first of all the effect of the work that is more moral than aesthetic: new evaluations, hitherto unheard of norms, are proposed by the work, confronting or shaking current customs” (1988 3:176). Because catharsis possesses a moral component, Ricoeur reasons, it is capable of instructing. Many rhetorical scholars would likely take issue with his assigning such seemingly “persuasive” effects to the realm of poetics rather than rhetoric. Does not Aristotle say that the stirring of emotions is as essential as logical argument to persuasion and judgment (1991, 38–39)? And is not the persuasion that moves people to act a critical means of continuing the spiraling process of interpretation and action? In my view, catharsis alone—while often necessary—cannot create the same kind of raw material necessary for the movement from mimesis<sub>1</sub>to mimesis<sub>2</sub>; it can only create the conditions of possibility for human action. A change in one's state of mind cannot easily be translated into the media of memory, whether the memory takes the form of a monument, speech, or biography. What we describe as “memory” is such because it intends to orient us toward future public actions, such as remembering, protesting, voting, speaking, writing policies, and so on. A rhetorical approach insists that memories are important because they can produce identification and public action rather than just an individual change of mind.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s08">
         <title>CONCLUSION</title>
         <p>The concept of public memory has brought with it the idea that human agency permeates the entire process of historical interpretation, representation, and appropriation. For good or ill, the emergence of memory as an analytical category has extended the right to participate in this process of representation beyond the professional historian. As Carl Becker presciently noted in a 1932 American Historical Society address, every person has become a historian. Agents contributing to the process of public memory include historical personages (e.g., George Washington, Harriet Tubman, or your suffragist great-great-grandmother), the contemporaries that produced and preserved their historical records, historians who fix and “objectify” the historical record, teachers who use historical texts in their classrooms, politicians and activists who advocate for inclusion of certain versions of history, community leaders who critique faulty historical representations, children who learn and read about individuals from long ago, and many more. Each of these agents contributes to the process of public memory creation and circulation in a different way, sometimes performing various roles simultaneously. It is clear that these many agents are related through their involvement in this process. But how, precisely, are they connected? I have suggested that the agential spiral may help us begin to answer that question.</p>
         <p>This framework also enhances our ability to answer two other questions. First, how is it that human action both imitates the past and mobilizes it as a resource for innovation? I follow Ricoeur and others in working to open what has often been thought of as a closed hermeneutic circle. Although they labored to unpack it, thinkers as formidable as Martin Heidegger and later Hans-Georg Gadamer nevertheless expressed concern that this circle was in fact the philosophical equivalent of a death spiral (Gadamer<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>, 190–92, 265–66, 293–94; Heidegger<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>, 142–43). Ricoeur hopefully proposed that the hermeneutic circle be considered “not a vicious but a healthy circle” (1984, 1:3). Ricoeur perceived the many latent possibilities in humanity's abilities to create and deploy news stories about an old past. But his work needs to be infused with a rhetorical sensibility in order to make this a convincing view. I believe that rhetorical scholars would be well served by returning to Ricoeur to explore how the rhetorical interest in judgment and action might contribute to our understanding of this “healthy” spiral.</p>
         <p>Second, how do we account for the fact that the processes of public memory are both created by individual choices and nurtured in collective contexts? Many scholars have productively addressed this question by unpacking specific examples in which individuals or groups vie to control public memories. The critical framework I recommend offers a more systematic approach to this issue. To view representations of the past through the nested lenses of rhetoric, public memory, and the agential spiral is to focus on how human beings—individually and in groups—forge connections with people of other times through the medium of public agency. The agential spiral, derived from my reading of Ricoeur's “threefold mimesis,” aims to pinpoint three moments in the construction of narratives in which human action is represented and reinterpreted within a temporal structure. As a critical framework, the agential spiral helps us to view the creation of public memories at three key moments and to see the process as a coiling whole. Using this tool, we can better understand why certain memories persist in certain societies and how those memories powerfully connect people across time as well as space.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>In his 2010 book<italic>Public Forgetting</italic>, Bradford Vivian occasionally cites Paul Ricoeur's views on memory and forgetting. However, this engagement could not be described as sustained, as Vivian focuses more on other thinkers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Whether blurring or shoring up such binaries, rhetorical scholars have amply demonstrated that the question of agency remains significant. For a sense of the stakes of the debate over agency, see Geisler<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>and<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>and Lundberg and Gunn<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>. For background, see Bormann, Cragan, and Shields<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Gunn<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">2003a</xref>,<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">2003b</xref>,<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">2004a</xref>, and<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">2004b</xref>; Lundberg<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Many early articulations of memory as a category of study separate from history envisioned the two as substantively distinct, even starkly opposed. According to historian Kerwin Lee Klein, such distinctions can be traced back to two early texts in the field, Yosef Yerushalmi's<italic>Zakhor: Jewish History and Jewish Memory</italic>(1982), and Pierra Nora's “Between Memory and History,” which originally appeared as the introduction to his 1984<italic>Lieux de mémoire</italic>. “Each of these texts,” explains Klein, “identified memory as a primitive or sacred form opposed to modern historical consciousness” (2000, 127).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur further develops the idea of the chronicle in<italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>(<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, 166–81).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For an example of scholarship that employs the “authorship” trope, see Palmer<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>, 341–57. On “articulation,” see DeLuca<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 334–48, and Stormer<xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>, 257–84.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ricoeur explains that mimesis is “not just a break but also … a connection” (1984, 1, 46). He also highlights this dual nature of mimesis in his discussions of distanciation and appropriation, two dialectically opposed and mutually supporting movements within the process of interpretation (2007b, 35–51). However, Ricoeur limits these functions to textual spaces and does not push them into the public realm.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Indeed, in this epilogue, Ricoeur addresses precisely the relationship between the political and the individual in the act of forgiveness. He concludes that forgiveness—arguably one of the loftiest goals of remembering and forgetting—can only be accomplished by the individuals and that it loses its power when translated into public institutions (2004, 458, 477, 488).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Characterizing<italic>doxa</italic>as an alternative to episteme also illuminates a distinction commonly made between memory and history. Public and scholarly discussions often map memory onto the realm of the probable when the epistemic goals of academic history are believed to have fallen short.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I use the term “creators” to refer to all individuals whose ideas went into the creation of the text (e.g., author, illustrator, editor). This term foregrounds the cooperative aspect of producing books for children and marks the distance between perceived intentions of the author and the resulting text.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I acknowledge with Ricoeur that, in written discourse, “the author's intention and the meaning of the text cease to coincide” 2007b, 148). This does not mean that the text can be completely divorced from its creator; it means that critics must exercise caution when drawing conclusions about the intention of an author and the ultimate import of a text for a given audience. My analysis focuses on an intermediary moment prior to the achievement of any supposed authorial intention.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r011">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The reader to whom Ricoeur refers may also include those who listen to a speech, view a memorial, or visit a museum.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r012">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>This argument responds to the Derridean-inspired approach to literary studies dominant when<italic>Time and Narrative</italic>was published. The influence of this approach has waned somewhat, but its influence can be observed in the general tendency to approach texts as<italic>products</italic>of something—culture, historical context, ideology, and the like—rather than as<italic>producers</italic>of something—actions, decisions, new ideas and practices, etc.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r013">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Second-order or metaphorical reference points outside of the text to a reality that is extra-empirical. Metaphorical reference engages reality and truth no less than demonstrative discourse; it simply follows a different path toward revealing meaning. In joining two unlike terms, metaphor upsets first-order reference, forces the reader to interpret the statement in terms of a different second-order reference, and invites associations not otherwise accessible to the imagination (Ricoeur<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">1977</xref>, 216–56;<xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr">2007b</xref>, 8–11).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r014">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ritivoi contrasts the two different types of imagination at work in this process, saying that, unlike poetic imagination, “rhetorical imagination represents a direct and intentional propeller to action, as it identifies a probable realm not to make it an object of contemplation but to urge us to actualize it” (2006, 54).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list content-type="references">
         <title>WORKS CITED</title>
         <ref id="r1">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Anderson, Benedict</string-name>.<year>1991</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Imagined Communities</italic>
               </source>. Rev. ed.:<publisher-name>Verso</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r2">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Anderson, Dana</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“Questioning the Motives of Habituated Action: Burke and Bourdieu on Practice.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>255</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r3">
            <mixed-citation>
               <collab>Aristotle</collab>.<year>1991</year>.<source>
                  <italic>On Rhetoric: A Theory of Civic Discourse</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<string-name>George Kennedy</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r4">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Becker, Carl</string-name>.<year>1932</year>.<article-title>“Everyman His Own Historian.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>American Historical Review</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>37</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>221</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r5">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Blair, Carole</string-name>,<string-name>Marsha S. Jeppeson</string-name>, and<string-name>Enrico Pucci Jr.</string-name>
               <year>1991</year>.<article-title>“Public Memorializing in Postmodernity: The Vietnam Veterans Memorial as Prototype.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>77</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r6">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Bodnar, John</string-name>.<year>1992</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Remaking America: Public Memory, Commemoration, and Patriotism in the Twentieth Century</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r7">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Bormann, Ernest G.</string-name>,<string-name>John F. Cragan</string-name>, and<string-name>Donald C. Shields</string-name>.<year>2003</year>.<article-title>“Defending Symbolic Convergence Theory from an Imaginary Gunn.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>89</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r8">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Browne, Stephen H.</string-name>
               <year>1995</year>.<article-title>“Reading, Rhetoric, and the Texture of Public Memory.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>81</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>–<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r9">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Browne, Stephen H.</string-name>
               <year>2004</year>.<chapter-title>“Arendt, Eichmann, and the Politics of Remembrance.”</chapter-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Framing Public Memory</italic>
               </source>, ed.<string-name>Kendall R. Phillips</string-name>,<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>64</lpage>.:<publisher-name>University of Alabama Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r10">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Campbell, Karlyn Kohrs</string-name>.<year>2005</year>.<article-title>“Agency: Promiscuous and Protean.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Communication and Critical/Cultural Studies</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r11">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Charland, Maurice</string-name>.<year>1987</year>.<article-title>“Constitutive Rhetoric: The Case of the<italic>Peuple Québécois</italic>.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>73</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r12">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Cubitt, Geoffrey</string-name>.<year>2007</year>.<source>
                  <italic>History and Memory</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Manchester University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r13">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>DeLuca, Kevin</string-name>.<year>1999</year>.<article-title>“Articulation Theory: A Discursive Grounding for Rhetorical Practice.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>32</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>–<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r14">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Dickinson, Greg</string-name>,<string-name>Carole Blair</string-name>, and<string-name>Brian L. Ott</string-name>, eds.<year>2010</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Places of Public Memory: The Rhetoric of Museums and Memorials</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Alabama Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r15">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gillis, John R.</string-name>, ed.<year>1994</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Commemorations: The Politics of National Identity</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r16">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ermarth, Elizabeth Deeds</string-name>.<year>2001</year>.<article-title>“Agency in the Discursive Condition.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>History and Theory</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>34</fpage>–<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r17">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gadamer, Hans-Georg</string-name>.<year>1997</year>.<chapter-title>“Rhetoric and Hermeneutics.”</chapter-title>Trans.<string-name>Joel Weinsheimer</string-name>. In<source>
                  <italic>Rhetoric and Hermeneutics in Our Time: A Reader</italic>
               </source>, ed.<string-name>Walter Jost</string-name>and<string-name>Michael J. Hyde</string-name>,<fpage>45</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r18">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gadamer, Hans-Georg</string-name>.<source>
                  <italic>Truth and Method.</italic>
               </source>
               <year>1998</year>.<edition>2nd rev. ed</edition>. Trans.<string-name>Joel Weinsheimer</string-name>and<string-name>Donald G. Marshall</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Continuum</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r19">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Geisler, Cheryl</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“How Ought We to Understand the Concept of Rhetorical Agency? Report from the ARS.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Rhetoric Society Quarterly</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>34</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>9</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r20">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Geisler, Cheryl</string-name>.<year>2005</year>.<article-title>“Teaching the Post-Modern Rhetor: Continuing the Conversation on Rhetorical Agency.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Rhetoric Society Quarterly</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r21">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Greene, Ronald Walter</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“Rhetoric and Production: Rhetorical Agency as Communicative Labor.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>188</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r22">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gunn, Joshua</string-name>.<year>2003a</year>.<article-title>“Refiguring Fantasy: Imagination and Its Decline in U.S. Rhetorical Studies.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>89</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>–<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r23">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gunn, Joshua</string-name>.<year>2003b</year>.<article-title>“Response.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>89</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r24">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gunn, Joshua</string-name>.<year>2004a</year>.<article-title>“On Dead Subjects: A Rejoinder to Lundberg on (a) Psychoanalytic Rhetoric.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>90</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r25">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Gunn, Joshua</string-name>.<year>2004b</year>.<article-title>“Refitting Fantasy: Psychoanalysis, Subjectivity, and Talking to the Dead.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>90</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r26">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Hansen, Andrew</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“Dimensions of Agency in Lincoln's Second Inaugural Address.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r27">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Hauser, Gerard A.</string-name>
               <year>1999</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Vernacular Voices: The Rhetoric of Publics and Public Spheres</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of South Carolina Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r28">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Heidegger, Martin</string-name>.<year>1996</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Being and Time</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<string-name>Joan Stambaugh</string-name>.:<publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r29">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Kammen, Michael G.</string-name>
               <year>1991</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Mystic Chords of Memory: The Transformation of Tradition in American Culture</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Knopf</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r30">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Kansteiner, Wulf</string-name>.<year>2002</year>.<article-title>“Finding Meaning in Memory: A Methodological Critique of Collective Memory Studies.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>History and Theory</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>41</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>–<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r31">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Kearney, Richard</string-name>.<year>2007</year>.<source>Foreword to Paul Ricoeur,<italic>From Text to Action: Essays in Hermeneutics</italic>
               </source>,<fpage>ix</fpage>–<lpage>xi</lpage>. Trans.<string-name>Kathleen Blamey</string-name>and<string-name>John B. Thompson</string-name>.<edition>2nd ed</edition>.:<publisher-name>Northwestern University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r32">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Klein, Kerwin Lee</string-name>.<year>2000</year>.<article-title>“On the Emergence of Memory in Historical Discourse.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Representations</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r33">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Leff, Michael</string-name>.<year>1987</year>.<chapter-title>“The Habitation of Rhetoric.”</chapter-title>In<source>
                  <italic>Argument and Critical Practice: Proceedings of the Fifth SCA/AFA Conference on Argumentation</italic>
               </source>, ed.<string-name>Joseph Wenzel</string-name>,<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Speech Communication Association</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r34">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Leff, Michael</string-name>.<year>2003</year>.<article-title>“Tradition and Agency in Humanistic Rhetoric.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>36</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>–<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r35">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Lundberg, Christian</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“The Royal Road Not Taken: Joshua Gunn's ‘Refitting Fantasy: Psychoanalysis, Subjectivity, and Talking to the Dead’ and Lacan's Symbolic Order.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>90</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>495</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r36">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Lundberg, Christian</string-name>, and<string-name>Joshua Gunn</string-name>.<year>2005</year>.<article-title>‘Ouija Board, Are There Any Communications?’ Agency, Ontotheology, and the Death of the Humanist Subject; or, Continuing the ARS Conversation.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Rhetoric Society Quarterly</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>–<lpage>105</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r37">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Palmer, David L.</string-name>
               <year>1998</year>.<article-title>“Virtuosity as Rhetoric: Agency and Transformation in Paganini's Mastery of the Violin.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>84</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>–<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r38">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Palti, Elías</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“The ‘Return of the Subject’ as a Historico-Intellectual Problem.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>History and Theory</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>43</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r39">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Phillips, Kendall R.</string-name>, ed.<year>2004</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Framing Public Memory</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Alabama Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r40">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Rickman, H. P.</string-name>
               <year>1981</year>.<article-title>“Rhetoric and Hermeneutics.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r41">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>1977</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Rule of Metaphor: Multi-Disciplinary Studies of the Creation of Meaning in Language</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<string-name>Robert Czerny</string-name>.:<publisher-name>University of Toronto Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r42">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>1981</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Hermeneutics and the Human Sciences: Essays on Language, Action, and Interpretation</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<string-name>John B. Thompson</string-name>.:<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r43">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>1984</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Narrative</italic>
               </source>.<volume>Vol. 1</volume>. Trans.<string-name>Kathleen McLaughlin</string-name>and<string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r44">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>1985</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Narrative</italic>
               </source>.<volume>Vol. 2</volume>. Trans.<string-name>Kathleen McLaughlin</string-name>and<string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r45">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>1988</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Time and Narrative</italic>
               </source>.<volume>Vol. 3</volume>. Trans.<string-name>Kathleen McLaughlin</string-name>and<string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r46">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>1997</year>.<chapter-title>“Rhetoric—Poetics—Hermeneutics.”</chapter-title>Trans.<string-name>Robert Harvey</string-name>. In<source>
                  <italic>Rhetoric and Hermeneutics in Our Time</italic>
               </source>, ed.<string-name>Walter Jost</string-name>and<string-name>Michael J. Hyde</string-name>,<fpage>60</fpage>–<lpage>72</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r47">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Memory, History, Forgetting</italic>
               </source>. Trans.<string-name>Kathleen Blamey</string-name>and<string-name>David Pellauer</string-name>.<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r48">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>2007a</year>.<source>
                  <italic>The Conflict of Interpretations: Essays in Hermeneutics</italic>
               </source>. Ed.<string-name>Don Idhe</string-name>. New ed.:<publisher-name>Northwestern University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r49">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ricoeur, Paul</string-name>.<year>2007b</year>.<source>
                  <italic>From Text to Action: Essays in Hermeneutics</italic>
               </source>.<volume>Vol. 2</volume>. Trans.<string-name>Kathleen Blamey</string-name>and<string-name>John B. Thompson</string-name>.<edition>2nd ed</edition>.:<publisher-name>Northwestern University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r50">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Ritivoi, Andreea Deciu</string-name>.<year>2006</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Paul Ricoeur: Tradition and Innovation in Rhetorical Theory</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>State University of New York Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r51">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Sewell, William H., Jr.</string-name>
               <year>2005</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Logics of History: Social Theory and Social Transformation</italic>
               </source>.<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r52">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Shaw, David Gary</string-name>.<year>2001</year>.<article-title>“Happy in Our Chains? Agency and Language in the Postmodern Age.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>History and Theory</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r53">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Stormer, Nathan</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“Articulation: A Working Paper on Rhetoric and Taxis.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Quarterly Journal of Speech</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>90</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>257</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r54">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Turnbull, Nick</string-name>.<year>2004</year>.<article-title>“Rhetorical Agency as a Property of Questioning.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Philosophy and Rhetoric</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>37</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r55">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Vivian, Bradford</string-name>.<year>2010</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Public Forgetting: The Rhetoric and Politics of Beginning Again.</italic>
               </source>:<publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r56">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Warnick, Barbara</string-name>.<year>1987</year>.<article-title>“A Ricoeurian Approach to Rhetorical Criticism.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Western Journal of Speech Communication</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>227</fpage>–<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r57">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>White, Hayden</string-name>.<year>1975</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Metahistory: The Historical Imagination in Nineteenth-Century Europe</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r58">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Zarefsky, David</string-name>.<year>2010</year>.<chapter-title>“Public Address Scholarship in the New Century: Achievements and Challenges.”</chapter-title>In<source>
                  <italic>The Handbook of Rhetoric and Public Address</italic>
               </source>, ed.<string-name>Shawn J. Parry-Giles</string-name>and<string-name>J. Michael Hogan</string-name>,<fpage>67</fpage>–<lpage>85</lpage>.:<publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r59">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Zelizer, Barbie</string-name>.<year>1995</year>.<article-title>“Reading the Past against the Grain: The Shape of Memory Studies.”</article-title>
               <source>
                  <italic>Critical Studies in Mass Communication</italic>
               </source>
               <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>214</fpage>–<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r60">
            <mixed-citation>
               <string-name>Zelizer, Barbie</string-name>.<year>1998</year>.<source>
                  <italic>Remembering to Forget: Holocaust Memory Through the Camera's Eye</italic>
               </source>.:<publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
