<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jaesteduc</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">Journal of Aesthetic Education</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Illinois Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00218510</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15437809</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jaesteduc.48.2.0016</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5406/jaesteduc.48.2.0016</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Clinical Ethics as Applied Aesthetics</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Cattorini</surname>
                  <given-names>Paolo M.</given-names>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>08</day>
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>Summer 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">48</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jaesteduc.48.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>16</fpage>
         <lpage>35</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2014 by the Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5406/jaesteduc.48.2.0016"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Medical humanities and ethics are getting more and more important in Europe as essential disciplines of the core curriculum for health-care professionals. The idea of the physician as a technician shows itself to be unbearable because of the global historical changes we daily face in caring settings. We deal with chronic diseases, which require a sensitive physician/patient covenant and a good performance in communication skills1 because a whole life-style transformation is often necessary. Moreover, citizens are more informed about both the technological progress and their civil rights, so that a shared decision has to be prepared and implemented by exploring the emotional reactions to illness, by explaining the effects of different ways of treatment, and by revealing in advance the choices that could be taken.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>William F. May,<italic>The Physician’s Covenant: Images of the Healer in Medical Ethics</italic>(Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1983).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paolo M. Cattorini, “Narrating Pain: The Role of Medical Humanities,”<italic>Eubios: Journal of Asian and International Bioethics</italic>6 (2006): 177–81.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Rita Charon, “Narrative Contributions to Medical Ethics,” in<italic>A Matter of Principles? Ferment in U.S. Bioethics</italic>, ed. Edwin R. DuBose, Ron Hamel, and Laurence J. O’Connell (Valley Forge, PA: Trinity University Press, 1994), 260–83; Tony Hope, Kenneth W. M. Fulford, and Anne Yates,<italic>The Oxford Practice Skills Course: Ethics, Law, and Communication Skills in Health Care Education</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996); Paolo M. Cattorini, ed.,<italic>Insegnare l’etica medica: Obiettivi e metodi di valutazione dell’apprendimento</italic>(Milano: FrancoAngeli, 1999); Paolo M. Cattorini, “Bioethics. Training and Teaching,” in<italic>Proceedings of the First Symposium of the Council of Europe on Bioethics</italic>, Strasbourg, December 1989; and “Teaching Bioethics to Medical Students: Questions, Comments, Proposals,” in<italic>Primum Non Nocere Today: A Symposium on Pediatric Bioethics</italic>, ed. Roberto G. Burgio and John D. Lantos (Amsterdam: Excerpta Medica, Elsevier, 1994), 139–56; Kathryn M. Hunter,<italic>Doctors’ Stories: The Narrative Structure of Medical Knowledge</italic>(Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1991).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paolo M. Cattorini, “Aesthetics in Ethics: Narrative and Theoretical Dimensions of Moral Evaluation,”<italic>Eubios: Journal of Asian and International Bioethics</italic>19 (2009): 47–53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>A turmoil that great literature and cinema have shown in detailed, unforgettable forms. See, for example, the thoughts and sensibilities of tubercular patients in Thomas Mann’s German novel<italic>The Magic Mountain</italic>(published in 1924) or the family anxiety toward an impending death in the Swedish motion picture<italic>Viskiningar och rop</italic>(<italic>Cries and Whispers</italic>) by Ingmar Bergman (1973). See also the moral importance of the different English language used by the woman and by the male detective inspector in the film<italic>Vera Drake</italic>by Mike Leigh (2004): the abortion gets a completely different meaning.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See our opening lecture “Some Like It Humane: A qualcuno piace umano. Narrazione, etica e medicina: il caso del cinema,” Proceedings edited by the National Center for Rare Diseases,<italic>Meeting “Narrative Medicine,” Rapporti ISTISAN</italic>09/50, ISSN 1123–3117, 27° Suppl., Superior Institute of Health, Ministry of Health, Rome, 4 (2009): 69–85.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paolo M. Cattorini, “Movies on Bioethics: A Double Review and Some Steps Forward,”<italic>The Journal of Aesthetic Education</italic>2 (2012): 111–21.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>We are referring to the novel<italic>Il Gattopardo</italic>(English trans.<italic>The Leopard</italic>, [New York: Pantheon Books, 1960]) written in Sicily by Giuseppe Tomasi di Lampedusa and published in 1958.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sofia Vanni Rovighi,<italic>Elementi di Filosofia</italic>, vol. 2 (Brescia: La Scuola, 1964), 203.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Arthur C. Danto,<italic>The Abuse of Beauty: Aesthetics and the Concept of Art</italic>(Chicago: Open Court, 2003), a text analyzed by Stefano Velotti, “Il giudizio estetico,” in<italic>Introduzione all’estetica analitica</italic>, ed. Paolo D’Angelo (Roma-Bari: Laterza, 2008), 140–72. See also Paolo M. Cattorini, “Estetica nell’etica: In dialogo con Arthur C. Danto,”<italic>Medicina nei Secoli: Arte e Scienza. Giornale di Storia della Medicina—Journal of History of Medicine</italic>1–3 (2010): 129–42.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Giuseppe Angelini,<italic>Teologia morale fondamentale</italic>(Milano: Glossa, 1999); see also Giuseppe Angelini, “Il senso orientato al sapere,” in<italic>L’evidenza e la fede</italic>, ed. Giuseppe Colombo (Milano: Glossa, 1988), 387–443.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The faithfulness of the painter Cézanne to his work is commented on by Maurice Merleau-Ponty,<italic>Sens et non-sens</italic>(Paris: Nagel, 1948) in the chapter about Cézanne’s doubt.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For the ethical and aesthetical dimension of the word<italic>style</italic>, see the books by Luigi Pareyson,<italic>L’Estetica e i suoi problemi</italic>(Milano: Marzorati, 1961) and<italic>Estetica: Teoria della formatività</italic>(Milano: Sansoni, 1974), where the notion of “being formed” is deepened. Paolo M. Cattorini has commented on this line of thought in the following writings: the book<italic>Estetica nell’etica: La forma di un’esistenza degna</italic>(Bologna: Dehoniane, 2010) and the article “Aesthetics in Ethics: Narrative and Theoretical Dimensions of Moral Evaluation,”<italic>Eubios. Journal of Asian and International Bioethics</italic>19 (2009): 47–53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14.</label>
            <mixed-citation>It is not by chance, unfortunately, that a frequent way of using the successful book by Tom L. Beauchamp and James F. Childress,<italic>Principles of Biomedical Ethics</italic>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1994) sets aside the consideration of the aesthetic dimensions of moral judgment, with the exception of few references to the so-called “virtue ethics” and of brief quotations of important authors like Iris Murdoch or Stanley Hauerwas. A sad consequence of this bias is that, in training bioethics consultants, almost no attention is paid to aesthetic research conducted by contemporary philosophers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15.</label>
            <mixed-citation>We are referring to the ethical criticism proposed by Wayne C. Booth. See Paolo M. Cattorini, “Etica e critica letteraria. La lezione di Wayne C. Booth,”<italic>Rivista di Storia della Medicina</italic>1–2 (2010): 61–98. We recommend the following works by Booth:<italic>The Company We Keep: An Ethics of Fiction</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1998);<italic>The Rhetoric of Fiction</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1961 [1st ed.]; 1991 [2d ed.]);<italic>The Rhetoric of Rhetoric: The Quest for Effective Communication</italic>(Malden: Blackwell, 2004).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Samuel Taylor Coleridge,<italic>Biographia Literaria or Biographical Sketches of Literary Life and Opinions</italic>, ed. James Engell and Walter Jackson Bate (London: Routledge Kegan Paul, 1983), chap. 14; Italian edition and translation by Mario Luzi,<italic>Poesie e prose</italic>(Milano, Cederna 1949), 133. The text has also been translated by Paola Colaiacomo as<italic>Biographia literaria ovvero schizzi biografici della mia vita e opinioni</italic>(Roma: Editori Riuniti, 1991). Coleridge says that the willing suspension of disbelief for the moment “constitutes poetic faith.” We would like to emphasize the word<italic>faith</italic>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Martha C. Nussbaum,<italic>Poetic Justice: The Literary Imagination and Public Life</italic>(Boston: Beacon Press, 1995); and the two chapters written by Nussbaum, “The Absence of the Ethical: Literary Theory and Ethical Theory” and “The ‘Ancient Quarrel’: Literature and Moral Philosophy,” in<italic>Ethics, Literature, Theory</italic>, ed. Stephen K. George (Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield Publishers, 2005), 99–106, 139–52; Giovanna Rosa,<italic>Il patto narrativo</italic>(Milano: Il Saggiatore, 2008); Paolo M. Cattorini, “Un’estetica per la formazione etica,”<italic>βio-ethoς: Rivista di bioetica, morale della persona e medical humanities</italic>9 (2010): 7–18; and Cattorini,<italic>Un buon racconto. Etica, teologia, narrazione</italic>(Bologna: Dehoniane, 2007).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18.</label>
            <mixed-citation>May,<italic>The Physician’s Covenant</italic>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Hannah Arendt’s chapter on Isak Dinesen (1885–1962) in<italic>Men in Dark Times</italic>(Harcourt: Brace &amp; World, 1968). Arendt’s theory is analyzed by Francesca Cattaneo,<italic>Etica e narrazione: Il contributo del narrativismo contemporaneo</italic>(Milano: Vita e Pensiero, 2011).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20.</label>
            <mixed-citation>It is the distinction explored by Theodor W. Adorno,<italic>Ohne Leitbild: Parva Aesthetica</italic>(Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp Verlag, 1967);<italic>Minima moralia: Reflexionen aus dem beschädigten Leben</italic>(Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp Verlag, 1951);<italic>Philosophie der neuen Musik</italic>(Tübingen: J.C.B. Mohr, 1949);<italic>Beethoven:</italic>
               <italic>Philosophie der Musik</italic>(Frankfurt a. M.: Suhrkamp Verlag, 1993). See also Arthur C. Danto,<italic>The Transfiguration of the Commonplace: A Philosophy of Art</italic>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1981).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Arthur C. Danto,<italic>The Philosophical Disenfranchisement of Art</italic>(New York: Columbia University Press, 1986).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>Du texte a l’action. Essais d’hermeneutique</italic>(Seuil, Points, 1998); Ricoeur,<italic>Soi-même comme un autre</italic>(Paris: Seuil, 1990); Peter Kemp, “Per un’etica narrativa: Un ponte tra l’etica e la riflessione narrativa in Ricoeur,”<italic>Aquinas</italic>31 (1988): 435–57. See also Richard Rorty,<italic>Contingency,</italic>
               <italic>Irony and Solidarity</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), who underlines the role of literature in changing the philosophical vocabulary.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23.</label>
            <mixed-citation>John F. Szwed,<italic>Jazz 101: A Complete Guide to Learning and Loving Jazz</italic>(New York: Hyperion, 2000); Italian translation:<italic>Jazz! Una guida completa per ascoltare e amare la musica jazz</italic>(Torino: Edt, 2009), 34.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paolo M. Cattorini, “Ben temperato: Etica, storia e musica,”<italic>Rivista di Storia della Medicina</italic>1–2. (2011): 77–102.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Flavia Monceri,<italic>Musica e razionalizzazione in Max Weber: Fra Romanticismo e Scuola di Vienna</italic>(Napoli: ESI, 1999), 78–79.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref26">
            <label>26.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Stuart Isacoff,<italic>Temperament: How Music Became a Battleground for the Great Minds of Western Civilization</italic>(New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 2001); Italian translation:<italic>Temperamento. Storia di un enigma musicale</italic>(Torino: Edt, 2001), 182 ff.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref27">
            <label>27.</label>
            <mixed-citation>See Monceri,<italic>Musica e razionalizzazione in Max Weber</italic>, 96–97; and Luigi Rognoni, “Introduzione. La musicologia filosofica di Adorno,” in Adorno,<italic>Philosophie der neuen Musik</italic>; Italian translation:<italic>Filosofia della musica moderna</italic>(Torino: Einaudi, 1959), xvi.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref28">
            <label>28.</label>
            <mixed-citation>These statements by Schönberg, “Probleme des Kunstunterrichts,” in<italic>Musikalisches Taschenbuch</italic>(Wien, 1911), are quoted and analyzed by Adorno in<italic>Filosofia della musica moderna</italic>, 48.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref29">
            <label>29.</label>
            <mixed-citation>We are reviving an intuition by Ronald Dworkin,<italic>Life’s Dominion: An Argument about Abortion, Euthanasia, and Individual Freedom</italic>(New York: Knopf, 1993); Italian translation<italic>Il dominio della vita: Aborto, eutanasia e libertà individuale</italic>(Milano: Comunità, 1994), 275. Ethical decisions are usually taken as we were evaluating the narrative quality of the next chapter of our life’s book or choosing the artistic gesture that fits the precious picture we have been painting.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref30">
            <label>30.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Friedrich Nietzsche,<italic>The Birth of Tragedy out of the Spirit of the Music</italic>(London: Penguin, 1995); Italian translation:<italic>La nascita della tragedia</italic>(Roma-Bari: Laterza, 1982).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref31">
            <label>31.</label>
            <mixed-citation>“Resistence or surrender?” we might ask, by using theologian Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s words. See his work<italic>Widerstand und Ergebung: Briefe und Aufweichnungen aus der Haft</italic>(München: Chr. Kaiser Verlag, 1970).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref32">
            <label>32.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Blaise Pascal,<italic>Pensées et opuscules</italic>(Paris: Hachette, 1917). See the first thought.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref33">
            <label>33.</label>
            <mixed-citation>DuBose et al.,<italic>A Matter of Principles?</italic>The ethical importance of sentiments is highlighted by Eugenio Lecaldano,<italic>Prima lezione di filosofia morale</italic>(Roma-Bari: Laterza, 2010); Maurizio Balistreri,<italic>Etica e romanzi. Paradigmi del soggetto morale</italic>(Firenze: Le Lettere, 2010); Piergiorgio Donatelli,<italic>La filosofia morale</italic>(Roma-Bari: Laterza, 2001); Dabney Townsend,<italic>Hume’s Aesthetic Theory: Taste and Sentiment</italic>(London: Routledge, 2001); Jane Adamson, Richard Freadman, and David Parker, eds.,<italic>Renegotiating Ethics in Literature, Philosophy and Theory</italic>(Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998); Anthony Cunningham,<italic>The Heart of What Matters: The Role of Literature in Moral Philosophy</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 2001).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref34">
            <label>34.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernard Williams,<italic>Ethics and the Limits of Philosophy</italic>(London: Collins and Harvard University Press, 1985); and Williams,<italic>Shame and Necessity</italic>(Berkeley: University of California Press, 1993).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref35">
            <label>35.</label>
            <mixed-citation>We are endorsing Warren T. Reich’s thesis, “Alle origini dell’etica medica: Mito del contratto o mito di cura?” in<italic>Modelli di medicina: Crisi e attualità dell’idea di professione</italic>, ed. Paolo M. Cattorini and Roberto Mordacci (Milano: ESU, 1993), 35–60.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref36">
            <label>36.</label>
            <mixed-citation>We have criticized new forms of theodicy in the introductory essay “Misericordioso? Lo scandalo del male nelle religioni monoteiste,” in<italic>Il significato della sofferenza: Tre religioni monoteiste interpretano l’esperienza della malattia</italic>, ed. Mario Picozzi, Luca Violoni, and Paolo M. Cattorini (Milano: FrancoAngeli, 2004), 21–25.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref37">
            <label>37.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Nietzsche,<italic>The Birth of Tragedy</italic>, Ital. trans.,<italic>La nascita della tragedia</italic>, 101. The Platonic dialogue gave future generations the image of a new form of art, the image of the novel.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref38">
            <label>38.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Giovanni Reale, “Platone,”<italic>Enciclopedia Filosofica</italic>(Milano: Bompiani, 2006), 8696.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref39">
            <label>39.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paolo M. Cattorini,<italic>Estetica nell’etica: La forma di un’esistenza degna</italic>(Bologna: Dehoniane, 2010).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref40">
            <label>40.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Hans Georg Gadamer,<italic>Wahrheit und Methode</italic>(Tübingen: Mohr, 1972); Italian translation:<italic>Verità e metodo</italic>(Milano: Bompiani, 1983), 545–46, 548.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref41">
            <label>41.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Robert Spaemann,<italic>Glück und Wohlwollen: Versuch über Ethik</italic>(Stuttgart: Ernst Klett Verlag für Wissen und Bildung, 1989); Italian translation:<italic>Felicità e benevolenza</italic>(Milano: Vita e Pensiero, 1998), 14, 26.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref42">
            <label>42.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Immanuel Kant,<italic>Kritik der Urtheilskraft</italic>(Berlin: Lagarde, 1790); English translation:<italic>The Critique of Judgment</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1978); Italian translation:<italic>Critica del giudizio</italic>(Bari: Laterza, 1972).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref43">
            <label>43.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paolo M. Cattorini,<italic>Bioetica e cinema:</italic>
               <italic>Racconti di malattia e dilemmi morali</italic>, 2d ed. (Milano: FrancoAngeli, 2006).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref44">
            <label>44.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sandra Shapshay, ed.,<italic>Bioethics at the Movies</italic>(Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2009).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref45">
            <label>45.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Paola Dalla Torre, ed.,<italic>Cinema contemporaneo e questioni bioetiche</italic>(Roma: Studium, 2010).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="ref46">
            <label>46.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Juan Jorge Michel Fariña and Jan Helge Solbakk, eds.,<italic>(Bio)ética y cine</italic>(Buenos Aires: Letra Viva, 2012).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
