<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">jroyaanthinst</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100913</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>The Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">13590987</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">14679655</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">23011430</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Cultural property, enunciatory authority, and the nation</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Being `rasikas': the affective pleasures of music and dance spectatorship and nationhood in Indian middle-class modernity</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Kalpana</given-names>
                  <surname>Ram</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>17</volume>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i23011419</issue-id>
         <fpage>S159</fpage>
         <lpage>S175</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2011 Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain &amp; Ireland</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:role="external-fulltext-any"
                   xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9655.2011.01694.x"
                   xlink:title="an external site"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>The long-standing dominance of history in the adjudication of debates on postcolonialism and modernity in India has resulted in the relegation of the knowledge claims of `classical' performance traditions and aesthetic concepts to the domain of the essentializing and the untrustworthy. This paper argues that performances of music and dance have preserved an understanding of tradition that is more dynamic and agential than that put forward by nationalist understandings of tradition, and that aesthetic conceptions continue to illuminate the values and efficacy of these practices in engaging the affects of spectators. The paper explores in particular the subject position of the rasika as offering a distinctive way of inhabiting the present. The class privilege implicit in being able to take up such an invitation is explored in the second part of the paper. La longue domination de l'histoire dans l'orientation des débats sur le post-colonialisme et la modernité en Inde a relégué les prétentions au statut de savoir des arts performatifs et des concepts esthétiques « classiques » au domaine des choses essentialisantes et peu fiables. Le présent article fait valoir que les performances de musique et de danse ont préservé une compréhension de la tradition plus dynamique et agentielle que celle mise en avant dans les interprétations nationalistes, et que les conceptions esthétiques continuent de mettre en lumière les valeurs et l'efficacité de ces pratiques en faisant appel aux affects des spectateurs. L'article explore en particulier la position de sujet du rasika comme une manière différente d'habiter le présent. Le privilège de classe, implicite dans la possibilité d'accepter une telle invitation, est exploré dans la deuxième partie de l'article.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="d3971e134a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e141" publication-type="other">
Zarilli (2000)</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e148a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e155" publication-type="other">
Viswanathan and Allen
(2004).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
      <ref-list>
         <title>REFERENCES</title>
         <ref id="d3971e174a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e178" publication-type="other">
Alter, J. 2004. Yoga in modern India. Princeton: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e185a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e189" publication-type="other">
Bhakle, J. 2005. Two men and music: nationalism in the making of an Indian classical tradition. Delhi:
Permanent Black.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e199a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e203" publication-type="other">
Bourdieu, P. 1984 [1979]. Distinction: a social critique of the judgement of taste (trans. R. Nice). London:
Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e213a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e217" publication-type="other">
Chakrabarty, D. 2000. Provincializing Europe: postcolonial thought and historical difference. Princeton:
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e228a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e232" publication-type="other">
Chatterjee, P. 1994. The nation and its fragments: colonial and postcolonial histories. Delhi: Oxford University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e242a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e246" publication-type="other">
Coorlawalla, U. 2005. The Birth of Bharatanatyam and the Sanskritised body. In Rukmini Devi Arundale:
a visionary architect of Indian culture and the performing arts (ed.) A. Meduri, 173-94. Delhi: Motilal
Banarsidass Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e259a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e263" publication-type="other">
Danesi, M. 1993. Vico, metaphor and the origin of language. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e270a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e274" publication-type="other">
Derrida, J. 1982. Signature, event, context. In Margins of philosophy (trans. A. Bass), 307-30. Brighton:
Harvester.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e284a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e288" publication-type="other">
Eco, U. 1984. Semiotics and the philosophy of language. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e295a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e299" publication-type="other">
Jain, K. 2007. Gods in the bazaar: the economies of Indian calendar art. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e307a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e311" publication-type="other">
Kersenboom, S. 1995. Word, sound, image: the life of the Tamil text. Oxford: Berg.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e318a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e322" publication-type="other">
Kosofsky Sedgwick, E. &amp; A. Frank (eds) 1995. Shame and its sisters: a Silvan Tomkins reader. Durham, N.C.:
Duke University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e332a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e336" publication-type="other">
Krishnamurti, Y. with R. Khandekar 1995. A passion for dance: my autobiography. New Delhi: Viking
Penguin.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e346a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e350" publication-type="other">
Mall, A. 2007. Structure, innovation and agency in pattern construction: the kolam of Southern India. In
Creativity and cultural improvisation (eds) E. Hallan &amp; T. Ingold, 55-78 (ASA Monographs 44). Oxford:
Berg.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e363a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e367" publication-type="other">
Meduri, A. (ed.) 2005. Rukmini Devi Arundale: a visionary architect of Indian culture and the performing arts.
Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e377a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e381" publication-type="other">
Mohanty, C. 1991. Under Western eyes: feminist scholarship and colonial discourse. In Third World women
and the politics of feminism (eds) C. Mohanty, A. Russo &amp; L. Torres, 51-80. Bloomington: Indiana University
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e395a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e399" publication-type="other">
The NatyaSastra 1996. English translation by A. Rangacharya with critical notes. New Delhi: Munshiram
Manoharlal Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e409a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e413" publication-type="other">
O'Shea, J. 2005. Rukmini Devi: Rethinking the Classical. In Rukmini Devi Arundale: a visionary
architect of Indian culture and the performing arts (ed.) A. Meduri, 225-46. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass
Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e426a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e430" publication-type="other">
-2007. At home in the world: Bharata Natyam on the global stage. Middletown, Conn.: Wesleyan
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e440a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e444" publication-type="other">
Parkins, W. &amp; G. Craig 2006. Slow living. Oxford: Berg.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e451a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e455" publication-type="other">
Pinney, C. 1997. Camera Indica: the social life of Indian photographs. Chicago: University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e462a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e466" publication-type="other">
Ram, K. 1995. The politics of a 'rasa': postcolonial contestations over 'sringara rasa'. Paper presented at
Anthropology Seminar Series of Australian National University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e477a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e481" publication-type="other">
-2000. Dancing the past into life: the rasa, nrtta and raga of immigrant existence. The Australian
Journal of Anthropology 11, 261-73.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e491a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e495" publication-type="other">
-2008. A new consciousness must come': affectivity and movement in Tamil Dalit women's activist
engagement with cosmopolitan modernity. In Anthropology and cosmopolitanism: rooted, feminist and
vernacular perspectives (ed.) P. Werbner, 135-55. Oxford: Berg.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e508a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e512" publication-type="other">
-2009a. Modernity as a 'rain of words': tracing the flows of 'rain' between Dalit women and intellec-
tuals in Tamil Nadu. Asian Studies Review Special Issue: The cultural politics of disadvantage in South Asia,
33: 4&gt; 501-17-</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e525a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e529" publication-type="other">
-2009b. Dancing off-stage: nationalism and its 'minor practices' in Tamil Nadu. In Dance matters:
performing India (eds) P. Chakravorty &amp; N. Gupta, 3-25. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e539a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e543" publication-type="other">
-- 2009c. 'I now have Arivu [Knowledge] which dispels fears': instabilities in what it means to 'know'
and the effects of Tamil political party and civil society intellectuals on rural women's discourses. South
Asia Special Issue: Democracy, civil society and governance: contemporary challenges in India, XXXII: 3,
485-500.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e559a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e563" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. 1978 [1975]. The rule of metaphor: multi-disciplinary studies in the creation of meaning in language
(trans. R. Czerny with K. McLaughlin &amp; J. Costello). London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e574a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e578" publication-type="other">
Said, E. 1978. Orientalism. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e585a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e589" publication-type="other">
Sarabhai, M. 2005. Rukmini Devi: an aesthetic visionary. In Rukmini Devi Arundale (ed.) A. Meduri, 97-100.
Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e599a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e603" publication-type="other">
Sarkar, S. 2002. Beyond nationalist frames: postmodernism, Hindu fundamentalism, history. Bloomington:
Indian University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e613a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e617" publication-type="other">
Sharma, P.L. 1992. Kala: manifestation in the arts. In Kalatattvakosa: a lexicon of fundamental concepts of the
Indian arts (ed.) K. Vatsyayan, 202-14. New Delhi: Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Arts/Motilal
Banarsidass Publishers.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e630a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e634" publication-type="other">
Shulman, D. 2005. The buzz of God and the click of delight. In Aesthetics in performance: formations
of symbolic construction and experience (ed.) A. Hobart &amp; B. Kapferer, 43-63. Oxford: Berghahn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e644a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e648" publication-type="other">
Subramanian, L. 2006. From the Tanjore court to the Madras Music Academy: a social history of music in South
India. New Delhi: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e659a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e663" publication-type="other">
Viswanathan, T. &amp; M. Allen 2004. Music in South India: experiencing music, expressing culture. Oxford:
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e673a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e677" publication-type="other">
Wade, B. 1979. Music in India: the classical traditions. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e684a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e688" publication-type="other">
Wilce, J. 2009. Crying shame: metaculture, modernity and the exaggerated death of lament. Oxford:
Wiley-Blackwell.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d3971e698a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d3971e702" publication-type="other">
Zarilli, P. 2000. Kathakali dance-drama. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
