<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">renadram1964</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="ucp-id">rd</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Renaissance Drama</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">04863739</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">21643415</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/678121</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">RD2014027</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Figures of Pain in Early Modern English Tragedy</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="af1" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Kimberly</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Huth</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af1">California State University, Dominguez Hills</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2014</year>
            <string-date>Fall 2014</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>42</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>673118</issue-id>
         <fpage>169</fpage>
         <lpage>190</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2014 Northwestern University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>Northwestern University.</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/678121"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>The relationship between physical pain and figurative language, metaphor in particular, is highly fraught, yet many early modern English tragedies are built upon a dual foundation of spectacular episodes of suffering and elaborate poetic conceits. Ingenuity in both language and spectacle certainly helped sell tickets in a saturated dramatic marketplace, but the cooperative conjunction of pain and metaphor more importantly helped these plays achieve the didactic and cathartic goals of the genre. Recent scholarship has demonstrated the many ways sensory experience contributed to understanding in the theater of Shakespeare and his contemporaries.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">
            <sup>1</sup>
         </xref>Unlike the sights, sounds, or even smells of a performance, however, the sensation of pain was neither felt by actors nor shared with audience members, hindering direct communication of an experience central to tragedy. Compounded with the potential meaninglessness of pain and the isolation that can accompany extreme suffering, this lack of direct communication could impede audience engagement with the subject matter and characters of the play. Metaphor and other types of figurative language are a means for tragic playwrights to meet the challenges of the dramatic representation of pain. These tropes offer a way to “make sense” of pain: to unite the physical sensation portrayed by the actor with an intellectual, emotional, and metaphysical exploration of the significance of pain in human life. Figures of pain—the bodies on the tragic stage and the imagery in the lines they speak—stimulate both imaginative and interpretive engagement with dramatic representations of physical suffering, drawing on audience members’ own experiences with pain that can resonate with what they see in the theater. These figures intertwine cognitive and affective response to pain, organizing this multifaceted experience in a way that reshapes physical torment into the performative and transformative suffering of tragedy.</p>
      <p>Early modern dramatists crafted a literary tradition that employed sight and sound to convey the sensations and significance of touch. In doing so, they provide us with a valuable opportunity to reconsider the relationship between pain and language, a conceptual problem in fields as diverse as medicine, politics, and art. While the figurative representation of pain can lead to problems of displacement and misinterpretation, metaphor remains a prominent and powerful tool in communicating pain, one that not only early modern playwrights but also people experiencing pain continually use. This essay will consider those metaphoric representations, both in early modern tragedy as well as in the words of artists who have incorporated their own suffering into their work, to demonstrate that figurative language operates as part of a larger epistemological system interweaving cognitive response, embodied empathy, and affective alignment. Figures of pain in early modern tragedy use an audience’s knowledge of the experience of pain as the basis for understanding tragic representation.</p>
      <p>The challenge for the writer of tragedy is to make the experience of pain as meaningful for the audience as it is for the character who suffers. Tragic spectatorship must be, in some way, dangerous.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2">
            <sup>2</sup>
         </xref>But the physical distance between the actors and the audience prevents the direct contact needed to convey sensations of touch, of which pain is one especially complex type.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3">
            <sup>3</sup>
         </xref>The process of pain perception, nociception, engages a host of bodily systems ranging from the skin to multiple areas of the brain; pain response involves physical, emotional, and cognitive reactions, further influenced by interpersonal and cultural factors.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4">
            <sup>4</sup>
         </xref>As pain researcher Irene Tracy explains, the complexity of the neurobiological response to painful stimuli mirrors the complicated nature of what we generally mean by “pain”: “So there are all these different parts of the brain—these sort of attentional networks, these emotional networks, motivational networks, decision making networks, sensory areas. And because pain is a complicated, multi-dimensional, multi-factorial experience, it has to access all those different parts of the brain in order to generate the experience that is pain.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5">
            <sup>5</sup>
         </xref>Pain perception is a biological process that is part of the human experience of the world, but it is also unique to each individual. This combination of physical, cultural, cognitive, and affective qualities makes pain an experience that is both universal and subjective.</p>
      <p>The universal nature of physical pain provides a potential foundation for audience engagement with tragic drama, but the highly subjective nature of pain experience presents major challenges in the expression or communication of its effects on the bodies and minds of those who suffer. That is to say, even if the audience sees and reacts to the dramatic enactment of pain, the significance of the character’s suffering is not necessarily obvious. Assigning meaning to pain is a delicate endeavor, one that risks giving sensibility to otherwise “senseless” violence. Kathleen M. Sands warns, “it is equally perilous to find and not to find meaning in suffering. To find meaning in suffering is in some sense to accept it, enabling the legitimation of suffering that may be unjust or unnecessary. But to find no meaning in suffering is to leave history not only unredeemed but unmourned and forgotten. And so it is with tragedy.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6">
            <sup>6</sup>
         </xref>The interpretation of pain is at the very heart of tragedy. And so must be the communication of the entire pain experience.</p>
      <p>The challenges inherent in such communication for early modern tragedy, especially the role of metaphor in this communication, can be usefully illuminated through consideration of a modern intersection of art and pain, the online collection<italic>The Pain Exhibit</italic>(<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://PainExhibit.org">http://PainExhibit.org</uri>). This project grew from founder Mark Collen’s experience of chronic pain, through which he came to realize that “Art was far more effective at communicating pain than words ever could be” (“History”). Many of the artists represented in the exhibit echo Collen’s sentiment, having turned to visual art when language failed them. Yet while verbal expression certainly has its limitations, the focus on “words” alone can eclipse a larger issue in artistic engagement with pain experience.<italic>The Pain Exhibit</italic>is a collection of visual artworks, but the artists’ own explanations of their works attest to the fact that words can produce effective artistic imagery as well. What this site and its artists really have to teach us about artistic representation of pain is that the process of making pain comprehensible, intelligible, and meaningful, for oneself and for others, necessitates imagery. The insufficiency is not in words themselves but in literalism.</p>
      <p>The works in the exhibit illustrate the profound effects of pain on an individual’s identity and self-image through several recurring themes: the fragmentation of the body and mind; a focus on a single, exaggerated part of the body; the permeability of the body’s borders; and the intrusive presence of foreign objects in the body. Collen’s piece<italic>CP II</italic>, for example, consists of a plaster foot with steel razor blades sticking through the skin (“Suffering” gallery), a visual representation that externalizes the experience of pain and employs imagery that concretizes the physical sensations felt in the body. The body itself often seems to hide pain rather than reveal it. In the words of Joan Crutcher, “No one can see the agony inside of me” (<italic>Fibromyalgia Pain Body</italic>, “Pain Visualized” gallery). The lack of visibility hinders expression, and tangible images stand in for less observable (if more medically accurate) causes of pain. In<italic>“My Migraine”—Self Portrait</italic>(“Portraits of Pain” gallery), Lynda Robinson incorporates numerous images intended to correspond to her invisible suffering, and the commentary included with the painting explains each one: “The screwdriver illustrates the searing, throbbing pain that is concentrated on the side of my head. … The needles in my hand signify the numbness. … The lettering signifies the vision disturbance.” This process of signification aims for a sort of synesthesia that will communicate a sense of touch through the sense of sight. The inclusion of images of concrete objects like razor blades and screwdrivers is an attempt to materialize a subjective sensory experience in a way that others may possibly understand. While very few people have experienced what is depicted in these works, such as a screwdriver pushing into one’s temple, the imagery approximates the physical sensations in the artists’ bodies in the hopes of prompting empathy through imaginative if not actual experience. Audiences are invited to imagine these sensations as a key step in the communication of pain experience.</p>
      <p>These images, these metaphors, are potent tools in the expression of pain. Another artist, Susan Gofstern, writes, “Pain is a solitary truth that defies communication, maddeningly subjective and resistant to language and measurement. To live in pain is to live in isolation. In the absence of speech, visual metaphor is a constructive tool, creating artifacts that can function as the speaking self” (<italic>Resonance: Erasure</italic>, “Portraits of Pain” gallery). Gofstern’s analysis of the use of metaphors of pain sees the trope as a “constructive” means of coping with pain’s destructive force. She and the other artists whose works are displayed in<italic>The Pain Exhibit</italic>clearly see the value of visual metaphors in the expression and communication of pain, but their own words affirm the power of verbal imagery to contribute to the creation of meaning. In both visual and verbal media, these artists turn to figurative imagery because it is the literal, not strictly the linguistic, that fails them—a fruitful lesson to bring to bear on early modern tragedy.</p>
      <p>In spite of the prominent role of metaphor in both contemporary visual art and the tragedies of early modern England, however, metaphor continues to occupy a precarious position in pain studies because even as it creates a concrete image, it can disconnect representation from physical reality. In particular, Elaine Scarry and Susan Sontag have critiqued any process, especially metaphorization, that renders bodily experience abstract. Though Scarry and Sontag each focus on different aspects of the relationship between metaphor and pain, both identify the potential distortion created by metaphoric thinking as a fundamental problem in using this trope to comprehend and communicate the experience of suffering.</p>
      <p>For Scarry, metaphorical descriptions demonstrate a fundamental problem in the expression of pain. She identifies two particular types of metaphors that those in pain often use: one that specifies an “external agent” of the pain, as in “It feels like a hammer coming down on my spine”; and a second that specifies “bodily damage,” as in “It feels as if my arm is broken … and [the bone is] sticking through the skin.” Both types of metaphors are made visible in the works in<italic>The Pain Exhibit</italic>. The trouble with these images—of “weapon” and “wound”—is that they are not identical with pain but rather are used “associatively” to describe characteristics of an otherwise nonreferential experience. Such language is inherently unstable and “permits a break in the identification of the referent and thus a misidentification of the thing to which the attribute belongs.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7">
            <sup>7</sup>
         </xref>In other words, if we move the agency of pain outside the body through an image like Robinson’s screwdriver, or locate pain in a wound that does not actually exist like the razor blade lacerations on Collen’s plaster foot, we risk separating the experience from the body who suffers through it. In the context of Scarry’s work—modern torture and warfare—this abstraction of pain from the real bodies involved can impede empathetic and humanitarian response to such atrocities.</p>
      <p>Sontag, by contrast, critiques the way illness and the suffering associated with it become metaphors. In the case of tuberculosis in the Romantic period, for example, the disease became the vehicle in the metaphor that Sontag calls the “secular myth of self-transcendence.” In the twentieth century, she contends, the notions and attitudes that contributed to the creation of such a “master narrative” are split between insanity and cancer, but her argument is that in any era, metaphorizing illness misrepresents that experience of suffering and can lead to rhetoric that blames the patient. If illnesses like TB or insanity express the patient’s character, it is a short step to claiming that the patient somehow caused the illness. “My point,” she writes, “is that illness is<italic>not</italic>a metaphor, and that the most truthful way of regarding illness—and the healthiest way of being ill—is one most purified of, most resistant to, metaphoric thinking.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn8">
            <sup>8</sup>
         </xref>Like Scarry, Sontag urges a resistance to metaphors because the associative process of metaphoric thinking misrepresents and abstracts the “real” experience of the body in pain.</p>
      <p>Yet metaphor is a part of the reality of pain—the reality as lived by individuals like the artists of<italic>The Pain Exhibit</italic>or the reality as constructed by early modern playwrights for characters within a play and an audience in a theater. Despite Scarry’s and Sontag’s cogent and important critiques of the conjunction of pain and metaphor in politics, war, and medicine, this and other forms of figurative language are particularly useful to writers of tragedy, often for the very same reasons they are treacherous in these other discursive fields. Metaphors both convey information and organize knowledge, essential functions in transforming representations of physical pain into the existential suffering of tragedy. The differing perspectives on the relationship of pain and metaphor offered by Scarry and Sontag actually highlight the duality of figures of pain playwrights exploit: pain serves as both tenor and vehicle of metaphor in early modern tragedy. In these plays, physical pain is something that must be communicated to audiences, but it is also, and more importantly, a means of conveying something beyond bodily experience. Metaphor’s particular combination of cognitive and affective response makes it an essential methodology in the tragic representation of suffering.</p>
      <p>Four aspects of metaphor in particular account for its valuable role in the construction of the tragic. The first two qualities—that metaphor is associative and interactive—concern the way the figure creates knowledge through the rhetorical union of two concepts or things. The associative qualities of metaphor are the very basis of Scarry’s critique, yet the other side of the danger of semantic inaccuracy is the potential for innovative conceptual reorganizations that enable learning and the development of new paradigms (especially in scientific fields<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn9">
            <sup>9</sup>
         </xref>). In the<italic>Rhetoric</italic>, Aristotle theorized that effective metaphors balance the strange with the familiar to bring the audience to a new knowledge or perspective; the farther the distance covered, the more perceptive the metaphor in discerning resemblances between the tenor and vehicle.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn10">
            <sup>10</sup>
         </xref>And the more inventive the metaphoric association, the more remarkable the knowledge gained through the figure. Max Black’s conception of metaphors as “interactive” extends this idea to make the relationship between tenor and vehicle mutually informative, drawing on what audiences know about both subjects to change the way each is viewed.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn11">
            <sup>11</sup>
         </xref>And because the metaphoric association is built on both resemblance and dissimilarity, I. A. Richards has argued, the interaction produces a “peculiar modification” in audience understanding<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn12">
            <sup>12</sup>
         </xref>—that is, a new interpretation. The interactive quality of metaphor is the essence of its interpretive power—which is precisely the focus of Sontag’s critique of metaphors of illness and yet is a recognized and valued aspect of metaphoric language even in early modern rhetorical theory, as Maria Franziska Fahey’s recent work on the trope has demonstrated.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn13">
            <sup>13</sup>
         </xref>George Puttenham, for example, advocated the use of metaphor “to enforce a sense and make the word more significative”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn14">
            <sup>14</sup>
         </xref>—an evocative linking of sensory experience and conceptual interpretation.</p>
      <p>The second two qualities of metaphor important to early modern tragedy’s use of the figure pertain to the effects of this conceptual reorganization on the audience. Many theorists of metaphor describe the figure as “provoking,” “inviting,” or “asking” something of the audience.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn15">
            <sup>15</sup>
         </xref>Thus, the third notable quality of metaphor is its function as, in the words of Ted Cohen, an “intimate” figure that forges a community by initiating a “cooperative act of comprehension.” Cohen argues that metaphor, as a special type of speech, emphasizes a process present but generally unstated in all communication: “Three aspects are involved: (1) the speaker issues a kind of concealed invitation; (2) the hearer expends a special effort to accept the invitation; and (3) this transaction constitutes the acknowledgment of a community.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn16">
            <sup>16</sup>
         </xref>In doing the work of deciphering the relationship between tenor and vehicle, the strange and the familiar, audiences become part of an interpretive community, both drawn into the interpretation intended by the maker of the metaphor and participating in the creation of new knowledge formulated through the metaphoric conjunction. If the metaphor is accepted, and thus both the tenor and vehicle are “modified” in the process, the poet and the audience have been carried by the metaphor into a new discursive community. In the tragic theater’s metaphors of pain, this process paves the way for further audience engagement with the play in the forms of empathy for the characters and potential adoption of a new worldview.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn17">
            <sup>17</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Metaphors of pain, however, require special attention due to the multivalent nature of an experience that encompasses physical, cognitive, emotional, and cultural aspects. In many ways, metaphor is suited to the complexity of pain for, as Paul Ricoeur asks, “if metaphor consists in talking about one thing in terms of another, does it not consist also in perceiving, thinking, or sensing one thing in terms of another?” The processes of interpretation instigated by metaphor are themselves diverse, and Ricoeur’s theory of metaphor extends the power of resemblance beyond cognition:<disp-quote>
            <p>If metaphor adds nothing to the description of the world, at least it adds to the ways in which we perceive; and this is the poetic function of metaphor. This still rests upon resemblance, but at the level of feelings. In symbolizing one situation by means of another, metaphor “infuses” the feelings attached to the symbolizing situation into the heart of the situation that is symbolized. In this “transference of feelings,” the similarity between feelings is induced by the resemblance of situations. In its poetic function, therefore, metaphor extends the power of double meaning from the cognitive realm to the affective.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn18">
                  <sup>18</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>The affective power of metaphor, the fourth aspect vital to its employment in early modern tragedy, is key for playwrights as they draw on physical knowledge of pain to elicit cathartic response to what is portrayed on stage.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn19">
            <sup>19</sup>
         </xref>These playwrights do not primarily use metaphor to convey the sensations of pain that are unfelt by the audience but rather to draw on audience experience of physical pain as a foundation for the construction of the philosophical, metaphysical, or spiritual perspective of the tragedy. The interconnection of ways of knowing—cognitive, physical, affective—is very much in line with early modern “understanding,” described by William N. West as a holistic experience that integrates the intellectual and the corporeal.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn20">
            <sup>20</sup>
         </xref>Creating such understanding of pain in the theater is a conceptual challenge that early modern playwrights met through metaphor.</p>
      <p>Figures of pain take many forms in early modern tragedy. One of the simplest, and relatively rare, types is the use of metaphor or another figure of comparison to describe a painful sensation through association; playwrights seem to resort to linguistic figures only when the figure on stage, the actor, is incapable of making pain or its full effect visible through his body. These moments can be seen as a sort of sensory catachresis, and the resulting figures form a sensory shorthand of familiar tropes. Such figures were especially useful in stage representations of one particular form of violence: poisoning. Murder by poisoning often leaves little bodily evidence. A few outward signs were cited in early modern English courts as evidence of poison, such as alterations in skin color or vomiting,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn21">
            <sup>21</sup>
         </xref>but these signs were neither reliably evident nor convincing. Moreover, they are not always easy to portray on stage. Imagery of burning, however, externalizes and concretizes the effects of poison in the victim’s body.</p>
      <p>There are numerous examples of the image of fiery poison that attest to its value as a tragic commonplace for this sensory experience. In Thomas Middleton’s<italic>The Lady’s Tragedy</italic>(also called<italic>The Second Maiden’s Tragedy</italic>), Votarius is pricked by a poisoned sword and cries out, “My breast is all afire—O—” (5.1.108).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn22">
            <sup>22</sup>
         </xref>In<italic>The Tragedy of Valentinian</italic>by Francis Beaumont and John Fletcher, the title character combines the standard metaphor with the hyperbole expected of a Roman emperor: “I find an hundred Hells, an hundred Piles / Already to my funerals are flaming.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn23">
            <sup>23</sup>
         </xref>And in John Webster’s<italic>The White Devil</italic>, Brachiano returns to a simpler version when his helmet is sprinkled with poison: “O my braine’s on fire” (5.3.4).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn24">
            <sup>24</sup>
         </xref>This imagery is immediately comprehensible but not simplistic. Quite the opposite: the efficiency and efficacy of the metaphor in the sensory realm enable the development of complex themes in the tragedy as a whole. The imagery of fire is multivalent in early modern culture, and these metaphors of pain often serve to link the deaths of these poisoned characters to other aspects of the plays’ plots through repetition of the motif in different situations. The flexibility of this image allows playwrights to organize the representation of pain and audience responses to character suffering. This capacity of metaphor to make artistic sense out of the sensory experience of the pain of poisoning is especially evident in the chaos of Middleton’s<italic>Women, Beware Women</italic>.</p>
      <p>In the final scene of this play, several tragic revenge plots coalesce in the performance of a court masque for the Duke of Florence. Hippolyto, a nobleman who has been having an incestuous affair with his niece Isabella while also resenting his sister Livia’s affair with the young factor Leantio, is cast in the role of a young lover who is to be hit by Cupid’s arrows (5.1.28–37).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn25">
            <sup>25</sup>
         </xref>In preparing for the play, Guardiano, whose ward was to be married to Isabella, orchestrates the murder of Hippolyto by poisoning the prop arrows. Guardiano’s plan literalizes and then subverts a traditional metaphor of love—much like Hippolyto himself has subverted traditional familial and romantic/erotic love by desiring his own niece and cuckolding her fiancé. So that the audience can recognize Hippolyto’s death as the culmination of this revenge plot, the effect of the arrows’ poison must be made evident. As he suffers, Hippolyto employs the standard imagery of fire to communicate his pain and the cause of his death: “O, death runs through my blood, in a wild flame too,” he exclaims as he asks for someone to dispatch him quickly “To quench this fire in blood” (5.1.177, 187).</p>
      <p>Given the disorder of the final scene, it is hardly surprising that the onstage audience, the Duke, fails to understand the play. At one point he asks, “What’s the conceit of that?” (5.1.157). Caught up in the play, the Duke seeks artistic interpretation, the “conceit,” not criminal explanation of the deaths he witnesses. His question indicates the failure of the masque to make sense out of the suffering the Duke mistakenly thinks is part of the tragic script. Offstage audiences, however, have a larger play-text to draw from when trying to parse the significance of this violence. Hippolyto’s metaphors of fire connect his pain with earlier moments in the play’s exploration of familial relationships and corporeal identity. Astute listeners will remember that in act 4, Hippolyto railed against his sister Livia’s affair with Leantio, saying that his zeal to put an end to her relationship with someone below his family’s class “Puts fire into my blood” (4.2.14). The fire metaphor of the final scene recalls this motif of “fire in the blood” and frames his physical suffering within a larger tragic structure. Fittingly for a revenge plot, Hippolyto is brought down in a manner that references his own character traits.</p>
      <p>The metaphors Middleton employs to communicate the sensations of Hippolyto’s pain and compose ongoing imagistic motifs that structure the play—contradicting the warnings of both Scarry and Sontag—are only part of<italic>Women, Beware Women</italic>’s larger figurative system. Poison itself appears throughout the play, amassing an assortment of meanings before it is deployed as a weapon in the final act. Before her affair with Hippolyto begins, Isabella meditates on the divine uses of poison: “That providence that has made ev’ry poison / Good for some use, and sets four warring elements / At peace in man, can make a harmony / In things that are most strange to human reason” (1.2.181–84). Rather than the invisible cause of pain that must be revealed through metaphor, here poison serves as the vehicle for explaining the mysterious “harmony” in even the most unfortunate of circumstances. When we see poison again, it carries with it the duality of the “strange” and the harmonious; Middleton, the providential force behind the plot of the play, develops an artistic harmony out of the chaotic confusion unleashed by the violence and pain of the final scene. Pain can serve as vehicle for such tragic harmonizing because it is a physical sensation that, most of the time, requires little verbal explication. Hippolyto’s death by poisoned arrow may include figurative descriptions of the feeling of his pain, but other characters who suffer more visually spectacular deaths (such as Isabella, who dies when doused with molten gold) do not use metaphors in the same way. They simply do not need to. The only figure of pain required is the body of the actor.</p>
      <p>In the spectacular moments of pain so often associated with early modern tragedy, the character’s suffering can be conveyed visually; language reinforces and interprets what has already been communicated. In Philip Massinger’s<italic>The Roman Actor</italic>, two characters, Junius Rusticus and Palphurius Sura, are tortured on stage. These men do not describe their pain; they merely smile through their torture and attribute their fortitude to Stoic philosophy (3.2.97–99).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn26">
            <sup>26</sup>
         </xref>The lack of language does not impede the communication of pain. Those watching the torture react bodily to the scene before them, and one witness, Parthenius, states, “my sinews shrink, / The spectacle is so horrid” (3.2.82–83). As an onstage witness, Parthenius provides, on the one hand, a model for responding to this sight and, on the other, a clear indication that such a model is unnecessary. Any witness, or audience member, would be subject to the bodily reaction he experiences.</p>
      <p>In scripting this physical reaction, Massinger foreshadows modern neurological research on the biological effects of seeing another person in pain.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn27">
            <sup>27</sup>
         </xref>Recent medical research utilizing MRI scans has revealed that subjects display similar brain responses when they experience pain themselves and when they know another person is in pain, a tangible bodily reaction to others’ physical suffering. These results show the involvement of the somatosensory cortex and limbic areas of the brain as well as what is called the “pain matrix”—the rostral anterior cingulate cortex, bilateral anterior insula, brain stem, and cerebellum. These areas of the brain differ from those involved in cognitively adopting the perspective of someone in pain or actively trying to put oneself in his or her position.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn28">
            <sup>28</sup>
         </xref>The findings suggest a physical basis for empathy, as seeing someone in pain generates a bodily response in the subject that is more reflective of the current state of the other than of the self.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn29">
            <sup>29</sup>
         </xref>Or, as one study defines empathy, “shar[ing] the other person’s feelings in an embodied manner.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn30">
            <sup>30</sup>
         </xref>Thus, in<italic>The Roman Actor</italic>, Parthenius’s own “sinews shrink” when he witnesses the torture of the others.</p>
      <p>Thankfully for audiences of tragic theater, embodied empathy does not perfectly align the physical experiences of two people. When an individual observes another in pain, a “large portion,” but not all, of the pain matrix is activated. The “attenuated form” of the neurological response “enables observers to experience another’s pain to the extent that it may motivate an empathic response but not overwhelm the observer with personal distress and self-protection.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn31">
            <sup>31</sup>
         </xref>This is precisely the note that theater seeks to strike with audiences. Theatrical performances present sights and sounds that communicate pain to audiences who are able to engage with it cognitively as well as physically, instinctively, or emotionally. Though metaphors are not often needed to convey pain, when they do appear and combine with the sensory cues offered by actors, the associative qualities of the trope do not abstract from real experience but rather, to return to Puttenham’s words, “enforce the sense” of it. That “sense” is always twofold: sensory perception<italic>and</italic>interpretive significance. Whereas early modern playwrights see little need for the type of descriptive metaphors Scarry critiques, they seek to do exactly what Sontag advises against: creating “master narratives” of pain through which audiences can access the significance of that physical sensation for the metaphysical perspective of the tragedy. In terms of metaphor, pain does not need to take the role of tenor; even if it is not felt by audience members, it is mediated through other senses of sight and sound. And once established as an experiential element of a tragedy, it can serve as the vehicle for a philosophical framework that structures the play as a whole. In metaphor’s union of the strange and the familiar, pain becomes the known term; what is portrayed on stage resonates with audiences’ own experience and bodily knowledge. Early modern tragedy uses metaphor most often to make meaning out of pain, building on the sensory connection that exists within the theater.</p>
      <p>These empathic responses, however, need not be limited to the location of the playhouse. As Donald C. Freeman has argued, the human tendency to schematize bodily experience and then “project elements of this structure and components of our physical experience onto our non-physical, abstract experience” is at work in the process of writing, reading, and watching tragedy.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn32">
            <sup>32</sup>
         </xref>Any engagement with tragedy necessarily entails at least an imagination of the types of pain that actors would portray on stage, but there is an undeniable intensity to theatrical portrayal of pain, as evidenced by those performances that cause audience members to look away or to wince. These types of reactions demonstrate the power of imagination, as if we feel in our own bodies what is enacted on stage. Through an inductive process stimulated by such imagination, tragedy uses representations of pain from things like poison or torture to communicate something about human suffering of all types. It is a genre built on associations of physical and metaphysical suffering that creates interpretive communities with a new understanding—physical, cognitive, affective, spiritual—of human pain.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn33">
            <sup>33</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>This process is illustrated evocatively in and by Shakespeare’s<italic>King Lear</italic>. In this play, physical pain is both a sensory experience and a metaphor for other, less corporeal types of suffering—a point noted both by audiences of the play and by its characters. These characters practice a distinct way of appealing to bodily knowledge to understand otherwise unintelligible things that does not treat physical pain merely as a prompt for philosophical reflection. Before the intense physical suffering of the characters even begins, Lear frequently uses metaphors and other figurative tropes that transform nonphysical pain into something more tangible when his emotional or psychological anguish seems to him utterly incomprehensible. Like many of the metaphors discussed above, these figures often ask audiences to imagine a type of physical pain they may not have actually experienced. But Lear’s imagery then uses those concrete associations to interpret the world in which he finds himself. The pain of his thankless daughters, for instance, is so baffling to Lear that he must consider it metaphorically in order to grasp associatively what he cannot process directly: “[She] Look’d black upon me, strook me with her tongue, / Most serpent-like” (2.4.160–61); “[You are] a disease that’s in my flesh, / Which I must needs call mine. Thou art a bile, / A plague-sore, or embossed carbuncle, / In my corrupted blood” (2.4.222–25); and of course, “How sharper than a serpent’s tooth it is / To have a thankless child!” (1.4.288–89).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn34">
            <sup>34</sup>
         </xref>This last image may be the most recognized, but it is the image of the diseased blood that brings Lear closest to understanding his own role in creating his thankless children, a theme he picks up later in his summative vision of life: “I am bound / Upon a wheel of fire, that mine own tears / Do scald like molten lead” (4.7.45–47). The metaphors reveal that his own flesh and blood, his own tears—and by extension his own tragic mistakes—play a role in his torture. And because this perspective is expressed metaphorically, Lear effectively draws everyone—himself, the other characters, the audience—into an interpretive community formed around his pain.</p>
      <p>The affective consequence of this method of understanding the world through the experience of pain is an abject pessimism expressed by Gloucester through a figure that transforms personal suffering into a general metaphysical truth. Before his blinding, Gloucester proclaims a belief in benevolent nature and the gods.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn35">
            <sup>35</sup>
         </xref>After his blinding, Gloucester holds an entirely different perspective: “As flies to wanton boys are we to th’ gods, / They kill us for their sport” (4.1.36–37). Audience members have already seen, heard, and experienced the pain of Gloucester and the other characters that is the basis of this analogy, and thus the figure works not to communicate pain but instead to interpret it. It teaches us that in this life, human suffering is divine entertainment. There will be no providential intervention to set this world aright, and, as Albany states in the next scene, continuing the use of rhetorical figures to enforce these realizations, “Humanity must perforce prey on itself, / Like monsters of the deep” (4.2.46–49).</p>
      <p>Gloucester’s lines have rightly been at the center of many critical readings of<italic>King Lear</italic>. As an example of how the play uses figurative language to formulate a fatalistic worldview, the image of the helpless flies underscores the characters’ descent into what Susan Oldrieve has called “experiential misery”: “here is the moment when emotion explodes, overwhelming reason and the capacity to make knowledge out of allegory.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn36">
            <sup>36</sup>
         </xref>Emily R. Wilson argues that the figure is indicative of “tragic overliving,” Gloucester’s blindness symbolic of his having lived too long and seen too much to integrate his experience into the narrative of his life.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn37">
            <sup>37</sup>
         </xref>Yet he does produce a figure of pain that helps audiences to integrate the events on stage into a tragic narrative, a figure that enables us to make sense out of the sensory experience we have just watched. It is the figure’s relationship to the physical performance that makes it powerful. As Edward L. Rocklin writes, the image of men as flies at the mercy of capricious gods “resonates so intensely because in performance it is incarnated before it is articulated.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn38">
            <sup>38</sup>
         </xref>We see the pain before we hear the rhetorical reflection on its meaning, and the lines are in fact a union of two figures of pain: Gloucester himself and the simile he produces.</p>
      <p>The prominence of figurative language in<italic>King Lear</italic>could be seen as evidence of trauma, especially considering the passage of time between Gloucester’s blinding and his resonant simile. Drawing on the work of Cathy Caruth, who defines trauma as an event that cannot be assimilated by an individual at the moment it happens, Patricia Cahill argues that early modern texts represent trauma not through ocularity but through touch, in particular a failure of touch: “Early modern traumatic representation … entails that which is literally incomprehensible: it cannot be grasped and taken in hand.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn39">
            <sup>39</sup>
         </xref>Gloucester’s comparison of men to flies at the hands of the gods may be such a belated attempt to interpret his suffering and that of his dramatic counterpart, Lear; and Lear’s imagery of his thankless daughters is a means of making tangible what he can hardly believe to be the reality of his situation. Yet even if these characters cannot immediately assimilate their suffering into a cohesive worldview, their figures of pain help the audience do just that.</p>
      <p>For at least one audience member of<italic>King Lear</italic>, however, viewing the play in the theater is itself a traumatic event that inhibits the interpretation necessary for assimilating the pain and violence into a unified tragic vision. In his lectures on Shakespeare’s tragedies, A. C. Bradley, perhaps in spite of himself and his sensibilities, is particularly interested in tragic pain—or, more precisely, he is interested in tragic suffering and the way the physical pain depicted on stage gets in the way of this more lofty ideal. Bradley repeatedly comments on the excessive or intolerable nature of the pain represented in Shakespeare’s plays, but there are methods of analysis that make some instances of pain more “bearable”: “if we fully imagine the inward tragedy in the souls of the persons as we read, the more obvious and almost physical sensations of pain or horror do not appear in their own likeness, and only serve to intensify the tragic feelings in which they are absorbed.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn40">
            <sup>40</sup>
         </xref>Here Bradley shifts the audience’s imaginative focus to the “inward” rather than the physical pain of the characters, espousing a classic view of tragedy that places bodily pain in service to something else—a different, purer sort of “tragic feeling.” The means of accessing the tragedy makes a significant difference to Bradley, as is abundantly clear in his analysis of<italic>King Lear</italic>. This play, he states, “is imperfectly dramatic, and there is something in its very essence which is at war with the senses, and demands a purely imaginative realization.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn41">
            <sup>41</sup>
         </xref>Watching and listening to<italic>King Lear</italic>in the theater is, for Bradley, counterproductive; the realization of the characters and their actions on stage actually inhibits the stirring of “tragic feelings” he takes to be Shakespeare’s goal.</p>
      <p>While Bradley’s discomfort in the theater may obstruct the interpretive work needed to comprehend those “tragic feelings,” his judgment artificially divorces the sense from the significance in the play’s world of pain. The horrifying, unbearable, excessive moments of bodily pain that Bradley cannot tolerate are the same events that stun Gloucester, Albany, and the other characters into their pessimistic perspectives of the world. The reaction to the physical pain portrayed on stage brings Bradley to the same stunned state as the characters. In particular, the blinding of Gloucester is a moment that, for Bradley, can only succeed for reading audiences. In the theater, “the mere physical horror of such a spectacle” overwhelms the “purely tragic emotions” with revulsion and shock. Reading, however, allows the “mere imagination [of] the physical horror” to be “so far deadened that it can do its duty as a stimulus to pity, and to that appalled dismay at the extremity of human cruelty which it is the essence of the tragedy to excite.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn42">
            <sup>42</sup>
         </xref>Bradley’s affective response exhibits the same effects of reason overwhelmed as other critics see in Gloucester and Caruth sees in victims of trauma. As horrible as scenes like his blinding may be, as much as we may want to keep that horror in check in our imaginations as Bradley does, these moments serve a vital purpose in bringing the audience to the same affective state as the characters with whom they empathize. To borrow the language of<italic>Roman Actor</italic>, our “sinews shrink” when Gloucester is tortured, and we understand his pessimistic theology because the play has deliberately brought us along with him. To judge by Bradley’s reaction, it has tortured us in a way, too.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn43">
            <sup>43</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>The bleak outlook developed through Gloucester’s pain and figurative language is hardly brightened in the following scenes that bring the deaths of Cordelia and Lear. As a proponent for a “redemptivist” reading of the play,<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn44">
            <sup>44</sup>
         </xref>Bradley actually finds value in the very suffering that traumatizes him. Of Lear in his final scenes, Bradley writes, “there is no figure, surely, in the world of poetry at once so grand, so pathetic, and so beautiful as his. Well, but Lear owes the whole of this to those sufferings which made us doubt whether life were not simply evil, and men like flies which wanton boys torture for their sport.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn45">
            <sup>45</sup>
         </xref>For Bradley, the suffering that produces the worldview described by Gloucester is the very same that creates the beauty of<italic>King Lear</italic>—or, more generally, the aesthetic accomplishment of any tragedy. Bradley may want to limit his engagement with the more spectacular moments of physical pain, but those scenes of pain and their correspondent metaphoric interpretations are in fact essential to tragedy as understood and practiced in early modern theater. The metaphoric quality of early modern tragic construction even seems to infect Bradley’s critical voice. In a striking figure of his own, he construes traumatic suffering as transformative: “And here adversity, to the blessed in spirit, is blessed. It wins fragrance from the crushed flower.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn46">
            <sup>46</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Bradley’s figure is a common reading of tragic pain—it is through suffering that a character’s virtue and strength are revealed—that, especially in early modern England, is greatly influenced by religious discourses on martyrdom and the<italic>imitatio Christi</italic>tradition.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn47">
            <sup>47</sup>
         </xref>That the incredibly dire vision of human helplessness in the face of divine sport that defines<italic>King Lear</italic>would inspire such an idea is not surprising. Bradley’s flower image potentially reclaims suffering as a meaningful experience from the metaphysical chasm opened up by Gloucester’s image of men as flies. What is remarkable, however, is that the conjunction of these two figures exactly reflects the metaphoric world constructed in another early modern tragedy, John Webster’s<italic>The Duchess of Malfi</italic>.</p>
      <p>Webster’s play, more than any other surveyed here, links the very genre of tragedy to metaphorical thinking. His self-conscious engagement with the genre incorporates both tragic action and tragic reflection or interpretation. That is to say, Webster integrates his own Bradley-like critics into the play itself, making room for both the pessimistic figure of pain and the redemptivist response to it, offering multiple options for affective response to the audience. His universe is one of doubt and uncertainty, and the play seems to be suggesting that metaphor—with all the issues of imprecision and distortion that accompany associative thinking—is an apt cognitive process for facing the tragic world. In the imagery of poison as fire, plays like<italic>Women, Beware Women</italic>use association to convey both sensory information and thematic significance. In<italic>King Lear</italic>, Shakespeare’s characters speak in metaphors that build on sensory experience to process spiritual truth. But in<italic>The Duchess of Malfi</italic>, metaphor becomes, in essence, the only way of knowing because the play continually undermines the veracity of sense perception. Over the course of the play, the Duchess has three children. Numerous characters see her pregnant body, and yet Bosola, employed to spy on her, still must seek further proof that she is with child. At one point, he feeds her unripe apricots, which cause her to go into labor. To conceal her condition and confuse Bosola, a rumor is circulated that she was poisoned—a reinterpretation of her pain that is so effective that even Bosola fears that the apricots might have been poisoned without his knowledge (2.2.31–32).<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn48">
            <sup>48</sup>
         </xref>And in the final act, the Duchess’s brother the Cardinal is murdered as his guards stand just outside the door, listening to his cries for help. But they had been told by the Cardinal himself that he would “faigne [him]self in danger” (5.4.15), and so they refuse to be taken in by what they think is his counterfeiting. The uncertainty of Webster’s tragic world infects the reality of sense experience and sets the stage for a proliferation of metaphor.</p>
      <p>Without the benefit of physical senses, the characters seem especially eager to nail down the philosophical “sense” of their experience, to get to the meaning of their suffering; thus the play’s series of<italic>sententiae</italic>that seem to provide the necessary metaphysical interpretation. It is Bosola who provides the metaphor that closely echoes Gloucester’s imagery of tragic helplessness in<italic>King Lear</italic>. Though Bosola participates in the torture and murder of the Duchess, the experience changes him; her suffering elicits prosocial feelings of empathy that lead Bosola to vow to help her husband Antonio revenge her death. This choice instigates a traditional revenge plot, but the play rejects Bosola’s attempt to rewrite the script. When he seeks out Antonio, he accidentally kills him in the dark, a turn of events that prompts Bosola to lament: “We are meerely the Starres tennys-balls (strooke, and banded / Which way please them)” (5.4.54–55). This dark image directly parallels Gloucester’s image of men as flies, though Bosola exacerbates the hopelessness of the situation by replacing “gods” with the fatalistic “stars” and casting humans as inanimate objects.<italic>The Duchess of Malfi</italic>—which includes psychological and physical torture, a severed hand, wax effigies, and a werewolf (“on the In-side” [5.2.18])—in many ways ups the ante of<italic>King Lear</italic>’s pessimism by combining it with horror and depravity so extreme that it could only be the product of blind fate. In these lines, the play provides one of the most bleak metaphysical representations of human life in early modern tragic drama. Later, Bosola describes the accidental death of Antonio as “Such a mistake, as I have often seene / In a play” (5.5.94–95), forging a connection between early modern understanding of the genre and Bosola’s metaphorically developed philosophy.</p>
      <p>Bosola’s figure is only one of the play’s many attempts to make sense out of seemingly senseless cruelty. The same world of suffering that leads to his image of the stars’ tennis match inspires a very different response from Antonio. In conversation with the Duchess, Antonio delivers one of the most notable of the play’s many “wise” statements: “Man (like to<italic>Cassia</italic>) is prov’d best, being bruiz’d” (3.5.71). In a precursor to Bradley’s meditations on the fragrance of a crushed flower, Antonio also responds to tragic events with an argument that our best selves are revealed through suffering, making pain a valuable experience and tragedy a process of identity formation. Antonio’s perspective, like Bradley’s, grows out of confrontation with a tragic world that appears destined to crush its inhabitants and through associations that find value in that process. But just as the play casts doubt on the ability of the senses to perceive reality, it also questions the capacity of metaphor to make sense of suffering. Webster’s strongest character, the Duchess, rejects Antonio’s philosophy—although even she cannot escape the metaphorical thinking ingrained in the world of the play. In response to Antonio, she produces two images of her own:<disp-quote>
            <verse-group>
               <verse-line>Must I like to a slave-borne Russian,</verse-line>
               <verse-line>Account it praise to suffer tyranny?</verse-line>
               <verse-line>And yet (O God) thy heavy hand is in’t.</verse-line>
               <verse-line>I have seene my litle boy, oft scourge his top,</verse-line>
               <verse-line>And compar’d my selfe to’t: naught made me ere</verse-line>
               <verse-line>Go right, But Heavens scourge-sticke.</verse-line>
               <verse-line>(3.5.72–77)</verse-line>
            </verse-group>
         </disp-quote>Though she initially rejects Antonio’s philosophy outright, the Duchess reveals her own uncertainty about the nature and meaning of her suffering by introducing a second figurative interpretation. Her images inject the play with what could be seen as an optimistic view of divine involvement in human life, and she asserts her own ability to make “sense” of her pain through concepts developed out of her personal experience, not generalized<italic>sententiae</italic>. And yet, even for her, knowledge comes through interpretive associations.</p>
      <p>The working of metaphor in<italic>The Duchess of Malfi</italic>and other early modern tragedies lays the foundation for the genre’s and the culture’s representations of violence. The associative and interpretive aspects of metaphor create discourse communities that understand pain as a meaningful experience with affective consequences beyond physical empathy. As a result, all forms of violence are potentially meaningful or even coercive. In<italic>The Duchess of Malfi</italic>, the tortures Ferdinand proposes for his sister and Antonio are made meaningful through metaphor, as he imagines forms of violence that target the aspects of her crime that he finds most repulsive:<disp-quote>
            <p>
               <verse-group>
                  <verse-line>I would have their bodies</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>Burn’t in a coale-pit, with the ventage stop’d,</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>That their curs’d smoake might not ascend to Heaven:</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>Or dippe the sheetes they lie in, in pitch or sulphure,</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>Wrap them in’t, and then light them like a match:</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>Or else to boile their Bastard to a cullisse [strong broth],</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>And give’t his leacherous father, to renew</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>The sinne of his backe.</verse-line>
                  <verse-line>(2.5.66–73)</verse-line>
               </verse-group>
               <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn49">
                  <sup>49</sup>
               </xref>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>The coal-pit scenario stems from a reaction against the possibility that heaven might bless their marriage, as suggested by the Duchess during the actual<italic>per verba de presenti</italic>contract (1.1.463, 475–76). The burning imagery from both this and the following vision recall the characterization of lust as a fire that consumes an individual, making it appropriate that Ferdinand would use the sheets from their bed as a tool of murder. The murder of the child becomes an indictment of the lust that created it as well as an echo of the ghastly practice of feeding a parent his or her own children seen in Seneca’s<italic>Thyestes</italic>and Shakespeare’s<italic>Titus Andronicus</italic>as perhaps the ultimate form of revenge. Ferdinand obviously sees specific value in each act of violence he longs to commit, in each sensation of pain he will inflict. Though we as audience members do not agree with his value system and in fact see the Duchess’s innocence even more clearly for all of his torture, we, too, take part in the meaningful interpretation of pain instigated by metaphor. As human beings who see her pain as potentially our own, we empathize with her. But as theatergoers watching a tragedy unfold on stage, we recognize her pain as valuable in an artistic sense. She is the crushed flower, the bruised cassia.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn50">
            <sup>50</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Figurative language may not be a primary means of conveying painful sensation, but it is paramount in assigning significance to those sensations and affecting audience reactions to its portrayal—perhaps even coercing them into an interpretation they would otherwise reject. In the artistic and theatrical exploration of human suffering, metaphors and pain are intimately linked because it is this interpretive trope that cues audience response and assigns meaning to an otherwise horrifyingly senseless bodily experience. The figures of pain discussed here attest to the artistry of these playwrights, but also to the power of metaphor and other tropes to shape the thinking of an entire culture. As Wayne C. Booth writes of metaphor’s role in community discourse, “The metaphors we care for most are always embedded in metaphoric structures that finally both depend on and constitute selves and societies.”<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn51">
            <sup>51</sup>
         </xref>Early modern culture utilized numerous discourses to make sense of pain, from seeing it as a sign of devotion in the Petrarchan lover or religious martyr to construing it as evidence of guilt in systems of corporal or capital punishment. Early modern tragic theater draws on those cultural narratives, but it also serves as a space for practicing the types of interpretation needed to make sense of pain—an understanding that extended outward at the close of the play. By being attentive to the moments of spectacular suffering that define these plays, by noting the philosophical and affective purposes those spectacles serve, we can see at work the same systems of interpretation that made possible many early modern cultural discourses, from the literary to the judicial to the spiritual. Far from being irreconcilable, pain and metaphor work in conjunction in early modern tragedy to create a durable interpretive community out of a single, yet multifaceted, physical experience.</p>
   </body>
   <back>
      <fn-group>
         <fn id="fn1">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>Bruce Smith,<italic>Phenomenal Shakespeare</italic>(Malden, MA: Wiley-Blackwell, 2010), and<italic>The Acoustic World of Early Modern England: Attending to the O-Factor</italic>(Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1999); Jonathan Gil Harris,<italic>Untimely Matter in the Time of Shakespeare</italic>(Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2009), esp. chap. 4, “The Smell of Gunpowder:<italic>Macbeth</italic>and the Palimpsests of Olfaction” (119–39); Eric F. Langley, “Anatomizing the Early-Modern Eye: A Literary Case Study,”<italic>Renaissance Studies</italic>20, no. 3 (2006): 340–55; Sergei Lovanov-Rostovsky, “Taming the Basilisk,” in<italic>The Body in Parts: Fantasies of Corporeality in Early Modern Europe</italic>, ed. David Hillman and Carla Mazzio (New York: Routledge, 1997), 195–217; Elizabeth D. Harvey, ed.,<italic>Sensible Flesh: On Touch in Early Modern Culture</italic>(Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2003).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn2">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>The concept of “hazardous, and potentially destructive spectatorship” in twentieth-century film has been examined by Martin Harries,<italic>Forgetting Lot’s Wife: On Destructive Spectatorship</italic>(New York: Fordham University Press, 2007), 13. For a discussion of dangerous art more generally, see Maggie Nelson,<italic>The Art of Cruelty: A Reckoning</italic>(New York: Norton, 2011), esp. 18ff. on Artaud.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn3">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>Ellen MacKay notes that theatrical spectatorship is underwritten by an “eye-to-flesh” relationship, a noncorrespondent situation in terms of sensory perception (<italic>Persecution, Plague, and Fire: Fugitive Histories of the Stage in Early Modern England</italic>[Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2011], 174).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn4">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>Allan I. Basbaum, “The Neurobiology of Pain” (33) and Robert T. Anderson and Scott T. Anderson, “Culture and Pain” (138), in<italic>The Puzzle of Pain</italic>, trans. Fideline A. Djité-Bruce (East Roseville, Australia: G+B Arts International Limited, 1994).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn5">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <italic>The Secret World of Pain</italic>, Films for the Humanities and Sciences (DVD, Films Media Group, Infobase Learning, BBC, 2011).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn6">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>Kathleen M. Sands, “Tragedy, Theology, and Feminism in the Time after Time,” in<italic>Rethinking Tragedy</italic>, ed. Rita Felski (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2008), 83.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn7">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>Elaine Scarry,<italic>The Body in Pain: The Making and Unmaking of the World</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1985), 15–17.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn8">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>Susan Sontag,<italic>Illness as Metaphor</italic>(New York: Vintage, 1979), 35, 45, 3.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn9">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>J. Martin and R. Harré, “Metaphor in Science,” in<italic>Metaphor: Problems and Perspectives</italic>, ed. David S. Miall (Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities Press, 1982), 89–105.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn10">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>Aristotle,<italic>On Rhetoric: A Theory of Civil Discourse</italic>, trans. George A. Kennedy (New York: Oxford University Press, 1991), 228 [1406b], 250 [1412a].</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn11">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>Max Black,<italic>Models and Metaphors: Studies in Language and Philosophy</italic>(Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1962), 40–41.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn12">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>I. A. Richards,<italic>The Philosophy of Rhetoric</italic>(New York: Oxford University Press, 1965), 127.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn13">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>Maria Franziska Fahey,<italic>Metaphor and Shakespearean Drama: Unchaste Signification</italic>(New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2011), chap. 1.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn14">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>George Puttenham,<italic>The Art of English Poesy</italic>, ed. Frank Whigham and Wayne A. Rebhorn (Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 2007), 263–64.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn15">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>For example, see F. C. T. Moore, “On Taking Metaphor Literally” (6 and 7) and Roger Tourangeau, “Metaphor and Cognitive Structure” (16), in Miall,<italic>Metaphor</italic>. See also Fahey,<italic>Metaphor and Shakespearean Drama</italic>, 15.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn16">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>Ted Cohen, “Metaphor and the Cultivation of Intimacy,” in<italic>On Metaphor</italic>, ed. Sheldon Sacks (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1979), 6–7.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn17">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>Erving Goffman has suggested that in the theater, “spectator” is too limited a term: “Each person who is a theatergoer is something else, too. He collaborates in the unreality onstage. He sympathetically and vicariously participates in the unreal world generated by the dramatic interplay of the scripted characters” (<italic>Frame Analysis: An Essay on the Organization of Experience</italic>[Cambridge, MA.: Harvard University Press, 1974], 130).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn18">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>Paul Ricoeur,<italic>The Rule of Metaphor: Multi-Disciplinary Studies of the Creation of Meaning in Language</italic>(Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2008), 83, 190. On the multivalent natures of both pain and metaphor, see also Jean-Didier Vincent, “Displayed Pain and Hidden Pleasure,” in Djité-Bruce,<italic>The Puzzle of Pain</italic>, 15–25; and Allan Paivio and Mary Walsh, “Psychological Processes in Metaphor Comprehension and Memory,” in<italic>Metaphor and Thought</italic>, ed. Andrew Ortony, 2nd ed. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993), 307–28.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn19">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>The meaning of<italic>catharsis</italic>in Aristotle’s<italic>Poetics</italic>is heavily debated, with most interpretations clustering around three key translations: purgation, purification, and clarification. In his 1599 treatise on tragicomedy, Giambattista Guarini likened catharsis to the medical procedure of purging, as neither seeks eradication of the target element but instead restoration of balance (<italic>The Compendium of Tragicomic Poetry (1599)</italic>, in<italic>Literary Criticism: Plato to Dryden</italic>, ed. Allan H. Gilbert [Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1962], 517–20; see also O. B. Hardison Jr., “Three Types of Renaissance Catharsis,” in<italic>Poetics and Praxis, Understanding and Imagination: The Collected Essays of O. B. Hardison, Jr.</italic>[Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1997], 78–94). Martha C. Nussbaum has characterized catharsis as a “clearing up” or “cleaning up” of emotions (“Tragedy and Self-Sufficiency: Plato and Aristotle on Fear and Pity,” in<italic>Essays on Aristotle’s</italic>Poetics, ed. Amélie Oksenberg Rorty [Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1992], 280), and Gerald F. Else has argued that catharsis is a purification of the act of the character rather than a purgation of the emotions of the audience (<italic>Aristotle’s Poetics: The Argument</italic>[Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1963], 230–31, 422–40). John P. Anton, critiquing Nietzsche’s reading of Aristotle’s<italic>Poetics</italic>, argues that Nietzsche was incorrect in construing catharsis as a purge of emotions, also claiming that it is a clarification of events (“Nietzsche’s Critique of Aristotle’s Theory of Tragic Emotions,” in<italic>Tragedy and Philosophy</italic>, ed. N. Georgopoulos [New York: St. Martin’s, 1993], 19–38). In light of this ongoing debate about the meaning of a single Greek word, several critics have suggested other language and models through which to examine the phenomenon of audience response to tragedy—a useful critical strategy for discussing how modern audiences might conceptualize their own reaction to what they see on stage. A. D. Nuttall endorses the more active idea of “exercise” instead of catharsis (<italic>Why Does Tragedy Give Pleasure?</italic>[Oxford: Clarendon, 1996], 75–76, 104), and E. M. Dadlez shifts attention from catharsis to the more familiar terms “sympathy” and “empathy” (<italic>What’s Hecuba to Him? Fictional Events and Actual Emotions</italic>[University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press, 1997]).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn20">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>William N. West, “Understanding in the Elizabethan Theaters,”<italic>Renaissance Drama</italic>35 (2006): 113–43.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn21">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>Vanessa McMahon,<italic>Murder in Shakespeare’s England</italic>(London: Hambledon &amp; London, 2004), 107, 121, 122.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn22">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>Thomas Middleton,<italic>The Lady’s Tragedy</italic>, ed. Julia Briggs, in<italic>Thomas Middleton: Collected Works</italic>, ed. Gary Taylor and John Lavagnino (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2010).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn23">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>Francis Beaumont and John Fletcher,<italic>The Tragedy of Valentinian</italic>(London, 1717), 5.2 [p. 61].</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn24">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>Citations from<italic>The White Devil</italic>and<italic>The Duchess of Malfi</italic>taken from<italic>The Works of John Webster: An Old-Spelling Critical Edition</italic>, ed. David Gunby, David Carnegie, Antony Hammond, and Doreen DelVecchio, 2 vols. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn25">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>Thomas Middleton,<italic>Women, Beware Women</italic>, ed. John Jowett, in<italic>Thomas Middleton: The Collected Works</italic>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn26">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>Philip Massinger,<italic>The Roman Actor</italic>, in<italic>Drama of the English Renaissance II: The Stuart Period</italic>, ed. Russell A. Fraser and Norman Rabkin (London: Macmillan, 1976).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn27">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>The palpable reaction experienced by Parthenius could be explained by the contemporary projection theory of sight, which held sway long after it was disproven through early modern anatomical research. As Bruce Smith has argued, this optical theory promoted a close relationship between sight and touch, such that “to see<italic>was</italic>to touch” (“Eyeing and Wording in<italic>Cymbeline</italic>,” in<italic>Knowing Shakespeare: Senses, Embodiment and Cognition</italic>, ed. Lowell Gallagher and Shankar Raman [New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2010], 56).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn28">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>Grit Hein and Tania Singer, “I Feel How You Feel but Not Always: The Empathic Brain and Its Modulation,”<italic>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</italic>18, no. 2 (2008): 153–58. See also X. Guo et al., “Empathic Neural Responses to Others’ Pain Depend on Monetary Reward,”<italic>Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience</italic>7, no. 5 (June 2012): 535–41; L. Aziz-Zadeh et al., “Understanding Otherness: The Neural Bases of Action Comprehension and Pain Empathy in a Congenital Amputee,”<italic>Cerebral Cortex</italic>22, no. 4 (April 2012): 811–19; and Sara D. Hodges and Kristi J. K. Klein, “Regulating the Costs of Empathy: The Price of Being Human,”<italic>Journal of Socio-Economics</italic>30, no. 5 (September–October 2001): 437–52.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn29">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>Stephanie D. Preston and Frans B. M. de Waal, “Empathy: Its Ultimate and Proximate Bases,”<italic>Behavioral and Brain Sciences</italic>25 (2002): 4.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn30">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>Hein and Singer, “I Feel How You Feel,” 153–54.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn31">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>Helen Reiss, “Empathy in Medicine—a Neurobiological Perspective,”<italic>JAMA</italic>304, no. 14 (October 13, 2010): 1605.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn32">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>Donald C. Freeman, “‘According to My Bond’:<italic>King Lear</italic>and Re-Cognition,”<italic>Language and Literature</italic>2, no. 1 (1993): 2.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn33">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>Michael Schoenfeldt has recently argued that such communal or social interaction was imagined as having analgesic effects in the early modern period and particularly in the work of Shakespeare. He suggests that moralizing about the pain of others, as in a tragedy, could be seen as an attempt to “inoculate ourselves against its frighteningly random patterns and its even more terrifying excesses” (“Shakespearean Pain,” in<italic>Shakespearean Sensations: Experiencing Literature in Early Modern England</italic>, ed. Katharine A. Craik and Tanya Pollard [Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2013], 195, 201).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn34">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>William Shakespeare,<italic>King Lear</italic>, in<italic>The Riverside Shakespeare</italic>, ed. G. Blakemore Evans et al., 2nd ed. (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1997).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn35">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>Edward L. Rocklin, “The Smell of Mortality: Performing Torture in<italic>King Lear</italic>3.7,” in King Lear:<italic>New Critical Essays</italic>, ed. Jeffrey Kahan, Shakespeare Criticism Vol. 33 (New York: Routledge, 2008), 306–7.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn36">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>Susan Oldrieve, “Fusion: Spenserian Metaphor and Sidnean Example in Shakespeare’s<italic>King Lear</italic>,” in<italic>Shakespeare and Spenser: Attractive Opposites</italic>, ed. J. B. Lethbridge (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2008), 219.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn37">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>Emily R. Wilson,<italic>Mocked with Death: Tragic Overliving from Sophocles to Milton</italic>(Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2004), 11. See also Wilson’s discussion of Gloucester’s lines on page 118.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn38">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>Rocklin, “The Smell of Mortality,” 311.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn39">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>Patricia Cahill, “Falling into Extremity,” in Gallagher and Raman,<italic>Knowing Shakespeare</italic>, 100.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn40">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>A. C. Bradley,<italic>Shakespearean Tragedy: Lectures on</italic>Hamlet, Othello, King Lear, Macbeth (London: Penguin, 1991), 175. This comment is included in Bradley’s first lecture on<italic>Othello</italic>, but the interpretive strategy it describes is clearly applied to other plays as well.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn41">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>Ibid., 229.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn42">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>Ibid., 232.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn43">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>Compare Rocklin: “The blinding of Gloucester … is a scene that reminds us with particular vividness that even as the medium of drama is the actor’s body, the medium of reception is the body of the spectator” (“The Smell of Mortality,” 315–16).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn44">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>On the tradition of “redemptive” readings of<italic>King Lear</italic>, see Edward Pechter, “On the Blinding of Gloucester,”<italic>ELH</italic>45, no. 2 (Summer 1978): 181–200.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn45">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>Bradley,<italic>Shakespearean Tragedy</italic>, 262.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn46">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>Ibid., 300.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn47">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>On the<italic>imitatio Christi</italic>tradition, see Elizabeth K. Hudson, “English Protestants and the<italic>imitatio Christi</italic>, 1580–1620,”<italic>Sixteenth-Century Journal</italic>18, no. 4 (Winter 1988): 541–58; Thomas S. Freeman, “‘<italic>Imitatio Christi</italic>with a Vengeance’: The Politicisation of Martyrdom in Early Modern England,” in<italic>Martyrs and Martyrdom in England, c. 1400–1700</italic>, ed. Freeman and Thomas F. Mayer (Suffolk: Boydell, 2007), 35–69; and an early modern handbook on Christ-like suffering,<italic>Of the Imitation of Christ. Three, both for wisedome, and godlines, most excellent bookes, made 170. yeeres since by one THOMAS of KEMPIS, and for the worthines thereof oft since translated out of Latine into sundrie languages by divers godlie and learned men</italic>, trans. Thomas Rogers (London: 1602).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn48">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>Katherine A. Armstrong has suggested that Bosola’s reaction is indicative of the period’s fears about the inability of current epistemologies, specifically of medicine, adequately to explain or control the female body and sexuality (“Possets, Pills and Poisons: Physicking the Female Body in Early Seventeenth-Century Drama,”<italic>Cahiers Élisabéthans</italic>61 [April 2002]: 49, 43.)</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn49">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>Some critics have read Ferdinand’s anger and his violent expression of it as demonstrating his incestuous desire for his sister. See Susan Zimmerman,<italic>The Early Modern Corpse and Shakespeare’s Theatre</italic>(Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2005): 142–59, and Lynn Enterline,<italic>The Tears of Narcissus: Melancholia and Masculinity in Early Modern Writing</italic>(Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 1995), chap. 5. Frank Whigham also notes Ferdinand’s concern with bodily purity. He argues that Ferdinand can be seen as a “threatened aristocrat, frightened by the contamination of his ascriptive social rank,” whose incestuous desire for his sister is one way in which he seeks purity in his own bloodline (“Incest and Ideology:<italic>The Duchess of Malfi</italic>(1614),” in<italic>Staging the Renaissance: Reinterpretations of Elizabethan and Jacobean Drama</italic>, ed. David Scott Kastan and Peter Stallybrass [New York: Routledge, 1991], 263–74).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn50">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>Compare Melissa Greenberg’s analysis of the similarity of early modern England’s conception of tyranny and tragic catharsis (“Tyranny of Tragedy: Catharsis in England and<italic>The Roman Actor</italic>,”<italic>Renaissance Drama</italic>39, no. 1 [2011]: 172).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn51">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>Wayne C. Booth, “Metaphor as Rhetoric: The Problem of Evaluation,” in Sacks,<italic>On Metaphor</italic>, 61.</p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
