<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">inteschu</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50015280</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Internationale Schulbuchforschung</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Verlag Moritz Diesterweg GmbH &amp; Co.</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">01728237</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23645288</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">43057053</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>Aufsätze</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>From truth to meaning: — some experiences of narrative history in Swedish schools</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Christer</given-names>
                  <surname>Karlegärd</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1996</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>18</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40118640</issue-id>
         <fpage>483</fpage>
         <lpage>499</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/43057053"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>At Malmö School of Education a project team has tried to find out to what extent people are capable of constructing and presenting historical stories. The practical approach has dominated the project. Participants have been a lot of teacher students and a dozen experienced history teachers at schools in the south of Sweden. The main purpose has been to create teacher-stories for classroom use. To a minor extent we also have examined what narrative competence teenagers can develop. We tried to answer these questions: Is it easy or difficult to create and tell stories that are 1) chronological, 2) true, and 3) meaningful? Our results — more empirically than scientifically based — are: 1) Not only teachers but also pupils can create chronologic presentations. 2) We found some problems when we tried to follow the truth criterion. Story-tellers found it difficult to construct good stories if being limited to use only true elements of the past (found for example in historical dissertations). 3) The biggest problems we met were when we tried to make meaningful stories out of our true stories. Narrative history probably is worth a renaissance. However, much work remains before we know the best ways to develop narrative competence. An der „School of Education“ von Malmö hat ein Forscherteam den Versuch unternommen herauszufinden, bis zu welchem Grad Menschen fähig sind, historische Geschichten zu entwickeln und zu erzählen. Ein praktischer Zugang bestimmte das Projekt. Eine Anzahl Lehramtsstudenten und ein Dutzend erfahrener Geschichtslehrer an Schulen Südschwedens nahmen an diesem Projekt teil. Das Hauptziel war, Geschichten für Lehrer zur Verwendung im Geschichtsunterricht auszuarbeiten. In zweiter Linie ging es darum zu untersuchen, welche narrative Kompetenz Jugendliche entwickeln können. Wir haben versucht, folgende Fragen zu beantworten: Ist es leicht oder schwierig, Geschichten zu schaffen und zu erzählen, die 1. chronologisch, 2. wahr und 3. sinnvoll sind? Unsere Ergebnisse — mehr empirisch als theoretisch begründet — sind: 1. Nicht allein Lehrer, auch Schüler können Darstellungen in chronologischer Ordnung entwerfen. 2. Es ist schwieriger, dem Wahrheitskriterium zu folgen. Geschichtenerzähler fanden es schwierig, gute Geschichten zu schreiben, wenn sie sich allein auf „ wahre Faktoren“ der Vergangenheit beschränken mußten, d. h. auf historische Tatsachen, die sie in historischer Forschungsliteratur gefunden hatten. 3. Das schwierigste Problem bestand darin, aus unseren wahren Geschichten sinnvolle zu bilden. Vielleicht sollte narrative history eine Renaissance erleben. Aber es bleibt viel zu tun, bevor wir die besten Wege wissen, narrative Kompetenz zu entwickeln. A la « School of Education » de Malmö, un groupe de recherche a consacré un projet à la question de savoir dans quelle mesure on peut construire et présenter une narration historique.Le projet a été essentiellement axé sur l'approche pratique. Les participants en ont été nombre d'étudiants se destinant au professorat et une douzaine de professeurs d'histoire expérimentés enseignant dans des écoles du sud de la Suède. Le but principal a consisté à développer une histoire narrative destinée à l'usage en classe. A été également analysée la question de savoir quelle compétence narrative les jeunes peuvent développer. Nous avons essayé de répondre aux questions suivantes: est-il facile ou difficile d'écrire et de raconter des histoires qui soient 1) chronologiques, 2) vraies, et 3) porteuses de sens? Voici nos résultats, qui reposent plus sur les données empiriques que scientifiques: 1) Non seulement les professeurs, mais aussi les élèves peuvent produire des présentations chronologiques. 2) Nous nous sommes heurtés à un grand problème lorsque nous avons essayé de suivre le critère de vérité. Tous les narrateurs ont trouvé difficile de construire de bonnes histoires en étant limités à l'utilisation exclusive d'éléments vrais du passé (trouvés par exemple dans des dissertations historiques). 3) Les plus grands problèmes ont été ceux que nous avons rencontrés quand nous avons essayé de produire des histoires porteuses de sens à partir d'histoires vraies. La narration historique mérite sans doute une renaissance, mais il reste beaucoup à faire avant que nous ne sachions comment développer au mieux une compétence narrative.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d6542e119a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e126" publication-type="other">
Hayden White, "The Content of the Form", Hopkins University
Press, 1987, chapter 1: "The Value of Narrativity in the Representation of Reality".</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e136a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e143" publication-type="other">
Harry Haue in "Historiedidaktik i
Norden 2", (printed by Danmarks laererhoj škole 1985), p 163 f,</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e152" publication-type="other">
Erik Rudeng, "Historiedidaktik i
Norden 1", (Bergen Laerenh0jsklole 1983), p 139 f</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e161" publication-type="other">
Sven Sodring-Jensen, "Historiedidaktik i
Norden 2", p 188</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e171a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e178" publication-type="other">
John Fines way of working is to be found (in English!) in "Historiedidaktik i Nor-
den 3" (lärarhögskolan i Malmö 1988), p 106-126, "Narrative and the classroom"</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e188a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e195" publication-type="other">
Hayden White, The Content of the Form, p 36.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e203a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e210" publication-type="other">
Carr, Time, Narrative, and History, Indiana University Press 1986, p. 64.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e217a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e224" publication-type="other">
Carr, p 49 ff.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e230" publication-type="other">
Hayden White: "Narration is a manner of speaking as universal as language
itself, and narrative is a mode of verbal representation so... natural to human consciousness."</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e240a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e247" publication-type="other">
Paul Ricoeur, "Life in quest of narrative" i "On Paul Ricoeur: Narrative and Interpretation,
David Wood (ed), Routledge 1991, p 20 ff</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e257a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e264" publication-type="other">
HiNo 3, Schoubye, p 253</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e271a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e278" publication-type="other">
Sven Sødring Jensen, Historie og Fiktion, Inst, for historie, Danmarks Laererhøjskole 1990</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e285a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e292" publication-type="other">
Behre/Norborg, "Geschichtsdidaktik - Geschichtswissenschaft-Gesell-
schaft, Stockholm 1985, chapter "Ängstliche Knaben haben keine Chance, hübsche Mädchen zu
küssen", p 115</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e306a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e313" publication-type="other">
Leif Becker Jensen, "Skal vi have historie eller gode historier?", HiNo 3, p 161</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e320a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e327" publication-type="other">
Carr, p7</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e334a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e341" publication-type="other">
Egan, K., "Teaching as Story-telling" ,Routledge 1988, pl4, p 23.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e347" publication-type="other">
Department, of Education, Stockholm
University 1994, pl8</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e357a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e364" publication-type="other">
White, p 50</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e371a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e378" publication-type="other">
White, p 43</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e385a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e392" publication-type="other">
Carretero, p 372 in Mario Carretero and James F. Voss (editors), "Cognitive and Instructional
Processes in History and the Social Sciences", Lawrence Erlbaum Ass, 1994 Hilsdale New Jersey</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d6542e403a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d6542e410" publication-type="other">
Jörn Rüsen, „Historisches Lernen", Böhlau, Köln 1994, S. 70</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
