<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">enviphil</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50016367</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Environmental Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Philosophy Documentation Center</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">17180198</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">21538905</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">26167941</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group>
               <subject>FEATURES</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Liberation Theology's Critique of the Developmentalist Worldview</article-title>
            <subtitle>Implications for Religious Environmental Engagement</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <surname>Scharper</surname>
                  <given-names>Stephen B.</given-names>
               </string-name>
               <bio>
                  <p>Stephen Scharper is Assistant Professor with the Centre for Environment and Centre for the Study of Religion at the University of Toronto. His current research, funded by the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada, entails exploring the interconnection of liberation theology, with its emphasis on structural poverty, and ecological theology, especially in its cosmological emphases. He is also, with Ingrid Leman Stefanovic, co-editing a book on The Natural City, forthcoming from the University of Toronto Press.</p>
               </bio>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>Spring 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">e26167934</issue-id>
         <fpage>47</fpage>
         <lpage>69</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/26167941"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>As the world's religious communities become more involved in environmental concerns, the question arises as to whether their most significant contributions are in the realm of worldviews, doctrine, and cosmology, or rather in the realm of political and economic critique and an articulation of social justice concerns arising from ecological despoliation. After reviewing liberation theology's early critique of economic developmentalism, as well as its more recent treatment of ecological concerns, this paper suggests that liberation theology is in fact positing a cosmological as well as political and economic critique of modernity, which proffers conduits of dialogue with other environmental approaches.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group content-type="unparsed-citations">
         <fn id="fn1">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mary Evelyn Tucker, Worldly Wonder: Religions Enter Their Ecological Phase (Chicago: Open Court Press, 2002), 8-9.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn2">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>The ten-volume series on Religions of the World and Ecology, published by Harvard Divinity School's Center for the Study of World Religions and distributed by Harvard University Press, is but one important manifestation of this intersection. Spearheaded by Mary Evelyn Tucker and John Grim, formerly of Bucknell University, the Harvard series is the fruit of a three-year research projected convened at Harvard from 1996-1998. The titles include<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Indigenous Traditions and Ecology: The Interbeing of Cosmology and Community, ed. John Grim (2001)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hinduism and Ecology: The Intersection of Earth, Sky, and Water, ed. Christopher Key Chapple and Mary Evelyn Tucker (2000)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jainism and Ecology: Nonviolence in the Web of Life, ed. Christopher Key Chapple (2002)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Buddhism and Ecology: The Interconnection of Dharma and Deeds, ed. Mary Evelyn Tucker and Duncan Ryuken Williams (1997)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Confucianism and Ecology; The Interrelation of Heaven, Earth, and Humans, ed. Mary Evelyn Tucker and John Berthrong (1998)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Daoism and Ecology: Ways within a Cosmic Landscape, ed. N.J. Girardot, James Miller, and Liu Xiaogan (2001)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Judaism and Ecology, ed. Hava Tirosh-Samuelson (2002)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Christianity and Ecology: Seeking the Well-Being of Earth and Humans, ed. Dieter T. Hessel and Rosemary Radford Ruether (2000)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Islam and Ecology: A Bestowed Trust, ed. Richard C. Foltz, Frederick Denny, and Azizan Bahafuddin (2003)</mixed-citation>, and<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shinto and Ecology, ed. Rosemarie Bernard (forthcoming)</mixed-citation>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn3">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>For an overview of some of these Christian developments, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stephen B. Scharper, "The Ecological Crisis," in Gregory Baum, ed., The Twentieth Century: A Theological Overview (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1999), 219-227.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn4">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vasudha Narayanan, "'One Tree Is Equal to Ten Sons': Hindu Responses to the Problems of Ecology, Population, and Consumption," Journal of the American Academy of Religion. 65, no. 2 (1997): 291-332.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn5">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mary Evelyn Tucker, "The Philosophy of Ch'i as an Ecological Cosmology," in Mary Evelyn Tucker and John Berthrong, eds. Confucianism and Ecology: The Interrelation of Heaven, Earth, and Humans, (Cambridge, Mass: Harvard University Press, 1998), 187-207.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn6">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Arthur Waskow ed. Torah of the Earth, Vol. 2: Exploring 4000 Years of Ecology in Jewish Thought. (Woodstock, Vermont: Jewish Lights Publishing, 2000).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn7">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>For a schematic thematization of these religious developments, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stephen B. Scharper, "Finding Our Places: The Ecological Challenge to Being Human," in Eco-Nightmare: Science and Faith Meet the Environmental Challenge, Proceedings of the 2005 Walter Gordon Massey Symposium (Toronto: Massey College, forthcoming).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn8">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>For a list of engaged religious activism around the world, see the<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Forum on Religion and Ecology website, http://environment.harvard.edu/religion</mixed-citation>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn9">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>Bill McKibben underscores the "Christian" dimensions of the U.S. in his article,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"The Christian Paradox: How a Faithful Nation Gets Jesus Wrong" (Harper's, August 2005, 31- 37)</mixed-citation>. McKibben writes, "Ours is among the most spiritually homogenous rich nations on earth. Depending on which poll you look at and how the question is asked, somewhere around 85 percent of us call ourselves Christian. Israel, by way of comparison, is 77 percent Jewish. That's what America is: a place saturated in Christian identity" (32). Interestingly, McKibben faults mainline U.S. evangelical Christianity for not taking seriously Jesus' prime command to take care of the poor, suggesting that the Christian identity of the U.S. is a corruption of the central Christian message, i.e., to love your neighbor as yourself, especially the least among you.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn10">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>The most celebrated of such critiques in an ecological context is cultural historian<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lynn White Jr., "The Historical Roots of Our Ecologic Crisis," Science 155 (1967): 1203-7.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn11">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>The term is from H. Paul Santmire's title,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Travail of Nature: The Ambiguous Ecological Promise of Christianity (Philadelphia: Fortress, 1985).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn12">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>For an engagement of this process within the Christian tradition via an examination of the role of the human in various Christian theological approaches, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stephen B. Scharper, Redeeming the Time: A Political Theology of the Environment. New York: Continuum, 1997</mixed-citation>, as well as, more popularly, ecological resonances within Scripture,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Scharper and Cunningham, eds., The Green Bible. New York: Lantern, 2002.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn13">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Richard Peet and Michael Watts, eds. Liberation Ecologies: Environment, Development, Social Movements [second edition], (Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn14">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stephen B. Scharper, "Option for the Poor and Option for the Earth: Toward a Sustainable Solidarity," in Option for the Poor: An Interdisciplinary Reader, ed. Gustavo Gutiérrez and Daniel Groody, C.S.C. (forthcoming)</mixed-citation>. Given my focus on Gutiérrez's original critique of developmentalism, references to A Theology of Liberation will be to the 1973 edition, unless otherwise indicated.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn15">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gustavo Gutiérrez, "Option for the Poor: Assessment and Implications" ARC: The Journal of the Faculty of Religious Studies, McGill University (1994), 66.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn16">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Samuel Ruiz Garcia, "Monsignor Oscar A. Romero: Martyr of the Option for the Poor," in Monsignor Romero: A Bishop for the Third Millennium, ed. Robert S. Pelton, C.S.C. (Notre Dame, Ind.: University of Notre Dame Press, 2004), 68.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn17">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez, "The Situation and Tasks of Liberation Theology Today," in Jeorg Rieger, ed., Opting for the Margins: Postmodernity and Liberation in Christian Theology (Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press, 2003), 89-104.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn18">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>There are numerous accounts of the Spanish and Portuguese plunder of Latin America and enslavement of its peoples; one of the most influential is<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eduardo Galeano's The Open Veins of Latin America: Five Centuries of the Pillage of a Continent (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1973).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn19">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Paul Farmer, "An Anthropology of Structural Violence," Current Anthropology, Vol. 45, No. 3 (June 2004), 309.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn20">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>For a stinging case study of how Haiti experienced the transition from European to American domination, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Farmer, op cit</mixed-citation>.</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn21">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez, A Theology of Liberation, 23.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn22">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez, "Liberation Movements and Theology," in Jesus Christ and Human Freedom (New York: Herder and Herder, 1974), 137.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn23">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>For interesting discussions of the goals and hope of the developmentalist agenda, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rebecca C. Chopp, The Praxis of Suffering: An Interpretation of Liberation and Political Theologies (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1986), 13-14</mixed-citation>and<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee Cormie, "Liberation and Salvation: A First World View" in The Challenge of Liberation Theology, ed. B. Mahan and L.D. Richesin (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1981), 21-47.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn24">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Myron Weiner, ed., Modernization: The Dynamics of Growth (New York: Basic Books, 1966), 2.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn25">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Walt W. Rostow, The Stages of Economic Growth: A Non-Communist Manifesto (London and New York: Cambridge University Press, 1962).</mixed-citation>Rostow was certainly not a "neutral" social scientist. He served as President John Kennedy's Director of Policy and Planning in the State Department, and as President Lyndon Johnson's chief advisor on Vietnam. See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lee Cormie, "The Sociology of National Development and Salvation History," in Gregory Baum, ed., Sociology and Human Destiny (New York: Seabury, 1980), 58-79.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn26">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rostow, Stages, 6-25</mixed-citation>. A helpful overview of Rostow's five stages is found in Cormie,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"Sociology of National Development," 58-62.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn27">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alex Inkeles, "The Modernization of Man," in Weiner, ed., Modernization, 138-50.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn28">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., 138.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn29">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">David C. McClelland, "The Impulse to Modernize," in Weiner, ed., Modernization, 34-35.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn30">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., 38-39.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn31">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Talcott Parsons, Societies: Evolutionary and Comparative Perspectives (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1966), 3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn32">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parsons, Societies, 3-4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn33">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>As Neil Smith argues, in the 1970s Rostow's Stages and other models of development and modernization "enjoyed the status of conventional wisdom" in geography departments among all but a handful of mainly "Marxist malcontents." Smith argues that "modernization was a mission, much as Christianization had been for many European colonists of the previous century." For Third World specialists, he writes, the question was not whether to sanction or advance modernization, but, rather, how to achieve this "unquestioned" good. One wonders if the same unquestioned "good" has been attached to notions of "globalization" and "sustainable development" within those same academic corridors that Smith trod in the 1970s. (<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Neil Smith, "The Satanic Geographies of Globalization: Uneven Development in the 1990s," Public Culture 10 (1) (1997: 169-189), 172.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn34">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">June Nash, "Ethnographic Aspects of the World Capitalist System," Annual Review of Anthropology 10: (1981), 407.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn35">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eric. R. Wolf, Europe and the People without History (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1982), 22.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn36">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Andre Gunder Frank, Latin America: Underdevelopment or Revolution: Essays on the Development of Underdevelopment and the Immediate Enemy (New York and London: Monthly Review Press, 1969), xiv.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn37">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., ix-x.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn38">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>Frank writes: "It is generally held that economic development occurs in a succession of capitalist stages and that today's underdeveloped countries are still in a stage through which now-developed countries passed long ago. Yet even a modest acquaintance with history shows that the underdevelopment is not original or traditional and that neither the past nor the present of the underdeveloped countries resemble in any important respect the past of the now-developed countries. The now-developed countries were never underdeveloped, though they may have been undeveloped. It is also widely believed that the contemporary underdevelopment of a country can be understood as the product of reflection solely of its own economic, political, social, and cultural characteristics of structure.<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Capitalism and Underdevelopment in Latin America (New York: Monthly Review Press, 1967), 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn39">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Frank, Capitalism and Underdevelopment in Latin America, 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn40">
            <label>40</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wolf, Europe, pp. 22-23.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn41">
            <label>41</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Frank, Underdevelopment of Revolution, p. xii</mixed-citation>. Frank writes: "Dialectically integrated society and economy which today obliges the bourgeoisie—including its most nationalist sectors—to pursue policies which, however much development they may generate for the minority, condemn the majority of Latin Americans to ever-deeper underdevelopment, and the bourgeoisie itself to increasing dependence on and absorption into the metropolitan bourgeoisie of the neo-imperialist system." In his more recent work, Frank attempts to understand economic systems from a global rather than Eurocentric perspective, and argues that the modern rise of Europe may be seen as a mere blip on a world economic landscape dominated by Asia. See his<mixed-citation publication-type="other">ReOrient: Global Economy in an Asian Age (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1998</mixed-citation>and<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Frank and B.K. Gills, eds. The World System: Five Hundred Years or Five Thousand? (London and New York: Routledge, 1993)</mixed-citation>.). Interestingly, Frank also argues that his world systems theory has not taken adequate account of questions of "ecology and cosmology," and thus are perhaps too "humanocentric" as some critics claim (<mixed-citation publication-type="other">ReOrient, xxvi</mixed-citation>).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn42">
            <label>42</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Immanuel Wallerstein, The Modern World System: Capitalist Agriculture and the Origins of the European World Economy in the Sixteenth Century (New York: Academic, 1975), 347-48.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn43">
            <label>43</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nash, "Ethnographic Aspects," 401.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn44">
            <label>44</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., 396.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn45">
            <label>45</label>
            <p>For an intriguing analysis of the use of the term "development" in magisterial documents, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Renè Laurentin, Liberation, Development, and Salvation, trans. Charles Underhill Quinn (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1972), pp. 39-59.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn46">
            <label>46</label>
            <p>General Secretariat of CELAM,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Church in the Present-day Transformation of Latin America in Light of the Council II, Conclusions (Bogota: 1970).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn47">
            <label>47</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Theo Witvliet, A Place in the Sun: Liberation Theology in the Third World (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1985), 121-22.</mixed-citation>Phillip Berryman underscores the importance of Medellín: "It would be difficult to exaggerate the importance of Medellín, at least for the "liberationist" sectors of the church, for which it undoubtedly is more meaningful than Vatican II. The Council in its central preoccupations and in its ideologically conditioned view of the world in terms of "progress" reflects a "developmentalist" mentality. Medellín is concerned with the participation of the church and of Christians in the celebration of [humanity].<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berryman, "Latin American Liberation Theology," in Theology in the Americas, ed. Sergio Torres and J. Eagleson (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1975), 25.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn48">
            <label>48</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">"Medellín Document on Peace," in Between Honesty and Hope (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Maryknoll Publications, 1970), 201-210.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn49">
            <label>49</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez, A Theology of Liberation, 25.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn50">
            <label>50</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., p. 26</mixed-citation>.<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez also reflects on developmentalism in "Notes for the Theology of Liberation," Theological Studies (31:1970), 243-61.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn51">
            <label>51</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez, A Theology of Liberation, 26.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn52">
            <label>52</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., 82-83.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn53">
            <label>53</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., 84.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn54">
            <label>54</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid., 26</mixed-citation>. Gutiérrez further reveals his incorporation of the theories of dependency: "The dynamism of capital economy creates a center and a periphery, producing at once progress and increasing riches for the few, and social unrest, political tension and poverty for the rest. So Latin America comes to be seen in a dependent situation, in which the basic decisions are taken outside the subcontinent."<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"Contestation in Latin America," in Contestation in the Church, ed. T.J. Urresti (New York: Herder and Herder, 1971), 42.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn55">
            <label>55</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">A Theology of Liberation, 36.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn56">
            <label>56</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez, The Power of the Poor in History (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1983), 29.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn57">
            <label>57</label>
            <p>See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gutiérrez, "Reflections from a Latin American Perspective: Finding Our Way to Talk about God," in Irruption of the Third World: Challenge to Theology, ed. Virginia Fabella and Sergio Torres (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1973), 223.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn58">
            <label>58</label>
            <p>See especially<mixed-citation publication-type="other">A Theology of Liberation, pp. 156-157, 165, 190-194</mixed-citation>;<mixed-citation publication-type="other">On Job: God Talk and the Suffering of the Innocent (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1987)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"Reflections from a Latin American Perspective," in Irruption, 224-234</mixed-citation>; and<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"The Irruption of the Poor in Latin America and the Christian Communities of the Common people," in The Challenge of Basic Christian Communities, ed. Sergio Torres and John Eagleson (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1980), 107-123.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn59">
            <label>59</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">A Theology of Liberation, 36-37.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn60">
            <label>60</label>
            <p>For analysis of how the preferential option for the poor contributes to environmental discourse, see my<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"Option for the Poor, Option for the Earth", in Option for the Poor: Responses, ed. Gustavo Gutiérrez and Daniel Groody, forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn61">
            <label>61</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Enrique Dussel,. The Underside of Modernity: Apel, Ricoeur, Rorty, Taylor and the Philosophy of Liberation. Trans. and ed. Eduardo Mendieta. (Atlantic Highlands, N.J.: Humanities Press, 1996), 20.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn62">
            <label>62</label>
            <p>These points are more fully developed in<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dussel's The Invention of the Americas: Eclipse of the "Other" and the Myth of Modernity (New York: Continuum, 1995).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn63">
            <label>63</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dussel, Underside, 21.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn64">
            <label>64</label>
            <p>Ivone Gebara notes the absence of sustained ecological reflection on behalf of liberation theologians: "The Latin American theology of the last thirty years has shown relatively little interest in feminist or ecological issues. I am not saying this to criticize my colleagues; it is merely a statement of fact" (<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gebara, Longing, 9</mixed-citation>).</p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn65">
            <label>65</label>
            <p>For a helpful overview of the provenance and progression of the notion of "liberation ecology," see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Richard Peet and Michael Watts, "Liberating Political Ecology," in Liberation Ecologies: Environment, Development, Social Movements , ed. R. Peet and M. Watts, second edition (London and New York: Routledge, 2004).</mixed-citation>For a rigorous analysis of the limits of progress and economic developmentalist models, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Richard Norgaard, Development Betrayed (New York: Routledge, 1994).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn66">
            <label>66</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leonardo Boff, Ecology and Liberation: A New Paradigm. (Trans. John Cumming, Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1995), 75.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn67">
            <label>67</label>
            <p>For a fuller discussion of Boff's social ecology, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Scharper, Redeeming the Time: A Political Theology of the Environment (New York: Continuum, 1997), 168-174.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn68">
            <label>68</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Boff, Ecology and Liberation, 102-104.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn69">
            <label>69</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ivone Gebara, Longing for Running Water: Ecofeminism and Liberation (Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 1999), vi.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn70">
            <label>70</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibid.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn71">
            <label>71</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gebara, Longing, 4-5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn72">
            <label>72</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gebara, Longing, 137-171.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn73">
            <label>73</label>
            <p>For a fuller discussion of Boff and Gebara, see<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Scharper, Redeeming the Time (New York: Continuum, 1997), 165-183.</mixed-citation>See also<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ivone Gebara, Longing for Running Water: Ecofeminism and Liberation. (Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 1999).</mixed-citation>
               <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mary, Mother of God, Mother of the Poor (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1999)</mixed-citation>,<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"Cosmic Theology: Ecofeminism and Panentheism," in Readings in Ecology and Feminist Theology, ed. Mary Heather MacKinnon and Moni McIntyre (Kansas City: Sheed &amp; Ward, 1995), 208-213</mixed-citation>and<mixed-citation publication-type="other">"The Trinity and Human Experience" in Women Healing Earth: Third World Women on Ecology, Feminism, and Religion, ed. Rosemary Radford Ruether (Maryknoll, N.Y.: Orbis Books, 1996), 13-23.</mixed-citation>A helpful overview of ecofeminist reflection in a global context can be found in<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Heather Eaton and Lois Ann Lorentzen, eds., Ecofeminism and Globalization: Exploring Culture, Context, and Religion (Lanham, Md.: Rowman and Littlefield, 2003).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="fn74">
            <label>74</label>
            <p>See See<mixed-citation publication-type="other">Richard Peet and Micahel Watts, eds. Liberation Ecologies.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
