<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philrefo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018096</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philosophia Reformata</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318035</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23528230</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24709643</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>PERSONS AND THEIR LIVES REFORMATIONAL PHILOSOPHY ON MAN, ETHICS, AND BEYOND</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Gerrit</given-names>
                  <surname>Glas</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2006</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>71</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24709638</issue-id>
         <fpage>31</fpage>
         <lpage>57</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Centre for Reformational Philosophy</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24709643"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d1711e107a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e114" publication-type="other">
'Objectivism' refers here to the psychoanalytic notion that truth consists of the latent,
hidden content beneath the surface of consciousness and of everyday life. This content should
be laid bare by 'analysis'. I admit that this way of phrasing the case against psychoanalysis is
one-sided. I am addressing what has been calied Freud's metapsychology, his theoretical ac-
count of the unconscious and of unconscious processes. Hermeneutical reinterpretations of
psychoanalytic theory, however, focus much more on relational aspects of the analytic encoun-
ter and view truth more as emerging 'within' the analytic situation, that is, in the interaction
between analyst and analysand.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e143a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e150" publication-type="other">
In clinical practice, though, both aspects often go together: the prevalent mood or affec-
tive stance expresses a particular existential dynamic and may at the same time refer to certain
events, imagined or real.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e163a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e170" publication-type="other">
Of course, one could say that these basic attitudes (moods, thentes) do not completely
lack an 'object'; their object is not 'nothing' or 'nothingness'. The 'object is rather existence
itself, as a 'whole', in a more or less encompassing sense.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e183a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e190" publication-type="other">
Other thinkers have also been instrumental in re-inteφreting philosophy as a way of re-
storing contact. I am thinking of Spren Kierkegaard, Martin Heidegger, Emmanuel Levinas,
Paul Ricoeur, Charles Taylor and Alasdair Maclntyre - Spren Kierkegaard (1844, 1845, 1848)
with his analysis of human freedom as entangled in itself and liberated by the 'jump' into faith;
Heidegger (1927) with his analysis of anxiety as openness for the possibility of one's (own) im-
possibility; Levinas (1974) with his notion of the Other as a disquieting openness or wound in
my existence, Ricoeur (1990) with his four-fold analysis of the self as a relatedness to oneself
opened-up by the presence of the other, Taylor (1989) with his notion of disengaged reason
and of the intrinsic relation of persons to (their) 'goods', Maclntyre (1981) with his concept of
'goods' internai to practices.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e226a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e233" publication-type="other">
The traditional protestant theological approach, we had in mind, tried to dérivé moral
guidelines for spécifie practical situations from général biblical principles and moral demands.
This approach seemed to lack sensitivity for the spécifie nature of, for instance, the médical
situation. The pragmatism of common médical ethics concerned for instance the well-known
principalism of Beauchamp and Childress (1989, 2001) who in their approach tried to com-
bine the dutv (rule) oriented view of the one and the utilitarian stance of the other author.
This example is not meant to detract from the important rôle this book has played to put eth-
ics on the médical agenda.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e262a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e269" publication-type="other">
Jochemsen and Glas ( 1997), chapter 3.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e276a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e283" publication-type="other">
The 'unanswered questions' refer to questions like: (a) how is philosophy as theoretical
activity related to the practice of Connecting? (b) is ethics about what is good or about what is
right (cf. the contribution of John Hare in this volume)? and (c) is ethics concerned with all
sorts of normativity, or only with a particular 'ethical' kind of normativity? and if so, (d) how to
define this ethical normativity? I realize that in a full account of the position I defend, these
questions have to be addressed. For now, I don't want to bother too much about these more or
less technical preliminary issues, because it would distract too much from the main thesis of
this article.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e312a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e319" publication-type="other">
In writing the last paragraphe and previous ones on double sensitivity in am indebted to
Soren Kierkegaard's notion of indirect communication, i.e., the idea that — in the current era
— we do not have immédiate access to truth ('from face to face') and that every understanding
of truth is necessarily mediated by the person's attitude to truth, which itself should be a mani-
festation of truth too.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e338a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e345" publication-type="other">
H. Dooyeweerd, NC II, p. 33.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e352a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e359" publication-type="other">
By saying this 1 do not imply that the physical vvorld, plants and animais, in the way they
function, lack any normative moment. Nor do I suggest that the ethical dimension is in some
way 'added' to the world by the subject. One of Dooyeweerd's great insights has been that the
non-human world is réceptive to normative qualities of human behaviour. This is expressed by
the concept of object function. Inanimate objects, plants, and animais have an ethical object
function, which means that their physical, biotic, and psychical functioning is receptive to and
can be opened up by appropriate moral functioning of human persons. Knives can be used to
kill and to heal. The knife is not just a knife, a merely physical object; it is in some cases a mur-
der weapon and in other cases a healing instrument. The ethical object function of the knife is
indicated by its mindering and healing qualities — qualities that are not 'added to' the knife,
from without so to say, but functional possibilities of the knife itself.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e398a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e407" publication-type="other">
I cannot go into the question whether substances can be such self-causing causes and
consequently how agency could be conceived in a metaphysics of substances. Moreland and
McRae (2000) argue for such an approach in their important work on anthropology and eth-
ics. I conclu with their spirit (a defense of the notion of soul in a biblical sense), without shar-
ing their mind-bodv dualism and the metaphysics behind it. One could make a case, I think, of
the statement that in their account the substantiveness of the body gradually disappears, in
spite of their body — soul dualism. Another issue is the distinctness between biblical and scien-
tific language. An important argument in almost all dualist accounts is the séparation between
body and 'soul' at death. I am not convinced that this 'séparation' can be used as an argument
for body-soul dualism as a philosophical position. Is what occurs at the moment of death not
just as mysterious as what occurs at the moment of conception (and in God's act of création)?
By introducing the biblical notion of the soul in a scientific discourse on mind-body dualism,
one is coerced to adapt the biblical meaning of the concept to the prevailing ontology of sub-
stances and entities; and this almost always implies not only réduction (loss of meaning), but
also adoption of certain conceptual characteristics inherent in the metaphysics of substances
(such as separateness of substances; or self-sustenance; or being bearer of a bundie of fea-
tures).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e464a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e471" publication-type="other">
For a classic account see Daniel Stern (1985).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e478a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e485" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur delineates how self-relatedness is implied in domains of speech, action, narra-
tion, and communal (institutional) interaction — in speech by the use of performatives (prom-
ises, assertions, déclarations) which refer to the integrity (tnistworthiness) of the speaker; in
action by the fact that acts are not simply events in the world but présupposé agency and re-
sponsibility; in narration by the subtle dialectics between character and plot, a dialectic in
which the narrating self aims at coherence of the I-self relationship over time; and, at the
communal level, because larger communal wholes (institutions) maintain their moral identity
only in the openness to otherness.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e514a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e521" publication-type="other">
I am very much aware of the fact that this notion of 'otherness' is highly unqualified and
needs further delineation. I already suggested a link to Reformational philosophical distinc-
tions when I said that the child does not just 'swallow up' otherness, but learns to discern and
to distinguish as one of the effects of the confrontation with otherness. Otherness mav
heighten one's sense for qualitative (and potentially structural) distinctions, in other words.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e540a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e547" publication-type="other">
The subject in these subject-object relationships is not the ego or I, 01 the mind, or any
Cartesian cogito. 'Subject' refers here to the 'active' side in the process of opening-up (activity
in itself not implying any consciousness of it), like the biotic 'object-side' of a bird's nest — as
such a physical structure — is opened-up by the biotic subject function of the bird.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e563a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e570" publication-type="other">
There is a certain order here: character is a set of dispositions at the level of the act-
structure; temperament is the ensemble of dispositions that is anchored in the psychical sub-
strncture; typical tendencies in motor behaviourand bodily expression are related to the biotic
and physical substnicture. It is interesting that the distinction between character and tem-
perament, after having become obsolete at the end of the fifties and after decades of absence
in the scientific literatnre on personality and personality development, has re-emerged some
15 years ago and has begnn a second life.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e597a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e604" publication-type="other">
Think for instance of the différence between being touched and touching oneself; the
'otherness' that is present in being touched is what fulfils; touching oneself may give a sense of
safety or be self-assuring or exciting, but always via conscious or non-conscious memories or
the use of imagination; memories and imaginations in other words that imply the existence of
others, real orimagined.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e623a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e630" publication-type="other">
The revival of virtue ethics has different backgrounds: concerns on moral pluralism, ni-
hilism and naturalist ethics in the work of Alasdair Maclntyre (1981) and Charles Taylor
(1989), respectively; interest in male/female distinctions in moral development in the Gilligan-
Kohlberg debate (Gilligan 1982); ensuing re-appreciation of the notion of care in both hu-
manist and catholic contributions to médical and nursing ethics.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e649a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e656" publication-type="other">
At the occasion of the présentation of Henk Jochemsen and my book on the foundations
of médical ethics, the Catholic bishop YV. Eyk welcomed our contribution as the final récogni-
tion of the familiarity between the Catholic appropriation of Aristotelian ethics and the Ref-
ormation view on création.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e672a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e679" publication-type="other">
Taylor (1989), 528. The dilemma itself is described at page 530.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e686a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e693" publication-type="other">
Al Wolters, in a more général sense, refers to the same difïiculty at the end of his paper
at the occasion of the célébration of the 25'1' anniversary of ICS in Toronto (1995); cf. Wolters
(1995), 45.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e706a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e713" publication-type="other">
See also Van der Hoeven (1980a), (1980b).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e721a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e728" publication-type="other">
Transparency is one of Kierkegaard's favorite terms to indicate that a person's freedom is
appropriately proportioned to that person's relationship to God. Persons may increase or loose
transparency (cf. Kierkegaard 1848). For my own account of this non-transparency (I use the
term speechlessness), see Glas (in press).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e744a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e751" publication-type="other">
This issue is explored by Goldberg (1996), Chapter 1.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d1711e758a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d1711e765" publication-type="other">
Interestingly enough it appears that the structural features of reconciliation show a re-
versed version of the structural features of evil. Resolving the evil I do toward the other re-
quires that I am able to say what I have done wrong (the reverse of silence and the
tinspeakable), that I recognize my guilt (which is incompatible with splitting) and that I ask for
forgiveness (which is very shameful, but may résolve shame when penitence is accepted and
forgiveness is given); see Glas (in press); Muφhyand Hampton (1988); Volf (1996).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d1711e797a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e801" publication-type="other">
Arendt, H. (1965). Eichmann in Jérusalem. A report on the banality of eail. Penguin Books
(revised and enlarged édition).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e811a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e815" publication-type="other">
Beauchamp, T.L. and J.F. Childress (1989, third édition; 2001 fifth édition). Principles
of biomédical ethics. Oxford University Press: New York/Oxford.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e825a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e829" publication-type="other">
Clark, D. and R.V. Rakestraw (1994). Readings in Christian ethics. Vol.l: Theory and method.
Grand Rapids: Baker Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e839a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e843" publication-type="other">
Damasio, A.R. (1994). Descartes' error. Emotion, reason, and the human trrain. New York:
AVON Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e854a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e858" publication-type="other">
Damasio, A.R (1999). The feeling of uihat happens. Body, émotion and the making of con-
sciousness. London: Vintage, Random House.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e868a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e872" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1942). De leer van de mensch in de wijsbegeerte der wetsidee. Corre-
spondentiebladenvan de vereniging voor calvinistische wijsbegeerte! (1942), p. 134-144.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e882a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e886" publication-type="other">
Dooyeweerd, H. (1953-1958). A neut critique of theoretical thought, Vol. I-TV. Amsterdam:
H.J. Paris/ Philadelphia: Presbyterian and Reformed Publishing Company (ab-
breviated as NC).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e899a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e903" publication-type="other">
Gilligan, C. (1982). In a different voice. Psychological theory and utom.en's development. Cam-
bridge (Mass.) and London: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e913a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e917" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1989). Emotie als struktuur-probleem. Een onderzoek aan de hand van
Dooyeweerds leer van het enkaptisch struktuurgeheei. Philosophia Reformata, 54,
29-43.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e930a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e934" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (1995). Ego, self, and the body. An assessment of Dooyeweerd's philosophical
anthropology. In: S. Griffioen and B.M. Balk (Eds.), Christian philosopliy at the close
of the twentieth century. Assessment and perspective. Kok: Kampen, 67-78.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e948a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e954" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (2000). Het kwaad, de schaamte en mogelijkheden voor een heteronome visie
op de moraal. In: E. Brugmans, G. Glas and S.J.M. Waanders (red.), Rechtvaar-
digheid en veizoening. Over de fundamenten van de moraal in een tijd van geweld. Vught:
Damon, 66-85.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e970a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e974" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (2001). Angst - beleving, structuur, macht, Amsterdam: Boom.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e981a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e985" publication-type="other">
Glas, G. (in press). Eléments of a phenomenology of evil and forgiveness. In: N. Potter (Ed.).
Trauma, truth and réconciliation, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e995a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e999" publication-type="other">
Goldberg, C. ( 1996). Speaking uiith the devil: a dialogue with evil. New York: Viking Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1006a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1010" publication-type="other">
Griffioen, S. (Ed.) (1990), What right does ethics have? Public philosophy in a pluralist cul-
ture. Amsterdam: VU-University.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1020a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1024" publication-type="other">
Hauerwas, S. (1990). Naming the silences. God, medicine, and the problem of suffering. W.B.
Eerdmans Publ. Comp.: Grand Rapids.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1035a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1039" publication-type="other">
Heschel, A.J. (1954). Man's quest for God. New York: Scribner.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1046a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1050" publication-type="other">
Heschel, A.J. (1955). God in search of man. New York: Farrar, Straus, and Giroux.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1057a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1061" publication-type="other">
Heschel, A.J. (1962). The Prop hels. Philadelphie: The Jewish Publication Society.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1068a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1072" publication-type="other">
Heidegger, M. (1927). Sein und Zeit. Tübingen: Niemeyer Verlag.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1079a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1083" publication-type="other">
Hoeven, J. van der (1980a). Het 'probleem' van het kwaad: vuurproef voor levensech-
theid en bescheidenheid van het filosoferen (in de hoofdrol Paul Ricoeur). In: J.
van der Hoeven: Peilingen. Korte exploraties in wijsgerig stroomgebied. Amsterdam: Bui-
jten and Schipperheijn, 168-193.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1099a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1103" publication-type="other">
Hoeven, J. van der (1980b). Appendix: enkele aantekeningen betreffende de
gnostiek, Augustinus, Kant en Hegel. In: J. van der Hoeven: Peilingen. Korte explo-
raties in wijsgerig stroomgebied. Amsterdam: Buijten and Schipperheijn, 194-207.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1117a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1121" publication-type="other">
Jochemsen, H. and G. Glas (1997). Verantwoord medisch handelen. Amsterdam: Buiten
and Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1131a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1135" publication-type="other">
Kierkegaard, S. (1844/1960). The concept of anxiety. A simplepsychologically orienting délib-
ération on the dogmatic issue of heriditary sin (Translation of Begrebet Angest. Ed.
and transi, by R. Thomte in collaboration with A.B. Anderson). Princeton: Prince-
ton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1151a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1155" publication-type="other">
Kierkegaard, S. (1845/1992). Concluding unscientificpostscri.pt to philosophical fragments
(ed. and transi, by Howard V. en Edna H. Hong). Princeton: Princeton LTniversity
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1168a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1172" publication-type="other">
Kierkegaard, S. (1848/1980). The sickness unlo death. A Christian psychological exposition
for upbuilding and awakening. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1182a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1186" publication-type="other">
Klapwijk, J. (1971). Over de mogelijkheid van christelijk filosoferen. Correspondentie-
bladen van de Vereniging voor Calvinistische Wijsbegeerte (september editie), 7-10.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1196a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1200" publication-type="other">
Kuiper, R. (2004). Human identity and reformational social philosophy. Philosophia Re-
formata, Vol. 69, 14-37.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1211a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1215" publication-type="other">
Lanzmann, C. ( 1985). Sh^ah. An oral history^ of the holocaust (documentary movie).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1222a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1226" publication-type="other">
Levinas, E. (1974; 1978 ). Autrement qu'être ou au delà de l'essence. Dordrecht: Kluwer
Academie Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1236a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1240" publication-type="other">
Lifton, R. (1986). The nazi doctors. Médical killing and the psychology of genocide. New
York: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1250a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1254" publication-type="other">
Maclntyre, A. (1981). After Virtue. A Study in Moral Theory. Notre Dame: Notre Dame
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1264a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1268" publication-type="other">
Margalit, A. (2002), The ethics of memory. Cambridge (Mass.)/London: Harvard Univer-
sity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1278a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1282" publication-type="other">
Moreland, J.P. and S.B. Rae (2000). Body and soul, Human nature and the crisis in ethics.
Downers Grove (II.): Intervarsity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1293a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1297" publication-type="other">
Mouw, R.J. (1990). The God who commands. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1307a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1311" publication-type="other">
Mouw, R.J. and S. Griffioen (1993). Pluralisms and horizons. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans
Publ. Comp.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1321a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1325" publication-type="other">
Murphy, J.G. and J. Hampton ( 1988). Forgiveness and mercy. Cambridge (Mass): Cambridge
University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1335a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1339" publication-type="other">
Olthuis, J. H. (2001). The beautiful Hsk. A new psychologe of loving and being loved. Grand
Rapids: Zondervan.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1349a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1353" publication-type="other">
Puolimatka, T. (1989). Moral realism and justification. Suomalainen Tiedeakatemia: Hel-
sinki.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1363a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1367" publication-type="other">
Rawls.J. (1971). A theory of justice. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1375a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1379" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. (1955). Philosophie de la volonté. Finitude et Culpabilité. II. La symbolique du mal
(Philosophie de l'esprit). Paris : Aubier.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1389a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1393" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. (1990) Soi-même comme un autre. Paris: Éditions du Seuil.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1400a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1404" publication-type="other">
Rorty, R. (1989). Contingency, irony, and solidarity. Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge Uni-
versity Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1414a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1418" publication-type="other">
Schuurman, Ε. (forthcoming). The technological world picture and an ethics of responsibil-
ity. Sioux Centre: Dordt Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1428a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1432" publication-type="other">
Stafleu, D. (2002). Een wereld vol relaties. Karakter en zin van natuurlijke dingen en proces-
sen. Amsterdam: Buijten and Schipperheijn.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1442a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1446" publication-type="other">
Stern, D.N. (1985). The interpersonal world of the infant. A view from psychoanalysis and
developmental psychology. New York: Basic Books.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1457a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1461" publication-type="other">
Strijbos, S. (1988). Het technische wereldbeeld. Een wijsgerig onderzoek van het systeemdenken.
Buijten and Schipperheijn: Amsterdam.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1471a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1475" publication-type="other">
Taylor, C. (1989). Sources of the self; The making of the modern identity. Cambridge: Cam-
bridge University Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1485a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1489" publication-type="other">
Troost, A. (1983). The Christian ethos - a philosophical survey. Patmos: Bloemfontein.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1496a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1500" publication-type="other">
Volf, M. (1996). Exclusion and embrace, A theological exploration of identity, otherness, and
reconciliation. Nashville: Abingdon Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d1711e1510a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d1711e1514" publication-type="other">
Wolters, A.M. (1995). Création order: a historical look. In: Walsh, B.J., Hart, H and
VanderVennen R.E. (Eds.) ( 1995). An ethos of compassion and the integrity of création.
Lanham/New York/London: University Press of America, 33-48.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
