<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3591681</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/428538</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR85125</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Michael A.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Johnson</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">Chicago, Illinois.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2005</year>
            <string-date>January 2005</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>85</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>jr.2005.85.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>148</fpage>
         <lpage>151</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Bourgeois, </surname>
               <given-names>Patrick L.</given-names>
            </string-name>
            <source>Philosophy at the Boundary of Reason: Ethics and Postmodernity</source>. Albany: State University of New York Press, 2001. xxi+280 pp. $25.95 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/428538"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>What’s the difference between a “limit” and a “boundary,” and does it make a difference? Does it matter, for example, that<italic>Grenzen</italic>in the title of Immanuel Kant’s major work on the philosophy of religion,<italic>Die Religion innerhalb der Grenzen der blossen Vernunft</italic>, is perhaps better translated as “boundaries” and not as “limits”? According to Patrick Bourgeois’s recent book,<italic>Philosophy at the Boundary of Reason: Ethics and Postmodernity</italic>, much hangs on this distinction. The book pursues three interlocking agendas, each concerning themes of interest to scholars of religion and ethics. The author’s primary agenda is to draw attention to what he sees as a neglected philosophical distinction within the Kantian critical philosophy crucial to a proper interpretation of the notion of the “limit‐boundary of reason” and to the ruinous effects the failure to apprehend this distinction unleashed within twentieth‐century philosophy. Second, he pursues an important new reading of Paul Ricoeur as a philosopher who gets the idea of the limit‐boundary of reason right in his hermeneutical phenomenology. Finally, Bourgeois tries to show how getting the distinction right makes it possible to extricate the positive elements of postmodern ethics (especially Emmanuel Lévinas’s recognition of the ethical claim of alterity) from deconstruction’s false philosophy of limit as closure. In Bourgeois’s view, deconstruction decenters meaning and subjectivity to so large a degree as to render responsible human agency ineffectual.</p>
      <p>The reader will find Bourgeois’s treatment of specific topics useful and insightful, topics such as Martin Heidegger on the relation of limit, death, and the “end of philosophy” (chap. 2) or Ricoeur’s engagement with Lévinas on ethics as the face‐to‐face relation to the other (chap. 8). However, the primary argument of the book as a whole sometimes devolves into a Procrustean bed, cutting away the complexity of Heideggerian and post‐Heideggerian thought to make it fit an overreaching, insufficiently qualified thesis regarding the trajectory of twentieth‐century philosophy. Unfortunately, the reader may find it difficult to disentangle the valuable contributions of the book from the more ambitious but problematic agenda driving it. The thrust of this overarching argument is that, at a pivotal juncture in continental intellectual history, a colossal error in construing Kant’s concept of the “boundary of reason” took hold, preventing a proper understanding of the relation of the enterprise of critique to its grounding in reason and leading (apparently inexorably) to the aporias of “philosophy in the twentieth century” (p. xiv). All the trouble about the closure of meaning in recent continental thought could have been averted, the author argues, if Heidegger and post‐Heideggerian philosophers (e.g., Jacques Derrida, John Caputo, Jean François Lyotard, Emmanuel Lévinas) merely had paid more careful attention to a critical conceptual distinction Kant took pains to make between a “boundary” (<italic>Grenze</italic>) and a “limit” (<italic>Schranke</italic>) in the<italic>Prolegomena to Any Future Metaphysics</italic>(sec. 57).</p>
      <p>For Kant, a “boundary” always presupposes a positive conception of the enclosing region (e.g., the field of noumena) beyond the enclosed space (e.g., the “field of experience”), defining a shared border where the two spaces “touch” (sec. 57). In contrast, a “limit” defines a border as merely a negation of an incomplete quantitative series. Theoretical reason (mathematics and natural science) has no boundary; new cognition extends to infinity. Bourgeois’s main point is that the very enterprise of critique founders without its boundary relation to the positive content provided by the Ideas of Reason (ideas of the completion of the series of conditions)—in particular, as “postulates of pure reason” practically indispensable for obedience to the objectively binding moral law. Bourgeois cites Kant: “[The end of reason] is ‘to point out to us actually not only the bounds of the pure use of reason, but also the way to determine them’” (p. 43). What grounds critique and critical metaphysics is not reason in its conditioned use, the understanding (<italic>Verstand</italic>) and its categories; rather, it is reason (<italic>Vernunft</italic>) in its unconditioned use that establishes the sources of cognition, their domain, boundaries, and relations.</p>
      <p>Bourgeois contends that there are two ways of getting the relation between the enterprise of critique and its grounding in reason wrong. Neither understands the distinction between limit and boundary adequately, and, consequently, both produce untenable philosophical positions, in Bourgeois’s view. The first way, exemplified by Heidegger, attempts to derive the limit from below in finite human subjectivity (or Dasein). Heidegger, fatefully neglecting the essential idea of boundary according to Bourgeois, argues, in<italic>Kant and the Problem of Metaphysics</italic>(1929), that the origin of Kant’s two sources of cognition, sensibility and the understanding, resides in the creative intuition of the productive imagination. Going beyond Kant, Heidegger locates the genesis of the pure concepts or categories of the understanding in the imagination. In fact, in Heidegger’s account, the transcendental imagination becomes nothing other than the primordial time of Dasein. Reason does not set the limits of knowledge. Rather, imagination, or Dasein, limits itself through the existential projection of the meaning of Being as determined by Dasein’s own structure of finite temporality.</p>
      <p>The other way of getting the relation of critique and reason wrong, in Bourgeois’s view, is deconstruction, exemplified primarily by Derrida. Deconstruction simply inverts Heidegger’s relations among imagination, time, and meaning. In a breathtakingly reductionistic account of the roots of deconstruction, Bourgeois asserts, “Deconstruction emerges logically from this,” referring to Heidegger’s reading of Kant (p. 20). The closure of meaning (or<italic>logos</italic>) is no longer seen as original but as an aftereffect of chance and the play of language (i.e.,<italic>différance</italic>) originating from an abyssal flux. Heidegger’s “finitization of reason” (p. 87) places too heavy a burden on an imagination unable to project its ownmost possibility (i.e., closure) out of itself. Realizing Heidegger’s incapacity to think the limit finitely, deconstruction capitalizes on this failure, “subordinating [the productive imagination] to chance or to language itself” (p. 130).</p>
      <p>Ricoeur gets the relation of critique and reason right, in Bourgeois’s eyes, as a philosopher who sees imagination tied to thinking at the boundary (not limit) of reason. In a chapter examining Derrida’s views on “sign, time, and trace” (chap. 7), Bourgeois elaborates Derrida’s view that Edmund Husserl’s distinction between meaningful expression and sign depends on a stable borderline between primary and secondary memory (or retention and recollection) in his theory of “the living present” (or duration), which, Derrida asserts, is phenomenologically unavailable. In light of this analysis, Bourgeois draws an interesting contrast between Derrida’s insistence on a discrete closure of meaning and Ricoeur’s theory of language and imagination based in a view of the living present of meaning and experience that refuses such discrete closure. Once more, however, Bourgeois overreaches when he attempts to identify these accurately drawn contrasts with the limit/boundary distinction. In Bourgeois’s reading of Ricoeur, imagination does not produce reason from below (as in Heidegger); rather, “reason itself limits knowledge to experience from above, putting the imagination in a central position both in knowledge and thinking” (p. 131). A productive imagination of living metaphor takes place at the boundary of reason, allowing the living present in meaning and action to escape deconstruction’s critique while still incorporating a positive relation to alterity. Nevertheless, Bourgeois may be drawing the wrong conclusion about these contrasts, for it seems possible to read both Ricoeur and Derrida as seeking to work at the boundary (not limit) of reason and to think somehow the presentation of the Idea in the Kantian sense. Whereas Ricoeur’s theory of metaphor and narrative allows him to present the semantic content of the Ideas of Reason positively, these remain for Derrida (as for Kant) unrepresentable, or “the impossible.” This problem has been Derrida’s enduring concern since his 1962<italic>Introduction to Husserl’s “The Origin of Geometry.”</italic>The real difference between the thought of Ricoeur and Derrida is the distinctive way each thinker supplements phenomenology to take into account the creativity of meaning at the boundary of reason. For Derrida, it is the<italic>différance</italic>of deconstruction; for Ricoeur, the graft of hermeneutics.</p>
   </body>
</article>
