<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Journal of Speculative Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0891625X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15279383</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil.26.2.0108</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0108</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>American Continental Philosophy in the Making:</article-title>
            <subtitle>The Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy's Early Days</subtitle>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>Robert C. Scharff</string-name>
               <aff>University of New Hampshire</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">26</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jspecphil.26.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>108</fpage>
         <lpage>117</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0108"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>I want to start by seconding what others have already said about how lucky we were to come of philosophical age as the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP) was being born. I look back in wonder at how many of the early speakers were in fact primary sources for American Continental philosophy, either present in the flesh or directly represented by their students. By the mid-1960s, I was learning about Husserl from Paul Ricoeur and Aron Gurwitsch, reading Merleau-Ponty backward from some later untranslated work (thanks to advice from James Edie), comparing William J. Richardson's two Heideggers with Otto Pöggeler's account of Heidegger's path (thanks to a tip from Calvin Schrag), listening to Erwin Straus describe lived time and the upright posture and Eugene Gendlin explain “expressive meaning,” hearing about European phenomenology of natural science from Joseph Kockelmans and about Schutz and Scheler from Maurice Natanson, and of course consulting Herbert Spiegelberg on just about everything.<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>1</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Yet, as much as the people I met, it was the intellectual atmosphere of those early SPEP conferences that made perhaps the deepest impression on me. As I still remember them now, those meetings were filled with a sense of experiential enthusiasm and theoretical disorder. A few of us recall, as a highlight of the second business meeting, an impassioned plea from Gurwitsch explaining why our new gathering could not be called the Society for Existential Philosophy and Phenomenology.<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>2</sup>
         </xref>Concocted in haste in order to have a label to use for the original meeting invitations, this title had innocently committed a cosmic mistake. It permitted the adjective<italic>existential</italic>to modify not just “philosophy” but “phenomenology” as well. Factical Dasein was thus allowed to encroach upon the transcendental ego, and this simply would not do. And so, after much animated discussion, we officially became SPEP instead of SEPP. “Phenomenology” was mercifully liberated from the taint of historicism, psychologism, and the anthropological pull of the natural attitude, and “existential philosophy” now stood properly alone but trailing after what some saw as the truest and deepest of all the sciences—but at least still called “existential philosophy” instead of “existentialism,” as Gurwitsch had initially suggested.</p>
      <p>Yet I think I speak for most of the witnesses when I retell this little episode with some affection and amusement, in remembrance of a man who had much more important things to give us than a proper label for what we were trying to do. Moreover—and this is the point I want to stress here—except maybe for William Earle, Gurwitsch's objection was not treated as ideological or as calling upon us to chose then and there between pure and adulterated phenomenology. Nor did anyone with a primary interest in neo-Marxism, critical social theory, classical pragmatism, or existentialized Thomism see themselves as excluded by either proposed label. And this, I want to say, was typical of SPEP meetings from the very beginning. The stress was on the things themselves—especially those things that the larger philosophical world ignored, distorted, or explained away—and not on their One True Articulation.</p>
      <p>Of course, whatever its label, our initial little band of a few dozen was indeed founded in dissent—as a living objection to the oppressive philosophical atmosphere and attitude of the Anglo-American mainstream. Yet historians will have to be careful here. The later accounts of Continental philosophy as antiestablishment, radical, deconstructive, or transgressive all have their place and say something correct. But we were not primarily a group of rebels or critics. Even if our interests made us suspect to the reigning majority, it was not as angry outsiders that we came to SPEP. On this matter, John Wild remains my representative founder. He was for me a living example of someone who understands that the most empowering source of philosophical issues is lifeworld experience and who refuses to be diverted by dominant fashions into settling for the usual story about such issues.<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>3</sup>
         </xref>Those who are satisfied to think<italic>about</italic>experience tend to take for granted that its “real meaning” can be adequately expressed in terms of well-established philosophical methods, themes, and concepts. But Wild urged us to think<italic>from</italic>the personal, social, and natural encounters we actually live through—and thus, as his own career exemplifies, to be forever ready to reshape and transform our philosophical inheritance as current experience seems to require.</p>
      <p>I remember, for example, spending a whole afternoon at the second meeting arguing with a group of other graduate students over how an “existential” is not like a “category.” We knew nothing yet of Derridean deferral or Heideggerian formal indication, and so we talked primarily about what existentialia are<italic>not</italic>—until Wild overheard us and complained in his characteristic raspy tones that our debate sounded tradition-bound and terribly “abstraaaact.” To him, it seemed obvious that if phenomenology starts from the lifeworld, descriptions will inspire themselves. He was thus precisely a proper envoy for the motley collection of philosophers, therapists, quasi-theologians, metascientists, political theorists, and lit crit enthusiasts who either attended or became discussion topics at SPEP meetings in the 1960s and 1970s. I still hear “To the things themselves!” announced in Wild's voice, not Husserl's.</p>
      <p>Yet in all of this, Wild also echoed the attitude of our forebears. They were, after all, Continental Europeans—which meant they were thoroughly trained in the very tradition they wished to criticize, and they knew that one must engage with this tradition in order to overcome or transform it. Unlike many analytic philosophers, they did not think they could decide all by themselves what contemporary philosophy should be and thus leave the mere history of philosophy to be picked over by “humanists.” Displays of this kind of foolish arrogance were not typical of either our European forebears or our founding American pioneers; nor were we encouraged to think of philosophical practice as something only “we” did. Hence, I grew up simply assuming that philosophy is necessarily pluralistic, dialogical, and historically determinate all the way down—an assumption that was confirmed for me not only every fall at SPEP but also every spring at Straus's Lexington conferences, “Phenomenology: Pure and Applied.”<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>4</sup>
         </xref>To stick just to examples from the first fifteen years of SPEP, in addition to hearing from many speakers now easily identified as “Continental” philosophers, I also heard presentations by J. N. Findlay, Wilfrid Sellars, Charles Taylor, Marjorie Green, John Searle, Dagfinn Føllesdal, Bas van Fraassen, Stanley Rosen, and Jaakko Hintikka.</p>
      <p>Here is part of what I meant when I said that the early meetings were theoretically disorganized. There was no mainstream of American Continental philosophy, no orthodoxy, and on our side at least, no bright red line between what was philosophy and what was not. The pervasive mood was youthful and inclusive—and so, exactly the sort of atmosphere where novices could find their own voices. From this unsynthesizable disarray of speakers and attendees, I learned to assume that just about anything, even mathematical and logical things, can be treated phenomenologically—indeed perhaps especially when tradition tells us not to. Yet I also learned that no one can ever be entirely sure about the best way to address the things themselves, even when we have them in our sights. In one of the earliest meetings—I think it may have been the fourth—I remember attending an evening seminar on phenomenology and natural science, where the speakers were Theodore Kisiel, Patrick Heelan, and van Fraassen. Except for the fact that they are all white males, I retain an image of their discussion as modeling what the study of science as a human practice will eventually be, when traditionally trained epistemologists have stopped writing most of the textbooks and nobody reads the Leiter report. As Heidegger quips, we should always strive to treat phenomena phenomenologically. It seemed that for the most part, we understood this point without assuming we had already found the best way to do it. In this situation, hearing many disparate voices helped.<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>5</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Yet I have to say that in those years, it was hard to maintain a consistently pluralistic and dialogical spirit, when the larger philosophical world not only ignored us but defined our interests in advance as “not philosophical.” We found ourselves not just kept at arm's length but perceived as unprofessional, old-fashioned, and irrelevant. It was this double sense of being confident that we were on to something important and being caught in a professional world that was sure we were not that set my own philosophical course.</p>
      <p>From the outset, all of us could see that nonscientific concerns, felt human sense, and pretheoretical understanding are not, as the patronizing label had it, “merely subjective” and thus philosophically unworthy. We all knew, for example, that no real human beings—except possibly Merleau-Ponty's Schneider—open their eyes in the morning and face the problem of whether percepts can be synthesized with concepts to make sure there is an external world. And whatever the good life is, it seemed pretty obvious that one gets no closer to it by defining ethical discourse as noncognitive or by obsessing over individuals and their moral rules while ignoring class interests, culture, and social structure. For me, the matter came to a head when I studied Dilthey on the difference between explaining nature and understanding people. On any fair reading of his beautiful accounts of how<italic>Verstehen</italic>works and how a whole group of genuine sciences could be founded on it, Dilthey seemed obviously right. And yet, I was reading a fifty-year-old book by someone who had in the meantime clearly lost the argument.<xref rid="r006" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>6</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>Of course, by the time SPEP was founded, the more blockheaded features of the logical empiricists' program were already losing their appeal. Rational reconstruction, the stress on theory verification but never theory discovery, the anachronistic habit of modeling all thinking on nineteenth-century physics, emotivism in ethics and politics—all the famous earmarks of twentieth-century positivism were being challenged. Yet we could see that these specific challenges were no great cause for optimism and certainly no occasion for celebrating anything like the rise of a real revolution in the philosophical mainstream.<xref rid="r007" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>7</sup>
         </xref>For one thing, much of the early opposition to logical empiricism involved criticizing its overt features by means of a silent acceptance of its underlying conception of philosophy itself, and it was this underlying ontological and epistemological sense of what is really real and how to think about it against which we were trying to access a lot of neglected things themselves.</p>
      <p>There was, for example, nothing phenomenologically promising about assurances that theory discovery was now to be made just as important as confirmation, when confirmation of predictive theories was still taken to be the “essence” of all science. In general, it is useful to remember that one of the best-known opponents of positivism at the time—someone historians of analytic philosophy now usually depict as the pioneer postpositivist—was Quine, who was still assuring his fellow revisionists in the 1970s that even after the demise of logical empiricism, “philosophy of science is philosophy enough.”<xref rid="r008" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>8</sup>
         </xref>Perhaps in mid-twentieth-century America, this was a good slogan for the Philosophy of Science Association; but for the American Philosophy Association (APA), it was intellectual bigotry. Analytic postpositivism was really just positivism-lite.<xref rid="r009" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>9</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>In relation to these frustrating circumstances, however, I benefited in still another way from the early SPEP meetings. Had I been simply caught between my friends and teachers at Illinois and Northwestern, on the one hand, and the larger hostile culture of the philosophical mainstream, on the other, I might well have chosen a career of either speaking mostly to my own kind or becoming a professional critic. But in the diversity of those early meetings, I also found that it was hard to define just what “my own kind” was supposed to be. For me, an important fact about our theoretically underorganized little band is that we ourselves sometimes seemed only marginally better than the tradition at putting our passions into proper words. The difference, of course, is that many of us knew this. The fact that we continued to compromise our own efforts to be phenomenological simply encouraged us to be more phenomenological.</p>
      <p>And so, although we certainly shared their concern for the neglected and misunderstood topics we read about in Kierkegaard, Dilthey, Jaspers, Sartre, Husserl, and Nietzsche, none of their accounts of these matters seemed fully responsive to their experiential sense. All of these thinkers seemed, to me at least, to partially betray their own best insights by how they presented them. Dilthey, for instance, leaves everything that stands in the way of his philosophical success in place. In the end, having self-identified as an epistemologist of the “other” sciences—that is, someone interested in a “second” method for understanding unobservable “inner” life instead of the standard method for explaining observable “outer” nature—he is ultimately able to do no better that assure us that even if<italic>Verstehen</italic>won't give us “objectivity” in the usual sense, it can at least give us what he weakly calls a “subjectively objective” analogue.<xref rid="r010" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>10</sup>
         </xref>
      </p>
      <p>I remember also being frustrated by Kierkegaard's tendency to reverse the modern idiom, so that he praises the power of “indirect” speech and elevates subjectivity over objectivity. Why, in a world full of objectivistic thinkers, should we start by voluntarily putting our bodies, our sense of what is important in life, and our shared social practices into ontological second place? Likewise, must we settle for Jaspers's mystification of<italic>Existenz</italic>and<italic>Transcendenz</italic>by calling them the UNrepresentable? And do we really articulate better how it is to be in a world with others by following Sartre's famous reversal of essence and existence—as if an inverted Cartesianism comes closer to expressing lifeworld concerns than the<italic>Meditations on First Philosophy</italic>?</p>
      <p>An early SPEP paper by Earle made a strong impression on me in this regard—though not, I think, in quite the way he intended.<xref rid="r011" ref-type="fn">
            <sup>11</sup>
         </xref>He argued that our fledgling movement seemed to be developing a dual personality. On the one hand, we seemed to be trading in the traditional metaphysics of human nature for a rigorous Husserlian science of human life's “essentials”; and on the other hand, we were producing an existentialist excess of “ontological autobiographies” that glorified various purely contingent and accidental senses of how life might be lived. But surely Earle's dualism was too traditional to capture what we all wanted to say both about the human condition “in general”<italic>and</italic>about the unique possibilities open to every individual. Indeed, Earle himself was especially hard on those who tried to avoid saying<italic>anything</italic>too generally, for fear they might objectify life's deepest dimensions, or<italic>anything</italic>too specifically, lest it be taken as merely philosophical special pleading. What, he demanded, do two<italic>Existenzen</italic>talk about? To be struck dumb by this question would be to betray one's possessing a very unphenomenological allegiance to an objectivist conception of language.</p>
      <p>Questions like this have shaped much of my own work. Being surrounded by so many enthusiastic but incompatibly articulate spokespersons for neglected lifeworld concerns, I concluded that criticism of tradition is most powerful when offered by those who are already in the midst of trying to be better phenomenologists—not, of course, in the sense that they are trying to be better members of a philosophical school but in the sense that they are motivated by the urge to find better ways to articulate something that tradition distorts or neglects. Why<italic>should</italic>accounts of what matters most in life first be measured against the standards of “clear and distinct” propositional speech? Does anyone really<italic>live though life</italic>, thinking of it as a process going on inside our bodies? Do we really<italic>experience</italic>freedom as an unconceptualizable combination of limitlessness and limit? And why throw the metaphorical wet blanket of a rigorously trained consciousness and its “correlates” over the<italic>pre</italic>theoretical practices of everyday life? Negative genuflections to philosophy's traditional priorities, privileging the subjective instead of the objective, inner instead of outer, lived body instead of house-for-the-mind—all of these inversions ultimately foster the continuing and undeserved hegemony of a traditionally objectivist understanding of what is Really Real. Kockelmans once told me that Merleau-Ponty eventually decided<italic>Phenomenology of Perception</italic>“was not yet a philosophical book.” To be sure, its content and much of its treatment of that content is phenomenological, but its structure is still Cartesian. To start with specifically<italic>bodily</italic>perception, however generously reconceived, still implies that other dimensions of presence to the world—linguistic, social, cultural, political, historical—can be added on at a later time, perhaps along with discussions of abstractly identified and timeless “topics” like freedom, the self, and so on.</p>
      <p>In short, it is exposure to the experientially inspired and theoretically casual atmosphere of those early SPEP meetings—where neglected topics and unorthodox modes of thinking and speaking were encouraged in an undisciplined way—to which I owe the most. Of course, SPEP grew up. It has experienced its share of embarrassing upheavals, as the heavy presence of its own versions of the social and political prejudices in the larger culture became too obvious to ignore. But it is now a major event—the four-day anchor for a week-long convention that takes over hotels, runs multiple concurrent sessions, fosters satellite groups, and often follows established lines of discussion. Some even call it the alternative APA. Yet I am sure that as long as lifeworld experience continues to trump whatever it is currently fashionable to say about it, grown-up SPEP will retain enough of its original vitality and intellectual generosity so that another generation of aging academics will have cause to repeat our present thank-yous in another fifty years.</p>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <ref id="r001">
            <label>1.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Eugene T. Gendlin, “Expressive Meanings,” in<italic>An Invitation to Phenomenology: Studies in the Philosophy of Experience</italic>, ed. James M. Edie (Chicago: Quadrangle, 1965), 240–51. Even before SPEP was started, anyone interested in “Phenomenology,” very broadly construed, could already consult the very thorough chronicle of its advocates and lines of thought in Herbert Spiegelberg,<italic>The Phenomenological Movement: A Historical Introduction</italic>, 2 vols. (Dordrecht: Martinus Nijhoff, 1960). Unfortunately, SPEP has never found its own Spiegelberg.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r002">
            <label>2.</label>
            <mixed-citation>Don Ihde remembers this happening at the 1964 meeting (<italic>Consequences of Phenomenology</italic>[Albany: State University of New York Press, 1986], 4), but this seems wrong on two counts. First, as I am suggesting here, it is misleading to elevate an account of the lively arguments that followed Gurwitsch's demand into the story of a “battle.” Second, the 1964 meeting was held at Yale, after the first two at Northwestern, and by the time the Yale meeting was advertised, “SPEP” had become the official title. I am grateful to Calvin Schrag for several discussions about this event, among other things for correcting my faulty recollection that the<italic>Namenstreit</italic>took place at the first meeting. As far as we can remember, no one from the New School attended the first meeting, a fact that may well have influenced William Earle's spirited rejoinders to Gurwitsch's expression of phenomenological orthodoxy.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r003">
            <label>3.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I have discussed this point in more detail in “John Wild, Lifeworld Experience, and the Founding of SPEP,”<italic>Continental Philosophy Review</italic>44, no. 3 (2011): 285–90.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r004">
            <label>4.</label>
            <mixed-citation>There were at least five spring Lexington conferences, in 1963 (central theme: “Pure and Applied Phenomenology”), 1964 (“Phenomenology of Will and Action”), 1965 (“Phenomenology of Memory”), 1967 (“Aisthesis and Aesthetics”), and 1972 (“Language and Language Disturbances”). Papers from these meetings, including the commentaries, were published by Duquesne University Press in 1964, 1967, 1970, 1970, and 1974, respectively; but all five are now out of print.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r005">
            <label>5.</label>
            <mixed-citation>On this issue, see Eugene Gendlin, “Two Phenomenologists Do Not Disagree,” in<italic>Phenomenology: Dialogues and Bridges</italic>, ed. Ronald Bruzina and Bruce Wilshire (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1982), 321–35.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r006">
            <label>6.</label>
            <mixed-citation>The manifesto for the winning side is Theodore Abel, “The Operation Called<italic>Verstehen</italic>,”<italic>American Journal of Sociology</italic>54 (1948): 211–18. Abel argues that<italic>Verstehen</italic>is “too personal” and lacking in cognitive status to “add to our store of knowledge,” but it is useful as a preliminary exercise when we study human beings because it “relieves us of our apprehension in connection with behavior that is unfamiliar or unexpected” and “serves as a source of ‘hunches,’ which help us in the formation of hypotheses” (217–18). Three decades later, when his article was still being widely anthologized as speaking for the mainstream, Abel complains to his critics that he was really thinking only of “motivational understanding” in 1948, whereas Habermas, Gadamer, and Winch are clearly thinking of something more like “cultural insight” (Theodore Abel, “Verstehen I and Verstehen II,”<italic>Theory and Decision</italic>6 [1975]: 99–102). How this qualification affects the underlying logical empiricism of his philosophy of science, Abel does not consider.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r007">
            <label>7.</label>
            <mixed-citation>I refer here to the title of the famous, deceptively titled self-advertisement of A. J. Ayer, W. C. Kneale, G. A. Paul, D. F. Pears, P. F. Strawson, G. J. Warnock, and R. A. Wollheim,<italic>The Revolution in Philosophy</italic>(London: Macmillan, 1956). See Matthew Sterenberg's recent discussion of this and several other publications as constituting a kind of “Whig history” of the period in “Tradition and Revolution in the Rhetoric of Analytic Philosophy,”<italic>Philosophy and Literature</italic>34, no. 1 (2010): 161–72.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r008">
            <label>8.</label>
            <mixed-citation>W. V. Quine, “Mr. Strawson on Logical Theory,” in<italic>The Ways of Paradox and Other Essays</italic>, rev. ed. (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1976), 151. Quine is explicitly identified as one of those whose loudly proclaimed postpositivism is only a surface phenomenon by Charles Taylor in “Understanding in Human Science,”<italic>Review of Metaphysics</italic>34, no. 1 (1980): 25–38, at 29–30.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r009">
            <label>9.</label>
            <mixed-citation>More perceptive histories of analytic philosophy have recently begun the task of demoting the largely public relations accounts written by fundamentally antihistorical thinkers who tell us that analytic philosophy began with Moore and Russell's revolt against British Idealism. This standard story is both shallow and mistaken, and it has the additional disadvantage of either ignoring the connections between early analytic philosophy and phenomenology or assuming that they occurred just long enough for analytic philosophers to make all the right choices and phenomenologists to make all the wrong ones. See, e.g., Michael Beaney, ed.,<italic>The Analytic Turn: Analysis in Early Analytic Philosophy and Phenomenology</italic>(London: Routledge, 2007); and Beaney's entry “The Historiography of Analytic Philosophy,” in<italic>The Oxford Handbook of the History of Analytic Philosophy</italic>, ed. Michael Beaney (Oxford: Oxford University Press, forthcoming).</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r010">
            <label>10.</label>
            <mixed-citation>For the details, see my “Becoming a Philosopher: What Heidegger Learned from Dilthey, 1919–25,”<italic>British Journal for the History of Philosophy</italic>, forthcoming.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="r011">
            <label>11.</label>
            <mixed-citation>William Earle, “Ontological Autobiography,” in<italic>Phenomenology in America: Studies in the Philosophy of Experience</italic>, ed. James M. Edie (Chicago: Quadrangle, 1967), 69–79.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
