<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Journal of Speculative Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0891625X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15279383</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil.26.2.0299</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0299</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>French Poststructuralism</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">26</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jspecphil.26.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>299</fpage>
         <lpage>320</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0299"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s01">
         <sec-meta>
            <contrib-group>
               <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <string-name>
                     <italic>Ladelle McWhorter</italic>
                  </string-name>
                  <aff>University of Richmond</aff>
               </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
         </sec-meta>
         <title>The Next Fifty Years</title>
         <p>Continental philosophy tends to be very textual, defined not so much by a set of problems as by a set of interpretive practices. We read Levinas or Irigaray and write interpretations of those texts. Of course, we do more than issue commentary; we<italic>think</italic>through texts, grappling with problems, concepts, and historical and cultural phenomena. Still, most of our work remains closely tied to texts. Consequently, it often reproduces a distinction between primary and secondary philosophical work that we might question. Nobody would deny the creativity of John Sallis's or David Wood's work or that of Debra Bergoffen or Kelly Oliver; they are<italic>doing</italic>philosophy, not just writing about others' doings. Yet how many Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP) papers are on the work of Sallis or Oliver or Bernasconi, outside of author-meets-critic and book sessions? How many simply proclaim themselves to be doing philosophy, independent of any text?</p>
         <p>Feminist philosophers more often treat each other's work as primary texts than do nonfeminists. One does hear papers on Butler and Young. But even among Continental feminists, this is not the norm, nor are papers totally detached from texts.</p>
         <p>Likewise, dissertations more often address European figures than North American Continentalists, which reflects the idea that serious Continental work must engage primarily with French or German thinkers. SPEP's book exhibit offers plenty of volumes on Derrida but no volumes on Allison or Alcoff.</p>
         <p>Perhaps most crucially, when we teach survey courses, do we teach our North American colleagues' work? Are undergraduates taught to take Badiou and Rancière more seriously than Schrag or Caputo? Is this what SPEP wants?</p>
         <p>My concern here is not who should be canonized but, rather, our philosophical practice. After fifty years, most of SPEP's founders are deceased or in permanent retirement. A much larger cohort is nearing the end of their careers. A major goal of those generations was to bring European philosophy to North America—which they did! That is not a task that we must take up as they lay it down. The task for us is to decide whether those generations will be remembered primarily as bearers of European gospels or as philosophers in their own right.</p>
         <p>Recently I picked up David Harvey's<italic>Cosmopolitanism and the Geographies of Freedom</italic>(<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) and read a lengthy and careful engagement with Ed Casey's work. I was surprised. Alongside Deleuze, Bachelard, Descartes, and Kant, Harvey treats our friend Ed like a real philosopher. But why be surprised? Harvey, a geographer, writes about space, so he must engage Casey, just as he engages Kant. Ed Casey<italic>is</italic>a real philosopher, and he is, surely,<italic>the</italic>space man of our day. But is his work taught in geography courses more regularly than it is taught in courses on phenomenology?</p>
         <p>One of our most enchanting colleagues is Alphonso Lingis. He never lectures or argues. He takes you where he wants you to go so you can see what he sees. The first time I attended one of Lingis's presentations was in 1997, not at SPEP but at my home institution. Lingis wandered to and fro, carrying his paper in his hands. The light on his clipboard illuminated his head so that his reddish silver hair appeared to be afire. He looked positively demonic, an incarnation of pure energy. His paper, entitled “Innocence,” published in Elizabeth Grosz's<italic>Becomings</italic>, still enchants me.</p>
         <p>One might say that the essay is political. It tells the story of fourteen people, members of the Túpac Amaru Revolutionary Movement, who stormed the Japanese ambassador's residence in Lima, Peru, on December 17, 1996, taking six hundred hostages, among whom were “thirty-five Japanese businessmen, eight military and police generals (including the chiefs of intelligence and antiterrorism), seven foreign ambassadors, six national congressmen, five supreme court justices, two government ministers, and [Peruvian] President Fujimori's mother, sister, and younger brother” (Lingis<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 214). Within days all but seventy-two of the hostages were released unharmed. The guerrillas' single demand was the release of 442 Túpac Amaru members held incommunicado, among whom was commando leader Néstor Cerpa Cartolini's wife, Nancy Gilvonio. When Lingis gave this paper in March 1997, the guerrillas were still inside the residence with their seventy-two hostages. They remained there until April 22, when government forces tunneled into the compound and thirty soldiers shot them dead. The published essay tells the end of the story, concluding with a quotation from a letter addressed to his son found on Cartolini's body: “If I ever leave this Japanese residence it will be because I have achieved what you are waiting for and dreaming of: having your mummy out of prison, being able again to see her, touch her, play with her and be in her arms” (Lingis<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 216).</p>
         <p>One might say that Lingis's essay is about love and desperation or about hope and sacrifice. And it is, and it isn't. To say any of these things is to say both too much and too little.</p>
         <p>The essay speaks in the second person, beginning: “You, Nancy Gilvonio, a<italic>charapa</italic>, half Indian, were born near the town of Tarapoto on the Amazonian side of the Peruvian Andes. How extremely improbable is your existence!” (Lingis<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 201). It continues thus, adding Nancy's brother, “You, Américo Gilvonio … growing to the threshold of manhood in Tarapoto” (Lingis<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 206), the brother Nancy would lose to a firing squad and whose death would be revealed to her by a stranger in the dark of night, Néstor Cerpa Cartolini, Américo's comrade. These addresses and the piece's emphatic rhythms and vivid descriptions conjure Gilvonio herself, the life coursing through her body and the world she inhabited. One feels<italic>her</italic>and, simultaneously, the gaping<italic>loss</italic>of her. If the essay is “about” anything, it is a<italic>turning</italic>about that describes an emptiness—not just the emptiness left by the dead and the disappeared but, more insistently, the emptiness that occurs at a moment of newness, birth, awakening, an innocence of all history—all causes, all reasons, all values; it is a break, a rupture with any past—like chance, like action.</p>
         <p>“What we call action,” Lingis writes, “is not simply an adjustment to compensate for what passes and passes away…. Our action arises upon an interruption, a break, of the continuity of operations, biological, physiological, and also laborious, that go on in us.” He continues,<disp-quote>
               <p>Philosophers of history, whether reactionary or radical, see actions as shaped by values…. They see in the driving force of an action the momentum of accumulated skills and habits. They explain an action out of an evolving environment….</p>
               <p>But our action … is an interruption of the continuous dialectic of history, an awakening from the drowsy murmur of the semiotics of a culture. (1999, 205)</p>
            </disp-quote>Everything—not just the chance encounter of sperm and egg that brought about the existence of one Nancy Gilvonio but all life—is utterly improbable. Reason—“the reasoning, reckoning intellect that identifies possibilities on the basis of past regularities” (Lingis<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 209–10)—is confounded, and one finds oneself in the sheer happening of whatever happens. Once a woman lost her brother, fell in love, joined a movement, gave birth, and languished in prison. A man who loved her stormed a building, took hostages, wrote a letter, and died at the hands of a SWAT team. It was all highly improbable. Once you and I wrote a dissertation, accepted a job offer, attended a conference. All that is highly improbable as well. Once there was a star on which there were animals who invented philosophy. And it was all very, very improbable. In Al Lingis's work, improbability and the innocence of becoming become palpable.</p>
         <p>Let me turn away now from discontinuity, rupture, coming-apart, to recall a philosophical coming-together, Elizabeth Grosz's 2010 SPEP plenary, “Matter, Life, and Other Variations,” in which she presented a prospectus for an enormous ontological project: “I want to think a concept of matter that has not yet cut itself off from that which it opposes, matter that is not defined as the<italic>absence</italic>of mind, life, Idea, form, or Spirit…. What I am seeking is a new concept of matter that also involves something incorporeal, a spark of virtuality that enables life to emerge” (2011, 17). Grosz returns to Darwin (as in her 2004 and 2005 books), reading him as a theorist of sexual difference. Elaborating this reading through Bergson, Deleuze, Simondon, and contemporary physics, she gives us a look into a radically different material world, a physical world of differing in a process of “endless becomings” (2011, 23).</p>
         <p>There is a tension throughout her essay between the verbal distinction between “life” and “matter” and the press to think them without opposition. She uses several strategies to disturb the opposition, two of which I will attend here. First, she speaks (with Deleuze) of nonorganic life and the life of events such as a “storm, the traffic, a political demonstration, a conversation” (2011, 21). Calling this life “the incorporeal,” she describes it as “the charge of being-otherwise,” of becoming. This is the material event's “potential for realignment and reorganization” (2011, 20). Following Bergson, Grosz holds that “wherever matter unwinds itself with the thinnest measure of indeterminacy, life has the chance to emerge and differentiate itself into numberless living individuals and species” (2011, 20). Life is matter's free play, contingency, differing.</p>
         <p>A second strategy is Grosz's desubjectivation of memory: “Matter and life are thus not opposites, binary pairs (plus or minus vital force), but intimately implicated in each other, different degrees of one and the same force. Life is matter extended into the virtual; matter is life compressed into dormancy. Life erupts from (and transforms) the material conditions that enable matter to ‘remember’” (2011, 20). Focusing on memory as material event, I place Grosz's work alongside that of Paul Cilliers, author of the 1998 book<italic>Complexity and Postmodernism</italic>. Cilliers defines “memory” as a “physical condition of the brain: which pathways are breached (‘facilitated’) and which are not. Memory is not a cognitive function performed by a conscious subject, but an unconscious characteristic of the brain (which is an organ, part of the body). Memory is the substrate that sets up the conditions for all the functions of the brain” (1998, 45–46). Memory is a distributed pattern of valences across a complex system. It is an essential aspect of complex systems open to their environments, Cilliers maintains, because it offers resistance to environmental changes. Repeated patterns of distribution strengthen the connectedness of various nodes or elements involved in a given systemic pattern; repetition intensifies some networks at the expense of others. Without these transformations, an open system would simply mirror its environment (Cilliers<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>, 92). However, such systems do not simply project immediate environmental inputs or conditions. Rather, in some configurations, matter retains or repeats patterns resulting from past stimulation; in some configurations, matter<italic>remembers</italic>. When it does, it differs from its environment while remaining fully within the impact and draw of whatever surrounds it. This differing is what enables a material system to organize itself, differing further from but responding constantly to its environment. Memory is not representation; Cilliers writes, “Memory traces are stored in a distributed fashion and are continuously altered by experience. In a manner of speaking, even though memory is the substrate for all the brain's higher functions, there are no ‘memories’” (1998, 108)—no representations, just repeated patterns imparting dynamic form to the matter that generates them. Thus such systems have histories—traces, in Derrida's sense (Cilliers<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>, 46)—yet their futures—whatever will emerge within and from them and transform them over time—remain unpredictable, contingent. Thus Grosz writes, “The plant has a kind of memory, embodied in its cellulose structure and the arrangement of roots, leaves, branches, and flowers or fruits, a memory that gives it regularized forms of engagement with what it needs to continue to live” (2011, 23). This is what Deleuze and Guattari call matter's “becoming brain” (Grosz<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>, 23), which is not an assertion of transgenetic re-formation but, rather, a way of speaking about matter's resistant responsiveness in its dynamic self-organizing systematicity—or its “life.”</p>
         <p>Affinity with Grosz's and Cillier's work can be seen in Charles Scott's<italic>The Lives of Things</italic>: “There are in our organism physical memories of the ways to build this body, to form this heart and keep it beating, to recognize and kill organisms that are injurious to this organism—billions of memories that inhabit and constitute cells, groups of cells, and organizations of those groups…. The cells and their organizations that compose us know of nurturance, affiliation, repulsion, fear, and death—of being alive—long before as well as while ‘we’ form objects of specific recognition through words and concepts…. Homologous, memorial awareness is integral to organic life” (2002, 92). Memory “is” not the product or possession of a subject; hence Scott's insistence in<italic>The Time of Memory</italic>that “memorial awareness is found in arrangements, institutions, rhythms of movement, and lineages of development” (1999, 11) apart from conscious existence. Memory “is” an event emerging in material existence as it organizes itself, as it becomes, and as its becoming.</p>
         <p>Unlike Grosz, Scott does not seek a new ontology. Instead of being, Scott is concerned with nothing—indifference, absence of meaning, forgetting, loss, and emptiness. Scott is a master at arranging a text to give forth what cannot be present. His texts point away from their own meaning, deflecting attention from their content toward the nothing “there” with every event.</p>
         <p>Scott's texts, therefore, are not primarily informative. Like Lingis's texts, they are effective.<italic>The Time of Memory</italic>seeks to “re-<italic>member</italic>memory,” “to reconnect it to its own loss” (Scott<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>, 21). This reconnection occurs not so much<italic>in</italic>the book as<italic>between</italic>book and reader. Scott's prose acts like a more or less gentle crowbar prying the lids off carefully packaged conceptual crates and barrels. As one reads and the crowbar pries, one's thoughts—often coming as involuntary memories—fly loose; they will not stay pinned down. Scott's books thus displace one's skill as reader, one's educated judgment, one's mastery of canon and methodology, as in their midst one confronts how little one understands, how much one cannot recall, and how tiny a measure of even what one calls “I” is really within one's grasp. Scott's work effects the impact of the not-I that happens with the I, the meaninglessnesses along with meaning.<italic>I</italic>might be humbled in this impact, but pushed beyond one's ego, one<italic>feels</italic>no humiliation, only a lightening. In reading Scott's work I am, as Foucault might say, freed of myself.</p>
         <p>Memory, as these texts figure it, is dynamic and self-transformative (which is another way of saying that its occurrence always involves forgetting) and happens beyond the control of the agents it informs and enables. Nonrepresentational, “it” is charged, valenced, and potent. Memories have lives.</p>
         <p>At the fiftieth anniversary meeting, SPEP gathered to remember a beginning that occurred before many of us were born. Still, in gathering, we remember. We gather to remember our earliest years, our evolving organization, the comings and goings of dear colleagues and revered mentors, our struggles and conflicts and outright fights, our growth, diversification, decisions, losses, accomplishments. We gather to affirm those memories and ourselves in them and to affirm the importance of remembering.</p>
         <p>If the thinkers I cite are right, remembering is both transformative of that in which it occurs and resistant to its own transformation. It is transformative in that the event of remembering strengthens living connections, patterns, and configurations of valences in the neural networks—or institution—in which it happens, and it does so at the expense of alternative connections, patterns, and configurations. It is resistant in the same instant and for the same reason. It resists mirroring its own surroundings, copying or projecting its immediate reality. It resists<italic>pre</italic>sentation and thus refuses to be<italic>repre</italic>sentation. It both is and enables differing.</p>
         <p>In this remembering, I suggest, SPEP might find a possibility for differing from its own past. My point is not that our canon should include, alongside Derrida and Deleuze, Casey, Lingis, Grosz, Scott, and so on but, rather, to urge transgression of the boundaries of the canonization—or the memorialization—that has enacted itself through the task of bringing twentieth-century European philosophy to this continent and continuation of what we begin here: celebrating, witnessing, interrogating, and furthering our own thinking through and beyond the texts we have discovered and cherished and those we have generated over the last fifty years. As important as twentieth-century European philosophers have been to us and despite the fact that there are superb European thinkers active today, the fact is that most of what we call Continental philosophy now happens here, among us in this organization. In the twenty-first century<italic>we</italic>, along with scattered colleagues elsewhere,<italic>are</italic>Continental philosophy.</p>
         <p>This organization is haunted by the specter of its own dis-identity. As membership has grown, diversified, and connected with philosophical work from all corners of the globe, we have worried about losing our sense of who we are and what we are about. We say, half-seriously, that SPEP is best defined as the philosophical society that embraces everything Anglo-American analytic philosophy shuns or disregards. Defined only by what we are not, we have no core; we are all philosophical periphery. Urging that we look more to this continent over the next fifty years may seem only to add density to that specter. So I close with a meditation on continents.</p>
         <p>A continent is not an island. Continents are big. They accommodate many different topographies, climates, flora, fauna, and human cultures. The people on any single continent have been of differing races and religions and have used differing languages and technologies for as long as anybody has known anything about continents. Many islands, by contrast, were homogeneous for long stretches of their histories. Nobody has ever owned a continent; unlike islands, continents, in their vastness and differing, defy possessive mastery.</p>
         <p>And continental thinking? In SPEP's first fifty years, continental thinking has been thinking with other thinkers who, from the perspective of the British, arose on<italic>the</italic>Continent, Europe. But why take the perspective of the British? Might we not be continental thinkers in that we shelter and enliven differings? Might we be continental thinkers in that we harbor no nostalgia for homogeneity and no desire for total possession or mastery?</p>
         <p>We might be troubled by the fact that continents seem awfully stable; their differings take place on or in a place, to which they give a foundation. We are not fond of foundations. But I must remind you of something we Virginians were reminded of on the afternoon of August 23, 2011: continents move. And when they do, everything moves, rather violently. The truth is that continents are not stable or unified or ahistorical. They sit on a ball of hot fluid and gas; they float on the face of a star.</p>
         <p>In 1915 Alfred Wegender hypothesized that all earth's continents were once one supercontinent, Pangaea. Subsequent theorists suggested that through earth's 4.6-billion-year history several supercontinents formed and broke apart before Pangaea. In the Cambrian period, part of the land that would become North America rested at the equator. It drifted northward and bumped into and joined another landmass that became the northeastern United States and maritime Canada. The Appalachian Mountains formed during the early Carboniferous period when an edge of what is now northwest Africa rammed into the side of what then was a continent called Euroamerica.</p>
         <p>Perhaps continental thinking affords common ground without need of firm identity, ground that transcends nationalities and canonical texts and accommodates, even inspires, differing, endless becoming, in Grosz's words, or, in Lingis's, an endless stream of improbabilities. There is room in our philosophy for things undreamt of, and for dreaming, for remembering and forgetting, for loss and potency, for emergence and for nothing, nothing at all. And while there is room for conflict and even hostility, as our own years together evince, there is no room for hostility toward heterogeneity and historicity. In our next fifty years, let us take up our continental differing anew, not viewing it through the narrowed eyes of island-thought but affirming it in its Pangaean splendor.</p>
         <ref-list content-type="references">
            <title>WORKS CITED</title>
            <ref id="r1">
               <mixed-citation>Cilliers, Paul. 1998.<italic>Complexity and Postmodernism</italic>. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r2">
               <mixed-citation>Grosz, Elizabeth. 2011. “Matter, Life, and Other Variations.”<italic>Philosophy Today</italic>55 (SPEP Suppl.): 17–27.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r3">
               <mixed-citation>Harvey, David. 2009.<italic>Cosmopolitanism and the Geographies of Freedom</italic>. New York: Columbia University Press.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r4">
               <mixed-citation>Lingis, Alphonso. 1999. “Innocence.” In<italic>Becomings: Explorations in Time, Memory, and Futures</italic>, ed. Elizabeth Grosz, 201–16. Ithaca: Cornell University Press.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r5">
               <mixed-citation>Scott, Charles E. 1999.<italic>The Time of Memory</italic>. Albany: State University of New York Press.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r6">
               <mixed-citation>Scott, Charles E. 2002.<italic>The Lives of Things</italic>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s02">
         <sec-meta>
            <contrib-group>
               <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <string-name>
                     <italic>Charles E. Scott</italic>
                  </string-name>
                  <aff>Vanderbilt University</aff>
               </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
         </sec-meta>
         <title>The Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy's<italic>Formation</italic>and “Postmodern” Thought: The First Twenty-Five Years</title>
         <p>The year 1961 seems like an age ago. In that year President Ike Eisenhower seemed old and tired. He spoke prophetically, however, in his farewell address when he introduced the phrase “military-industrial complex.” It named what he considered to be a major threat for a new dimension of corruption of the political and governmental processes in this country. He also predicted that universities in the United States would lose a significant measure of their academic freedom if they accepted federal funds for government-initiated research. John F. Kennedy, in 1961, took the oath of office as this country's thirty-fifth president. He was a figure of hope and a new generation of dynamic leaders, and in his inaugural address he spoke eloquently of freeing the oppressed people of the world but seemed oblivious to issues of oppression and social justice in this country.</p>
         <p>In that year three states did not allow women to serve on juries, and the idea of women CEOs of large corporations seemed absurd in the popular imagination. In that imagination the proper place for them was in the home as wives and mothers, hospitals as nurses, primary and secondary schools as teachers, or libraries. The minimum wage increased by fifteen cents to $1.15 an hour. Algeria, Kenya, Angola, and many other countries were colonies, although major anticolonial movements took place around the world as Western colonial power crumbled. In May of that year the Freedom Rides and the extreme violence that went with them took place in the deep South and worked a largely unexpected revolution for interstate public transportation and for the standing and influence of the civil rights movement. Charlayne Hunter and Hamilton Homes entered the University of Georgia under heavy guard and brought the beginning of the end to segregation in that university. “Acid rain” first became a recognized concept in this country in 1961.</p>
         <p>Michel Foucault's<italic>Folie et déraison</italic>was published in that year. Jacques Derrida had not completed any of his major works. Gilles Deleuze had published only his<italic>Empirisme et subjectivité</italic>, but it was largely unknown in this country. A significant academic discussion that focused on a complex structural approach to language and culture called structuralism had a heavy impact on the human sciences, literature, and Marxism in the decade before 1961 that continued through the 1960s. Insofar as structuralist thought, however, was posed in opposition to existential and phenomenological thought, with their emphasis on consciousness and subjectivity, the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP), in its initial conception, might be considered a poststructuralist movement even in the absence of Foucault, Derrida, Deleuze, Lyotard, Kristeva, and Cixous. Its momentum took a direction that would sidestep or later absorb and transform some aspects of structuralist methodology and intention. French existentialism and especially Sartre held the spotlight as the archetype of post–World War II French literature and philosophy in 1961. Nietzsche (whom many philosophers considered irrelevant to serious philosophical thought) and Heidegger were often identified as existential philosophers. At that time neither had significant impact in North American, academic philosophy. Further, only a very few philosophers in the United States had even an introductory knowledge of Husserl's work.</p>
         <p>
            <italic>And</italic>in 1961 SPEP was conceived as an organization that was strictly academic. Its paternity is clear, although its maternity is shrouded in darkness. John Wild had left Harvard and joined the Northwestern Philosophy Department. He, Calvin Schrag from Purdue, James Edie and William Earle from Northwestern, and George Schrader from Yale constituted the founders who drew up the plans in the seminar room of Brentano Hall at Northwestern for the organization of SPEP and the preliminary plans for its first meeting in 1962 at Northwestern.</p>
         <p>In 1961 the relatively few philosophers in the United States who were interested in phenomenological and existentialist thought had few occasions to teach it or to work together professionally. Most philosophers in the tradition of positivism or that of what came to be known as analytic philosophy did not consider either phenomenology or existentialism as proper philosophy, and most philosophy departments were not interested in hiring even token colleagues in either area of expertise. The American Philosophical Association, of course, did not welcome papers in those areas. The New School for Social Research and Duquesne University had a core of philosophers, many of whom came to the States consequent to German National Socialism, who knew well the major phenomenological works. Northwestern University also became a leader in phenomenological thought, while Yale, thanks primarily to George Schrader, and Purdue, thanks to Cal Schrag and Richard Grabau, had graduate programs in 1961 where people could concentrate in phenomenology and existentialism (although Purdue formulated its Ph.D. program in philosophy in 1963, an M.A. in philosophy was possible in 1961). The full story of the early development of those two areas in the United States is complex and has yet to be told, but I want to note that the effort of many people who were on the front lines confronting a hostile professional atmosphere made possible SPEP's origination and set it on a course that worked a major change in our profession. That is a change that is not unlike the one effected by postmodern developments within SPEP itself, as we shall see.</p>
         <p>Some of the goals in SPEP's founding included providing occasions for presenting papers and carrying out formal and informal discussions as well as making opportunities for the formation of collegiality among philosophers from many different schools in the context of the phenomenological/existential traditions. They also included the crucial development of book series and journals for the publication of new work and translations of German and French works in these traditions. The German heritage, especially in the context of SPEP, brought with it an emphasis on the importance of the history of philosophy that was unique in the professional atmosphere in philosophy in the United States at that time. That heritage taught that Kant's work, for example, had significance that exceeded considerably part 1 of<italic>The Critique of Pure Reason</italic>. Plato, Aristotle, medieval thought, Hegel, and many other nineteenth-century German philosophers were part of the phenomenological canon in 1961, in addition to the modern period that analytic philosophers regularly taught. The European tradition that arrived in North America recognized those philosophers in the Western tradition as alive in contemporary thought, as distinct to being relics in a theoretical museum with the quaint name of the History of Philosophy. An inherent intention in SPEP's founding was to introduce phenomenology and existential thought to academics and intellectuals in this country and to make that introduction in the context of the history of Western philosophy.</p>
         <p>In the context of this essay on SPEP and postmodern thought (as it is called in popular discourse) I note that our beginning was strictly academic and professional with a primary emphasis on Husserlian phenomenology—Merleau-Ponty, Heidegger, and Sartre were strong secondary interests. The emphasis also fell on a transcendental orientation with additional recognition of the importance of the history of philosophy, a recognition that is not always apparent in Husserl's works. Typical of those academic times, there was minimal expressed alertness to issues of race, color, gender, or colonial domination. Some of the phenomenological and existential works did indeed hold the inception of the revolutionary turn of postmodern thought that would take place in SPEP, but that inception was largely imperceptible in the United States in 1961. It was contained in some of Sartre's work, especially in his way of developing an overt atheism and in his political writings; in Merleau-Ponty's work; and in Heidegger's early work and in the few pieces people read from his post–<italic>Being and Time</italic>writings, such as<italic>Vom Wesen der Wahrheit</italic>. Confrontations of various phenomenological and existential authors with William James, Ludwig Wittgenstein, and writings in structuralism also had effects that would grow in significance during the society's first fifteen years. As far as I can determine on the basis of available information, the first woman—Marjorie Grene—gave a paper (in a “paper session”) at SPEP in 1972 (although a few women gave “presentations” in sessions called workshops), ten years after its first meeting.</p>
         <p>I noted in the context of SPEP's beginning that “social issues” were usually separated from strictly “academic” ones. Postmodern thought in this country grew in part from the recognition that “modern” sensibility, for all its vagueness, included a type of identifiable Western white male domination that narrowed disastrously the range, perception, styles of thought, and sense of philosophical mission. Philosophers might well be concerned with conceptions of justice, freedom, human dignity, responsibility, and the social self in those early programs, but the gulf between such interest and direct social action was deep and wide. Philosophy had its own demanding and strictly patrolled life that set it apart from the everyday dimensions of existence with its tragic dominations, unquestioned codes of acceptability, and distributions of power. The volatility of emotions—especially those identified as “women's emotions”—and the hopeless messiness and relativity of people's psychological lives placed them in outlying regions of fundamental instability and beyond proper philosophical concern for most phenomenologists. The idea that truth might originate in error and senselessly perpetuate mere lack of the possibility for truth as it is traditionally and philosophically understood was not an operative part of SPEP's transformative vision for philosophy in the United States. Also missing was the sense that disciplined thought, moral values, and wisdom are founded by nothing they resemble. Few philosopher in those early years recognized that Western, white male orientations might be more of a problem that an admirable basis for recognizing and judging civilized behavior. Although SPEP's mission was to disturb the perceived complacency of North American philosophy in the “Anglo” tradition by the vigorous infusion of phenomenological and existential thought into the U.S. academy, it was also unwittingly poised for its own deep disturbance. That disturbance arose from innovative and transformative currents, some of them within phenomenology, existentialism, and the history of philosophy as they were appropriated in the United States and others developing in Europe and on the fringes of academic work in the United States. These disturbances grew in intensity<italic>both</italic>in highly disciplined philosophical thought<italic>and</italic>in a growing sense that everyday life, with its unstable, often violent psychological, social, and political complexity, must become a central focus for philosophers. One difficult issue we are moving toward is found in the question: How are we to retain an emphasis on well-trained historical knowledge and highly disciplined knowledge of important texts, on the one hand, and, on the other, carry out active, philosophical engagement with specific issues of language, power, injustice, irrationality, and cultural as well as academic complacency?</p>
         <p>There are perceptible changes in the orientation of SPEP papers in the 1960s. The eleven papers from the first two programs that James Edie edited and published in 1965 range within the phenomenological/existential area from issues of perception, lifeworld, and Husserlian horizons to authentic existence, solitude, and avoidance of the void.<xref rid="r001" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>1</sup>
            </xref>The next three meetings broadened the range of topics considerably by featuring papers that connected phenomenology to artificial intelligence, natural science, linguistics, schizophrenia, body image, social roles, tragedy, the experience of the holy, Hume, Kant, and Wittgenstein. A new person in the European scene, Jacques Derrida, was invited to the fifth conference, but he was unable to attend (he sent a mimeographed copy of his paper that was available in French for those at the conference who might wish to read it).</p>
         <p>In 1966 SPEP overtly reached out to philosophers who were not identified as phenomenologists or existentialists. This inclusiveness continued to grow as some of the leaders attempted to establish productive engagements especially with those who were analytically oriented but available for discussion with phenomenologists. Wittgenstein and Hume and issues of knowledge and language constituted early bridges for this connection. Behind the scenes many people thought that the SPEP meetings were diluted because of a desire to make phenomenology, if not existentialism, acceptable to the mainstream of respectability and power in North American philosophy. Others thought that if SPEP were to carry out its mission of transforming the philosophical sensibility in North America, it must take the first steps toward something like a productive exchange in which we invite their folks to our meetings and they invite ours to their meetings. This tactic had limited success due in part to the enormity of difference in conceptual commitments and in the traditions and canons that defined the various schools of thought. If it had succeeded and a significant number of analytically oriented people had become active and effective in SPEP, the atmosphere and sensibility of the organization might have been less receptive to postmodern thought than they were at the beginning of the 1970s. But in that decade SPEP attracted people with constructive interests in Marx, Nietzsche, hermeneutics (especially the work of Hans-Georg Gadamer), and a new generation of French thinkers who did not fit the labels of phenomenologist, existentialist, or analyst.</p>
         <p>I noted the sense of mission the founders and early leaders felt. They saw in the organization a means to make phenomenological and existential philosophy forces in North American thought, and they foresaw inclusion of a variety of philosophical approaches and topics to occasion among philosophers dialogue that was focused by phenomenology and existentialism while at the same time bringing together and in certain ways unifying the philosophers who where already engaged in what we now think of as Continental thought. In spite of the controversies and factions that developed along the way, the dominance of transcendentally oriented phenomenology became less and less pronounced during SPEP's first fifteen years. Interest in Sartre, Camus, and Heidegger grew. Emphasis intensified on language, interpretation, and historical developments and on such other disciplines as sociology, psychology, psychoanalysis, cognitive science, natural science, and religion. The Society for Phenomenology and the Human Sciences began holding sessions concurrently with some segments of the SPEP conferences. That group brought into SPEP's space a markedly different set of questions, issues, and approaches when compared with those that defined SPEP's orientation in the 1960s. These diversifying factors, combined with SPEP's ties with Germany, France, Belgium, and the Netherlands, fostered a growing interest in recent work that often departed from the kind of transcendental orientation found in classical phenomenology.</p>
         <p>By 1975 Don Ihde and Richard Zaner, who edited the fifth volume of selected papers from recent SPEP conferences, could write: “Phenomenology in the United States is in a state of ferment and change.”<xref rid="r002" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>2</sup>
            </xref>They began their book with Derrida's “The Copula Supplement” and noted that another “style” of philosophy “pertaining to language, signitive, and symbolic activity, and the relations of these to thought” had “begun to open the doors to themes introduced by the phenomenological and existential traditions”: “Jacques Derrida's opening essay on the copula supplement clearly represents one of the more radical approaches to language in Continental thought. Following Nietzsche and Heidegger, he calls into question the whole role of logic and grammar as it has related to the question of truth in Western philosophy.”<xref rid="r003" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>3</sup>
            </xref>
         </p>
         <p>Three years later in the next edition of selected SPEP papers the editors, Ronald Bruzina and Bruce Wilshire, noted an article by David Allison, “Structuralism Revisited: Levi Straus and Diachrony.”<xref rid="r004" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>4</sup>
            </xref>They suggested that to understand it the reader would need to draw from knowledge of Heidegger, Derrida, Deleuze, and Ricoeur. They also noted a paper by Matthieu Casalis, “Hermeneutics, Death of God, and Dissolution of the Subject: A Phenomenological Appraisal,” that indicates a growing challenge to what we could call a strong tendency toward totalization in some aspect of phenomenological thought, as well as the high stakes that are at issue. Interest in Marxist thought and critical theory as well as in social science also intensified during the 1970s, and by the end of the decade papers in these areas were common, while papers also emerged on politics and political action. The currents crossing the phenomenological mainstream were now strong and, for some members, challenging in a disconcerting way that most people in SPEP in the 1960s could not have imagined. Many people who were deeply impacted by the civil rights struggle (in spite of the absence in SPEP of a significant presence of people of color), the Vietnam War protests, and the growing awareness of colonialism and gender inequality were taking philosophy in the context of phenomenology and existentialism out of the modern transcendental and metaphysical domain, some by direct challenges to interpretations of canonical texts and others by setting new directions that arose out of contemporary problems and concern for social justice. Social-historical factors and careful analyses of narrative forms began to replace epistemology as leading interests, and these factors and forms often replaced metaphysical foundations in their work. “Humanism” became increasingly a problem rather than an unquestioned term concerning human life and the context of its interpretation.</p>
         <p>In 1979 at the eighteenth annual meeting at Purdue, SPEP held a referendum on the resolution: “The Society for Phenomenology and Existentialism will not in the future commit itself to hold meetings in states that have not yet passed the Equal Rights Amendment to the United States Constitution.” Profession combined with politics officially for the first time in the organization and in effect put in question the kind of professionalism that accompanied SPEP's founding. Also in 1979 the Nietzsche Society met for the first time concurrently with SPEP and was introduced by Anne Ashbaugh. Nietzsche had been a marginalized philosopher except as a subject for critique and, according to some members, superficial commentary. Now a new organizational space developed during SPEP's meetings for constructive engagement with the more radical dimensions of Nietzsche's thought and their affinity with the new “postmodern” work that had taken root in France. I find also significant the fact that at this time it was officially introduced by a woman. By 1979 “crosscurrents” had morphed into a pluralistic context that defined SPEP, and there was no longer a dominant mainstream but, rather, many different, constituent parts in a much expanded philosophical environment. Postmodern characteristics and style had become definitive of the<italic>organization</italic>of SPEP, not because of a new consensus concerning new ideas or methodologies or politics but because of diversification (some called it fragmentation) that constituted a major shift away from the direction and control of the identity to which the early SPEP has aspired. Discussion of the ideal of a community of consensus was not on the agenda, and due to developments in SPEP during the 1970s, the establishment of a community of consensus was not going to happen. Diversification and pluralization began to create a new, at least partially decentralized environment that was defined by no specific group that participated in it. Most members were no longer inclined to show the superiority of phenomenology vis-à-vis other approaches. Many people were rather more inclined to show the inadequacies of phenomenology and to take adversarial positions regarding it. At the same time, existentialism was slipping into a historical aspect of a larger context called, vaguely enough, Continental thought. The virtue of that term (and in solidarity with the vagueness of the term<italic>postmodern</italic>) was found in the accompanying impossibility to determine<italic>exactly</italic>what its defining limits might be.</p>
         <p>You can see that by 1980 SPEP was on a course, although it was not apparent then to many members, that is defined in SPEP's recent mission statement. Here is its wording:<disp-quote>
               <p>SPEP is the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy, a professional organization devoted to supporting philosophy inspired by continental European traditions.</p>
               <p>With a membership of over 2500 people it is one of the largest American philosophical societies, and strives to encourage work not only in the philosophical traditions of phenomenology and existentialism, but also in those areas commonly associated with “continental philosophy,” such as animal studies, critical theory, cultural studies, deconstruction, environmental philosophy, feminism, German idealism, hermeneutics, philosophy of the Americas, post-colonialism, post-structuralism, psychoanalysis, queer theory, and race theory.</p>
               <p>We foster discussion on all philosophical topics, from art and nature to politics and science, and in the classical philosophical disciplines of metaphysics, epistemology, ethics, and aesthetics. SPEP is actively committed to philosophical pluralism and to support of historically underrepresented groups in the philosophical profession.</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>This statement expresses a postmodern perspective more effectively than such concepts as deconstruction, death of God, poststructuralism, or genealogical thought. By virtue of is vagueness it articulates the absence of a defining subject, mastering terms, or a foundation for thought. It privileges varieties of approach and subject matter that destabilize each other and avoids a definitive framework that would guide the organization. Instead it offers SPEP as an open space for incompatible as well as compatible types of knowledge, approach, and philosophical sensibility. It affirms an indeterminate ambiguity in all words that people might otherwise interpret as centralizing and directive in an exclusive way. I believe that it reflects a kind of democratic pluralism rather more than the philosophical traditions could tolerate that came from Europe and played defining roles in SPEP's early years. I am quite sure that some of the organization's early leaders would consider the mission statement no less nihilistic than they found Nietzsche, Sartre, Derrida, Foucault, and all other philosophers identified as postmodern in 1980.</p>
         <p>We find one of the major conditions for this diversification in the growth of SPEP's membership and the number of participants on the programs. In its early days, when thirty or fewer people attended meetings, most sessions could be plenary, and people could expect during the conference conversations on papers and commentaries that everyone had heard. But as the members and range of interest increased, the number of sessions also increased to accommodate the volume of submissions and to lessen conflict with those who felt that their interests had inadequate representation on the programs. Growth brought with it complex new political problems involving incompatible points of view as well as gender and generational differences. The consequences of this growth included diversification and restructuring of the programs, an increased suspicion of and attention to the Executive Committee, an intensified alertness to exclusions, and the formation of a dynamic organization that had less and less to do with its name. These conditions helped to give birth to a new organizational arrangement where centralized power became increasingly fragmented. There was no one mission. There were multiple missions that gave rise to conflict and needed negotiation to function collaboratively, if often with suspicion of each other. But the revolution was not over.</p>
         <p>Before 1980 men dominated the organization and programs of SPEP. The growth of women's involvement in SPEP was a key factor in what I am identifying as its postmodern turn.<xref rid="r005" ref-type="fn">
               <sup>5</sup>
            </xref>On the basis of available information, 1972 appears to be a breakthrough year for women on the SPEP program: Five gave “presentations” in workshops, and Marjorie Grene presented what appears to be the first stand-alone paper that was published in a SPEP volume. The SPEP volume that included papers from 1976 and 1977 (entitled<italic>Dialogues and Bridges</italic>—not, you will notice,<italic>Crosscurrents</italic>—and edited by Ronald Bruzina and Bruce Wilshire) included papers by Joan Stambaugh, Sandra Rosenthal, Janet Farrell Smith, and Marie-Louise Schubert-Kalski. The volume<italic>Phenomenology in a Pluralistic Context</italic>(edited by William McBride and Calvin Schrag) included papers from 1978 by Mary C. Rawlinson and Arleen Dallery. From the 1979 meeting, the volume published Linda Bell's paper “Loser Wins: The Importance of Play in Sartre's Ethics of Authenticity.” From 1972 though 1979 seventeen women participated in SPEP programs. I do not have an adequate basis to state that no women participated in programs prior to 1972, but I believe that there is adequate information to show that relatively few women were included in SPEP programs before 1980 and that few if any of them directly addressed women's issues. At the same time we can safely assume that a considerable amount of ferment was taking place that set the stage for a major new development in SPEP. If you accept my observation that SPEP's postmodern turn includes organizational decentralization and uprooting of organizational foundations, then I believe you will agree that the feminist impact on SPEP in the 1980s constituted a major development in its postmodern turn.</p>
         <p>In 1980<italic>feminism</italic>was for the first time one of the program's keywords. A symposium took place titled “Feminism, Marxism, and Philosophy of Law.” Margaret Simons presented the paper “Beauvoir and Sartre: The Question of Influence.” (This appears to be the first paper on Beauvoir at a SPEP conference.) Four other women participated in or moderated workshops.</p>
         <p>In the SPEP volume published in 1983 and made up of selected papers from the seventeenth, eighteenth, and nineteenth meetings, the editors, William McBride and Calvin Schrag, commented on the “radicality, openness, passion for dialogue, freedom, and interest in pluralism” that the included papers made apparent. The year 1984 marked a significant turning point especially for the organization. The Committee on the Status of Women formed with the purpose of increasing the participation of women in SPEP. In 1981 six women participated in the program, three of them as moderators. In 1982 four women participated, one as moderator, and Joan Stambaugh gave an invited paper at the Nietzsche Society. In 1983 nine women participated, and two others gave papers at the Society for Phenomenology and the Human Sciences. In 1984, five women participated, with one moderator among them, and there were three women giving papers at the Society for Phenomenology and the Human Sciences. Then, after the founding of the Committee on the Status of Women in 1984, the program in 1985 had sixteen women on the program inclusive of two moderators, a keynote address by Julia Kristeva, and a book session on Ofelia Shutte's book<italic>Beyond Nihilism</italic>. One woman gave a paper at the Nietzsche Society. In that year Arleen Dallery became the first woman elected to SPEP's Executive Committee. The voting members at the twenty-fifth SPEP conference in 1986 selected Professor Dallery as the first woman co-director of SPEP, and twenty-four women were on the program, with four moderators. A panel discussed Linda Nicholson's book<italic>Gender and History</italic>, and Joan Stambaugh gave the paper “The Future of Continental Philosophy” in a plenary session symposium. Also in that year, at a tumultuous business session, the membership agreed that the Executive Committee would provide annually statistics on the number of papers by women that were submitted and that were accepted. Due to a certain hierarchy that had developed because of the distinctions among workshops (in which most women on the programs had participated), panels, and symposia, those distinctions would be dropped. The membership also agreed that increasing the number of concurrent speaking slots would be a good idea if warranted by acceptable submissions, and “every effort shall be made to make the program as diverse as possible in its representation of constituencies and of philosophical approaches to Continental philosophy.”</p>
         <p>I believe that in its twenty-fifth year SPEP brought to fruition a movement of incremental postmodern developments and made a full turn out of the modern orientation of its origin. That turn opened a new era for SPEP. Its origin had given SPEP life and vision and played a large role in transforming professional philosophy in the United States as it also transformed into a society that no one could have imagined in 1961.</p>
         <p>In 1986, however, SPEP's present mission statement could not have been conceived. Many important issues and questions remained unrecognized or simply ignored. But the opening before the organization was now a “postmodern” one, and a hallmark of what is called postmodern thought is its requirement that it transform in the force of its own lack of founded stability. I believe that 1986 began a series of developments that is turning SPEP toward ways of thought and life that cannot be labeled postmodern. I doubt that this turning constitutes a midlife crisis for SPEP in its fiftieth year. But it does highlight for me the fact that I have been giving a historical narrative that has to do with continuities in the dissolution of continuities, that I have not been—if I may put it this way—postmodern in an orthodox manner, although I have refused to give an unambiguous meaning to the term that has played a major role in organizing this essay. I do not know whether this discussion is postmodern, post-postmodern, or modern, and I do not care. I do care, however, about the openings that SPEP has provided for collegiality, conflict, unresolved differences, transformations, and sites for presentations, discussion, and critique. In my experience, in its own organizational development and travail, it has occasioned changes in the lives of many philosophers (mine among them). I expect that its indeterminate opening now—its continuing transformations in the interaction of many differences—will continue to surprise, irritate, and change those of us who participate in its opportunities. I close with a sense of beginning and an acknowledgment of the strangeness of the continuity that a series of beginnings provides: continuity without substance, continuity coming to pass.</p>
         <ref-list content-type="endnotes">
            <title>NOTES</title>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>Melinda Hall, who worked as a research assistant during the preparation of this paper, canvassed all the available Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP) programs and selected published papers. I am indebted to her for her excellent scholarly care and dedication in correlating topics and trends in the programs and compiling other information that I found crucial as I formulated and supported this essay's claims and interpretations.</mixed-citation>
               <mixed-citation>I note also that I highlight the word<italic>formation</italic>in the title to indicate that the issue of formation in the context of the development of SPEP in a way that I describe as “postmodern” will define an unresolved tension that guides the essay. I put<italic>postmodern</italic>inside quotation marks in the title. I do that to indicate that the term is a “so-called” one that many of us would define in different ways. A conviction that guides this essay is that its vagueness and lack of precision do not discourage its use by philosophers and nonphilosophers, and I will assume that when I use the term you will know, at least sort of, what it means. I will address “poststructuralism” indirectly in the context of the postmodern turn that SPEP as an organization took in its first twenty-five years.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r001">
               <label>1.</label>
               <mixed-citation>James Edie, ed.,<italic>An Invitation to Phenomenology: Studies in the Philosophy of Experience</italic>(Chicago: Quadrangle Books, 1965). There are two additional essays in that volume that were not presented at either program.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r002">
               <label>2.</label>
               <mixed-citation>Don Ihde and Richard Zaner, eds.,<italic>Dialogues in Phenomenology</italic>(The Hague: Springer, 1975), 1.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r003">
               <label>3.</label>
               <mixed-citation>Ibid., 2.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r004">
               <label>4.</label>
               <mixed-citation>Ronald Bruzina and Bruce Wilshire, eds.,<italic>Crosscurrents in Phenomenology</italic>(The Hague: Martinus Nijhoff, 1978).</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="r005">
               <label>5.</label>
               <mixed-citation>Information about participants on programs in the 1960s at the time I wrote this paper was limited to the published volumes of selected papers and a single program (1966). There are no papers by women in those volumes or in the 1966 program.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
