<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">40207523</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/600285</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR89332</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Kevin</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Trainor</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of Vermont.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2009</year>
            <string-date>July 2009</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>89</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>598689</issue-id>
         <fpage>456</fpage>
         <lpage>457</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Mrozik, </surname>
               <given-names>Susanne</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>Virtuous Bodies: The Physical Dimensions of Morality in Buddhist Ethics</source>. AAR Religion, Culture, and History Series. New York: Oxford University Press, 2007. ix+184 pp. $45.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2009 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved. For permission to reuse, please contact journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/600285"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>One of the dominant trends in Buddhist studies and in the study of religion more broadly during the past few decades has been the increasing focus on the significance of the material dimensions of religion. This emphasis on materiality is commonly advocated as a corrective to earlier scholarship that tended to privilege the intellectual, spiritual, and textualized forms of religion, and the effects of this reorientation can be seen in the increasing volume of scholarship devoted to material culture and religious ritual, ranging from studies that attend to the built environments within which religious practices take place and to the material objects employed by practitioners, to analyses of the complex interactions of embodied agents engaged in ritual practice. Feminist scholars of religion have contributed greatly to the turn to the material by drawing out the interpretive implications of the fact that those ritual agents are generally embodied as either males or females, as are the scholars who observe, analyze, and, in many cases, participate in those rituals.</p>
      <p>Susanne Mrozik’s<italic>Virtuous Bodies</italic>represents a significant contribution to this current rethinking of religion and Buddhist studies. The author explicitly locates her approach within the interdisciplinary field of feminist studies while also effectively placing the subject of her analysis, Śāntideva’s<italic>Compendium of Training</italic>(<italic>Śikṣ āsamuccaya</italic>), in dialogue with the work of such scholars as Michel Foucault, Elizabeth Grosz, Paul Ricoeur, and Charles Hallisey. In one respect, this study can be seen as quite traditional: the author develops her argument through a close reading of an influential Buddhist text, paying careful attention to the subtleties of its Sanskrit vocabulary and attempting to situate it within the medieval North Indian monastic milieu within which it took shape. This textual analysis provides the basis on which Mrozik advances toward the first stated goal of her work, to correct “the widespread misconception in scholarship on Buddhism and Buddhist ethics that South Asian Buddhists (with the exception of practitioners of Vajrayana or Tantric Buddhism) ascribed little value to bodies” (6). And Mrozik succeeds admirably in this regard, skillfully articulating how diverse and often seemingly contradictory perspectives on human embodiment come together in support of a religious ideal in which the “bodied being” (<italic>ātmabhāva</italic>) of bodhisattvas, interacting with the bodies of those whom they aim to liberate, plays a foundational role. Having first identified two dominant and contrasting somatic discourses in the<italic>Compendium of Training</italic>, one “physiomoral” and the other “ascetic,” Mrozik argues that the text presents a coherent ethical perspective, one in which “an ascetic discourse is in service of producing a range of virtuous bodied beings, valued for their physical as well as moral qualities” (116). As she notes, ascetic disciplines are grounded in an implicit assumption that embodiment matters greatly, even if these disciplines or “technologies of the self” enjoin the adoption of practices aimed at controlling and limiting particular aspects of somatic experience, in this case male sexual desire for women. As the text sets forth, the resplendent bodies of bodhisattvas produced by such technologies have the power to transform or “ripen” (<italic>paripac</italic>) other embodied beings, who take pleasure (<italic>prasāda</italic>) in them by seeing, touching, or even eating them.</p>
      <p>In another respect, however, Mrozik’s work moves beyond the aims of classical historical and philological research by attempting to engage this text as a “living argument” that has implications for how contemporary scholars and religious practitioners should engage in ethical reflection. This engagement represents the second goal of her work, to “explore the ethical implications of the<italic>Compendium of Training</italic>'s discourse on bodies for both medieval and contemporary audiences” (7), a goal that she takes up explicitly only in a brief concluding chapter. This project clearly resonates with the work of other contemporary scholars, including those who, influenced by feminist and postcolonial critiques of positivist methodologies, emphasize the intersubjective character of human encounter and understanding. Here Mrozik, drawing on Ricoeur’s work, employs a feminist “hermeneutics of recovery and suspicion” that seeks to take seriously the truth claims presented by the text as a valuable resource for contemporary ethics while also critiquing the text’s validation of particular social hierarchies, including those based on sex and caste. The author questions the assertion of some scholars that Indian Mahayana Buddhism invariably represented an elevation of the status of Buddhist women and argues against attempts to downplay evidence of sexual inequality by recourse to the Buddhist doctrine of “emptiness.” For Mrozik, the diverse forms of human embodiment provide the ground on which a serious engagement with ideals of human virtue must proceed.</p>
      <p>This second, more normative dimension of Mrozik’s project opens up some challenging questions. If it is the case, as she suggests, that a sympathetic reading of the<italic>Compendium of Training</italic>can provide valuable intellectual resources for contemporary ethical reflection, it remains unclear to me how our engagement with this text should proceed, given the significant disparities in cosmological assumptions (e.g., karmic causation and rebirth) and forms of practice that separate Mrozik’s contemporary readers from the text’s original audience. The text, moreover, appears less concerned with advancing particular truth claims than with creating a distinctive kind of religious subjectivity through ascetic and ritualized practice. Can we assess the value of the text’s ethical ideals apart from the forms of discipline and practice with which they were linked in medieval India? If<italic>Virtuous Bodies</italic>leaves such questions open to further exploration and analysis, its nuanced reading of the<italic>Compendium of Training</italic>brings into sharper focus the centrality of human embodiment in South Asian Buddhist religious discourses and encourages us to reflect deeply on its implications for our own ethical inquiry.</p>
   </body>
</article>
