<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">philrefo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50018096</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Philosophia Reformata</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Brill</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">00318035</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">23528230</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24707304</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>CHANGES IN THE CLIMATE OF THOUGHT</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Sander</given-names>
                  <surname>Griffioen</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1981</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>46</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24707302</issue-id>
         <fpage>103</fpage>
         <lpage>118</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24707304"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <fn-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         <title>[Footnotes]</title>
         <fn id="d376e101a1310">
            <label>1</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e108" publication-type="other">
John Maynard Keynes, The General Theory of Employment, Interest and
Money, London: Macmillan, 1936, p. 383. The passage continues: 'Practical men,
who believe themselves to be quite exempt from any intellectual influences, are
usually the slaves of some defunct economist. Madmen in authority, who hear
voices in the air, are distilling their frenzy from some academic scribbler of a few
years back. I am sure that the power of vested interests is vastly exaggerated com-
pared with the gradual encroachment of ideas.'</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e134a1310">
            <label>2</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e141" publication-type="other">
Richard H. Popkin, 'Manicheanism in the Enlightenment', in The Critical
Spirit. Essays in Honor of Herbert Marcuse, ed. by Kurt H. Wolff and Barrington
Moore, Jr., Boston: Beacon Press, 19683, pp. 31—54. The philosophes' pessimistic
undertone fîrst struck me when I was reading Peter Gay's work on the Enlighten-
ment; see The Enlightenment, Vol 1: The Rise of Modem Paganism, London:
Wildwood House, 1973, esp. pp. 59—68.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e164a1310">
            <label>3</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e171" publication-type="other">
See A. Troost on philosophy and ethos. Cf. Albert Wolters 'Ideas have Legs',
in A Christian Union in Labour's Wasteland, ed. by Edward Vanderkloet, Toronto,
Wedge, 1978, pp. 59—70. See also A. Wolters, 'World-view and Philosophy', Edito-
rial Anakainosis (A Journal for Reformational Thought), Toronto: AACS, Vol 3,
No. 1 (Sept. 1980). Undoubtedly the relation cultural climate — philosophy is less
unilatéral than would appear from my schematic représentation.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e194a1310">
            <label>4</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e201" publication-type="other">
H. van Riessen, Wat is filosoferen? (What is philosophizing?) Valedictory lec-
ture given on the occasion of his retirement from his post as Professor of Cal-
vinistic Philosophy at the Technical University in Delft, 25th Sept. 1974, Delft
University Press, pp. 14f (reproduced freely here). To avoid misunderstanding let
me say that what is proposed here does not imply that philosophy is merely a
matter of choices made on the basis of faith. Cf. also Van Riessen: 'This, of course,
does not make philosophizing an activity of faith. It is still qualified by the scientific
peculiarity of striving to put into words that which is seen of the transcendent at
the boundary line', (p. 14).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e234a1310">
            <label>5</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e241" publication-type="other">
On this last point see my oration Relatieve autonomie als kruispunt van wegen
(Relative autonomy at the crossroads), given on the occasion of my taking up the
post of professor of the philosophy of the socio-cultural sciences at the Free
University, lOth October 1980. There I pointed out that marxists on the whole
gloss over this choice (esp. note 25). Peter Singer recently made a number of inter-
esting observations about this in the context of a review of several new publications
on Marx's view of history. See for example the following passages on William H.
Shaw's Marx's Theory of History (Stanford Univ. Press): 'Shaw has to admit that
the arguments Marx offers for the key idea of historical materialism — that material
production dominâtes social life — are "flimsy and perfunctory". How can this be,
if Marx considered himself a scientist and this was his great discovery? Shaw's
explanation is that Marx was so convinced that the primacy of production was
obvious that he did not see the need for more argument. But why was he so con-
vinced that it was obvious? Here Shaw uneasily confesses: "one senses that Marx
and Engels attached some sort of ontological primacy to material production, from
which its explanatory weight for social science follows". In short, Marx and Engels
simply regarded production as more "real" than politics, religion and ideas.' (Peter
Singer, New York Review of Books, 20 December 1979, p. 45).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e302a1310">
            <label>6</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e309" publication-type="other">
H. Algra, 'Wat is normaal?' ('What is normal?') in Wat is normaal?, Hendrik
Algra, Bob Goudzwaard and J. P. A. Mekkes, Baarn: Bosch &amp; Keuning, 1974, p. 19.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e319a1310">
            <label>7</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e326" publication-type="other">
Κ. Rosenkranz: 'Erblickt man in der Folge der philosophischen Système nur
eine Galerie von zufàlligen Meinungen, so gibt es nichts Trostloseres, als das
Studium der Geschichte der Philosophie' das nur einen oberflàchichen Skepticis-
mus, den weltmânnischen Standpunkt des Pilatus, zur Folge haben kann.' (Hegel als
Deutscher Nationalphilosoph, Leipzig, 1870, p. 218). Cf. also G. J. P. J. Bolland's
address In den strijd om de waarheid (In the struggle for truth), 'What is truth?
asks the official représentative of the prevailing non-christian world. And in our
days the non-christian world has more inclination than ever to say with Sextus the
sceptic, nothing is true'. (Academische les) (Academie Lesson), Leiden University,
30th September 1905, Leiden: Α. H. Adriani, 1905, p. 55).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e361a1310">
            <label>8</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e368" publication-type="other">
Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel, Sàmtliche Werke, Stuttgart: H. Glockner,
1927—1940, Vol 19, p. 96 (In the Theorie Werkausgabe of Suhrkamp Verlag,
Vol 19, p. 489). For corresponding texts see esp. Einleitung in die Geschichte der
Philosophie, Berlin: J. Hoffmeister, 1966. See in addition my dissertation De Roos
en het Kruis (The Rose and the Cross). An appraisal of finiteness in the later Hegel,
Assen: Van Gorcum, 1976, esp. pp. 170—178.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e391a1310">
            <label>9</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e398" publication-type="other">
J. Ν. Findlay, The philosophy of Hegel, New York: Collier Books, 19662,
pp. 142f.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e408a1310">
            <label>10</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e415" publication-type="other">
Fr. Nietzsche, Unzeitgemasse Betrachtungen, part 2: Vom Nutzen und Nach-
teil der Historie, Friedrich Nietzsche Werke, publ. Karl Schlechta, München:
Hanser, 1966, p. 263.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e429a1310">
            <label>11</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e436" publication-type="other">
There was neither time nor space in this oration to deal with the ambiguity
of 'everything' ('... and everything is justified on the basis of it'). The non-rational,
the inadequate and purely phénoménal, or in short, the finite, is only justified when
it ceases to exist (aufgehoben). With the vanishing of the finite, i.e. where its radical
inadequacy manifests itself, the infinité makes its appearance. 'Das Nichtsein des
Endlichen ist das Sein des Absoluten' (see my dissertation, p. 146), or rather with
a Bolland variation, 'the very insignificance of all finite truth is the validity of the
infinité'. (In den strijd om de waarheid, p. 56).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e465a1310">
            <label>12</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e472" publication-type="other">
The justification of the Enlightenment is the main theme of an essay which
I have not yet published, the title of which is 'The triumph of inconclusiveness in
Hegei's Philosophy of the Christian Religion'. For the broader context see my dis-
sertation, chapter 5 of part I, 'De macht van de geschiedenis' ('The power of
history').</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e491a1310">
            <label>13</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e498" publication-type="other">
See the oration mentioned in note 5.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e505a1310">
            <label>14</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e512" publication-type="other">
See for instance J. P. A. Mekkes, Tijd der bezinning (Time of reflection).
Buijten en Schipperheijn, 1973, pp. 52f. et al. (On the capitulation to the powers).
See in addition H. van Riessen, Mondigheid en de machten (Emancipation and the
powers), Amsterdam: Buijten en Schipperheijn, 1976; and E. Schuurman, Tech-
niek, Middel of Moloch? Kampen: Kok, 19802 (Egbert Schuurman, Reflections on
the Technological Society, Toronto: Wedge, 1977).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e535a1310">
            <label>15</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e542" publication-type="other">
J. P. A. Mekkes, 'Methodologie en praxis' ('Methodology and praxis'), vale-
dictory address given on the occasion of departure as professor of Calvinistic
philosophy at Erasmus University in Rotterdam on 16th November 1972, Philo-
sophia Reformata, 43 (1978), pp. 2—10; the passage quoted is on p. 8.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e558a1310">
            <label>16</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e565" publication-type="other">
Chapters IV, V of Louis Althusser/Étienne Balibar, Lire le Capital, I, Paris:
Maspero, 1969. In the address mentioned in note 5 I dealt with the fourth chapter
in greater depth.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e579a1310">
            <label>17</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e586" publication-type="other">
L. Althusser, Antwoord aan John Lewis (Answer to John Lewis), Nijmegen:
SUN, 1974, pp. 79—84: Opmerking over een categorie: "proces zonder Subject of
Doeleinde(n)" ' (Observation on a category: "Process without Subject or Pur-
pose(s)" '), see also Pour Marx, Paris: Maspero, 1969, final chapter ('Marxisme et
Humanisme').</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e605a1310">
            <label>18</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e612" publication-type="other">
See for instance Paolo Caruso's discussion with Foucault which was printed
in the German collection Von der Subversion des Wissens, publ. Walter Seitter,
München, Cari Hanser, 1974, pp. 7—31. In one place Foucault proposes that the
notion 'man' took on about the same function in the last century as the idea of
God had in previous centuries, namely as the final crowning point of the hierarchy
of being.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e635a1310">
            <label>19</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e642" publication-type="other">
See esp. his 'Nietzsche, l'histoire, la généalogie', in Hommage à Jean Hyppolite,
Paris, 1971; German translation in Von der Subversion des Wissens, pp. 83—109.
A further implication of his affinity with Nietzsche is that he is more critical of
Marx and Marxism than is Althusser. See for instance Peter Dews, 'The Nouvelle
Philosophie and Foucault', in Economy and Society, Vol. 8, Number 2 (May 1979),
pp. 131—171. For a more général context see also the equally clear and instructive
article by James Miller, 'Some Implications of Nietzsche's Thought for Marxism',
in Telos, Number 37 (Fall 1978), pp. 22—41.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e671a1310">
            <label>20</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e678" publication-type="other">
See for instance Von der Subversion, pp. 90f. A subject in which seeking for
unity cornes to the fore is that of discourse. See his inaugural address at the Collège
de France, L'ordre du discours, 1971. The relation between 'unity' and 'Western'
with respect to Foucault was pointed out by Young -ahn Kang, a philosophy student
at Louvain and a former student of Dr Bon Ho Son at the Hankuk University of
Foreign Studies te Séoul, 'Against Subjectivistic Philosophy, Foucault Sees Hidden
Will or Power by Decentring of Subjects', in The Argus, Hankuk University, Séoul,
February 1, 1980, p. 7.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e707a1310">
            <label>21</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e714" publication-type="other">
Jozef van de Wiele, Nietzsche en het Westerse denken (Nietzsche and Western
Thought). De bekoring van het naturalisme (The charm of naturalism), Louvain:
Acco, 1976, pp. 123f; the inverted commas are the author's.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e727a1310">
            <label>22</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e734" publication-type="other">
Jan M. Broekman, Mens en mensbeeld uan ons recht (Man and the image of
man in law). Over recht en antropologie (On law and anthropology). Part I: Antro-
pologie (Anthropology). Louvain: Acco, 1979, p. 44 (cf. p. 32 e.a.).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e748a1310">
            <label>23</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e755" publication-type="other">
R. C. Kwant, Subject en zin (Subject and Meaning), Inaugural address on
taking up the post of professor at the University of Utrecht, 6th November 1961,
Utrecht/Antwerp, Het Spectrum, 1961.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e768a1310">
            <label>24</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e775" publication-type="other">
Maatschappijkritiek (Social Criticism), Alphen a.d. Rijn: Samsom, 1976,
pp. 181—186 ('Vraagtekens bij het humanisme') ('Questions posed to humanism')
and pp. 187—188 ('De relatieve autonomie van het maatschappelijke') ('The relative
autonomy of society'); the passage quoted is on p. 187.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e791a1310">
            <label>25</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e798" publication-type="other">
Op. cit., p. 186.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e805a1310">
            <label>26</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e812" publication-type="other">
Cf. Kwant, op. cit., pp. 185f.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e819a1310">
            <label>27</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e826" publication-type="other">
In my Free University oration I dealt with this extensively.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e833a1310">
            <label>28</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e840" publication-type="other">
The reference to Spinoza is not at all far-fetched as Althusser himself is
seeking a closer affinity with Spinoza's teaching in the matter of the various kinds
of knowledge. See H. Manschot, Althusser over het marxisme (Althusser on mar-
xism), dissertation, University of Groningen, 1979, Chapter IX, 1 ('De Imaginatio
bij Spinoza') ('The Imagination in Spinoza') and 2 ('Althussers gebruik van de
spinozistiese ideologietheorie') ('Althusser's use of the spinozistic theory of
ideology').</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e867a1310">
            <label>29</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e874" publication-type="other">
See for instance Lire le Capital, I, pp. 47f, 169f. See also MansChot, op. cit.,
pp. IV—17, IV—21f. 'Not in the superstructure' does not mean here simply 'then
it is in the basis'. The 'problem' is that scientific thought, as thought, cannot be
put in the same category as material powers of production; cf. Lire le Capital,
p. 47 : 'Ce système de production théorique, système matériel autant que "spiri-
tuel"...'. Manschot admits 'that Althusser has not yet been able to develop a new
formulation of the problem of the relation science-society. Strictly speaking, he has
not got further than the assertion that the old notions of this relationship are no
longer tenable'. (IV—22).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e906a1310">
            <label>30</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e913" publication-type="other">
'Where, then, does natural science belong in the Marxian model? Insofar as
its conceptions and findings can be used to make material use-values (that is,
generally), it belongs to the realm of productive forces...', according to John
McMurtry in his clear but uncritical study The Structure of Marx's World-View,
(Princeton Univ. Pr., 1978, p. 125, note 2). The same is true for technology; in as
much as it is useful, it is free of ail suspicion of ideology. It seems to me that this
idea stands in the way of a critical reflection on natural science and technology.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e939a1310">
            <label>31</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e946" publication-type="other">
Foucault, Von der Subversion des Wissens, pp. 13, 31.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e953a1310">
            <label>32</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e960" publication-type="other">
See for example the following remark by R. C. Kwant: 'Foucault doubts
whether the 'ordre du discours' established and thrust upon us by our society is
the true one, the really décisive one. His thesis is that there is a more essential,
more determing 'ordre du discours' which détermines our speaking, and so our
knowing, without our being conscious of it.' (Structuralisten en Structuralisme
(Structuralists and Structuralism), Alphen a. d. Rijn: Samsom, 1978, p. 155).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e983a1310">
            <label>33</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e990" publication-type="other">
'Sagen wir also, dass die Rolle des Philosophen, der zu sagen hat, "was los
ist", heute vielleicht darin liegt, aufzuweisen, dass die Menschheit die Möglichkeit
eines Funktionierens ohne Mythen zu entdecken beginnt. Das Verschwinden der
Philsophien und Religionen könnte damit zusammenhàngen.', Von der Subversion,
p. 31. The critical passage from Paul Ricoeur's essay 'Ideologie und Ideologiekritik'
is mutatis mutandis applicable here. 'Ein nicht-ideologischer Diskurs iiber die
Ideologie stösst hier auf die Unmöglichkeit, eine soziale Wirklichkeit vor der Sym-
bolisierung ausfindig zu machen.' (Phanomenologie und Marxismus, I, publ. by
B. Waldenfels, J. M. Broekman and A. Pazanin, Frankfurt a. Main: Suhrkamp,
1977, p. 212).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e1025a1310">
            <label>34</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e1032" publication-type="other">
Kwant refers somewhere to Foucault's expression 'fundamental ideas which
intrude for a moment': According to Kwant's sober commentary, 'Formerly other
fundamental ideas used to intrude, tomorrow perhaps there will be still others.
Foucault appears to have a very strange notion of "grondbegrippen" (fundamental
ideas).' (Structuralisten, p. 149).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e1052a1310">
            <label>35</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e1059" publication-type="other">
Cf. Mekkes on the neo-kantian doctrine of values: 'The idea of autonomy of
modern value-philosophy has taken its position in the element of truth of subjective
responsibility ('In het waarheidsmoment der subjectieve verantwoordelijkheid heeft
de autonomiegedachte der moderne waardenleer stelling genomen...') (De be-
teekenis van het subject in de moderne waarde-philosophie onder het licht der wets-
idee (The meaning of the subject in modern valuephilosophy in the light of the
cosmonomic idea), Inaugural address at the University of Leyden, 14th October
1949, Leiden: Leiden University Press, 1949, p. 66).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e1088a1310">
            <label>36</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e1095" publication-type="other">
See Ricoeur in the essay mentioned in note 33 on the transition from 'sub-
ject' to 'structure' in Althusser's works: 'Zugleich wird damit die Wachsamkeit
gegenüber Verifizierung und Falsifizierung geschwàcht' (p. 208). Openness on this
point cannot, in my opinion, be expected until followers of Althusser show a
readiness to abandon the disastrous notion that the appealing, interpellating
^uthority which demands accountibility can be no other than Ideology. See for
instance Althusser, 'Ideologie en ideologische staatsapparaten' ('Ideology and
ideological state apparatuses'), in Te elfder ure (At the eleventh hour), 24 (1978,
no. 1), pp. 99f: 'the individual is addressed as a (free) subject, so that it subjects
itself in freedom to the commandments of the Subject' (100), '... the ideology
brings about simultaneously (1) the addressing of the 'individuals' as subjects; (2)
their subjection to the Subject' (99).</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e1137a1310">
            <label>37</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e1144" publication-type="other">
Heinz Kimmerle, Philosophie der Geisteswissenschaften als Kritik ihrer
Methoden, Den Haag: Nijhoff, 1978, pp. 95, 82, 86, 89, et al.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e1154a1310">
            <label>38</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e1161" publication-type="other">
'Methodologie en praxis', p. 4.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
         <fn id="d376e1168a1310">
            <label>39</label>
            <p>
               <mixed-citation id="d376e1175" publication-type="other">
J. P. van Praag, 'Levensovertuiging, filosofie en wetenschap' ('World-view,
philosophy and science'), valedictory address given on retirement from the Univer-
sity of Leiden, 13th November 1979, Utrecht, Humanistisch Verbond, pp. 9, 7, 10.</mixed-citation>
            </p>
         </fn>
      </fn-group>
   </back>
</article>
