<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">alifjcomppoet</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j100021</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Alif: Journal of Comparative Poetics</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>American University in Cairo. Department of English and Comparative Literature</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">11108673</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4047433</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title> ﺣﻔﺮﻳﺎﺕ أدبية في شعر محمود درويش: مشروع قراءة في قصيدة (( ﺍﻟﻬﺪﻫﺩ)) / Literary Excavations in Mahmud Darwish's Poetry: A Reading Project of the "The Hoopoe" </article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>‮محمد</given-names>
                  <surname>عجينة‬</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Mohammaed</given-names>
                  <surname>Agina</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2004</year>
         </pub-date>
         <issue>24</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i376713</issue-id>
         <fpage>89</fpage>
         <lpage>118</lpage>
         <page-range>89-118</page-range>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement> 2004 Department of English and Comparative Literature / ‮حقوق النشر محفوظة لقسم الأدب الإنجليزي والمقارن وقسم النشر بالجامعة الأمريكية بالقاهرة، ٢٠٠٤ ٠‬ </copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/4047433"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>This article constitutes an exploration of Mahmud Darwish's poem, "The Hoopoe," as part of a study on the relationship of myths to culture, in general, and to literature and poetry, in particular. It starts from the hoopoe as a mythical symbol pulling the text in two directions. First, a direction that relates the poem, through time, to the realms of the universe, dream, and poetry, using the language of insinuations and allusions; second, a fictional direction that makes of the the poem-through evocation of previous quest journeys, including texts by Al-Jahiz, Avicenna, Al-Suhrawardi, Al-Hallaj, Aristophanes, and Farid Al-Din Attar-a quest into the depths of the individual and the collective self. Memory, history, and language, culminate in the discovery of the mother-land. Thus, Darwish's poem may be classified as poetry, prose, drama, and epic. It is, in fact, a mixture of all these genres, as well as a literary myth narrating the story of the search for a sacred time-the time of beginnings, and of childhood. /تمثل المقالة حفراﹰ استبطانياﹰ في قصيدة "الهدهد" لمحمود درويش - ضمن بحث في علاقة الأساطير بالثقافة عامة وبالأدب والشعر خاصة - انطلاقاﹰ من الهدهد كرمز أسطوري يتجاذب النص في اتجاهين اثنين: أ- اتجاه جدولي، يصل القصيدة - عبر الزمن - بعالم الكون وعالم المنام وعالم الشعر في لغة اللمح والإشارة٠ ب- اتجاه أفقي قصصي، يجعل من القصيدة - عبر رحلات نموذجية سابقة ومن خلال نصوص حاضرة غائبة للجاحظ، وابن سينا، والسهروردي، والحلاج، وأرسطوفان، وفريد الدين العطار، وغيرهم - رحلة في أعماق الذات الفردية، وفي أعماق الذات الجماعية ذاكرة وتاريخاﹰ٠ تجمع قصيدة درويش بين "الشعر" و"النثر" والمسرحية والملحمة، كما أنها أسطورة أدبية تقص علينا قصة بحث عن زمن مقدس هو زمن البدايات والطفولة٠‬</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>ara</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
