<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4625875</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519893</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JR87320</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Friedrich</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Schweitzer</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve">,</x>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of Tuebingen.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2007</year>
            <string-date>July 2007</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>87</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>509554</issue-id>
         <fpage>462</fpage>
         <lpage>463</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name name-style="western">
               <surname>Browning, </surname>
               <given-names>Don S.</given-names>
            </string-name>
            <source>Christian Ethics and the Moral Psychologies</source>. Religion, Marriage, and Family. Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2006. ix+244 pp. $30.00 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/519893"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>This book is based on Don Browning’s most recent work on the relation of Christian ethics and the moral psychologies—a plural that the author uses in order to indicate the pluralist nature of this academic field. Browning states his guiding question as follows: should “moral theologians critique these psychologies and perhaps cleanse both theology and the wider culture of the possible mistaken images of moral responsibility proffered by them?” His “brief answer” is that “<italic>contemporary moral psychology can contribute to Christian ethics, but only when it does its research with competent pre‐scientific or pre‐empirical understandings of morality”</italic>(2). Accordingly, Browning’s special interest refers to the understandings of morality that research presupposes. It is these preunderstandings that require critical analysis by, among others, theologians. The model that Browning uses in his analysis is an adaptation of Paul Ricoeur’s critical hermeneutical ethics. This ethics combines hermeneutical sensitivity to different cultural and religious traditions with a critical point of view informed by, among others, the social sciences and philosophical ethics. It gives due attention to particular visions of the good life and of the “status of humans” (10) without losing touch with the claims of universalist ethical criteria (“the deontological test” [52]). It may also be called “antifoundationalist” in that it begins with history and moral tradition rather than with empirical research as a supposedly objective basis.</p>
      <p>The individual chapters of the book refer to this critical hermeneutical understanding developed in the introduction and in chapter 1 (in conversation with Reinhold Niebuhr) in different ways by taking up various models from the field of moral psychology and by discussing them critically: psychoanalysis (Sigmund Freud and, in a special chapter devoted to the understanding of generativity, Erik H. Erikson), structural‐developmental theories (Lawrence Kohlberg, Carol Gilligan), Johannes van der Ven’s understanding of moral education and practical theology, evolutionary psychology, feminist approaches, rational‐choice economics, and, throughout the book, the collaborative “Hardwired to Connect” study on “authoritative communities” published a few years ago. In addition, there are chapters with a focus on Christian and philosophical ethics: on Niebuhr and Ricoeur, whose influence on Browning is visible in his whole approach, but also on a number of contemporary ethicists like Martha Nussbaum, Owen Flanagan, Gene Outka, and Antonio R. Damasio.</p>
      <p>Whoever has followed Browning’s publications over the last three decades will easily recognize the impressive continuity of his interest in the relationship between practical theology and ethics. As he points out himself (193), the present book elaborates what Browning refers to as the different “levels or dimensions of the human” implied in the conversation between theology and psychology (193). At the same time, the book is much more than a mere sequel to Browning’s earlier statements. It is a major step toward a “practical theological ethics” (85) that brings together theology, philosophical ethics, and the varieties of moral psychology. It takes up the most recent challenges of evolutionary psychology. Finally, it makes a major step toward a theological understanding of premoral goods—a topic that Browning rightly considers of key importance for the public role of theology.</p>
      <p>While this book will be of great interest to Christian ethicists as well as to religious and moral educators, it should also be read by social scientists, philosophers, and evolutionary psychologists. Browning’s view that nontheological disciplines depend on images of the human that play a guiding role for their research, as well as for the interpretation of their results, points to the continued need for more interdisciplinary work. According to this point of view, theology should play a public role in identifying such prescientific or preempirical images as well as in describing and advancing refined and responsible images based on the Christian tradition. The present volume goes a long way in either direction.</p>
   </body>
</article>
