<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">reviportfilo</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50000595</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Revista Portuguesa de Filosofia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Faculdade de Filosofia</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">08705283</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">2183461X</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">40336506</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Towards the Elimination of the Concept of Truth in Analytical Construction</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Menuel</given-names>
                  <surname>Lourenço</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>1982</year>
      
            <day>1</day>
            <month>3</month>
            <year>1982</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">38</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">1</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i40014441</issue-id>
         <fpage>153</fpage>
         <lpage>169</lpage>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/40336506"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>It is here proposed the elimination of the concept of truth in analytical construction by substituting for it the concept of terminal evidence of an assertion. Terminal evidence is in turn explained in terms of anschauliche non-deterministic sequences and portions of finitist logic generated by these sequences are sketched both for statements without quantifiers and statements with first order quantifiers. Emphasis is given to the nature of negation and existence in the proposed elimination. /// Es wird vorgeschlagen, die Eliminierung des Wahrheitsbegriffes in der analytischen Konstruktion durch die Einsetzung des Begriffes der endgultigen Evidenz einer Aussage durchzufuhren. Bei der Einfuhrung von anschaulichen akausalen Folgen lasst sich der Begriff der endgultigen Evidenz erklaren und Teile der finiten Logik, die solche Folgen erzeugen, werden skizziert sowohl fur Aussagen ohne Quantoren als auch fur solche, bei denen nur Quantoren der ersten Stufe vorkommen. Die Natur der Negation und des Existenz-Begriffes ist insbesondere hervorgehoben. /// É proposto efectuar-se a eliminação do conceito de verdade na construção analitica pela introdução do conceito da evidência terminal de uma asserção. Com a introdução de sucessões não-deterministas é elucidado o conceito de evidência terminal e os fragmentos de lógica finitista que estas sucessões originam são esboçados quer para o caso de asserçães sem quantores quer para aquelas asserções em que só ocorrem quantores de 1.a ordem. A natureza da negação e do conceito da existência são especialmente destacados.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>Bibliography</title>
         <ref id="d221439e120a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e124" publication-type="other">
Brouwer, L. E. J. «Intuitionististische Betrachtungen fiber den Formalismus» Sit-
zungsberichte der Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, Phys.-
-Math. Klasse, 1928, pgs. 48-52.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e137a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e141" publication-type="other">
Brouwer L. E. J. «Mathematik, Wissenschaft und Sprache” Monatshefte fiir Mathe-
matik und Physik, Leipzig 1929.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e151a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e155" publication-type="other">
Brouzvery L. E. J. «Consciousness, Philosophy and Mathematics* Proceedings of the
X International Congress of Philosophy , Amsterdam 1948.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e165a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e169" publication-type="other">
Dummetty M. “Truth”Proceedings of the Aristotelean Society3 vol. 59, 1958-1959,
pgs. 141-62.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e180a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e184" publication-type="other">
Ferencziy S. Schriften zur Psychoanalyse, Auswahl in Zwei Banden, herausge-
geben und eingeleitet von M. Balint, S. Fischer Verlag, 1970</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e194a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e198" publication-type="other">
Freud, S. Gesammelte Werke, Chronologisch Geordnet, Imago Publishing
Co., Ltd., London 1949.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e208a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e212" publication-type="other">
Hey ting, A. “Die formalen Regeln der intuitionistischen Logik” Sitzungsberi-
chte der Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin 1930,
pgs. 42-56.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e225a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e229" publication-type="other">
Hey ting, A, Intuitionism, An Introduction, North Holland Publishing Co.,
Amsterdam 1956.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e239a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e243" publication-type="other">
Kreisel, G. “Informal Rigor and Completeness Proofs” Problems in the Philo-
sophy of Mathematics, ed. I. Lakatos, Amsterdam 1974.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e253a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e257" publication-type="other">
Ricoeur, P. “The Question of Proof in Freud's Psychoanalytic Writings”
The Philosophy of Paul Ricoeur : An Anthology of His Work, ed.
by Ch. Reagan and D. Stewart, Boston Beacon Press, 1978, pgs.
184-210.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e274a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e278" publication-type="other">
Specht, E. K. «Die sprachphilosphischen und ontologischen Grundlagen im
Spatwerk Ludwig Wittgenstein* Kantstudien, Erganzungshefte
herausgegeben von Ingeborg Heidemann, Kolner Universitats
Verlag, 1963.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d221439e294a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d221439e298" publication-type="other">
Wittgenstein, L. Bemerkungen tiber die Grundlagen der Mathematik, Basil Blackwell,
Oxford 1956.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
