<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jmodernhistory</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Modern History</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00222801</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375358</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4501317</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/511206</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JMH78040401</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Reviews</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Stéphane</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Gerson</surname>
               </string-name>
               <x xml:space="preserve"/>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">New York University</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>December 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>78</volume>
         <issue>4</issue>
         <issue-id>jmh.2006.78.issue-4</issue-id>
         <fpage>932</fpage>
         <lpage>933</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>History, Historians, and Autobiography</source>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Jeremy D. </given-names>
               <surname>Popkin</surname>
            </string-name>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,<year>2005</year>. Pp. x+339. $60.00 (cloth); $22.95 (paper).</product>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/511206"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Modesty, sublimation, effacement of the self: such are the demands the historical profession has long made of its members. While historians have not shied away from self‐revelation—be it in autobiographies or, since the 1980s, in increasingly prevalent essays, interviews, and lectures—history still entertains an uneasy relationship with literary expressions of the self. Jeremy D. Popkin has accordingly left his usual hunting grounds (the press in modern France) to take a closer look at the historian’s autobiography. His learned and passionate<italic>History, Historians, and Autobiography</italic>analyzes the genre’s formal and sociological characteristics. Responding to the historians and literary scholars who, in his view, have unfairly castigated or neglected such autobiographies, it also redeems the genre as a distinctive gateway into the riches of the past and human experience. While the shifts between registers are sometimes dizzying, Popkin’s fine analysis and deep empathy yield an illuminating and singularly humane book.</p>
      <p>Popkin defines such autobiographies as published personal narratives in which professional historians discuss first and foremost their lives. His corpus includes close to four hundred book‐length and shorter texts by Western historians—essentially Americans and Europeans. Following Paul Ricoeur, Popkin emphasizes the literary autonomy of autobiography. While it shares traits with history and fiction, this “hybrid genre” alone brings together “an unstable mixture of fabulation and actual experience,” an independence from documentation, an investigation into “the inner experience of time,” a lack of closure, and an ability to supplement reality through rhetorical transformation (45, 47).</p>
      <p>This posited, Popkin furnishes a wealth of information on the origins of the historian’s autobiography (Hume, Gibbon, Vico), its nineteenth‐century expressions (Dilthey, Henry Adams), and especially its sociological and literary characteristics during the second half of the twentieth century. Most authors have been white males, from middle‐class backgrounds, nearing the end of distinguished careers. Still, women, minorities (especially Jews), historians of working‐class origin, and middle‐aged authors have made inroads since the 1980s. This produces significant differences: women, for instance, are less likely than men to link their vocation to their teenage interest in history or to depict a nurturing community of scholars. Popkin minimizes, however, the impact of sociology. Commonalities predominate in his analysis. Most historian‐autobiographers, for one, frame their life stories as bildungsroman narratives, in which the author’s personality takes shape through the choice of a vocation. Like Friedrich Meinecke, they tell tales of self‐discovery, free will, and success. Their chronological accounts usually begin with warm childhoods in families that encouraged reading, education, and a thoughtful path toward a meaningful career. They then describe the pivotal apprenticeship and university years, the key mentors, and the decision‐making process through which the authors exercised their will and defined themselves. Theirs is invariably a process of choice rather than conflict or sudden illumination, even if world events captured the imaginations of many budding historians.</p>
      <p>Omissions are plentiful in these accounts: the selection of a field, the routines of teaching, squabbles with colleagues, rivalries, ambition and desire for recognition. Exceptions surface here too—women who discuss gender bias in their profession, authors from the working class who struggle to adapt to the academic world—but most authors keep mute on the same questions. Popkin offers several explanations for these silences, ranging from shame to fear of colleagues’ reactions to narrative concerns (tedium, lack of drama). The most significant and fascinating factor, however, is that these authors write autobiographies as, first and foremost, members of a profession. They free themselves, it is true, from this profession’s norm of self‐effacement by expressing their individuality and discussing private matters. But they do not shed their disciplinary identity in the process. On the contrary, their autobiographies sustain the profession’s norms and values. They minimize conflicts, belittle individual achievements (in the classroom, for instance), and omit mention of aspirations that question the ideal of fraternal, disinterested scholars who live a pure life of the mind. This is true of other disciplines as well, but history, reliant as it is on cumulative, collective scholarship, finds it especially difficult to celebrate individual achievement. Autobiography, this most personal of genres, hence services collective authority, professional community, and an ostensible containment of the self.</p>
      <p>While acknowledging the genre’s limitations, Popkin also insists that the best achieve literary excellence by dramatizing the humdrum rhythms of academic research into meaningful stories—about physical and emotional experiences in the archives, for instance, or the links between historical research and larger issues. Such autobiography thus enriches the understanding of both the human condition and the past. Popkin argues in an excellent chapter that historians’ memoirs of the Holocaust are both transformative texts, through which authors question their “earlier senses of self” (224), and sources of original historical understanding. By defining themselves as scholars rather than as Jews alone, their authors suggest that all survivors did not come out of the war with strengthened Jewish identities. Whether one agrees or not that autobiographies alone could have yielded such insights, the chapter’s broader claim—that the genre illuminates dimensions that conventional scholarship may have missed—is tenable. But one wonders what exactly Popkin is driving at. Should historians simply grant the genre more respect? Engage in it? Use it less fearfully as a source?</p>
      <p>Instructive as his book is, Popkin could also have explored in greater depth yet the relationship between historical scholarship and expressions of the self. By focusing on autobiographies alone, he misses an opportunity to examine how such texts and scholarly publications related to (and possibly affected) one another, most notably in their divergent or convergent patterns of self‐representation. The boundary between autobiographical and scholarly writings may be more porous than Popkin intimates. Paul Hollander’s recent study of academic acknowledgments arrives, for instance, at conclusions that mirror Popkin’s regarding self‐representation and professional norms (“Acknowledgments: An Academic Ritual,”<italic>Academic Questions</italic>15, no. 1 [2001–2]: 63–76). Likewise, one could question why Popkin limited himself to the discursive analysis of published sources and “the motives that historian‐autobiographers acknowledge in their texts” (78). Autobiographies are also social practices that call for systematic research outside the text, in archival and published sources (and, perhaps, interviews as well). But Popkin is too good a historian not to know this. His book is by and about historians; it is dedicated to historians, but it is not only for historians. Its chief objective may well be to show how much the historian’s autobiography has contributed “to the literature of personal life writing” (8). In this respect as in many others,<italic>History, Historians, and Autobiography</italic>is a success.</p>
   </body>
</article>
