<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">contagion</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Contagion: Journal of Violence, Mimesis, and Culture</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Michigan State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">10757201</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">19301200</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">contagion.21.2014.0029</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.14321/contagion.21.2014.0029</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Articles</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Mimesis and Freedom</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Raymund</given-names>
                  <x/>
                  <surname>Schwager‡</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff>University of Innsbruck, Austria</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">21</volume>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">contagion.21.issue-2014</issue-id>
         <fpage>29</fpage>
         <lpage>46</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2014 Michigan State University Press</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>Michigan State University Press</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.14321/contagion.21.2014.0029"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <notes>
         <title>NOTES</title>
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1" fn-type="other">
               <label>1.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “This text from Provo is inspired from beginning to end, and for the first time the power of its thought comes home to me.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn2" fn-type="other">
               <label>2.</label>
               <p>Paul Dumouchel, “Chroniques. Violence et non-violence,” in<italic>Esprit</italic>(1982), 160–62.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn3" fn-type="other">
               <label>3.</label>
               <p>Ed.: In the German original text Schwager added a very short portion to this sentence only stating, once more, that Dumouchel's critique served as the starting point of his following evaluation of the biblical tradition and the relationship of Girard's theory with this tradition.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn4" fn-type="other">
               <label>4.</label>
               <p>Ed.: The words “with all your heart” are not included in the German original text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn5" fn-type="other">
               <label>5.</label>
               <p>Ed.: In the German original text, but not in the English translation, this word is put in italics.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn6" fn-type="other">
               <label>6.</label>
               <p>Ed.: All biblical references but Dt. 6:13f are not included in the English translation for the Provo conference and are, therefore, added from the German original.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn7" fn-type="other">
               <label>7.</label>
               <p>Schwager's own (?) translation from: Norbert Lohfink,<italic>Unsere großen Wörter. Das Alte Testament zu Themen dieser Jahre</italic>(Herder: Freiburg i. Breisgau, 1977), 129.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn8" fn-type="other">
               <label>8.</label>
               <p>Schwager's own (?) translation from: Othmar Keel,<italic>Feinde und Gottesleugner. Studien zum Image der Widersacher in den Individualpsalmen</italic>(Katholisches Bibelwerk: Stuttgart, 1969), 219.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn9" fn-type="other">
               <label>9.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “Snuffing up the wind” is put here instead of the translation's own wording “sniffing for air.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn10" fn-type="other">
               <label>10.</label>
               <p>Ed.: In the English translation the word “lust” is used; probably “desire” is more adequate for the German term “Begierde.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn11" fn-type="other">
               <label>11.</label>
               <p>Ed.: In the English translation the word “lust” is used; probably “desire” is more adequate for the German term “Begierde.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn12" fn-type="other">
               <label>12.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “By means of military alliances” is a translation from a portion of the German original, which was not included in the English version for the Provo symposium.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn13" fn-type="other">
               <label>13.</label>
               <p>Ed.: In the English translation for the Provo symposium, the inadequate “many” was used to translate the German word “manche.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn14" fn-type="other">
               <label>14.</label>
               <p>Ed.: The words in this parenthesis are only included in the English version, but not the German original text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn15" fn-type="other">
               <label>15.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “Upon the account of the fall” is only used in the English version, not the German original text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn16" fn-type="other">
               <label>16.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “Mimetic desire,” which is more faithful to the German “begehrende Mimesis,” is put instead of “(conflictual) mimesis” in the English translation for the Provo symposium.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn17" fn-type="other">
               <label>17.</label>
               <p>Ed.: The word in this parenthesis is only included in the English version, not the German original text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn18" fn-type="other">
               <label>18.</label>
               <p>René Girard,<italic>Deceit, Desire and the Novel. Self and Other in Literary Structure</italic>, 4th ed., trans. Yvonne Freccero (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1988), 286.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn19" fn-type="other">
               <label>19.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “Seemingly,” which is more faithful to the German word “scheinbar,” is put instead of “apparently” in the English translation for the Provo symposium.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn20" fn-type="other">
               <label>20.</label>
               <p>René Girard,<italic>Things Hidden since the Foundation of the World: Research Undertaken in Collaboration with Jean-Michel Oughourlian and Guy Lefort</italic>, trans. Stephen Bann and Michael Metteer (London: the Athlone Press, 1987), 95.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn21" fn-type="other">
               <label>21.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “In spite of their openness to the absolute” is a translation from a portion of the German original text, which was not included in the English version for the Provo symposium.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn22" fn-type="other">
               <label>22.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “Against God” is a translation from a portion of the German original text, which was not included in the English version for the Provo symposium.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn23" fn-type="other">
               <label>23.</label>
               <p>Schwager's own (?) translation from: Rudolf Pesch,<italic>Das Abendmahl und Jesu Todesverständnis</italic>(Herder: Freiburg i. Breisgau, 1978), 106.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn24" fn-type="other">
               <label>24.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “The self-sufficiency of animal instinct and especially toward” is my translation from a portion of the German original text, which was not included in the English version for the Provo symposium.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn25" fn-type="other">
               <label>25.</label>
               <p>For example Michel Gutsatz, “Les dangers de l'auto,” in<italic>L'autoorganisation. De la physique au politique</italic>, ed. Paul Dumouchel and Jean-Pierre Dupuy (Paris: Ed. du Seuil, 1983), 36.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn26" fn-type="other">
               <label>26.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “Suggests itself” is a more faithful translation of the German “drängt sich […] auf” than the English translation in the text for the Provo symposium “forces itself on me.”</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn27" fn-type="other">
               <label>27.</label>
               <p>Ed.: Probably the meaning of “hope” should be included in this translation of the German word “Erwartung” in the original text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn28" fn-type="other">
               <label>28.</label>
               <p>Ed.: U. Horstmann gave up his professorship in Münster in 1987. Since 1991 he has been teaching English and American literature at the University of Gießen (Germany).</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn29" fn-type="other">
               <label>29.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “According to Horstmann” is not in the original German text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn30" fn-type="other">
               <label>30.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “By bringing about final disaster“ is not in the original German text.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn31" fn-type="other">
               <label>31.</label>
               <p>Schwager's own (?) translation from: Ulrich Horstmann,<italic>Das Untier. Konturen einer Philosophie der Menschenflucht</italic>(Wien: Medusa, 1983), 100.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn32" fn-type="other">
               <label>32.</label>
               <p>Ed.: “Life is extinguished and when” is not in the original German text. Schwager added this element in his own handwriting in the English translation.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="fn33" fn-type="other">
               <label>33.</label>
               <p>Schwager's own (?) translation from: Horstmann,<italic>Das Untier</italic>, 100.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
   </back>
</article>
