<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">amerjsoci</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>American Journal of Sociology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00029602</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375390</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">3081551</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/376294</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">AJS108128</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Review</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Steven</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Sherwood</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="aff_1">University of California, Los Angeles</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2002</year>
            <string-date>July 2002</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>108</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>ajs.2002.108.issue-1</issue-id>
         <fpage>263</fpage>
         <lpage>265</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <source>Art as a Social System</source>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Niklas </given-names>
               <surname>Luhmann</surname>
            </string-name>. Stanford, Calif.: Stanford University Press, 2000. Pp. x+425. $45.00 (cloth); $24.95 (paper).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Permission to reprint a book review printed in this section may be obtained only from the author.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/376294"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>“Art is merely one of society’s functional systems,” states Niklas Luhmann in<italic>Art as a social System</italic>, and therein lies the tale his book tells. “We are not offering a helpful theory of art. … Art becomes a topic in the first place because of the assumption that a social theory claiming universality cannot ignore the existence of art” (p. 3). Luchmann’s clearly stated objective, then, is not to provide us with a theory of art, but to assimilate what he calls the “system of art” into his well‐known theoretical edifice, a theory predicated upon what he calls “evolutionary differentiation.”</p>
      <p>The God‐term in Luhmann’s universe is “autopoesis,” essentially the self‐direction of the systems of society, including that of art, toward greater autonomy and complexity. Although Luhmann was a student of Talcott Parsons and his work bears the evolutionary interest of the functionalist paradigm, it is what many partisans of the older version might consider to be a mutant functionalism. As Luhmann avers, he considers “system differentiation” as “the heart of Parsons’s theory” (p. 350, n. 4) yet unlike Parsons’s optimistic sense that differentiation was undergirded by functional imperatives such as adaptive upgrading, Luhmann’s own sense is that the process of societal evolution “does not presuppose central norms, no matter how generalized” (p. 2). Essentially what this means is that society is composed of a set of systems (economy, politics, law, and art, among others) that evolve and complexify but not toward any unified state, such as Parsons’s “societal community.” Rather, each system tends toward its own independence and standards, and thus much of Luhmann’s book explores what he calls “the autonomy of art,” that is, the ability of the art system to develop its own “self‐description.”</p>
      <p>Although an influential figure within German social theory for decades, Luhmann has never been an especially popular figure in American circles, perhaps because his theory is in actuality what many sociologists have accused Parson’s of being: a theory reducing social actors to nothing more than epiphenomena of their social system. Hence, Luhmann’s book consists of his application of concepts such as system/environment, medium/form, first‐ and second‐order observation, self‐reference and external reference and above all the distinction between psychic systems (systems of consciousness) and social systems (systems of communication) to the realm of art, thereby conceptually transforming it into the “art system.” One of the ironies in Luhmann’s analysis is that his claim for the “autonomy of art” is seemingly refuted by his own, wholly social, assessment of it. Indeed, reading Luhmann’s book is a little like watching Frankenstein at work: his conceptual apparatus renders the ostensibly organic associations we might have of art as being instead mechanical and clinical. For all of Parsons’s own romance with systems theory and cybernetics, his central concern was always with the cultural product of those systems, which he referred to variously as “instrumental activism” and “institutionalized individualism,” that is, the way in which differentiation led to the production of a more complex and sophisticated individualism within the societal community. This constituted Parsons’s standard for the evolution of societies. Luhmann, meanwhile, consistently held that social systems operate “behind the backs” of actors, operating to reduce complexity for such actors, on the one hand, while furthering systems imperatives, on the other. This contrast between mentor and student becomes most obvious in their respective views of culture: while Parsons never fully unpacked the concept of culture in his own work, his emphasis on values and norms opened the door to what today is known as the “sociology of culture” in the work of influential students like Robert Bellah and Clifford Geertz (Geertz’s own assessment of art some years ago, for example, was pointedly entitled<italic>Art as a Cultural System</italic>). Luhmann’s view could not be blunter nor more different, as he calls culture “one of the most detrimental concepts ever to be invented” (p. 247).</p>
      <p>“What interests us here … is how art functions as communication,” Luhmann says (p. 39), and that is the crux of his conception of art: it is the medium and not the message that is important. The work of art is produced<italic>exclusively</italic>for the purpose of communication and that it accomplishes this goal or fails to do so by facing the usual, and perhaps increased, risks involved in all communication. Art communicates<italic>by using perceptions contrary to their primary purpose</italic>. … Art seeks a different kind of relationship between perception and communication—one that is irritating and defies normality—<italic>and just this is communicated</italic>” (pp. 22–23; author’s emphasis). Thus, what is most interesting about Luhmann’s view of art is also what is most interesting about his general theory: its sophisticated and elaborate explorations in the evolutionary development of the media of communication, which are perhaps unparalleled in contemporary theory. But due to his bracketing of the cultural dimension of art, he views the message or meaning that the artwork itself claims to convey as wholly residual. And what is art without meaning? Not only is this a problem for art, it is a problem for Luhmann’s theory; he cannot clearly define the source of art’s “irritating” character nor the “normality” it seeks to defy because he brackets the ideas and ideals that constitute the meaning (read: message) of any conceivable artwork. This gives the 300‐plus pages of Luhmann’s book a rather repetitive and tiring quality; it constantly seems as if he is writing<italic>around</italic>art rather than<italic>about</italic>it. This is the price he pays for a theory in which the criterion is systems complexity rather than cultural meaning.</p>
      <p>Theories are always, in some way, about their theorists. While Luhmann’s variant of mutant functionalism is not palatable to American tastes, his theories are as reflective of late‐20th‐century European sensibilities as Parsons’s were of mid‐20th‐century America or Bellah and Geertz’s of the upheaval of the 1960s and 1970s. Indeed, some art critics have warmed to Luhmann’s book as an exemplar of one of the newer “cool” theories of art; that is, those that challenge more subject‐centered and humanist theories and aim to accommodate the growth of new mediums such as digital art and cyberspace. But in any conception of art that includes culture, the medium is only as good as the meaning it conveys. And it is the meaning of art that is sorely lacking in Luhmann’s appraisal. Paul Ricoeur once wrote that “materialism is the truth of a world without truth.” It might then be said of Luhmann’s conception of the art system that it is the truth of art without meaning.</p>
   </body>
</article>
