<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="research-article"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">libraryq</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Library Quarterly: Information, Community, Policy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00242519</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">1549652X</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">4309827</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/511140</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">LQ760310</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Toward a Practical and Normative Ethics for Librarianship</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>John M.</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Budd</surname>
               </string-name>
               <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1">1</xref>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2006</year>
            <string-date>July 2006</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>76</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>lq.2006.76.issue-3</issue-id>
         <fpage>251</fpage>
         <lpage>269</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2006 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2006</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/511140"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>Just about everything that librarians do as professionals carries ethical implications. Matters of intellectual freedom are most commonly recognized as loci for ethics‐based decision making, but the totality of individual and collective conduct is in need of practical, normative ethical structure. What is argued for here is a framework founded on rights. In order to achieve the goal of rights as foundation, processes of deliberation within librarianship must be established. The most attractive form of deliberation is discourse ethics that recognizes the dialectic nature of this (or any) profession. The result is an ethical state that serves the good of both the profession and communities.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
      <notes notes-type="footnote">
         <fn-group>
            <fn id="fn1">
               <label>1. </label>
               <p>Professor, School of Information Science and Learning Technologies, University of Missouri–Columbia, 303 Townsend Hall, Columbia, MO 65211. Telephone 573‐882‐3258; Fax 573‐884‐4944; E‐mail<email xlink:href="mailto:buddj@missouri.edu" xlink:type="simple">buddj@missouri.edu</email>.</p>
            </fn>
         </fn-group>
      </notes>
      <notes notes-type="epigraph">
         <disp-quote>
            <p>Ethics cannot be separated from politics. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf1">1</xref>, p. 21]</p>
         </disp-quote>
      </notes>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>In the profession of librarianship, the topic of ethics has been the focus of considerable attention in recent years. Some of this attention has been direct and has addressed such things as codes of ethics, freedom of information, and the Library Bill of Rights (LBR). Other writings have approached ethics less directly, as we can see from efforts to articulate the field’s core values. These areas of focus are closely related and, while there have been some very detailed examinations of particular issues, the need remains for an extensive look at points of concern and areas in which ethical action is called for. In particular, this article addresses the practical (the ways we live as professionals in relation to our communities) and the normative (what standards for action we can agree upon and why). Practical ethics can be conceived of in several ways (including consideration of what is right and wrong, how action affects others, and how we look at ourselves), but even in the face of criticism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf2">2</xref>], there is a need to understand what we should do in certain circumstances. The normative element is the anchor for such understanding; Shelly Kagan says that it “involves substantive proposals concerning how to act, how to live, or what kind of person to be. In particular, it attempts to state and defend the most basic principle governing these matters” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf3">3</xref>, p. 2]. Amartya Sen wisely observes that “it would be rather absurd to devote much attention to the subject of ethics if it were really the case that ethical considerations would never affect people’s actual behaviour” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf4">4</xref>, p. 52].</p>
      <p>The foregoing recognizes that the practical side of ethics is vital to work in librarianship. The essential character of ethics in librarianship includes recognition that, as a profession, the concern is for the public life of participants and their public actions. As Alisdair MacIntyre emphasizes (and as the epigraph by Adriaan T. Peperzak affirms), the political and the moral do not have separate histories (or presents, for that matter). Theorizing and belief are both political and moral actions. “Every action is the bearer and expression of more or less theory‐laden beliefs and concepts; every piece of theorizing and every expression of belief is a political and moral action” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf5">5</xref>, p. 61]. MacIntyre’s point is extremely important; history is integral to any understanding of ethics and moral philosophy. History, as is ethics, is human and social; it is an essential component to any understanding of our places in society. The challenge is to create an institutional ethos that achieves a very explicit set of goals. In order to achieve the goals, some principles of rights and obligations have to be recognized and upheld. The easiest of these rights and obligations to accept, and the least controversial, are those grounded in law. Individuals must not be harassed, physically attacked, and so on. These fundamental principles are referred to by John Rawls (who stresses that political philosophy is not a comprehensive ethical or moral theory) as a system of social cooperation:<disp-quote>
            <p>The central organizing idea of social cooperation has at least three essential features:<list>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>
                        <italic>a</italic>) </label>
                     <p>Social cooperation is distinct from merely socially coordinated activity. … Rather, social cooperation is guided by publicly recognized rules and procedures that those cooperating accept as appropriate to regulate their conduct.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>
                        <italic>b</italic>) </label>
                     <p>The idea of cooperation includes the idea of fair terms of cooperation: these are terms each participant may reasonably accept, and should accept, provided that everyone else likewise accepts them.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>
                        <italic>c</italic>) </label>
                     <p>The idea of cooperation also includes the idea of each participant’s rational advantage, or good. The idea of rational advantage specifies what it is that those engaged in cooperation are seeking to advance from the standpoint of their own good. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf6">6</xref>, p. 6]</p>
                  </list-item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </disp-quote>
      </p>
      <p>Less simple are those rights and obligations that are based in fairness and justice. Rawls reduces these rights to two: “(<italic>a</italic>) Each person has the same indefeasible claim to a fully adequate scheme of equal basic liberties for all; and (<italic>b</italic>) Social and economic inequalities are to satisfy two conditions: first, they are to be attached to offices and positions open to all under conditions of fair equality of opportunity; and second, they are to be to the greatest benefit to the least‐advantaged members of society” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf6">6</xref>, p. 42]. At this point, we will leave Rawls’s idea of rights and the implications for positions leaning toward rights or toward welfare, but we will return to it in more detailed discussions of individual rights and institutional responsibilities.</p>
      <p>Frequently occurring in philosophical ethics is a tendency to assume a stability of human nature, of reason, of choice, and so on. As we consider ethics and our profession, though, we have to realize that there have been some social, cultural, and, especially, technological changes. The previous ethical thought, for the most part, assured a neutral relationship between us and our creations. The most forceful and articulate challenger to the old assumptions has been Hans Jonas. Jonas states that “technology, apart from its objective works, assumes ethical significance by the central place it now occupies in human purpose” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf7">7</xref>, p. 9], which leads him to conclude, “If the realm of making has invaded the space of essential action, then morality must invade the realm of making, from which it has formerly stayed aloof, and must do so in the form of public policy” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf7">7</xref>, p. 9]. It may be impossible to overstate the importance of Jonas’s conclusion. A profession that uses technology as a tool in its work (and this includes most, if not all, professions) must see the effects of technology on praxis and the telos (purpose) of the profession in its adoption and use of technology.</p>
      <sec id="sc1">
         <title>Practical Concerns</title>
         <p>The scope of ethics is huge, and the scope of ethics and our profession is only slightly more constrained. One of our concerns is with what might be called peripheral issues. Librarians and information specialists, by and large, do not directly produce the information to which they provide access. Other parties—publishers, media producers, and individuals—form a system of production and dissemination of information. While these parties operate in a sphere that is mostly separate from libraries and information agencies, their decisions, actions, and practices do have a substantial impact on our profession. This means that the ethical choices made by these other parties also affect us. Let us look at a hypothetical scenario. Suppose that, in the heat of a contentious political battle, a person decides to write a book on a candidate for national office. That person consciously chooses to distort some factual information, omit information that would weaken his case against the candidate, draw conclusions that are not supported by evidence, and fabricate some information relating to the candidate’s personal life. A publisher decides to rush that person’s book into production and to distribute it as widely as possible. Many bookstores, aware that this book is likely to sell well, stock it and even feature it prominently in displays. Several reviews of the book are published very soon after its release that point to the distortions and fabrications. Should a library or other information agency purchase the book? Should descriptions of the book in cataloging records in any way indicate the book’s flaws? This scenario demonstrates the dilemma our profession faces as a result of the actions of other parties.</p>
         <p>To begin with, there is a very complicated element of First Amendment application inherent in the scenario. What is in question is not a work that engenders disagreement (in which case the library’s decision could simply be not to allow one voice to stifle others), nor is it a matter of finding offense (including materials in library collections that some find offensive is not merely allowed, it is frequently necessary); it involves legality. There has been a reluctance to enforce aggressively either slander or libel when the individual in question is a public figure. The right or wrong of such a situation is outside the scope of this article, except insofar as it constitutes something of an absence of a barrier for libraries. In other words, the legality of libel is not likely to impinge upon a library’s decision to acquire or retain the book. Suppose, however, we (collectively) adopt a rights‐based approach, such as what Rawls argues for. If fairness is central to our thinking, we definitely need to consider the strong positive right to free speech, but we would also have to consider the position of the political candidate who is being lied about. The importance of access to the book (including the potential for archival copies being preserved) would have to be weighed against the possible damage to the candidate’s campaign, career, and life. Because there may be some laxity regarding the enforcement of libel does not erase the fact that the First Amendment, plus federal and state laws, does not permit any and all speech. Even with existing laws, the matter described above is not without controversy. Ronald Dworkin, recognizing that laws of libel and slander are efficacious, still stresses that the First Amendment is constitutively, rather than instrumentally, justified, and, so, “because we are a liberal society committed to individual moral responsibility … any censorship on grounds of content is inconsistent with that commitment” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf8">8</xref>, p. 205]. Dworkin argues that such a constitutive justification is based in moral reasoning intended to ensure freedom, and his argument is a forceful one. There remains the problematic dissemination of speech that is in fact intentionally false and spread in order to do harm to someone. Current and emerging technologies only make consideration of access to information more difficult. A full resolution to the dilemma presented in the scenario relies on dialectics, as we will see later.</p>
         <p>The technologies we employ, as Hans Jonas has shown, are also third‐party interventions that affect professional ethical action. This is also recognized by Rafael Capurro, who, in addressing more than ethical principles, argues for technological tools to follow principles of accessibility, confidentiality, and completeness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf9">9</xref>]. It may be that our applications of technology illustrate most clearly a distinction between “good” and “value.” This distinction may appear to be a philosophical nicety, but it is vital to ethical considerations in any profession. It is necessary to decide what is good—that is, we must consider seriously what may have some objective status, what may be independent of us. It is also necessary for us to decide what has value—that is, what can be used by us to realize some of the ethical goals and objectives we establish. In other words, what has value necessarily is connected to some questions, such as for whom? at what times? and in what amounts? Thomas Froehlich reminds us that database producers exercise the prerogative of selection (what to include and what to exclude) and, in so doing, may subvert critical and creative thought by offering ready‐made solutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf10">10</xref>]. Technology, in following the above reasoning, is not good in itself, but it can have value. Electronic resources of information, for example, do not have a universal intrinsic good, but they can enable us to retrieve useful information for some people in a timely manner (thus demonstrating value). Another way to look at the good‐value distinction is that good has an ontological quality; its very being embodies the good (e.g., having integrity is good). In some ways, this definition of good is similar to Kant’s categorical imperative (something that is an end in itself) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf11">11</xref>]. Value, however, is realized through application; there is a pragmatic quality attached to it (providing timely access to requested information has value). Jonas succinctly expresses the relationship of good and value through responsibility: “The concept of responsibility implies that of an ought—first of an ought‐to‐be of something, then of an ought‐to‐do of someone in response to the first” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf7">7</xref>, p. 130]. “Value” can thus be conceived as an important concept to practical ethics.</p>
         <p>Jonas’s directive is an effort to solve what has been a persistent debate in philosophical ethics for many years—reconciling “ought” with “is.” The debate sometimes uses the terms “fact” and “value” to express what is a dichotomy for some philosophers. Dating back at least to David Hume, there has been an admonition that we cannot infer “is” from “ought.” Another way of looking at this stricture is that what we value is not necessarily (i.e., there is no causal link) what constitutes a fact. The claim makes sense; we see every day that, for instance, just because there are traffic laws that we all agree are best for public safety, they are not always followed. Jonas’s point is that, while “ought” cannot cause “is,” each individual can try to bring about “is” from “ought.” Another way of looking at the seeming dichotomy is to realize that every school of ethical thought contains—implicitly or explicitly—responsibility. At the very least, it is incumbent upon each of us to hold principles and to be true to those principles. By virtue of responsibility, value is a very important part of ethics. As Hilary Putnam has written, “It is much easier to say, ‘that’s a value judgment.’ Meaning, ‘that’s just a matter of subjective preference,’ than to do what Socrates tried to teach us: to examine who we are and what our deepest convictions are and hold those convictions up to the searching test of reflective examination” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf12">12</xref>, p. 44].</p>
         <p>One specific example may illustrate how the perceived fact‐value dilemma manifests itself in librarianship. There is much that is of value that derives from the literature and practice of business. It is rational to learn, say, how to alert communities to services and resources and how to listen to community members to assess what impact the library has on their lives. There are valuable suggestions, grounded in empirical inquiry, regarding how to present what the library can offer. Does the value of business contributions translate to a fact, a good, that we should emulate businesses? Is the relationship between value and fact the product of a conscious and deliberate evaluation both of the “theory” of business and market economics and of the cultural, social, intellectual, and educative imperatives of libraries? A practical and normative ethics requires that these two questions be taken very seriously. If the theory of market economics comes to be taken as fact (or good), there are consequences for the profession, for libraries, and for communities. The word “customer” appears frequently in professional discourse but without a clear definition (whereas, in market economics, “customer” means something quite specific). One of the requirements of a practical and normative ethics is the profound contemplation of the uses of language; it is incumbent upon professionals to examine whether “customer” and “community” are congruent or discordant. “Customer” and “community” are theoretical terms, in this loose sense, that are components in a larger cognitive‐professional framework that will affect action. Use of a word or term may have cognitive effects on the ways we think about and work in libraries. Ludwig Wittgenstein offers a cautionary note: “Every sign<italic>by itself</italic>is dead.<italic>What</italic>gives it life?—In use it is<italic>alive</italic>. Is life breathed into it there?—Or is the<italic>use</italic>its life?” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf13">13</xref>, p. 128].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc2">
         <title>Statements from the Profession</title>
         <p>The framework for a practical and normative ethics entails not just our professional ethos and action but also the externalities spoken of earlier. For instance, the report of the American Library Association’s (ALA) Core Values Task Force II explicitly acknowledges the values‐based nature of the mission statement. The values that are identified in the report are “Access; Confidentiality/Privacy; Democracy; Diversity; Education and Lifelong Learning; Intellectual Freedom; Preservation; The Public Good; Professionalism; Service; Social Responsibility” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf14">14</xref>]. If we take these goals to be genuine expressions of the professional ethos, then the reality of external forces—politics, economics, information production, and the public good—must be considered. If there are conflicts and contests among these forces, we as professionals have to address them. Suppose the decision is to trust the market to create and/or make available that which is best (in every sense of the word) for people. One outcome may be, as Pierre Bourdieu observes, “that everything the new technology and economically integrated communications groups put into circulation—that is to say, televised messages as well as books, films, or games, all generally subsumed under the term of ‘information’—be conceived as a mere commodity, and consequently treated as any other product and subjected to the law of profit” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf15">15</xref>, p. 68]. Given the empirical reality of market consolidation of mass media companies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf16">16</xref>], practical and normative ethical action calls for a skepticism regarding market‐based claims. The concentration on efficiency that market economics dictates can, in fact, be antithetical to stated professional goals. “Indeed, if economic efficiency (in the sense of Pareto optimality) were the only criterion for economic judgement, and if the various conditions (such as no externality) imposed by the so‐called ‘Fundamental Theorem of Welfare Economics’ were to hold, then there would be in general no welfare‐economic argument for anyone to behave in a way other than that required for self‐interest maximization” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf4">4</xref>, p. 52].</p>
         <p>Another scenario can be used here to connect values to ALA’s Code of Ethics. The main speaker at a library association conference program dealing with codes of ethics focuses on the ALA Code of Ethics (the revised version adopted by the ALA Council in 1995). The code includes items about intellectual freedom, intellectual property rights, privacy and confidentiality, and ensuring that personal or private interests do not interfere with access to information. The speaker, though, spends most of his time on one item of the code: “We provide the highest level of service to all library users through appropriate and usefully organized resources; equitable access; and accurate, unbiased, and courteous responses to all requests” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf17">17</xref>]. The speaker adamantly defends this part of the code. A responding speaker on the program challenges the main speaker’s position and that item of the code saying that the addition of accuracy in the statement introduces bias. The second speaker argues that accuracy is a construction based on domination and oppression and should be challenged in the interests of pluralism and cultural sensitivity. She brings up the report of ALA’s Core Values Task Force II and points out that accuracy appears nowhere in it; not even the value of service mentions accuracy. She further says that the value of social responsibility implicitly urges advocacy on social issues and argues that advocacy trumps accuracy, becoming our genuine ethical goal. Can/should a code of ethics explicitly address things such as accuracy? Is there a realistic and/or objective norm for accurate responses to questions? Should truth be a tenet of a code of ethics?</p>
         <p>The first question might be viewed as a first‐order question; the answer to it is primary and defines other subsequent questions. If we do not consider ethics for a moment, we might have considerable difficulty conceiving of an information or library service that is not grounded in accuracy (or at least every reasonable effort to find accurate information). That stance may presume that accuracy is not problematic. In some ways it is problematic: if a student asks a librarian, “Is<italic>Huckleberry Finn</italic>a good book?” it is difficult to determine the accuracy of a response. A simple yes or no reply does not represent an effort to arrive at an accurate answer. However, interaction with the student that entails a serious examination of critical response to the novel, impact (socially, culturally, and politically), and lasting attention to the book may constitute an accurate response. On the other side of the debate, Michel Foucault’s words may be involved: “Certainly, as a proposition, the division between true and false is neither arbitrary, nor modifiable, nor institutional, nor violent. Putting the question in different terms, however—asking what has been, what still is, throughout our discourse, this will to truth which has survived throughout so many centuries of our history; or if we ask what is, in its very general form, the kind of division governing our will to knowledge—then we may well discern something like a system of exclusion (historical, modifiable, institutionally constraining) in the process of development” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf18">18</xref>, p. 218].</p>
         <p>Foucault, however, is articulating the historical situation of what is taken to be true, especially within the context of the power that perceived truth commands and the uses to which it may be put. His is an important observation, but it does not obviate any ethical imperative aimed at seeking truth (in a weak and fallibilist sense). That ethical imperative demands that advocacy also be based in truth and that accuracy and advocacy be contingent upon the quest for truth. Further, an advocacy stance necessitates some conception of “right” and the acceptance that one particular way of looking at an issue is right (or at least closer to right than the alternatives). The stance itself includes a measure of accuracy if it is to be based in some version of truth. The choice of a position of advocacy is one of judgment, and that judgment has to have some foundation. Michael Lynch warns that “if there is no such thing as being right, wrong, or in‐between, then we can’t really disagree in opinion. We may of course still differ in all sorts of ways—in our hopes, fears, and desires. But we aren’t disagreeing over who is right and who isn’t” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf19">19</xref>, p. 161]. The opinion, then, that “accuracy” is biased and not a sufficient value when placed next to advocacy is itself a claim to accuracy (in the sense of being “right”).</p>
         <p>There is an enormous amount of territory we could cover here, but it may be most fruitful to use our limited space considering a matter that has been the focus of attention for many decades—intellectual freedom. Any discussion of intellectual freedom in our profession should begin with the Library Bill of Rights. A brief history of the document appears in the<italic>Intellectual Freedom Manual</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf20">20</xref>], and a much more complete background has been provided by Louise Robbins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf21">21</xref>]. The first iteration was approved by the ALA Council in 1939. The intention of the LBR is to be normative and regulative, although it does not carry the power of law. It is also intended, as the<italic>Intellectual Freedom Manual</italic>indicates, to be unambiguous, although it is acknowledged in the<italic>Manual</italic>that questions do arise. The LBR does raise some questions regarding practical action.</p>
         <p>A recent article by Martin Frické, Kay Mathiesen, and Don Fallis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf22">22</xref>] reviews some examinations of the LBR that argue that it is ambiguous and political and emphasizes censorship while underemphasizing intellectual property rights and patron privacy. They then contend that, given a philosophical foundation of fallibilism (no knowledge is absolutely certain, and there is the possibility of correction), some of the tenets of the LBR are problematic. They point in particular to Articles II, III, and V. The third article, for example, prohibits censorship; the authors raise the question of what should be done when one right (the right to free expression) conflicts with another right (say, to privacy). Their questioning is reflected in the first scenario presented above. At that point of conflict, a decision must be made, and the LBR does not address such conflict directly. Some interpretations of the LBR do address privacy rights but from the standpoint of access to information and patron records rather than from the standpoint of the content of the information carriers. Frické and his colleagues urge that social‐contract theory be the basis for considering intellectual freedom within the context of the LBR. Building upon Rawls’s conception of rights, they argue that, while some individuals have an idea of the good, “it may be that not all conceptions of the good should be accommodated, by means of the principle chosen for distributing information in society. If we contemplated from behind the veil of ignorance the possibility that we might be placed in society as child pornographers, perhaps we would desire society to supply the means for sympathetic understanding and medical help, rather than public libraries full of child pornography” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf22">22</xref>, p. 482].</p>
         <p>In applying their social‐contract argument, Frické, Mathiesen, and Fallis point out that the fifth article states that access is not to be decided on the basis of origin, age, background, or views. Again, they argue that the fundamental thrust of the LBR is well intentioned but that the absolutism presents difficulties for praxis. They maintain that the LBR’s literal meaning could be construed as removing moral responsibilities for the welfare of, say, children. It is evident that their argument, consciously or not, meets with approval in many libraries. A recent survey asked a sample of librarians if they favor restricting access to pornographic Web sites in the library (if technology made this possible). A total of 37.3 percent of the respondents were somewhat or strongly in favor of that kind of restriction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf23">23</xref>, p. 370]. Perhaps the most common example of restriction at this time is the existence of acceptable‐use policies in libraries. For the most part, but not exclusively, these policies refer to electronic resources, such as Internet searching and use. Many types of libraries adopt acceptable‐use policies, but they are most commonly applied in public libraries and school library media centers. One purpose of these policies is to alert library users about copyright laws and the limitations they impose. Other purposes extend beyond law and move into the realm of more discretionary information resources. The policy of the Eugene School District’s 4JNet (a communications network) states that “the use of profanity, obscenity or other language that may be offensive to another user” is prohibited, as is the “use of the network to access pornographic or obscene material” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf24">24</xref>]. The Salt Lake County Library System uses similar language: “Using the library’s Internet connection (either in a Library or via the Home Page) to view pornography or obscenity is prohibited” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf25">25</xref>]. Dworkin points out that cities can enact zoning regulations that limit where adult entertainment establishments may be located without violating the First Amendment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf8">8</xref>, p. 218]. Acceptable‐use policies may appear to be at odds with the LBR, but are they equivalents of zoning regulations? This is the kind of issue that requires a practical and normative ethics, arrived at deliberatively.</p>
         <p>A defense of a strong version of intellectual freedom is proposed by Tony Doyle. Doyle rests his argument on utilitarianism, especially on John Stuart Mill’s liberalism. There is much in Mill’s thought that presents cogent points in favor of freedom, most notably that a free society benefits in multiple ways from a free and open exchange of ideas. Because of the many benefits, it is thus better for society to allow all works to circulate; those that have no utility will be recognized for their shortcomings. Doyle says, “The utilitarian will concede that some things would be better left unexpressed, unpublished, unseen, and unread. The trouble is, we cannot know beforehand precisely which set of ideas or images, if published, would do more harm than good” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf26">26</xref>, p. 69]. There are no reasonable grounds for ignoring the consequences of actions. Utilitarianism has, over the years, encountered substantive criticism and numerous challenges. Two in particular can be mentioned here as a means of demonstrating that utilitarianism is not an adequate practical and normative ethical position. Samuel Scheffler argues for an agent‐centered prerogative that must be infused into any ethical theory and that is absent from all consequentialist theories. Recognition of individual integrity, according to Scheffler, is vital to realization of human agency and authenticity. Based on that recognition, agents must be free to not always produce the best results or outcomes for society as a whole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf27">27</xref>]. Fallis and Mathiesen, responding to Doyle, state, “The question is what will have worse consequences from the point of view of utilitarianism: (<italic>a</italic>) censoring some material that ought not to be or (<italic>b</italic>) not censoring some material that should be. This is an empirical question. And there may be extremely compelling evidence that certain material is so potentially harmful … that it is better to have some benign material censored along with it than to have it not censored at all” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf28">28</xref>, p. 438]. Fallis and Mathiesen are acknowledging one aspect of utilitarianism that can be called “negative responsibility.” The best example of negative responsibility is the requirement of the Hippocratic oath to do no harm. If utilitarianism does include negative responsibility, then the potential harm that might result from information cannot be ignored.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc3">
         <title>Toward a Practical and Normative Ethics</title>
         <p>The project presented here was hinted at above in the references to Rawls’s strictures regarding social cooperation, justice, and fairness. On a practical plain, Jonas emphasizes that our creations, especially our technologies, are not separate and apart from ourselves and so must be judged according to moral tenets. These are not neutral stances; they represent advocacy not only for ways of thinking about ethics but, more important, ways of acting as individuals and with and for one another. Since the final advocated stance is so important, an essential aspect of practical and normative ethics for librarianship should be emphasized—procedure. Stressing procedure by no means diminishes outcomes, but it does locate the profession’s attention at the initial point of deliberation. It is here that a part of professional discourse is challenged. The challenge is not new; Robert Wengert has already articulated it:<disp-quote>
               <p>Library professionals will not take a stand on ethical matters beyond the insistence that patrons should have equal and open access to whatever sources they desire. An information‐professional might correct you were you to state that Chicago is the capital of the state of Illinois, but that same professional apparently will refrain from criticizing your opinion were you to state that sadism is to be encouraged. Notice that making such distinct responses assumes that the two items of belief are radically different in kind: the one is factual information about which a professional can make judgments, the other is not. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf29">29</xref>, pp. 497–98]</p>
            </disp-quote>
         </p>
         <p>Over time, statements such as the LBR have been discussed and alternatives weighed, but librarianship’s discursive practice has, in recent years, largely constituted an orthodoxy that may not be sensitive or responsive to disputation. One voice of this orthodoxy is Robert Hauptman, who writes, “We are free to articulate anything we imagine” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf30">30</xref>, p. 18], and “If there are more fundamental rights than freedom of thought, then anyone, naturally, can cite those rights when attempting to control what students may read in a class, what libraries may collect, and what Americans may access on the Internet” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf30">30</xref>, p. 138]. His first idea is incorrect; there are, in fact, laws that limit what a person can say. Paradoxically, Hauptman also argues against research misconduct on the grounds of responsibility and public interest, but if we are indeed free to say anything we can imagine, we can lie and falsify with impunity. The positive ethos of research integrity is indisputable; violation of the ethos can cause harm. That positive ethos does, however, come into conflict with Hauptman’s first maxim. His second claim is puzzling; if there are more fundamental rights, then those rights probably should supersede a right to access to information. For example, a right to privacy trumps another’s “right” to certain of an individual’s personal information. A right to freedom from harm trumps a person’s “right” to libel another intentionally and with malice. Hauptman also proposes that, in combating censorship, the minority cannot dictate to the majority. However, Paul Ricoeur, arguing for the kind of normative ethics suggested here, says, “Whoever might be a victim must not be sacrificed to the benefit of some common good. This is the anti‐utilitarian point of the Rawlsian theory of justice” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf31">31</xref>, p. 65]. It is obvious that the whims of the minority should not hold sway simply because they wish it to be so, but, likewise, the majority should not be able to cause harm to others on the basis of an indefensible claim of neutrality (the claim is, itself, not neutral, as Gordon Baldwin demonstrates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf32">32</xref>]).</p>
         <p>One practical and normative standard according to which the profession can act publicly relates to political speech. If a work of any sort (book, video, or Web site) expresses a political opinion regarding anything of public concern, it can be included in a library’s collection. Furthermore, challenges to the presence of the work in the collection should be resisted on clear First Amendment grounds. This standard should be uncontroversial, but its application requires that we ourselves (i.e., every one of us who claims to be a professional) accept that it applies to all discourse. Whitney Davison‐Turley reports that her public expression of disagreement to some resolutions proposed at an ALA annual conference met with derision and insult [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf33">33</xref>, p. 33]. Her account, if accurate, points to some logically and ethically faulty reasoning used in response to her position. It is incumbent upon us as public professionals to adhere fully to any normative ethical position that has not been shown to be fallible; otherwise, any ethical argument we may make can be subject to refutation on the grounds of inconsistency and selective application. Another way to look at the proposed standard is that it is a positive right—the right of people to engage in free public political speech.</p>
         <p>Another practical and normative standard relates to nonpolitical speech. In many instances, the legal regulation of some speech has been enacted as a means to protect freedom of political speech. In other words, if someone or some organization attempts to silence some voices through, say, ownership of media outlets, there has been resistance. Recently, the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) approved relaxed criteria for ownership of broadcast outlets, but Congress refused to go along with the FCC action because public discourse would be negatively affected. This standard, too, may seem uncontroversial, but it does entail some restriction of speech in the public interest. Also, once again, laws of slander and libel prohibit damaging individuals or groups through false and malicious speech (see the first scenario above). This standard fits within Rawls’s framework of justice as fairness, especially the point of fairness being a legitimate good recognized by all free and rational participants. He emphasizes that right and good must be considered as parts of a whole: “That the right and the good are complementary is illustrated by this reflection: just institutions and the political virtues would serve no purpose—would have no point—unless those institutions and virtues not only permitted but also sustained conceptions of the good (associated with comprehensive doctrines) that citizens can affirm as worthy of their allegiance” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf6">6</xref>, pp. 140–41].</p>
         <p>The concept of the good may apply particularly pointedly to professional codes of ethics. The codes are aimed at the positive right of free speech and also at professional responsibility. They attempt to articulate practical and normative standards of ethics. Both the ALA Code of Ethics and the American Society for Information Science and Technology Professional Guidelines speak in terms of responsibility to communities, to the profession, and to society as a whole. Public pronouncement of the codes does serve to affirm the existence of libraries as just institutions in a democracy. Related to the second scenario above, accuracy does fit with the good since it is in people’s interest to obtain accurate information that they can employ for their own well‐being. Advocacy is certainly not always and everywhere prohibited, but it is secondary to people’s right to information that is as accurate as it is possible to provide. Accuracy also embraces a commitment to truth, which recognizes a fundamental inequality of some information (the true and the false; refer again to the first scenario). It is generally taken to be responsible professionalism to check information sources against one another to corroborate information. This action, as Lynch observes, is not a substitute for truth; it is a means to truth (in the weak sense) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf19">19</xref>, p. 81]. Toward the end of accuracy and truth, there are some closely related matters. For one thing, there have been some persistent challenges related to government information and its accessibility versus its effective suppression. This is an area in which advocacy and accuracy merge, with the common aim of presenting library users with the most authoritative information possible. Also, libraries’ access mechanisms, including subject headings, can benefit from advocacy directed toward language that encompasses the culture, linguistic distinctions, and other facets of the people who will search for information.</p>
         <p>The foregoing is certainly not an exhaustive list of the elements of a practical and normative ethics for librarianship. No one person can pretend to suggest an all‐inclusive set of elements. The question to be faced is, How do we, as public professionals, address the need for a more comprehensive consideration of ethics? The answer to this question grows out of the rights‐based premises upon which this article is based. As a public profession, librarianship is committed to a democratic form of public polity. An essential part of the democratic way of being is deliberation, especially public deliberation. Among the many ways we can define democracy is by aggregative or deliberative means. An aggregative position assumes that collective preferences are given; that is, the preferences are taken to be legitimated so that no further justification is required. Invocation of the LBR or ALA’s Code of Ethics as immutable dogmas of the profession may be indicative of an aggregative definition of democracy. The principal shortcoming of this stance is that challenge of taken‐for‐granted preferences is very difficult and meets with tenacious resistance. An alternative—deliberative democracy—admits to pluralism of preferences and of participants. Amy Gutmann and Dennis Thompson maintain that “deliberation is generally the best way to arrive at just decision, or, more accurately, the least unsatisfactory” way [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf34">34</xref>, p. 41].</p>
         <p>Deliberation poses some stringent requirements within the framework of ultimately reaching a just and fair outcome. This is, in fact, the case with ethical and moral theory in general. Jürgen Habermas points out, “Since moralities are tailored to suit the fragility of human beings individuated through socialization, they must always solve two tasks at once. They must emphasize the inviolability of the individual by postulating equal respect for the dignity of each individual. But they must also protect the web of intersubjective relations of mutual recognition by which these individuals survive as members of a community” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf35">35</xref>, p. 200]. Habermas’s is a fundamentally phenomenological perspective insofar as the relationship between self and other is a foundational imperative. (You are different from me, and you and your ideas have legitimacy. You and I share the moral imperative; moreover, I must acknowledge and operate according to your right to be.) Building on the phenomenological base, he outlines a discourse ethics as a practical means of deliberating and accepting moral norms. There are advantages to discourse ethics within our professional community. For one thing, even in the initial stages of deliberation, the positions taken by all participants can be known; there is a starting point from which to begin. For another, discourse ethics requires that there be publicity, that positions and, more important, reasons for holding positions be made public so that they can be deliberated. There is a genuine process of argumentation at work in order for both the validity of an argument (the logical connection between conclusion and premises) and the truth of the premises and propositions to be tested in an open forum.</p>
         <p>The practical and normative ethics of our profession will undoubtedly be accompanied by emotive and affective reactions. After all, human action is motivated by emotion, cognition, reason, and other things. The profession’s desire to identify core values is a product of these multiple motivations. Just as identification of a core value requires an explication of what qualities are attached to a thing that is valued and for whom the thing is valuable and why, so too does discourse ethics in general require such full argumentation. More than just formal argument, though, discourse ethics entails participation broadly; it invites those concerned to have a voice within the communicative endeavor. The voicing, however, follows some norms that are aimed at the outcome of the deliberation—workable and agreed‐upon practices. Habermas says that “discourse ethics, then, stands or falls with two assumptions: (<italic>a</italic>) that normative claims to validity have cognitive meaning and can be treated like claims to truth and (<italic>b</italic>) that the justification of norms and commands requires that a real discourse be carried out and thus cannot occur in a strictly monological form” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf35">35</xref>, p. 68]. Habermas presents an ideal that can suggest a beginning for the furtherance of a practical and normative ethics for librarianship.</p>
         <p>To anticipate a criticism of the use of Habermas’s discourse ethics, there should be acknowledgment of Bent Flyvbjerg’s opinion, which is shared by a number of people: “The basic weakness of Habermas’s project is its lack of agreement between ideal and reality, between intentions and their implementation” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf36">36</xref>, p. 215]. In directly countering Habermas’s discourse ethics, Foucault says, “The problem, then, is not to try to dissolve [power relations] in the utopia of completely transparent communication but to acquire the rules of law, the management techniques, and also the morality, the ethos, the practice of the self, that will allow us to play these games of power with as little domination as possible” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf37">37</xref>, p. 298]. However, Habermas does admit, “Bargaining processes are tailored for situations in which social power relations cannot be neutralized in the way rational discourses presuppose” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf38">38</xref>, p. 166]. Their positions are not so far apart, and the common ground is the ethics of the discursive practice. Furthermore, Habermas and Foucault share some phenomenological justification for their positions. Communication may not be transparent, as the Habermasian ideal would prefer, but neither is power a totally corrupting force. There are times when the discourse in librarianship will be agonistic (competitive and possibly strained); an agreed‐upon set of rules for ethical communication is still the most effective antidote to disruption and authoritarianism and assurance of rights being recognized.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sc4">
         <title>Conclusion</title>
         <p>The derivation of a formal, consistent, agreed‐upon practical and normative ethics is no mean feat. In actuality, librarianship has, in many ways over many years, aimed at this goal. The LBR, codes of ethics, expressions of core values, and other statements are tangible products of the effort. The commentary on these statements and related ethical concerns is also part of the attempt to articulate a coherent ethical theory. Moreover, the statements and the commentary are marks of progress. They constitute a nascent discourse ethics, but the tacit realm in which they have existed needs to become explicit. A foundation built upon rights does not deny consequences, welfare, or duty, but it does couch ethics in terms of the well‐being of everyone in the community. A strong positive right of access to information is weighed only against the negative liberty of not being subjected to any palpable harm. Acceptance of these rights does constitute something of a social contract. “The contract is a moral bond. It connects the strong and the weak, the lucky and the unlucky, the rich and the poor, creating a union that transcends all differences of interest, drawing its strength from history, culture, religion, language, and so on” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf39">39</xref>, pp. 82–83]. In connecting the advantaged and the disadvantaged, the library’s responsibility is considerable. It cannot be accomplished dogmatically, and it cannot be ignorant to constitutive rights.</p>
         <p>A genuine atmosphere of deliberation requires three principles: “The basic premise of reciprocity is that citizens owe one another justifications for the institutions, laws, and public policies that collectively bind them. … Together with reciprocity, two other principles specify the conditions of democratic deliberation. The principle of publicity requires that reason‐giving be public in order that it may be mutually justifiable. The principle of accountability specifies that officials who make decisions on behalf of other people, whether or not they are electoral constituents, should be accountable to those people” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf34">34</xref>, pp. 133, 135]. Within the framework of rights (encompassing justice as fairness) and the process of deliberation according to a discourse ethical approach, librarianship can be better able to address the difficult issues it faces. The reality of pluralism necessitates both rights and deliberation. Deliberation, as a process, cannot help but be dialectical. As has been shown here, there are differing conceptions of right and good, of intellectual freedom and censorship, even of ethical theories. To at least some extent, the discussion and controversy surrounding these issues are antinomies, contradictions between statements that each has reasonable grounds. Dialectics, as a means of resolving contradictions and reconciling division, has its foundations in Hegel. Steven Smith ably summarizes the key elements of a dialectical approach:<disp-quote>
               <p>Three general features of this method can be noted in advance. First, this method must be immanent or internal to its subject matter. Dialectical theorists reject outright the idea that the thinker can occupy some privileged Archimedean point outside the subject of investigation. … A second feature of dialectical method is its dialogical character. Theorizing is an activity taking place not simply within the mind but between minds. Thinking is dialogical because it always takes the form of an exchange or a conversation between ourselves, our contemporaries, and our predecessors. … Third, the dialogical element is related to the historical dimension of theory. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="rf40">40</xref>, pp. 167–68]</p>
            </disp-quote>It is by such an approach that we, as a profession, can arrive at a fully formed practical and normative ethics. It would be fruitless to ignore the divisions and disagreements; they must be addressed dialogically. Further, the dialogue is inescapably phenomenological (as described above) in that legitimacy, which includes beliefs and voice, must be assumed by all, with regard to all. The foregoing is an attempt to further the dialogue.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
   <back>
      <ref-list content-type="unparsed">
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="rf1">
            <label>1.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Peperzak, Adriaan T.<italic>Elements of Ethics</italic>. Palo Alto, CA: Stanford University Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf2">
            <label>2.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Edel, Abraham; Flower, Elizabeth; and O’Connor, Finbarr W.<italic>Critique of Applied Ethics: Reflections and Recommendations</italic>. Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf3">
            <label>3.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Kagan, Shelly.<italic>Normative Ethics</italic>. Boulder, CO: Westview, 1998.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf4">
            <label>4.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Sen, Amartya.<italic>On Ethics and Economics</italic>. Oxford: Blackwell, 1987.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf5">
            <label>5.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">MacIntyre, Alasdair.<italic>After Virtue</italic>. 2nd ed. Notre Dame, IN: Notre Dame University Press, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf6">
            <label>6.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Rawls, John.<italic>Justice as Fairness: A Restatement</italic>. Edited by Erin Kelly. Cambridge, MA: Belknap, 2001.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf7">
            <label>7.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Jonas, Hans.<italic>The Imperative of Responsibility: In Search of an Ethics for the Technological Age</italic>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1984.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf8">
            <label>8.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Dworkin, Ronald.<italic>Freedom’s Law: The Moral Reading of the American Constitution</italic>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf9">
            <label>9.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Kant, Immanuel.<italic>The Metaphysics of Morals</italic>. Edited by Mary Gregor. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf10">
            <label>10.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Capurro, Rafael. “Moral Issues of Information Science.”<italic>Journal of Information Science</italic>11, no. 3 (1985): 113–23.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf11">
            <label>11.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Froehlich, Thomas J. “Ethical Considerations in Technology Transfer.”<italic>Library Trends</italic>40 (Fall 1991): 275–302.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf12">
            <label>12.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Putnam, Hilary.<italic>The Collapse of the Fact/Value Dichotomy and Other Essays</italic>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf13">
            <label>13.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Wittgenstein, Ludwig.<italic>Philosophical Investigations</italic>. 3rd ed. Translated by G. E. M. Anscombe. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice‐Hall, 1958.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf14">
            <label>14.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">American Library Association. “Mission, Priority Areas, Goals.” 2006.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://www.ala.org/ala/ourassociation/governingdocs/policymanual/mission.htm"
                         xlink:type="simple">http://www.ala.org/ala/ourassociation/governingdocs/policymanual/mission.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf15">
            <label>15.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Bourdieu, Pierre.<italic>Firing Back: Against the Tyranny of the Market 2</italic>. Translated by Loïc Wacquant. New York: New Press, 2003.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf16">
            <label>16.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">McChesney, Robert W.<italic>Rich Media, Poor Democracy: Communication Politics in Dubious Times</italic>. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1999.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf17">
            <label>17.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">American Library Association. “Code of Ethics of the American Library Association.” 2006.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://www.ala.org/ala/oif/statementspols/codeofethics/codeethics.htm"
                         xlink:type="simple">http://www.ala.org/ala/oif/statementspols/codeofethics/codeethics.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf18">
            <label>18.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Foucault, Michel.<italic>The Archaeology of Knowledge and the Discourse on Language</italic>. Translated by A. M. Sheridan Smith. New York: Pantheon, 1972.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf19">
            <label>19.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Lynch, Michael P.<italic>True to Life: Why Truth Matters</italic>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf20">
            <label>20.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">American Library Association, Office for Intellectual Freedom.<italic>Intellectual Freedom Manual</italic>. 6th ed. Chicago: American Library Association, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf21">
            <label>21.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Robbins, Louise S.<italic>Censorship and the American Library: The American Library Association’s Response to Threats to Intellectual Freedom, 1939–1969</italic>. Westport, CT: Greenwood, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf22">
            <label>22.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Frické, Martin; Mathiesen, Kay; and Fallis, Don. “The Ethical Presuppositions behind the Library Bill of Rights.”<italic>Library Quarterly</italic>70, no. 4 (October 2000): 468–91.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf23">
            <label>23.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Harkovitch, Michael; Hirst, Amanda; and Loomis, Jennifer. “Intellectual Freedom in Belief and in Practice.”<italic>Public Libraries</italic>42 (November/December 2003): 367–74.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf24">
            <label>24.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Eugene (Oregon) School District 4J. “4JNet Acceptable Use Guidelines.” 2004.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://www.4j.lane.edu/4jnet/4jnetguidelines.html"
                         xlink:type="simple">http://www.4j.lane.edu/4jnet/4jnetguidelines.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf25">
            <label>25.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Salt Lake County (Utah) Library System. “Salt Lake County Library System Internet Acceptable Use Statement.”<ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                         xlink:href="http://www.slco.lib.ut.us/usesite1.htm"
                         xlink:type="simple">http://www.slco.lib.ut.us/usesite1.htm</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf26">
            <label>26.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Doyle, Tony. “A Utilitarian Case for Intellectual Freedom in Libraries.”<italic>Library Quarterly</italic>71, no. 1 (January 2001): 44–71.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf27">
            <label>27.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Scheffler, Samuel.<italic>The Rejection of Consequentialism</italic>. Rev. ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1994.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf28">
            <label>28.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Fallis, Don, and Mathiesen, Kay. “Response to Doyle.”<italic>Library Quarterly</italic>71, no. 3 (July 2001): 437–38.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf29">
            <label>29.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Wengert, Robert G. “Some Ethical Aspects of Being an Information Professional.”<italic>Library Trends</italic>49 (Winter 2001): 486–509.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf30">
            <label>30.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Hauptman, Robert.<italic>Ethics and Librarianship</italic>. Jefferson, NC: McFarland, 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf31">
            <label>31.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Ricoeur, Paul.<italic>The Just</italic>. Translated by David Pellauer. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2000.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf32">
            <label>32.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Baldwin, Gordon B. “The Library Bill of Rights—a Critique.”<italic>Library Trends</italic>45 (Summer 1996): 7–27.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf33">
            <label>33.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Davison‐Turley, Whitney. “Differing Opinions Need Not Apply.”<italic>American Libraries</italic>35 (September 2004): 33.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf34">
            <label>34.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Gutmann, Amy, and Thompson, Dennis.<italic>Why Deliberative Democracy</italic>? Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2004.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf35">
            <label>35.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Habermas, Jürgen.<italic>Moral Consciousness and Communicative Action</italic>. Translated by Christian Lenhardt and Sherry Weber Nicholsen. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1990.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf36">
            <label>36.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Flyvbjerg, Bent. “Habermas and Foucault: Thinkers for Civil Society?”<italic>British Journal of Sociology</italic>49, no. 2 (June 1998): 210–33.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf37">
            <label>37.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Foucault, Michel. “The Ethics of the Concern of the Self as a Practice of Freedom.” In<italic>Ethics: Subjectivity and Truth; The Essential Works of Foucault, 1954–1984</italic>, edited by Paul Rabinow, translated by Robert Hurley and others, vol. 1, pp. 281–301. New York: New Press, 1997.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf38">
            <label>38.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Habermas, Jürgen.<italic>Between Facts and Norms: Contributions to a Discursive Theory of Law and Democracy</italic>. Translated by William Rehg. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1996.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf39">
            <label>39.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Walzer, Michael.<italic>Spheres of Justice: A Defense of Pluralism and Equality</italic>. New York: Basic Books, 1983.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="rf40">
            <label>40.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
            </label>
            <mixed-citation xlink:type="simple">Smith, Steven B.<italic>Hegel’s Critique of Liberalism: Rights in Context</italic>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1989.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
