<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jmodernhistory</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Modern History</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>The University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00222801</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15375358</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor-stable">27744309</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/598731</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="msid">JHM810105025</article-id>
         <article-categories>
            <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
               <subject>Book Reviews</subject>
            </subj-group>
         </article-categories>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Brett</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
                  <surname>Bowles</surname>
               </string-name>
               <aff id="a1">State University of New York at Albany</aff>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <month>3</month>
            <year>2009</year>
            <string-date>March 2009</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>81</volume>
         <issue>1</issue>
         <issue-id>598752</issue-id>
         <fpage>206</fpage>
         <lpage>207</lpage>
         <product product-type="book" xlink:type="simple">
            <source>Le cinéma post‐colonial français</source>. By<string-name name-style="western">
               <given-names>Caroline</given-names>
               <x xml:space="preserve"> </x>
               <surname>Eades</surname>
            </string-name>.:<publisher-name>Éditions du Cerf</publisher-name>,<year>2006</year>. Pp. 433. €41.00.</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© 2009 by The University of Chicago. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
            <copyright-holder>The University of Chicago</copyright-holder>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/598731"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Contrary to the most common applications of the term<italic>postcolonial</italic>in cinema studies and history, this dense and ambitious work deals neither with films made by directors from former French colonies nor with movies depicting the experiences of immigrants in France during the same period. Noting that both topics have already received significant scholarly attention, Caroline Eades focuses on another group of works: retrospective cinematic representations of the colonial period and decolonization crafted by French directors since the early 1960s. Her working corpus comprises fifty‐three feature films, almost all of which are set in the twentieth century and of which the largest subset deals with the tumultuous period encompassing the wars in Indochina (1946–54) and Algeria (1955–62). Stylistically and ideologically this is a broadly heterogeneous collection that includes politically engaged, painstakingly realistic historical reconstructions such as Gillo Pontecorvo's<italic>La bataille d'Alger</italic>(1965) and Pierre Schoendoerffer's<italic>Diên Biên Phú</italic>(1991); dark, tongue‐in‐cheek satires such as Jean‐Jacques Annaud's<italic>La victoire en chantant</italic>(1976) and Bertrand Tavernier's<italic>Coup de torchon</italic>(1981); and nostalgic, self‐indulgent melodramas such as Claire Denis's<italic>Chocolat</italic>(1988) and Régis Wargnier's<italic>Indochine</italic>(1991).</p>
      <p>Such diversity inevitably generates interpretive contradictions and makes the author's stated goals—to compare the films' thematic content and form with those of the colonial cinema that preceded it and to use postcolonial film as a barometer for assessing how French collective memory has come to terms with its imperialist history—difficult to achieve. While Eades's painstaking analysis of the continuities and ruptures between colonial and postcolonial cinema is impressive, her contention that the latter “forced recognition of a reality grudgingly accepted by political authorities and the general population” (22) until the mid‐1990s and “called into question imperial ideology in all its dimensions” (203) is less convincing. While the majority of these films do at some level acknowledge the failures and abuses of French imperialism, most also avoid explicit reference to controversial issues and events (most notably, the French army's practice of torture in Algeria) and ignore the subjective experience of colonized peoples, highlighting instead the plight of colonizers caught in morally untenable situations because of the corrupt system that surrounds them. The result, as Eades recognizes, is that the colonized tend to remain little more than stereotypes while audiences are encouraged to identify with the European perspective. In so doing, postcolonial cinema implicitly perpetuates the epistemological prejudices of overtly imperialist films from the 1920s and 1930s.</p>
      <p>Attention to critical reception, box‐office performance, or censorship might help resolve the ambiguity inherent in the films' content and potential impact on collective memory, but Eades offers no such information apart from a handful of review citations scattered throughout the four hundred pages of text. The heated public debates surrounding films such as the aforementioned<italic>Battle of Algiers,</italic>which was banned from theaters almost immediately by French authorities on its release and not shown on French television until 2004, are ignored almost entirely. And though the author mentions in passing the importance of documentaries in contesting denial and indifference, she does not deal substantively with either that genre or with fiction films about colonialism and decolonization made outside France for French consumption. As such, the impact of widely distributed, critically acclaimed productions such as Euzhan Palcy's<italic>La rue cases‐nègres</italic>(1983, an ethnographic dramatization of the suffering endured by sugarcane workers in 1930s Martinique) and Bertrand Tavernier's<italic>La guerre sans nom</italic>(1992, a four‐hour landmark documentary about the Algerian War that openly addresses torture) goes unaddressed. With regard to periodization, Eades notes an intensification in postcolonial productions during the first half of the 1990s when the French government began formally acknowledging and memorializing the dark aspects of colonialism, but we get no sense of how the films' political stance evolved over the preceding thirty years. My own sense is that the sheer number and consistently anticolonialist stance of documentaries, especially those made in the last fifteen years about the Algerian War, have been significantly more influential than fiction films in promoting collective realization of the human rights violations committed under the aegis of France's “civilizing mission.”</p>
      <p>These methodological oversights are surprising since Eades is clearly familiar with research exploring the links between history, memory, and collective representations. She cites Jacques Le Goff, Marc Ferro, Pierre Nora, Michel de Certeau, Paul Ricoeur, and Henry Rousso alongside a wide range of colonial/postcolonial historians and theorists, including Robert Stam, Benjamin Stora, Edward Said, Homi Bhabha, and Dominick LaCapra. In the end, theory and formal analysis drown out contextual issues of production, distribution, and reception. Three of the book's four chapters deal primarily with theme and form; only the first examines historiographic issues in their own right. This imbalance is not necessarily a flaw, but it does illustrate the challenges of interdisciplinary research and writing. Many film scholars will welcome the author's extraordinarily detailed inventory of the strategies used in postcolonial cinema to critique imperialism, particularly the creative subversion (and to a lesser extent, perpetuation) of representational conventions inherited from colonial‐era painting, literature, and movies. On the other hand, cultural historians will likely be disappointed by the lack of attention paid to the life of these films in society, the multiple meanings attached to them by viewers, and their relation to competing discourses of the same era.</p>
      <p>Readers without solid background knowledge of French film and colonial history may have some difficulty navigating through Eades's tightly packed, allusive prose, especially since no index of any kind is provided. This absence is difficult to understand in a work of serious scholarship aimed at academic readers, as is the press's decision to invest in numerous glossy still‐frame illustrations that add nothing substantive to the analysis. However, the extensive, thematically organized filmographies and bibliographies that conclude the volume should prove very useful to all readers by providing a starting point for further reading and research.</p>
   </body>
</article>
