<article dtd-version="1.0" article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">afrdevafrdev</journal-id>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="jstor">j50014718</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <journal-title>Africa Development / Afrique et Développement</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>CODESRIA</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">08503907</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="jstor">24484618</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Is There One Science, Western Science?</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib>
               <string-name xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
                  <given-names>Theophilus</given-names>
                  <surname>Okere</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>1</month>
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                 xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                 xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">30</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
                xmlns:oasis="http://docs.oasis-open.org/ns/oasis-exchange/table">3</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">i24480412</issue-id>
         <fpage>20</fpage>
         <lpage>34</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>© Council for the Development of Social Science Research in Africa, 2005</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/24484618"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>All humans by nature desire to know and humans are distinguished from the rest of creation by the miracle of knowledge. If all cultures have developed their own forms of knowledge, the spectacular success of a certain form of knowledge, science, notably in the west, has frequently led to its being exclusively attributed to the west. Yet science remains only one of many forms of knowledge and the west only one of its producers. The success of the west has tended to marginalize other forms of knowledge and other contributions to knowledge and, thus to impoverish an otherwise potentially rich and complex world knowledge landscape. It has tended to inhibit or even prevent the development of a really universal, human-knowledge project. Its very success, due essentially to its sustained application to technology, has enabled the development of a false superiority over other forms of knowledge and a real power hegemony of the west over other peoples. The future of lasting peaceful co-existence in the world may depend, in part, on the emancipation of other knowledge modes and forms. De par leur nature, tous les êtres humains éprouvent le désir de savoir, et les humains se distinguent des autres êtres de la Création par le miracle de la connaissance. Bien que toutes les cultures aient développé leurs propres formes de connaissance, le succès spectaculaire, notamment en Europe, d'une forme particulière de la connaissance, la science, a fait que cette dernière a été exclusivement attribuée à l'Occident. Pourtant, la science ne représente qu'une des nombreuses formes de la connaissance et l'Occident n'est qu'un producteur de celle-ci, parmi tant d'autres. Le succès de l'Occident a contribué à marginaliser les autres formes de connaissance et autres contributions à la connaissance, et ainsi, a fini par appauvrir le paysage international de la connaissance, qui autrement, aurait pu être extrêmement riche et diversifié. Ce succès de l'Occident a fini par inhiber, voire empêcher le développement d'un projet universel de connaissance humaine. Ce succès, dû essentiellement à l'application continue de la science à la technologie, a contribué à l'instauration d'une pseudo-supériorité de celle-ci sur les autres formes de connaissance, ainsi qu'à l'établissement d'une réelle hégémonie de l'Occident sur les autres peuples. La pérennité d'une coexistence pacifique internationale dépendra, en partie de l'émancipation des autres formes de la connaissance.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <back>
      <ref-list>
         <title>References</title>
         <ref id="d679073e116a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e120" publication-type="other">
Anderson Warwick, 2002, 'Post-colonial Techno-science' in Social Studies of
Science, 32/5-6, Oct. - Dec.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e130a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e134" publication-type="other">
Barth, Fredrik, 2002, 'An Anthropology of Knowledge' in Current Anthropology,
Vol 43, No 1, Feb 2002.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e144a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e148" publication-type="other">
Devisch, Rene, 2001, 'Cultures, Sciences &amp; Endogenous Knowledge Practices:
Anthropological Perspectives' in: Science and Tradition: Roots and Wings
for Development, Brussels: Royal Academy for Overseas Science &amp; UNESCO:
29 - 53.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e164a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e168" publication-type="other">
Franklin Sarah, 1995: 'Science as Culture and Cultures of Science s Annual Review
of Anthropology, 24, 163-84.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e179a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e183" publication-type="other">
Flabermas, Juergen, 1971, Knowledge and Human Interests, Hamburg: Boston
Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e193a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e197" publication-type="other">
Kuhn, Thomas S., 1970, The Structure of Scientific Revolutions, Chicago:
University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e207a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e211" publication-type="other">
Nader, Laura, ed., 1996, Naked Science, Anthropological Inquiry into Boundaries
of Power and Knowledge, New York, London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e221a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e225" publication-type="other">
Ravetz. J. R., 1970, The Merger of Knowledge and Power: Essays in Critical
Science, London &amp; New York: Mansell Publishing Ltd.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
         <ref id="d679073e235a1310">
            <mixed-citation id="d679073e239" publication-type="other">
Standen, Anthony, 1950, Science is a Sacred Cow, New York: E.P. Dutton &amp; Co.
Inc. von Weizsaecker, C. F., 1969, Kritik der Wissenschaften,
Tonbandnachschrift.</mixed-citation>
         </ref>
      </ref-list>
   </back>
</article>
