<article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         article-type="research-article">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">socitheo</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="jstor">j100735</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Sociological Theory</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishers</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">07352751</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="jstor">223313</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Revisiting the Notion of "Public" in Habermas's Theory-Toward a Theory of Politics of Public Credibility</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Agnes S.</given-names>
                  <surname>Ku</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date>
            <day>1</day>
            <month>7</month>
            <year>2000</year>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>18</volume>
         <issue>2</issue>
         <issue-id>i211061</issue-id>
         <fpage>216</fpage>
         <lpage>240</lpage>
         <page-range>216-240</page-range>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright 2000 American Sociological Association</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/223313"/>
         <abstract>
            <p>There exist around the notion of the public three different yet overlapping dichotomies posed on different levels of analysis: public (sphere) versus private (sphere), public versus mass, and publicness versus privacy/secrecy. Habermas's book ([1962]1989) incorporates all the three sets of dichotomy without resolving the contradictory meanings and bridging the gaps among them. As a result, his conception of the public sphere becomes paradoxical in terms, and it undertheorizes the cultural property of publicness. This article proposes an alternative conception of the public that may encompass the structural, institutional, and cultural levels of theorization in a more precise and coherent way. It is argued that the public is an imagined category about citizen membership that is attached to both institutions of state and civil society. In political practices, a symbolic "public" is institutionalized through an open communicative space where it is called upon, constructed, and contested as the central source of cultural references. In this connection, a notion of public credibility is introduced as an attempt to bring forth a richer and more dynamic conception about the role of culture in democratic struggles than that of critical rationality by Habermas.</p>
         </abstract>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
</article>
