<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="eng">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" journal-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title content-type="full">The Journal of Speculative Philosophy</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>Pennsylvania State University Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">0891625X</issn>
         <issn xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="epub">15279383</issn>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jspecphil.26.2.0321</article-id>
         <article-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-id-type="doi">10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0321</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Philosophy of Technology</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" pub-type="ppub">
            <day>1</day>
            <month>4</month>
            <year>2012</year>
            <string-date>2012</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">26</volume>
         <issue xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2</issue>
         <issue-id xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jspecphil.26.2.issue-2</issue-id>
         <fpage>321</fpage>
         <lpage>332</lpage>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by The Pennsylvania State University. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
            <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                   xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5325/jspecphil.26.2.0321"/>
         <custom-meta-group xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>eng</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec id="s01">
         <sec-meta>
            <contrib-group>
               <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <string-name>
                     <italic>Don Ihde</italic>
                  </string-name>
                  <aff>Stony Brook University</aff>
               </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
         </sec-meta>
         <title>Can Continental Philosophy Deal with the New Technologies?</title>
         <p>Beginnings: My first experience of the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy (SPEP) was at Northwestern University; the business meeting was trying to decide whether its name should be “the Society for Existential Philosophy and Phenomenology” or “the Society for Phenomenology and Existential Philosophy”—it spent nearly three hours with impassioned speeches made by many now departed mighty dead and others still here. I was a graduate student, just starting a dissertation on Paul Ricoeur, and I sat wondering where all this would lead. And we are now half a century later, with SPEP the second-largest philosophy group in America. The task for me is somehow to condense fifty years around a specific theme entailing technologies and their treatment by “Continental” philosophies. I will do this by doing time slices as related to a cast of characters, both individual and social. “SPEP” will be my corporate character for Continental philosophy; it is where its interests are expressed and indicated. Then as a primary individual character, I will refer to “Heidegger's ghost,” always and still a prominent figure and interpreter of Technology; here his death date, 1976, will stand for a watershed between what I will caricature as the Old Technologies and the New Technologies. I, myself, will be the narrator but also an actor, with my own three-decades-plus history in the philosophy of technology.</p>
         <sec id="s01_1">
            <title>Time Slice One: The Sixties</title>
            <list list-type="bullet">
               <list-item>
                  <label>•</label>
                  <p>Exciting and dramatic times: civil rights marches with dogs in Selma, bombs in Birmingham; the beginnings of protest against American engagement in Vietnam; the Cold War still in full engagement; the assassination of John F. Kennedy.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>•</label>
                  <p>Technologies of the times include military technologies spawning fear of nuclear holocaust, with children hiding under desks during the Cuban Missile Crisis, B-52s flying nonstop “Doctor Strangelove” missions, and napalm and Agent Orange bombings; agricultural technologies, with vast armies of multiple wheat combines combing equally vast corporate farms; industrial technologies, coal-fired iron smelters belching acid into the rain clouds; and transportation technologies, with the Interstate Highway system, grinding to a halt at commute times, turning the Long Island Expressway into the world's longest “parking lot.” In short: megatechnologies, mass technologies, and even in entertainment there is commercialized television and for youth, the loud rage of rock concerts.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>•</label>
                  <p>Meanwhile in academia, in philosophy, positivism was still very much alive; analytic or Anglo-American philosophy dominated the universities and the professional societies. But the undergraduates were often, instead, busy reading<italic>existentialism</italic>, with Camus, Sartre, Nietzsche, and Kierkegaard discussed in coffeehouses and beer halls. Heidegger was just being discovered, an existential/sometimes religious Heidegger. Bill Richardson's<italic>From Phenomenology to Thought</italic>, introducing Heidegger, was published in 1963.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>•</label>
                  <p>SPEP, with<italic>phenomenology</italic>trumping<italic>existentialism</italic>in its title, saw itself as a minoritarian challenge to the extant dominance of linguistic logicism. SPEP gradually became the umbrella society for a wide variety of “Continental” philosophies, as is now the case.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>•</label>
                  <p>If SPEP began to challenge sixties professional philosophy externally, internally positivism was also being challenged. Its dominant form was undergoing a different set of challenges, which related to the notion of science itself. This was the era of the positivist/antipositivist controversies (there was not yet what could be called a parallel or related philosophy of technology subdiscipline). For those of you too young to remember, or not even yet born, it should be noted that for many positivists and some analysts, philosophy of science was all that was needed for philosophy. Philosophy of science equaled philosophy. Metaphysics, aesthetics, and whole areas of traditional philosophy were to be abandoned or regarded as “nonsense.” This version of philosophy-science, however, was met by Thomas Kuhn's<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">1962</xref>
                     <italic>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</italic>, to become the twentieth-century's most cited book, along with his kin, Karl Popper, Imre Lakatos, and Paul Feyerabend, who collectively were depicting a very different science, discontinuous, historical, using technologies (instruments), no longer simply a logo-linguistic, propositional theory machine.</p>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <label>•</label>
                  <p>What of technology, particularly for Continentals? For those dominating philosophy of science, technologies are merely “applied science,” derived and dependent upon science. But again in academia, in parallel with popular existentialism, there was another disjunct. The technology guru being everywhere read was Herbert Marcuse,<italic>One Dimensional Man</italic>(<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">1964</xref>)—and lurking behind him but not yet widely read concerning technology, Martin Heidegger. Note that this interpretation of technology was not that of applied science but that of Technology gone autonomous, become that which encloses and overwhelms the human. This was to be, for long stretches of time, the dominant SPEP “technology,” just as existentialism had been its earliest philosophy.</p>
               </list-item>
            </list>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s01_2">
            <title>Time Slice Two: Pregnant Event Dates</title>
            <p>I now turn to a few especially significant event markers:<list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>1968. The first significant event marker, 1968 was the international year of student revolts. I was in Paris, along with many now retirement-cusp SPEP people, experiencing the “events of May.” Similar events reached from Tokyo to Berlin to Columbia and Kent State. Several academic but symptomatic results include the disappearance of tweed and ties but also titles—since then I am everywhere “Don” and rarely “Professor Ihde.” This was also the epitome of the organized protest march, become the standard to this day from Tiananmen Square to Tahrir Square, Egypt. The practices invented then have challenged and often enough, brought down regimes, and youthful democratization movements still repeat themselves.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>1976. Heidegger's death: he joins the mighty dead and remains today as “Heidegger's ghost.” Often cited as the founder of philosophy of technology, he remains almost the only figure of a cadre of European philosophers of the early twentieth century still discussed concerning technology. I use his death date as the watershed between the “Old” and “New” technologies. Heidegger divided his technologies in various ways, most often by contrasting old, largely handcraft technologies to “Modern” or industrial technologies. Stone bridges, jugs, peasant shoes, Greek temples, and his famous hammer stand out for the first; Rhine River dams, steel bridges, the atom bomb, death chambers, and modern agriculture are examples of the modern. Modern technologies are mass-produced, gigantic, and largely mechanical—in short, “industrial” of the sort so familiar early in the twentieth century. I stick to 1976 as my watershed, in spite of the fact that most of his late work on technology was done in the mid-1950s.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>1979. I list this date because it was the year several books were published that changed the interpretation of technologies for our era.<italic>Laboratory Life</italic>, by Bruno Latour and Steve Woolgar (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>), shifted the interpretation of both science and technology to a praxis-oriented and materially sensitive interpretation. Latour followed up with<italic>Science in Action</italic>(<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>), in which instruments played crucial roles in producing scientific facts. The year 1979 was also when the analytic philosopher Mario Bunge, in “Five Buds of Techno-philosophy,” pronounced that while technologies ought to occupy philosophical attention, to date, he claimed, there had not been a single monograph on the philosophy of technology. But this was also the year of my own<italic>Technics and Praxis: A Philosophy of Technology</italic>(1979), jointly published by the Boston Philosophy of Science and Synthese Library series. It, too, took a praxis turn, with a look at how science is materially<italic>embodied</italic>in technologies. Later it was cited as the first philosophy of technology book from North America and contained the first English overview of Heidegger's philosophy of technology. And externally, this was also the year of the Iranian revolution, a primary information technology of which was the cassette recorder, which carried the ayatollah's and mullah's messages and which was small and decentralized compared with other media. This miniaturized-decentralized technology is one dimension of the New Technologies.</p>
                  </list-item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>We now reach the point at which I address the question in my title: “Can Continental philosophy deal with the New Technologies?” I characterized this earlier as somewhat ironic—because SPEP has never had questions of science and technology as forefront issues. One of my hobbies, as a veteran SPEPer myself, has been an annual “bean count” of the figures and topics in the program index. Very few entries could ever be found, with most not bearing the Heidegger–Marcuse tilt, and my own SPEP entries. This count shows up ratios of interest and changes of trends. So, with exceptions noted, Heidegger and Marcuse remained the primary “canonical” figures interpreting technology for SPEP. And it is to these figures that I address my critique of what I will call the “old philosophy of technology.”</p>
            <p>Externally the technological world was changing; New Technologies were emerging, becoming important and coming into practical use primarily in the 1980s and 1990s. The European Union has recently nominated four “converging technologies” as the new technologies most likely to shape lives in the twenty-first century, with commissions to address the possible outcomes (it may be noted that 20 percent of grants dealing with new science/technology development must include considerations of ethical, cultural, and political implications—the United States has nothing comparable):<list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>These are nano-, bio-, info-, and cognotechnologies. For reasons I will clarify, I add robo- and imaging technologies to this list. But before some specific examples, take note of how these new technologies<italic>differ</italic>from the mega-, mechanical, industrial technologies called “modern” by Heidegger. In each case the target entities with which these technologies intervene are extreme<italic>microphenomena</italic>. Nanotechnologies manipulate at the atomic and molecular levels, trapping atoms, deflecting photons; biotechnologies operate at the genetic level, DNA, RNA, proteins; cognotechnologies, also employing imaging, depict neurotransmissions and the like. I shall later address the info-, robo-, and imaging technologies. At the end of the Cold War, physics, while interested in subatomic particles and wedded to monster colliders to investigate these phenomena, was about to lose its biggest instrument, the supercollider, which was canceled in 1994, in part because it was not deemed so important. The subsequent emergence of biology, also wed to microphenomena, could use much smaller instruments.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>While in a few cases, the origins of these new technologies go back prior to my 1976 watershed date, only those interested in actual technol- ogies and innovation were familiar with these early forms. Heidegger, eschewing particular technologies and largely ignorant of technological history, was not one of these. Heidegger did mention the atomic bomb, nuclear physics, and television—to which in late life he accommodated in order to watch soccer games—but little else. He did pause to condemn the typewriter and praise the handheld pen—the first almost ready to become a relic, the second already a relic.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>If the operational level of entities for these technologies is microphenomena, for the most part the technologies themselves often follow<italic>miniaturization trajectories</italic>. Take, for example, memory and data storage devices. My first 1984 PC used two 5” floppies just to boot up; today I mostly use flash drives that can store multiple book manuscripts. My new Mac laptop has more capacity for multiple tasks than the early megacomputers used when Monte Carlo simulations were featured in designing the atomic bomb.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>Then, too, most of the new technologies transform experienced space-time. What today is popularly called cyberspace is the technological capacity to bring the remote near. If the technologies are good, the experienced instantaneity of distance is the same in the infotechnologies of e-mail and the Internet and, except for slight time factors, the audio technologies, telephone and radio—and the audio dimension of audio-video television. In robotechnologies, both remote sensing (the Mars exploration rovers) and robot warfare (Predator drones), even robotic medicine (“Nintendo” surgery), can be controlled from afar. And as noted, miniaturization today characterizes many robotics, from surgery to the insect-sized surveillance drones now being developed by the military.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>I have long argued that any technology can be<italic>multistable</italic>and have given many examples; the new technologies often deliberately design in multistability as<italic>multitasking</italic>. A Swiss army knife is an older mechanical example; laptops, iPads and cell phones are electronic examples.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>Yet another contrast between the old and new technologies, incorporating some of the already noted capacities above, is the move away from direct, material connectivity to what we often call the “wireless.” A few years ago I was a referee for a fascinating book by Reviel Netz (<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) on the history of barbed wire. The author actually showed how three nineteenth-century technologies paralleled each other in physical form: barbed wire fences, railroad beds and tracks, and the telegraph. Each contained long, connected steel wires or tracks; each was framed with wooden posts; and each reached for long distances in the still expanding frontier. And while telegraphy has virtually disappeared, rails remain in improved form (Europe, China, Japan) or in dilapidated states (United States); barbed wire takes new forms (to keep out human invaders rather than keeping cattle in). Only the infotechnologies that replaced the telegraph abandon the physical connectivity of the original design. Microwave towers now sprout up globally, sometimes replacing but more often establishing the new technological means of communicating.</p>
                  </list-item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I have not exhausted the contrasts between the old and new technologies, but hopefully my narrative has depicted changes between the “industrial” and “electronic” eras. At the very least here, one should be able to see that the descriptors used by Heidegger no longer hold. I want to make only two more moves: First, I want to develop a suggestive paradigmatic example of the transition to new technologies, and second, I want to make a few historical generalizations about technologies in human history.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec id="s01_3">
            <title>The Cell Phone and Heidegger's Hammer</title>
            <p>One of the pleasures I have had in doing philosophy of technology—in addition to getting to play with the new toys (virtual reality caves in Sweden, robots in Japan)—is to serve as an external adviser for dissertations from which I learn so much. Here I will shamelessly borrow, and cite, an interesting thesis being developed by Galit Wellner from Bar-Ilan University. She notes that today a “tool” far more common than a hammer, but which functions as a<italic>ready-to-hand</italic>device, is the<italic>cell phone</italic>. She is doing an empirical- turn case study of its evolution and role with exciting implications.</p>
            <p>I will borrow this idea here to illustrate how a new technology transforms in new ways our relations to the world and thus concentrate what I have outlined above. First, the cell phone may come close to being the early twenty-first century's almost universal technology. Social scientists claim that<italic>95 percent of the global population today has access to cell phones</italic>! Not all have cell phones; for example, in Bangladesh, “phone ladies” supplied with cell phones provided by the Grameen Bank service entire villages. But also the cell phone is a “leapfrog technology” in that it skips the long evolution of wired systems and can sprout up in remote and undeveloped territories. Maasai warriors can communicate in the bush with them. But I turn to the characteristics I have claimed for new technologies and provocatively compare these with Heidegger's hammer:<list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>First, what of<italic>readiness-to-hand</italic>? This part of Heidegger's still phenomenological description applies to both. In use, both the hammer and cell phone “withdraw” and become the embodied means of praxis, not its goal. Both have “assignments” and belong to complex relationships with the environment, and both reveal the worldliness of the world—but even without further description you no doubt are already aware that the size, shape, and reach of these assignments are vastly different. The hammer remains embodied bodily; the cell phone includes hermeneutic relations and alterity relations as well.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>In this latter context one can note that both the hammer and cell phone are multistable, but in vastly different ways. Classical hammers exemplified different uses through different, largely single-style designs: carpenters' hammers, cobblers' hammers, tack hammers, sledgehammers. Cell phones are deliberately multitask designed—audio phone, text capacity, camera, GPS, bar code reader, calculator—all built into a single “handy” device.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>And even beyond designed multistability, embodied users can imagine and utilize unintended uses—a hammer may be a murder weapon, a paperweight, an art object, and so on; cell phones have been used as detonators and as devices to help victim hunters find people after earthquakes or may, as in the hacking incidents of summer 2011, be used to snoop, deceive, and even bring down politicians, newspeople, and BskyB billion-dollar deals.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>The contrast is more stark if we consider what could be called “reach.” The hammer has a very limited reach for the hand or, if Thor's hammer, as far as it can be thrown. The cell phone's reach is<italic>global</italic>and more. As global, wirelessly connecting through voice, text, and the Internet, it can reach virtually the entire human community or, through data and imaging, the universe as well.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>Another feature of the cell phone and related technologies is the “democracy” of uses. Like the earlier decentralized cassette recorders, “handy” electronic, now globally connected info- and communication technologies are proving hard to “control” or close down. Repressive regimes try and sometimes succeed until routes around are discovered and reestablished.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>Again, I am far from exhausting the far more vast affordances of the cell phone over the hammer, but before I leave this example I will mention that Galit Wellner also sees in the cell phone a memory and life-identity set of affordances—its memory can carry a favored photo album and one's songs and tunes, as well as favored texts.</p>
                  </list-item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Hopefully you can discern that these same capacities belong in their different ways to most of the new technologies I have mentioned: multistability as enhanced by designed-in multitasking, space-time reach through remote and wireless connectivity, the interchangeability of data and imaging through computer tomography and the like. For me, the emergence of these new convergent technologies bespeaks another revolutionary change as far reaching as the previous Industrial Revolution.</p>
            <p>I am not claiming this second revolution to fit into the discontinuous frame style of either Heidegger, with epochs of being, or Foucault, with<italic>epistemes</italic>, or even Kuhn, with paradigm shifts, since the new technologies have not entirely replaced the old ones. Rather, in a more empirical style of technology history, the new technologies have been added to and often intersect with the old ones. What old ones will disappear cannot yet be fully discerned. An empirical history also has to recognize that technologies do get abandoned, forgotten, and broken, and they do disappear.</p>
            <p>One of my favorite deep history examples centers in the technologies of the ice ages, from roughly 40,000 to 10,000 B.P. Many tools, lithic or “Stone Age,” have been found but, with the possible exception of a few very isolated islands of humans, have all been abandoned. My “Acheulean hand ax” only serves as an archaeological artifact on my desk. Yet some of these same technologies persist in modified forms to this very day. Only in recent times have the 25,000 B.P. “Venuses” been recognized to be wearing textiles, and textiles remain. Or again, recently discovered bear bone flutes (45,000 B.P.) and vulture wing flutes (30,000 B.P.) with tuning systems of a diatonic style also exist in contemporary practices. Is it ironic that the weaponry, heavy-duty, and largely “male”-used artifacts were the ones primarily abandoned?</p>
            <p>Or take an example from ancient physics (2400 B.P.), Democritean atoms. Democritus theorized bits of matter so small<italic>in fact</italic>but also<italic>in principle</italic>to be too small to be humanly perceived. Yet he went on to hypothesize that their shapes were<italic>causes</italic>of our perceptions. Thus smooth round shapes caused sweet tastes, while barbed ones caused bitter. From today's technologically embodied science we have now overcome his limitations with scanning, tunneling electronic microscopes and now know, recently, that two-atom-thick carbon films can be arranged into thirteen different multistable forms through imaging of the atoms. Thus, using the vocabulary of modernist realism, we could conclude that Democritean atoms never existed, or using the vocabulary of social constructionism, we could say that the ancient “scientific objects—Democritus's atoms” have disappeared to be replaced in the nineteenth century by Rutherfordian mini–solar system atoms and today again replaced by quantum structures. Or we could turn postphenomenological and note that through improved new instrumental technologies, we can now mediatedly “see” the carbon structures noted. What has changed with both Democritus and Rutherford are lifeworlds in which objects, knowledge production, and human–world interrelationships have been superseded.</p>
            <p>Or how about technologies predicted to become dominant that never materialize? The leading contender for a universal development of a technology pronounced in the<italic>New York Herald</italic>in 1900 was<italic>compressed air</italic>. Or take the age of steam power: the ship, train, and factory engines powered by steam are all but gone except as tourist attractions (ironically steam is retained for nuclear plants as hybrids of industrial and atomic technologies). Yes, Heidegger's “rustbelt” technologies still operate alongside the new technologies, but as alongside, this already means that they are but one style, region, or type of technology. His descriptors are not an “essence.” From my perspective to avoid looking, phenomenologically and empirically, at specific technologies, to seek a “one-size-fits-all” essence of technology overall, is both arrogant and irresponsible—and badly outdated.</p>
            <p>So, to some preliminary answers as to whether Continental philosophy can deal with the new technologies:<list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>If we stick to the<italic>old</italic>philosophies of technology, themselves largely reflections upon<italic>old</italic>technologies, no. And if, as many of the old philosophies of technology did, we refuse to examine the particulars of technologies and seek only “essences,” then also no. If, instead, by both maintaining phenomenological rigor and doing an “empirical turn” to examine deeply the human–technology interrelationships, then yes.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>In short, this is an argument that holds that in the light of the rapid changes in technologies, there must be reciprocal changes in the philosophies that respond to, reflect upon, and deal with technologies. I am holding that the “old” philosophies must now be seen as limited, as in many ways dated, and certainly as<italic>transcendental</italic>, only partial at best in terms of insight.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                     <label>•</label>
                     <p>But are there new philosophies of technology? In my narrative I have implied my own style of a “postphenomenology,” which today is practiced by a significant number of younger philosophers—I would include here Peter Paul Verbeek, Evan Selinger, Robert Rosenberger, and many others who have presented and published “empirical turn studies.” Hans Achterhuis describes this concrete turn very well in<italic>American Philosophy of Technology: The Empirical Turn</italic>(<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Andrew Feenberg, himself an interpreter and critic of both Heidegger and Marcuse, has done his own analyses of new technologies. And in Europe, a social scientist-philosopher, actually more cited than Derrida, Bruno Latour is known for his distinctive “actor network theory” of analysis. And Donna Haraway must be added for her biology-centered work as well. I mention these movements in passing to show that the field has already changed and all of these are “Continental” in heritage. Indeed, the field is much larger, and “technoscience studies” are engaged in by the new sociologies of science, feminist studies of science, and many emergent cultural studies now proliferating in both Europe and America. Here, however, I did not want to do a field survey but, rather, take note of our own responses to technologies from the SPEP anniversary.</p>
                  </list-item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I want to conclude with one more argument from my own work. I have very often argued that philosophers of technology, regarding the expectations of society and their own traditions and habits, may come “too late” to technologies. They too often undertake their reflections<italic>after</italic>the technologies are in place. Rather, I argue, they should reposition themselves at what I call the “R&amp;D” position where technologies are taking developmental shape, in think tanks, in incubator facilities, in research centers. Only then can truly “new” and emerging technologies be fully philosophically engaged.</p>
            <ref-list content-type="references">
               <title>WORKS CITED</title>
               <ref id="r1">
                  <mixed-citation>Achterhuis, Hans. 2001.<italic>American Philosophy of Technology: The Empirical Turn</italic>. Trans. Robert Crease. Bloomington: Indiana University Press.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r2">
                  <mixed-citation>Bunge, Mario. 1979. “The Five Buds of Techno-philosophy.”<italic>Technology in Society</italic>1:67–74.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r3">
                  <mixed-citation>Ihde, Don. 1979.<italic>Technics and Praxis: A Philosophy of Technology</italic>. Dordrecht: Reidl.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r4">
                  <mixed-citation>Kuhn, Thomas. 1962.<italic>The Structure of Scientific Revolutions</italic>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r5">
                  <mixed-citation>Latour, Bruno. 1987.<italic>Science in Action</italic>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r6">
                  <mixed-citation>Latour, Bruno, and Steve Woolgar. 1979.<italic>Laboratory Life</italic>. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r7">
                  <mixed-citation>Marcuse, Herbert. 1964.<italic>One Dimensional Man</italic>. Boston: Beacon Press.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r8">
                  <mixed-citation>Netz, Reviel. 2004.<italic>Barbed Wire: An Ecology of Modernity</italic>. Middletown, Conn.: Wesleyan University Press.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
               <ref id="r9">
                  <mixed-citation>Richardson, William. 1963.<italic>Heidegger: From Phenomenology to Thought</italic>. Dordrecht: Martinus Nijhoff.</mixed-citation>
               </ref>
            </ref-list>
         </sec>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
