<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         article-type="book-review"
         dtd-version="1.0"
         xml:lang="en">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jreligion</journal-id>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="ucp-id">jr</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Journal of Religion</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <publisher>
            <publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name>
         </publisher>
         <issn pub-type="ppub">00224189</issn>
         <issn pub-type="epub">15496538</issn>
         <custom-meta-group/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/672230</article-id>
         <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JR296117</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title/>
         </title-group>
         <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author" rid="af17" xlink:type="simple">
               <string-name>
                  <given-names>Hava</given-names>
                  <x xml:space="preserve"/>
                  <surname>Tirosh-Samuelson</surname>
               </string-name>
            </contrib>
            <aff id="af17">Arizona State University.</aff>
         </contrib-group>
         <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2013</year>
            <string-date>July 2013</string-date>
         </pub-date>
         <volume>93</volume>
         <issue>3</issue>
         <issue-id>670329</issue-id>
         <fpage>401</fpage>
         <lpage>403</lpage>
         <product xlink:type="simple">
            <string-name>
               <surname>Fisher</surname>,<given-names>Cass</given-names>
            </string-name>.<source>Contemplative Nation: A Philosophical Account of Jewish Theological Language</source>. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 2012. ix–xi+301 pp. $60.00 (cloth).</product>
         <permissions>
            <copyright-statement>For permission to reuse, please contact<email xlink:type="simple">journalpermissions@press.uchicago.edu</email>.</copyright-statement>
         </permissions>
         <self-uri xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/672230"/>
         <custom-meta-group>
            <custom-meta>
               <meta-name>lang</meta-name>
               <meta-value>en</meta-value>
            </custom-meta>
         </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Cass Fisher has set for himself a noble goal: “to reframe the debate about the role of theology in Judaism and Jewish studies by proposing a new model for understanding Jewish theological language” (2). The impetus for this project is the awareness that although the discipline of Jewish studies has thrived in the past half century, theology is still marginal because of the mistaken perception that “there is no Jewish theology” (3) or that “Judaism has produced the wrong kind of theology” (4). Fisher correctly and persuasively argues that such perception not only is historically incorrect but also ignores a thriving “post-Holocaust theology, feminist theology, exegetical theology, and covenantal theology” (3), a list that could have included environmental theology. To appreciate the degree to which theological thinking is central to Judaism, a new and more appropriate understanding of theology is in order. Theology is not to be reduced to propositional speculations about God but should rather be understood as belief-forming activities that are an integral part of Jewish religious practice, including exegesis, hermeneutics, rational discourse on divine perfection, and religious experience.</p>
      <p>In the first two chapters Fisher explains how he selected these four components through critical engagement with the theories of Hans-Georg Gadamer and Paul Ricoeur (chap. 1), and Pierre Hadot and William Alston (chap. 2). In the remaining two chapters Fisher applies the Jewish theological practice model to two Jewish texts: the rabbinic anthology<italic>Mekhilta of Rabbi Ishmael</italic>(chap. 3) and Franz Rosenzweig’s<italic>Star of Redemption</italic>(chap. 4). With a new understanding of theology, the reader is expected to understand not only why it is wrong to marginalize Jewish theology within Jewish studies but also why Jewish thinking is inherently theological. Borrowing from Philo, Fisher titles his book<italic>Contemplative Nation</italic>to indicate that “Israel” should be defined not by ethnicity, politics, or culture but rather by “being genuinely concerned with God and the divine-human relationship” (16). In his conclusion, Fisher reiterates that “the task of the Jewish people, and not just its religious elite, [is] to direct their thoughts to God and the divine-human relationship” (223). If “Israel” and “Jewish people” are interchangeable terms, to be Jewish is inherently a theological practice, as far as Fisher is concerned.</p>
      <p>The strength of the book lies in its remarkable clarity of expression and tight argumentation. Patiently and methodologically, Fisher builds his model of Jewish theological practice and accounts for each step of this construction project, explaining what he takes from other thinkers, where he disagrees with his interlocutors, and how they complement each other. Gadamer’s hermeneutics, Ricouer’s theory of textuality, Hadot’s analysis of ancient philosophy as a way of life, William Alston’s theories of religious experience as belief-forming practices provide the “building blocks,” so to speak, of his carefully constructed model. The exposition of their views is exemplary and the tightness of the exposition is both the strength and weakness of the book. Jewish theological practice appropriately highlights the close nexus between theory and praxis in Judaism, rejecting the bifurcation of the two that has been “the hallmark of modern life” (222). Second, the model correctly shows that theology manifests itself in multiple forms, most importantly in exegesis (namely, the reading of the Bible as a self-coherent text) and hermeneutics (namely, the reading of the scripture to cohere with one’s historical and cultural situatedness). Third, the model explains how practice is “comprised of a set of mutually supportive belief-forming mechanisms” (93) so that “Jewish theology provides the conceptual framework that underlies the divine-human relationship and the cognitive means enhancing that relationship” (95).</p>
      <p>However, Fisher’s methodology seems somewhat circular: he privileges four elements that fit his understanding of theology and then “proves” their presence in two select Jewish texts, one ancient and one modern. This procedure leaves out about fifteen hundred years of Jewish philosophical theology that may or may not confirm the model. It is no coincidence that Fisher left out Jewish philosophy from Saadia Gaon to Mendelssohn, since it has a strong propositional dimension in addition to being exegetical and hermeneutical. Conversely, Fisher’s analysis excludes the Jewish mystical tradition, which could have given further support for his Jewish theological practice model. In other words, more textual work is needed before Jewish theological practice could be accepted as definitive.</p>
      <p>The treatment of the ancient and modern examples is also somewhat too neat and overly selective. For example, it is definitely appropriate to analyze the relationship between theory and practice in rabbinic Judaism on the basis of Hadot’s analysis of ancient philosophy. But Fisher should have reflected on the interplay of theory and praxis in rabbinic Judaism in light of the Aristotelian tradition, which is utterly and consistently ignored in this book. Similarly, Fisher admits that his analysis of<italic>Mekhihta of Rabbi Yishmael</italic>is indebted to Max Kadushin’s insightful presentation of rabbinic Judaism as “organismic” system of value concepts (105), but Fisher does not analyze the philosophical basis of Kadushin’s reading, as does Peter Ochs, whose book is cited in the notes but whose analysis is not engaged. The treatment of Rosenzweig also exhibits a penchant for selectivity. To show how his model of Jewish theological practice applies to contemporary debates about Rosenzweig and therefore to contemporary Jewish theology, Fisher singles out two interpreters: Leora Batnitzky (whose interpretation he finds “idiosyncratic” [163]) and Peter Gordon (who is accused of “grossly distor[ting] Rosenzweig’s point” [166]). While Fisher’s own interpretation of Rosenzweig is most suggestive, whether Jewish theological practice is a viable model cannot be decided by showing the limitations of two interpretations of Rosenzweig to the exclusion of all others.</p>
      <p>Despite these caveats,<italic>Contemplative Nation</italic>is highly recommended for scholars of Jewish studies, religious studies, philosophy, and theology. The book is an excellent example of how to apply hermeneutical theories to the study of Judaism, how to bridge the gap between continental philosophy and analytic philosophy, and how to expand the scope of Jewish studies by appreciating the nature of theological discourse. While Judaica scholars could use the book in university-level courses, and rabbis could apply its approach to synagogue life, the claim that “Israel” is a “contemplative nation” will hardly resonate with most Jews today. It is very doubtful that the book could “guide the way for [the] future” of the Jewish people’s survival (226), precisely because Jews today are overwhelmingly secular, and the culture in which Jews live, both in Israel and in the Diaspora, is anti-intellectual and antitheological. Furthermore, if Fisher is so keen on Philo, he should have also reminded his readers of the fate of Philo’s enterprise: it was no coincidence that Philo became one of the Church Fathers and that his exegetical/hermeneutical project was not adopted by the tradition that became normative Judaism. When “Israel” denotes a nation of divine contemplators, “carnal Israel” (namely “Israel” as a historical, cultural, and ethnic entity) is marginalized, denigrated, and persecuted. It is true that Jewish religious life is theological, but being Jewish cannot be reduced to contemplating God.</p>
   </body>
</article>
